<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF16_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1859-02">February 1859</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1859-02">5619</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f16_0011_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f16_0011_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f16_0011_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f16_0011_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                <date><sic>feb.</sic> 5619</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">A reply to the <persName>Rev. Mr Calish</persName> by a
                student.<lb/> of hebrew theology</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir:</p>
            <p>Being a friend of hebrew <sic>litterature</sic> and having spent the most<lb/> of my
                leisure time to improve myself in this beautiful science<lb/> as much as I could, I
                think I have a right to bespeak<lb/> that subject as good as anybody. I feel
                therefore very <sic>sory</sic> that<lb/> the hebrew <sic>litterature</sic> has
                become a level in the party spirit which<lb/> now prevails among the Israelites in
                this country as well as<lb/> in <placeName>Germany</placeName> and that they who can
                not anymore subscribe<lb/> to the doctrines and ceremonies (of course I speak
                principally of<lb/> their leaders of those who take an active part in the matter)
                of<lb/> the Israelites in general, look with hatred down upon those even<lb/> who
                use the paper as a vehicle of their thoughts, which is edited<lb/> by an
                    <sic>Israelit</sic>, who still cling to that system, which they think<lb/>
                proper and becoming to scorn at, as if it was not the mother<lb/> which gave birth
                to their new system or as they say, the real system—<add>*Ben Leëb— (*) as a
                    specimen may serve the majority of the Israelites know no difference between ב
                    and ך.</add>—This reminds me<lb/> as to the conditions of the different sects
                among the gentiles among we live,<lb/> who dispute the right of the, so called,
                mother church, which however,<lb/> (notwithstanding its pernicious
                    <sic>probnoxious</sic> doctrines, of course by<lb/> the mother church
                    <del>calumny and</del> not acknowledged, and which is according to her, calumny they<lb/>
                <del>source</del> fruits of infidelity to and unbelief is the whole existence of the
                church,)<lb/> has a full right and claim to that name. It is not my duty here,
                to<lb/> investigate, who gave the first cause to that hatred, sufficient that<lb/>
                this hatred exist. And the noble <del>men</del> courage is wanting to give up
                    <del>mis</del> unfortunate<lb/> feeling, which, if not abated, will and
                    <del>can</del> must cause a distinct separation between the parties,<lb/> we
                have seen already the greatest <sic>prove</sic> that this will be, for fathers and
                more<lb/> so mothers have prohibited <sic>intermariage</sic>. <sic>Brethern</sic>!
                be careful in the course<lb/> you <sic>persue</sic>
                <add>Hebrew</add>. If you think there are errors in the old system, do<lb/> not
                leave it therefore, but enlighten its <sic>adherrer</sic>
                <del>them</del>. And if you unfortunately can<lb/> not subscribe any more at all, to
                the system of the <sic>Isrealites</sic>, which<lb/> is often the case, leave them
                and occupy your mind and heart with<lb/> other things, what a difference between the
                gentleman who left us shortly<lb/> for <placeName>Ireland</placeName>, and the noble
                hearted <persName>Spinoza</persName> of old. But let me<lb/> come to the point. The
                Hebrew <sic>litterature</sic>, I said, has become a level<lb/> in this party spirit
                and is it not so? He, who with a critique eye<lb/> followed the arguments set forth
                at <sic>intervalls</sic> in „the Israelite” by<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Calish</persName>, for instance, sees very clearly that this
                gentleman,</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>misrepresents our literature, of course what knows the mass<lb/> of the people about
                it, he who speaks the last wins it, and he<lb/> who keeps on the <sic>longuest</sic>
                is of a <sic>surity</sic> the smartest. Ask the mass<lb/> of the readers, ask them
                all, a very few excepted, their opinion of „a<lb/>
                <sic>a</sic>
                <sic>disquisiton</sic> concerning the time of composing the accents etc”<lb/> and
                they will tell you It is <sic>exellent</sic>! <hi rend="underline">he</hi> is a man!
                    <hi rend="underline">he</hi> is right!<lb/> down with orthodoxy! No my
                    <sic>bretheren</sic>, be calm do not judge about<lb/> things, which you do not
                understand, that is very unbecoming of<lb/> men of good sense. I <del>tell</del>
                inform you, if <persName>Mr Calish</persName>, meant here<lb/> that he wrote
                something worthy to be read by a man who knows<lb/> something about that subject, he
                may be noble hearted, and<lb/> a man of kind feelings, a thorough read man, but he knows<lb/>
                <del>nothing</del> little of Hebrew <sic>litterature</sic> and not worthy to trust
                his<lb/> ideas in those things. A friend of mine, a tolerable hebrew scholar,<lb/>
                after having read that article asked my opinion about it. Upon<lb/> which I
                    <del>repl</del> answered, <persName>Mr N</persName>.... You must not look upon
                that article,<lb/> as written for the learned, or as a final <sic>dicision</sic> of
                a thorough<lb/> scholar of hebrew literature, But as mere <hi rend="underline"
                    >opinions</hi> of a man<lb/> who is biased and influenced by a kind of party
                spirit,<lb/> which exist a few years in this country among the Israelites,<lb/> and
                who among other things, <sic>carying</sic> on a system to <sic>remoddel</sic><lb/>
                the <sic>synagogual</sic> ceremonies and rites after a plan of the<lb/> Lutheran
                churches in <placeName>Germany</placeName>. <persName>Mr Calish</persName> is a
                German, who<lb/> has not had a great deal of opportunity to hear plain and correct<lb/>
                <sic>hebrew</sic> reading and does not know wherein it consists, he is quite a
                foreigner in this department. And when I may trust a friend who heard him<lb/>
                reading the prayers and the <sic>pentateuch</sic> with the required<lb/> accents,
                then he himself does not understand that art. He<lb/> reads the Hebrew, with the
                    <sic>syriac</sic>
                <sic>pronounciation</sic>, which I have<lb/> shewn to you on several occasions, is
                very absurd, and false and<lb/>
                <sic>inconsisted</sic> with the Hebrew grammar, mostly all the
                <sic>german</sic><lb/> and is generally the majority of the <sic>isralites</sic>,
                know not to<lb/> read otherwise and is disgusting to him whose ear is accustomed to
                those soft <sic>hebrew</sic> sounds * and as a german Hebrew scholar expresses himself<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, it is a gross mistake which they will not correct. (*)<lb/>
                Generally the philosophy of the Hebrew tongue is unknown among the most of</p>
            <p>*Ben Leëb— (*) as a specimen may serve the majority of the Israelites know no
                difference between ב and ך. <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> and pronounced alike, To the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> and <add>Hebrew</add>, <add>Hebrew</add> and some add
                    <add>Hebrew</add>, <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p><sic>of</sic> the <sic>hebrews</sic>, even among those who claim to be
                    <sic>hebrew</sic> scholars,<lb/> hence that want of taste for what we call the
                    <sic>arabic</sic>
                <sic>pronounciation</sic><lb/> and accentuation, which is the proper
                    <sic>pronounciation</sic>, as near<lb/> as can be, of the Hebrew tongue. To shew
                farther how less <persName>Mr<lb/> Calish</persName> is competent to treat that
                subject, it is <sic>suficient</sic>, that<lb/> he wishes to have it read, with the
                    <sic>syriac</sic>
                <sic>pronounciation</sic> and in<lb/> a tune or <sic>beter</sic>
                <sic>cadance</sic> wherein we read English, <sic>german</sic> or
                <sic>french</sic><lb/> verse. Verily this does not shew a great deal of taste for the<lb/>
                <sic>hebrew</sic> tongue. Verily this does not shew a great deal of knowledge<lb/>
                of the art of manner how the oriental tongues were read.<lb/> To refute his remarks
                is useless, because <persName>Mr Calish</persName> knows<lb/> very well himself,
                that he did not write for a learned community,<lb/> it was not intended for an
                learned article to become discussed,<lb/> but only to please the
                    remaddllers<add>?</add> of <sic>synogogual</sic> ceremonies.<lb/> Otherwise he
                would not have used such a sophistry. „For a learned<lb/> man, and especially a <hi
                    rend="underline">teacher must surely</hi> know it, that etc, By<lb/> this is
                confessedly proved etc” I say by this is confessedly<lb/> proved nothing of the
                kind. <persName>Mr Calish</persName> does not know,<lb/> that the language at that
                time was spoken according to the<lb/>
                <sic>arabic</sic> dialect and not <del>what we call</del> according to the
                    <sic>syriac</sic> dialect and<lb/> that the <sic>arabic</sic> has in the
                structure of such words always<lb/> the accent penultima either, <add>Hebrew</add>
                or <add>Hebrew</add>. <persName>Mr Calish</persName> takes it for<lb/> granted that
                we have the real Septuagint, that shews he never has<lb/> compared the Septuagint
                with the text as I and thousand<lb/> others have, otherwise how can he make such a
                statement. I<lb/> refer him to 1 <persName>Samuel</persName> the two first chapters.
                Or does he think<lb/> because I refer him to this place that he is right on the
                    <sic>pentateuch</sic>?<lb/> I can refer him also to the <sic>pentateuch</sic> to
                more than one place, which<lb/> he knows very well I only refer to
                    <persName>Sam.</persName> because there it is more striking.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Calish</persName> ought to know that we<lb/> find the accents mentioned
                is the Lahor, Adra etc that<lb/> was as before the Mishnah, although he may say
                these<lb/> passages are interpolated, his exposition of the 5 verses is<lb/> not a
                true one. But <persName>Mr Calish</persName> says, as a man who does<lb/> not know
                to write about such matters, „hence it is irrefutable<lb/> proved” But what is the
                world, are these words of a calm</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>scholar? When I tell now <persName>Mr Calish</persName> that
                    <persName>Moses</persName> taught the <sic>Israelits</sic><lb/> the accents, is
                irrefutable—namely what he did read to the Israelites must have here accompanied of
                the p. 180 common sense and the nature of<lb/> that and other oriental tongues shew
                that clearly, that it<lb/> is irrefutable proved, that <persName>Mr
                    Calish</persName> knows nothing about the<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, no more than <del>simple school boy, perhaps less</del> what is
                generally taught in the <sic>jewish</sic> schools, and that is really nothing,
                which<lb/> he himself shews is his last note. <persName>Mr Calish</persName> has
                no<lb/> idea what <add>Hebrew</add> means, he does not understand<lb/> neither the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> neither its figures, neither its powers<lb/> has decidedly
                never studied the accents of the Psalms<lb/>
                <persName>Job</persName> and proverbs, knows perhaps not <del>their</del> its names.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Calish</persName> think because <hi rend="underline">he</hi> does not
                know, how they were<lb/> used in reading and how they are a part of the language
                like the <sic>vowl</sic> point, which he has assailed at the same time, nobody can
                know anything about it.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Calish</persName> can not explain in what way they required<lb/>
                different names, which are still existing he can not shew how they originated?
                    <persName>Mr. Calish</persName><lb/>
                <sic>think</sic> he can treat that subject in two lines and then<lb/>
                    punctum<add>?</add>. No Dear <persName>Mr Calish</persName> it was not fair of
                you<lb/> to hurt my feelings in such a degree, you ought to have thought,<lb/>
                perhaps is there any one else who has <del>gone</del> investigated that subject
                as<lb/> good as I have done let me hear what he has to say about<lb/> it and let me
                not write against any <sic>sience</sic>, because I do not like it, and wish it to
                see abolished. O? you were wrong. Why are your opinions irrefutable? After calm
                reflection you<lb/> could have found some refutation partly in the books you<lb/>
                have quoted yourself, f. i. you quote <persName>Ihn Esra</persName>, who said<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> and amply by these <sic>authers</sic> and works<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>
                <persName>Mendelsohn</persName>, <persName>E. Levita</persName>, <persName>L. de
                    Modena</persName>, <persName>Bandorf<lb/> Vater</persName>, <persName>Ludevicus
                    de Dien</persName>, <persName>Schultens</persName>,
                    <persName>Schröder</persName>, <persName>de Wette</persName><lb/> in preface
                Hakktab Wehakbula <add>Hebrew</add>, by <persName>Kirchheim</persName>, in
                    <add>Hebrew</add>,<lb/> by <add>Hebrew</add>, in <persName>Arkwalti's</persName>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, in <add>Hebrew</add> in <add>Hebrew</add>,
                    <persName>Kerder</persName><lb/> Philo. and many others.</p>
            <p>I wish that they who write on such grave and learned subjects (of course<lb/> de man
                does not see any beauty in it and will laugh at my preposterity<lb/> for those
                subjects) would bear in mind that smatterings does not <del>ble</del> satisfy a<lb/>
                student of Hebr. <sic>litterature</sic>. In conclusion I <sic>advice</sic>
                <persName>Mr Calish</persName> to instruct his <sic>bretheren</sic> among he
                resides<lb/> to read the <sic>hebrew</sic> in its elegant original
                    <sic>pronounciation</sic>
                <del>and</del> to abolish that miserable kind of dialect, wherein he now reads and
                to study the <add>Hebrew</add> with its simple <sic>cadances</sic>,<lb/> without
                these no text can be read for an audience and I am assured much good would result,
                and perhaps peace will again come in <placeName>Israel</placeName>. Be not like the
                for with the grapes, and finally<lb/> read Locke's essay „of the conduct of human
                understanding, articles, Bias, ideas, opinions, etc. and<lb/> you will write against
                    <del>to</del> your opponents with more dignity. As soon as I have leisure I will
                write somethings on the<lb/> beauty of hebrew accents. <add>Hebrew</add></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
