<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M., Dr.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF4_67</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M.,
                            Dr.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1857-09">10 September 1857</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1857-09">10 September 5617</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0064_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0064_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0064_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0064_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Charleston, S. C.</placeName>
                <date>Sept. 10. 5617/1857</date>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir—More than four weeks ago<lb/> I addressed a letter to you,
                with the request to send me<lb/> a copy of your octavo Bible bound in purple velvet,
                with<lb/> gilded clasp &amp;c, designed for a nuptial present, and in-<lb/>close my
                bill the amount of which I do not know. The<lb/> wedding took place yesterday, and I
                have not yet received<lb/> the Bible, although I wrote that I wanted it in the
                first<lb/> week of <date>September</date>. As it is, I would be glad, to
                receive<lb/> it at least before <add>ר"ה</add>. It is to be presented to
                    <persName>Mrs.<lb/> Sarah I. Davega</persName>, formerly <persName>Mrs. I. J.
                    Moses</persName>, sister to my wife.<lb/> What say to this news? No doubt, you
                heard of this “match”<lb/> before, considering that you are generally <hi
                    rend="underline">an courant</hi> with<lb/> all that transpires at least amongst
                the Israelites of <placeName>Charles-<lb/>ton</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But, have you been informed also of the<lb/> discussion which has
                been carried on, for the last weeks, on<lb/> the subject of the Swiss Treaty, in the
                    <hi rend="underline">Courier</hi> of this city? Have<lb/> you been informed
                that, after I had published an Article, on<lb/> the <date>13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    of August</date> last, calling upon the Jews of
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>, “to<lb/> act now in concert, and forget all
                differences of religious opinion,” and appealing to the Press for assistance, “<hi
                    rend="underline">A Jew</hi>” appeared<lb/> in the same paper charging me with
                “either ignorance<lb/> or hasty and impetuous zeal,” and cautioning the Jews
                against<lb/> being aroused to action, since by that treaty “their rights, as
                Americans</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>are not assailed, and their religious privilege in no way molested”? I<lb/> replied,
                sustaining my position, and declared at the conclusion that<lb/> I should no farther
                notice any “<hi rend="underline">anonymous</hi>” communication. Yet, “A Jew”<lb/>
                again came forth, defending the treaty, repeating the charge of my ignorance,<lb/>
                and calling all that had as yet been written on the subject by<lb/> Editors “flimsy
                remarks.” In reply to him, <persName>Mr. J. N. Cardoza</persName><lb/> entered the
                arena in a most gentlemanly and quiet Article.<lb/> To this “A Jew” replied in a
                most scurrilous and insulting<lb/> Article, without even once coming to the point at
                issue, nay! he was<lb/> even so ungenerous &amp; uncharitable, not to say
                ungentlemanly, to cast<lb/> some open flings at me, although I had withdrawn from
                the controversy<lb/> and thus placed myself beyond the possibility of
                    <sic>defence</sic>.</p>
            <p>Now <persName>Mr. N.</persName> published an Article, containing a most
                withering<lb/> lesson for the unavoidable position which “A Jew” had taken in this
                affair.<lb/> The latter took <sic>offence</sic> at this and published a card,
                demanding<lb/> an explanation from <persName>Mr. C.</persName> This was not given,
                and so there<lb/> was for the last 3 days a fine prospect of a duel. Things,<lb/>
                however, I think, are now settled. You yourself were drawn<lb/> into this
                controversy. In his first Article, <persName>Mr. C.</persName> quoted from<lb/> the
                Occident, Vol. XII, p. 95-100, to prove that you had then already<lb/> written
                against the Treaty <hi rend="underline">as it now stands</hi>; “A Jew” denied<lb/>
                this fact, in his reply, maintaining that you meant the original draft<lb/>
                containing the word “<hi rend="underline">Christian</hi>,” and to prove this, he quoted<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">from Vol. 15, <date>March '51</date></hi>!!! Is this not very
                fair, after <persName>Mr C.</persName> had<lb/> quoted your very words and which
                could certainly not be found in the<lb/>
                <date>March</date> Number of <date>1851</date>!? What must “A Jew” now think of<lb/>
                this incidental point, after having read your Article on the<lb/> Swiss Treaty, in
                which you refer to the very pages quoted<lb/> by <persName>Mr. C.</persName>? Has
                your usual informant or reporter not com-</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>municated all this to you? If he has, did he give you also the<lb/> name of “A Jew.”?
                At all events, I will give it to you. It is<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. <hi rend="underline">Charles H. Moise</hi></persName>. I do not envy
                him for the laurels which<lb/> he has won in this warfare; all he gained is this,
                that the Press of <placeName>S. C.</placeName><lb/> become lukewarm &amp;
                indifferent, after some papers had taken<lb/> up our cause. Nevertheless, a memorial
                will be sent to the President<lb/> by Jews, if not <hi rend="underline">the</hi>
                Jews of <placeName>Charleston</placeName>; it is now being circulated<lb/> for
                subscription. Will you expose this extraordinary proceeding of a<lb/> Jew in this
                affair? Justice demands it!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I read your Article on the New Prayer-book “<hi rend="underline"
                    >Minhag</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline"><placeName>America</placeName></hi>,” in the last month's <hi
                    rend="underline">Occidents</hi>. I agree fully with you<lb/> concerning the
                transgression of power by the Compilers; I wrote<lb/> the <hi rend="underline"
                    >same</hi> truths to <persName>Dr Cohn</persName> in
                    <placeName>Albany</placeName>
                <hi rend="underline">already two months</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">ago</hi>, that is, before you published your strictures. I
                think the<lb/> very title is a piece of presumption and usurpation which<lb/> cannot
                be justified save by means of vulgar abuse and<lb/> contemptible insults.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now an open and honest explanation; I received your<lb/> invitation
                to the Consecration of your Synagogue. I did not<lb/> answer, nor attend. Why?
                Because I endorse every word contained<lb/> in the Editorial of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Asmonean</hi>, of <date>May 9.</date> last, and referring<lb/>
                to the establishment of your congregation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">With my wife's and my own best regard, and our wishes<lb/> for the
                coming New-Year, I remain, as ever,</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">Yours,</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">most respectfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">Dr M Mayer</persName>
            </p>
            <p>P.S. What is <persName>Mr. S. Jacobs</persName> doing? Is it </p>
            <p>true, that he has been appointed Professor of </p>
            <p>the Hebrew, at the Girard College, with a salary</p>
            <p>of $2000 a year? So <persName>Mr A. H. Abrahams</persName> tells the people here.</p>
            <p>What is is salary as Lecturer? Did you ever <sic>here</sic> the particulars of his
                resignation?</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
