<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">"A Looker-on"</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF1_52</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">"A Looker-on"</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1866-12">9 December 1866</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_3r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 5 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <placeName>Jewish Ministry</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)">Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">If ever I have felt enhanced the interest with<lb/> which I peruse
                the pages of the “Occident”it was on <sic>successeively</sic><lb/> reading the
                leaders in your <sic>isseues</sic> of <date>June</date>
                <date>July</date> &amp; <date>August</date> &amp; I feel<lb/> how very inadequately
                I am permitted to applaud you for thus con-<lb/>vincingly demonstrating the
                necessity of a Jewish Theological high<lb/> school whence may come forth men earnest
                in the cause of<lb/> God to teach the unlettered &amp; thus contribute their portion
                to the<lb/> welfare of their fellow creatures. I may in the way of<lb/> preface
                remark — altho' by the bye preambles are not part of my<lb/> habits, on the
                contrary, I am known to introduce myself unawares<lb/> even at the risk of meeting
                an unwelcome, in the way of preface<lb/> however, I must say that altho' I entirely
                coincide with you in the<lb/> basis of your dissertation there are points commented
                upon by<lb/> you in which there is an honest difference in our views.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It would be affectation to attempt if even a mild insinuation<lb/>
                that Judaism does not feel the want of pious teachers, men who will<lb/> undertake
                to instruct the people the tenets of their faith as held by<lb/> our father
                    <persName>Abraham</persName> of blessed memory, - we are happily not
                with-<lb/>out a few such but as unfortunately the number is small, there<lb/> is a
                pressing <del>a</del> demand to afford the means that <del>their <add>?</add> is
                        <add>?</add>
                </del>
                <lb/> it may increase I wish not to be understood as speaking dis-<lb/>paragingly of
                those who have sacrificed their time to the cause of their<lb/> faith, on the
                contrary they are the bright specks<add>?</add> on which the mind<lb/> loves to
                reflect &amp; the only regret which the reflections bring forth<lb/> is that the
                entire ministry is not so well composed.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The mission of the Minister is not fully applied <add>by those who
                    undertake it</add> &amp; thus it<lb/> is that the love of gain, a prevailing
                defect let us admit it, &amp; the ambi-<lb/>-tion</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2</p>
            <p>of being at the head of a congregation, thereby recuring<add>?</add> a
                respec-<lb/>table position, sometimes for life time have brought forth as<lb/> God's
                messengers men, who not being of the right stamp have com-<lb/>pletely failed in the
                work, where in piety &amp; sincerity were upper-<lb/>most a perfect success would
                have been the consequence. You<lb/> rightly observe Sir “if he wishes to do his
                whole duty” &amp; here is the<lb/> hinge of a great many of the differences &amp;
                dissensions which we so often<lb/> experience in the ranks of religion. A minister's
                duties! <sic>how</sic><lb/> varied they are, to what material benefit they would
                tend if piously<lb/> fulfilled, how honorable the profession if sincerity was made
                the<lb/> leading trait &amp; of what blessings it would prove if rightly
                    <sic>practised</sic>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Let us suppose Sir — but no, it is not supposition the writer<lb/>
                of this has such a personal experience — that a minister in private<lb/>
                conversation repeatedly admits a certain principle which he<lb/> thinks practicable
                &amp; recommends the means to attain the deside-<lb/>ratum &amp; when the parties
                thus instructed are preparing them-<lb/>selves for the task, their guide ascends the
                pulpit &amp; there, where no hu-<lb/>man voice can contradict him he advances
                notions diametri-<lb/>cally opposed to what he had agreed upon &amp; emits the
                thunders of<lb/> his vatican on those who believe &amp; are prepared to act in the
                man-<lb/>ner which he impressed <add>on</add> them to be his belief &amp; his
                readiness to act.<lb/> Now Sir, can any genuine honor he attached to such a host
                &amp; can<lb/> the man who thus deceives lay claim to that deference which<lb/>
                ennobles him who knows to whom to grant it? I know<lb/> your reuse of right &amp; I
                imagine I see you shuddering at the state-<lb/>ment I have made I imagine hearing
                you exclaim<lb/> Oh! That such pretended advocates of Truth could be laid aside
                &amp; if<lb/> for the glory of our religion they cannot reform, could they be
                made<lb/> to be quiet whilst they are among the people &amp; holding there an
                exal-<lb/>ted office. Whether the words which escape the lips of</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">3</p>
            <p>such an individual be the choicest, or whether he be versed in rhe-<lb/>toric &amp;
                knows all the mimics particular to oratory, it is <sic>imposseible</sic><lb/> for
                his exhortations to have the desired effect on those who know that<lb/> the lips
                beguile the heart true! There may be some who<lb/> imagine that their favorite
                preacher<lb/> is the personification of truth, he is all that can be desired, he
                may<lb/> even be supposed to be unlike his specie, frail &amp; erring. But of
                course<lb/> such conclusions are not the result of calm &amp; deliberate
                reflection<lb/> &amp; they are only mentioned here as forming a connecting link<lb/>
                to the moral weakness which is so general. There is perhaps no<lb/> occupation in
                life from which more honor &amp; satisfaction could<lb/> be attained than the
                ministry, but of course it has its solemn respon-<lb/>sibilites &amp; if there are
                sacrifices it is but natural to picture that shame<lb/> &amp; disgrace will ensue.
                The Jewish minister's chief aim should<lb/> be to establish peace in his
                congregation &amp; by no means should he<lb/> be found fanning the flame which may
                unfortunately exist, but<lb/> always holding the olive branch, it is his mission to
                propagate<lb/> peace &amp; be the medium of reconciling those who are divided,
                he<lb/> should make his flock one large family of which he is appointed<lb/> to act
                as father, <sic>counsellor</sic> &amp; guide, he is to be their judge &amp;
                with<lb/> the scale of Justice weighing in equal poise he is to arrange
                what-<lb/>ever differences arise. Oh what an opportunity for a<lb/> faithful &amp;
                sincere heart to manifest its throbbings, of what high<lb/> importance would such a
                chief be in truth could it be said of<lb/> him that his value exceedeth that of
                rubies. Identifying him-<lb/>self with the being of his flock, he is to partake of
                their pleasures &amp;<lb/> mourn with them over their sorrows, a true friend, he
                proves him-<lb/>self as such in the time of need. With satisfaction he joins<lb/>
                them in the events when gladness pervades their home, &amp; with</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">4</p>
            <p>the experiences which should naturally characterize his post he<lb/> warns them of
                the uncertainty of the duration of earthly pleasures<lb/> in kindress it
                    <sic>behoves</sic> him to say to them “boast not of to-day”<lb/> and likewise
                when the ills of life from which none are excluded<lb/> embitter their existence it
                is the spiritual guide whose office again<lb/> becomes necessary &amp; whilst he
                condoles with them in their be-<lb/>reavement he kindly offers a balm to the blow
                over which they<lb/> weep, he soothes their sorrows &amp; removes every impression
                which<lb/> might heighten affliction &amp; how unlike his high calling would be<lb/>
                the minister who performs not this duty, how base in him to increase<lb/> their
                afflictions with allusions foreign to the circumstances. It is<lb/> indeed in the
                hours of distress when sickness prostrates us &amp; when the<lb/> work of death has
                cast gloom &amp; desolation in our homes that the faith-<lb/>ful friend, such as the
                pastor is expected to be, mediates with kindness<lb/> &amp; endeavors to relieve the
                overburdened heart of its griefs. There is no circum<lb/>stance to justify his
                absence from the house of mourning, nothing<lb/> to extenuate such an utter neglect
                of the minister's most solemn<lb/> privilege. But it is not to be expected that the
                compact<lb/> between Pastor &amp; flock imposes obligations on the former only, -
                no<lb/> the Congregation has also its share of duties equally high &amp;
                impor-<lb/>tant, &amp; at the door of such as discard them blame must
                inevita<lb/>bly be attached, the minister's love &amp; kindness must find their
                coun-<lb/>terpart among his people &amp; cheerfully should they return <hi
                    rend="underline">the treat-</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">ment </hi>which he
                extends to them. The world's history<lb/> points to times when priesthood as a mass
                have been a curse to hu-<lb/>manity when they have stained their mission by their
                vices, their<lb/> ignorance &amp; tyranny, the prospects are that such such time are
                not<lb/> to return, still however it is our duty to check the growth of evil
                where-<lb/>ever it shows itself. The entire ministry is not yet what it<lb/> should
                be, still no one will deny its necessity &amp; that its influence<lb/> can be made
                most beneficial.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">5</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I therefore heartily approve of the suggestions cast forth by<lb/>
                you of establishing a Theological high school, &amp; whenever the work<lb/> is
                undertaken I offer to contribute my mite towards its proper<lb/> establishment,
                being convinced that it would prove of the highest<lb/> benefit to our religion
                &amp; finally be the means of adding pious &amp;<lb/> sincere ministers of the small
                number that we never have among<lb/> us. I trust not to have encroached on your
                valuable space &amp; that<lb/> my remarks hastily sketched will meet your approval,
                in fact<lb/> I know sufficient of you to be convinced that in your estimation<lb/> I
                have not overacted the duties of spiritual guide.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">With my renewed wishes for your welfare</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I am yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">Very Sincerely</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">A. Looker-on</persName>.</p>
            <p>
                <placeName>St. Thomas W I</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <date>9th December 1866</date>
            </p>
            <p>Postscript</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The foregoing was written about two months ago, but<lb/> owing to
                indisposition I could not before then, attend to its forwar-<lb/>ding.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
