<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF4_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Marcuson,
                            Mr.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p>Wax seal</p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>
                <addressee>Mr Marcusson</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">To the Editor of the Jewish Chronicle of <placeName>New
                    York</placeName></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I met with you <date>August</date>
                <add>?</add> at the house of one of my friends which, in<lb/> perusing I came to an
                article headed “Conversion<add>?</add>,” which speaking of the conversion<lb/> of
                certain Jews to Christianity, embraces my name among others, to my<lb/> grief,
                    <sic>surprize</sic> &amp; astonishment. My indignation might have been less,
                had<lb/> I given the least assent to your doctrines in the conversation I had<lb/>
                with some of your faith in <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>. But as I deem the
                whole system<lb/> of Christian faith little better than a dream, awaking fancy
                perhaps, and<lb/> nothing more, I am at less to imagine how you <add>?</add>
                could<lb/> do me the injustice to state I had changed my faith, one as
                    <add>?</add><lb/><add>?</add> as the God who first bestowed it on us through his servant<lb/>
                <persName>Moses</persName>. To a Jew nothing can be more disgraceful than being
                charged<lb/> with deserting his religion; and this disgrace this injustice you
                have<lb/> fastened on me in your unauthorized publication. In selecting
                <add>?</add><lb/> on his people God through his prophet called on a stiff necked
                genera<lb/>tion; but also He styled us a “Great nation, having wisdom &amp;
                understand<lb/>ing, which two elements are necessary in a rational religion, so as
                to<lb/> prevent us from believing every idle tale &amp; fiction which may be
                    retold<add>?</add><lb/> to us. I give you this information for your guidance,
                that you may not so<lb/> readily believe in time to come if you hear of the
                    conversion<add>?</add> of a Jew, espe<lb/>cially if he be one who has learned
                something; since Sir you may be sure,<lb/> that you hear a thing which slight not to
                be believed, or that he is one of the<lb/> most ignorant of his people.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now the only way I can account for the origin of the report is as
                follows:<lb/> the <del>person</del> missionary who sent you the letter in the
                    <add>?</add> of the above number came several<lb/> times to my residence, and we
                had several communications about religious mat<lb/>ters, and <add>?</add> he had the
                worst of the argument, as he will I hope<lb/> have the cand<add>?</add> to
                acknowledge for every interview we had he failed to answer</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>my objections; and once when we had argued before many people his best<lb/> reply was
                that <add>?</add> all the doctrine of the trinity is a <add>?</add>; “but it is<lb/>
                very plain to us,” I replied, and so it is, thank God, for we know that it<lb/> is
                not founded in fact nor revelation. After this he told me that<lb/> the minister of
                the city wished to become acquainted with me, and that they<lb/>
                <add>?</add> to learn Hebrew for which they would pay me; and so he recom<lb/>mended
                me to them. After I became a little better acquainted with them,<lb/> we often spoke
                together about religion, but I always had the last word,<lb/> they failing to
                maintain their side. On one occasion, after conversing<lb/> for some time, one of
                them took the liberty to tell me <del>?</del> on finding<lb/> himself unable to
                contend any farther with me, after this f<add>?</add>: “All<lb/> that you say is so
                high &amp; deep; but in religious matters it is only necess<lb/>ary to have faith
                (i.e. Only to believe whether there are good reasons for so<lb/> doing or not); and
                the only reason why you Jews do not believe in <persName>Jesus</persName><lb/> (I do
                not want to call him <persName>Christ</persName>, because he never was this and<lb/>
                never will be) is because you do not take the Bible in the true light,<lb/> and you
                are cursed that you shall have ears &amp; not hear, eyes &amp;<lb/> not see, a head
                and not understand.” This assertion hurt my<lb/> feelings deeply, and my heart was
                made sick, and I replied to him<lb/> “We were the first to whom the Almighty God
                delivered the Bible by the hands of<lb/>
                <persName>Moses</persName>, and you have obtained it solely from us; and if
                therefore if<lb/> you hear it, we hear it be a certainty; and still you dare to
                say<lb/> that you understand it in its true light! and have a better knowledge
                of<lb/> its contents than we!” After this I began to show them that not only<lb/>
                have they not the true light, but they have no light at all; and I proved<lb/> to
                them that <add>?</add>
                <persName>Dr. Clarke</persName> in his commentaries was in error, and did<lb/> not
                understand the true sense of the Hebrew.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Most of their conversation was about the Trinity; and the manner in
                which</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>they attempted to explain it to my understanding was truly ridiculous; and<lb/> I
                showed them that even of their own faith they do not know enough to help
                themselves,<lb/> and I was able to give them better reasons than theirs; but I
                proved to them<lb/> at the same time that their belief is false, and that it is not
                possible to believe<lb/> in three persons as the Deity; and if their <add>?</add>
                holds good, they either<lb/> believe in four or two gods; but three can never be
                one. I also demonstrated<lb/> to them that <add>?</add>
                <persName>Dr. Clarke</persName> established a plural in the <add>?</add><lb/> with
                the name of God, that he did not understand the meaning of the<lb/> words at all. I
                also explained to them in a correct manner the mean<lb/>ing of the word Shiloh (Gen.
                XIIX 101); let them repeat to you my answer;<lb/> and if they are not able to do so
                because it is “too high or deep” I will do<lb/> myself<lb/> so with pleasure at a
                later period, if God pleases to spare me</p>
            <p>In speaking of the crucifixion, I asked where this was predicted in the<lb/> Old
                Testament? The therefore presented me with a little book, (which<lb/> I shall
                carefully preserve,) wherein I read that this important event is<lb/> foretold in
                Deuteronomy XXI 22, 23; to which I <add>?</add> that if this be<lb/> so, I could
                frame no objection to this position. But I pray you to read<lb/> the first referred
                to; and I am sure you will agree with me,<lb/> that no Christian argument can be
                derived from it. The second<lb/> passage could in the one relating to the brazen
                serpent which <persName>Moses</persName><lb/> was ordered to make in the desert, of
                which it is said that it is a sign,<lb/> that “as the serpent was lifted up, so was
                    <persName>Jesus</persName> to be crucified.”<lb/> I then asked them whether they
                were satisfied to take the whole<lb/> history of the brazen serpent as a sign of
                    <persName>Jesus</persName>; since it would be im<lb/>proper to take the half
                only. They answered: “To be sure, we take the<lb/> whole history.” I expressed
                myself perfectly satisfied with this; but as I gave<lb/> them no reason for this,
                they perhaps thought that I was not able to an<lb/>swer; yet this however, thank
                God, is not the case; the reason for my</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>not saying more was, that the thing was too trifling to require<lb/> farther
                illustration. But as it seems that I was misunderstood,<lb/> I will now enter into
                farther details. In saying <hi rend="underline">the whole</hi> history,<lb/> I meant
                that of the lifting up of the serpent by <persName>Moses</persName> was a sign<lb/>
                of <persName>Jesus</persName>, the destruction of the serpent by the <persName>King
                    Hezekiah</persName> in 2 Kings<lb/> XVIII 4 must also be a sign of him, as after
                he had been crucified<lb/> he was buried and became dust like the rest of mankind.
                You<lb/> can find no more signs that either the serpent or its type arose<lb/> after
                this; and <add>?</add>
                <persName>Hezekiah</persName> called it “Nehushtan,” which<lb/> in your version
                    <del>if</del> is left untranslated; but I will tell you what<lb/> it means, it
                is a Hebrew word, and signifies a piece of brass<lb/> or copper. Now you can see who
                takes the Bible in a true light,<lb/> the Christians of the jews.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now I beg you do not make any more mistakes; I can show<lb/> you
                many things; but I do not wish to have a controversy, if<lb/> you do not provoke me
                again. I shall be perfectly satisfied with<lb/> this course; but if you like warfare
                better, I am ready to meet<lb/> you; but I advise you to take care that you do not
                provoke me<lb/> to write myself some of these days a commentary on the New<lb/>
                Testament; which I hope will be better than <persName>Dr. Clarke's</persName> at
                least it<lb/> shall be more in accordance with truth.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your reporter says that I shall become a faithful missionary;<lb/>
                certainly not in the sense which he wishes you to understand this:<lb/> but if you
                want <hi rend="underline">light</hi>, I am prepared to give it to you to the best
                of<lb/> my abilities, if you will but open your heart and mind to receive the<lb/>
                truth. And do not say that the Jews do not understand the scriptures<lb/> in their
                true light. I can refer you to <add>?</add> as regards<lb/> my qualifications; but
                after all I pray you to let me rest. I wish to live<lb/> in the faith of our <hi
                    rend="underline">ancient</hi> heavenly Father &amp; I desire to follow his<lb/>
                commandments; and though you say, “The law condemn us;” still do I<lb/> say, that it
                is the truth and everlasting life. Do you <add>?</add><lb/> as many persons as you
                like; I will call on the only true God<lb/> alone, for He is the sole saving Person,
                as He is the sole Creator<add>?</add>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
