<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Halevi, Joseph</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF17_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Halevi,
                            Joseph</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0005_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0005_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0005_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0005_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>
                <hi rend="underline">
                    <add>Hebrew</add>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">“Better is open reproof than secret love”</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">(Proverbs 27)</p>
            <p>(Ever since I came here this portion of <placeName>America</placeName>, the city of
                    <placeName>Cleveland</placeName>,<lb/> about 3 years ago, there came into my
                hand the book of the “Occident”,<lb/> containing all the interests of the Israelites
                of these lands, words of<lb/> truth and peace, announcing the news of various
                communities, their man-<lb/>ners and customs, and gathering also valuable speeches
                for the explana-<lb/>tion of the Scriptures, according to the depth of their
                meaning, and I<lb/> rejoiced as over great wealth to see the honored ones and the
                heads of<lb/> the communities arousing within themselves that jealousy which is
                dear<lb/> in the sight of God, namely the jealousy among writers through which<lb/>
                wisdom is increased).</p>
            <p>Note—the rest of this, which is evidently intended for the “Occident”,<lb/> is a
                learned exposition on the virtue of humility. The author seems to<lb/> be well
                versed in Talmudic and rabbinic learning. He quotes extensively<lb/> and on almost
                every line. The only passage of interest seems to be one<lb/> on the second page, in
                which the author gives the reason for writing the<lb/> article. It runs as
                follows:—</p>
            <p>Not long ago I read in the “Occident” for the month of <date>Shebat</date> just
                past,<lb/> a letter by the editor. It is long and valuable. In it he argues
                with<lb/> his opponen<del>e</del>t, the <persName>Rabbi Solomon Jacobs</persName>,
                the latter and complained bit<lb/>terly about him in the “Asmonean” because he had
                sent him his address<lb/> which had already been printed, and the editor of the
                “Occident”, after<lb/> praising him for his learning, had nevertheless found
                something to cri-<lb/>ticise about him. This is the reason why <persName>Mr.
                    Jacobs</persName> speaks harshly<lb/> about the editor, saying that his
                intention was to make him disdainful<lb/> in the eyes of the people and to hurt his
                dignity. He upbraids him with<lb/> insulting words and accuses him of not knowing
                the source of his address,<lb/> and says that he is a student who forgot what he has
                studied or that he<lb/> does not believe in the tradition of the sages. He bends his
                bow to<lb/> shoot his sharp arrows into the heart of the editor of the
                “Occident”,<lb/> and sharpens his sword, a sword of vengeance, to reveal his shame
                in all<lb/> the corners of the lands of <placeName>America</placeName>.
                    <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> answered him with words</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2</p>
            <p>of peace, that it was never his intention to disgrace him, and, at the<lb/> same
                time, shows his learning in the explanation of the verse in all its<lb/> branches,
                about which they are arguing,—According to the grammar of the<lb/> Hebrew language
                and by drawing from all the wells of the great ones of<lb/> our faith. I, knowing
                    <sic>thesmallness</sic> of my worth, do not come to decide<lb/> between them.
                For, as I said above, it is possible for both to be corre<lb/><sic>rect</sic>.
                Besides, the matter does not touch upon a law of action, and among<lb/> us it is a
                rule that one must not question a Midrashic interpretation.<lb/> But for this reason
                my soul signs in secret, that the fire of dissension<lb/> has broken out among the
                profound scholars and the flame of quarrels has<lb/> gone up to heaven. Instead of
                literary jealousy, there has come its de-<lb/>spised sister, the jealousy for honor,
                the envy of man for his friend.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Jacobs</persName> has opened wide his mouth and prides himself by
                saying, “My lips<lb/> are with me, I shall make <sic>marsh</sic> my tongue, the time
                for peace has set, the<lb/> day of vengeance has arrived”, for this reason the heart
                of every under-<lb/>standing man aches. Who has seen such things in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>? This is not<lb/> the way of the Torah, whose ways
                are the ways of sweetness, and all its<lb/> paths are peace,<sic>etc.</sic></p>
            <p>The letter is signed <persName role="author">Joseph Halevi</persName>, merchant in
                the city of <placeName>Cleveland</placeName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
