<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Henry, H. A.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF9_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Henry, H. A.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>San Francisco, CA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1862-06">10 June 1862</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f9_0015_3v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>
                <date>June 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1862</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dr Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">You must not think me<lb/> neglectful in not having written to you
                before<lb/> this. Many things at times prevent me from <lb/>writing at the time and
                then it passes over.<lb/> No doubt ere this you have received a Letter<lb/> from
                    <persName>Mr Myers</persName> and with it the receipt signed<lb/> by me of the
                Books he placed in my possession<lb/> on sale for you. I shall try and do my
                best<lb/> to dispose of them for you. The prices here are<lb/> too high there are so
                few buyers, please let<lb/> me know positively the lowest price at which<lb/> I may
                sell, so that I can act safely and I<lb/> will do all I can. I hope you received
                my<lb/> parcel by <persName>Rabbi Nissan</persName> if you can send me<lb/> any more
                of the Back Nos for which I wrote<lb/> you will oblige me, at the same time
                have<lb/> you any whole <hi rend="underline">Nos</hi> as 1-2-3-4-5-6-7-8<lb/> I have
                none of these Vols. I should like to have<lb/> them either bound or unbound I shall
                then<lb/> be the only <hi rend="underline">one</hi> in the <placeName>Pacific
                    Coast</placeName> who will<lb/> have a regular file of them. Of course I
                will</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>pay for them. Please let me know what I<lb/> owe you up to the present, and I will
                hand<lb/> it to <persName>Mr Myers</persName> to whom I have spoken on<lb/> the
                subject. Religious matters here are of<lb/> no importance, all is quiet. Your
                    <date>April</date>
                <hi rend="underline">No</hi><lb/> caused a great consternation among a certain<lb/>
                class who were delighted to find that these acts<lb/> were made known to the world,
                altho' they are<lb/> not able to prevent them of course the Gleaner<lb/> has its
                supporters as there are so many<lb/> who will do wrong in spite of every thing<lb/>
                you will no doubt see how the Gleaner<lb/> answers for itself. Not one thing
                satisfactory<lb/> because as you know <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> still we must do our
                duty. The Letter<lb/> which he inserts is from one of the ladies<lb/> whom I refused
                to marry. I have no<lb/> doubt that the Gleaner managed this<lb/> matter to be
                    <add>?</add>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> but the truth was not stated therein and<lb/> if even all was
                true, what right had<lb/>
                <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> to marry her. He certainly does<lb/> not think I am
                greater than he is to act<lb/> in opposition to a Law because I or<lb/> any man
                ventures an opinion, which you<lb/> yourself can see how he shirks the question.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Many here surmise that I inform you of<lb/> all that passes—but I do not wish my
                name<lb/> to appear for many reasons—especially as<lb/> some of my members and other
                of the <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> are friends to the Gleaner, and have pity on the poor
                old man as they call him x<lb/> that encourages him in all his doings—<lb/> I shall
                still inform you of all that passes<lb/> because I do think that ultimately by
                so<lb/> doing we shall in time affect some good<lb/> In the pulpit I speak of these
                things fearlessly<lb/> I will send you a sermon I preached on<lb/> the <date>1<hi
                        rend="sup">st</hi></date> day <add>Hebrew</add> by which you will see<lb/>
                that I do as I say and act upon the principle<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>. <persName>Eckman</persName> does all he can to<lb/> injure me in
                the minds of the people as<lb/> my Election is only from year to year but<lb/> I
                tell my folks that my <add>Hebrew</add> is in God x<lb/> not in man, even the
                Reformers hold<lb/> me in respect altho' I tell them of their<lb/> wrongs.
                    <sic>even</sic>
                <persName>Dr Cohn</persName> will not do such<lb/> things as these men do. He works
                hard with<lb/> me to get the people to keep <add>Hebrew</add> . I have<lb/>
                succeeded in one or two instances and I hope<lb/> in time we shall do more—but it is
                very difficult<lb/> the Dollars &amp; cents are the main thing with<lb/> our people
                here—still we must do our duty</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I must give you Credit for the very able<lb/> note you appended to the article
                &amp;<lb/> I can assure you that all the <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> here were pleased
                with it in the<lb/> hope that we may be <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <add>Hebrew</add>
            </p>
            <p>some people here think that we should not<lb/> publish such matters as it brings us
                into<lb/> disrepute before the world and exposes<lb/> our religion to ridicule, they
                say better let<lb/> us chose between the two evils, and they<lb/> think that the
                    “<hi rend="underline">wrong doings</hi>” is the lesser<lb/> evil. I tell them
                plainly I differ from<lb/> them entirely upon the principle</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">“<add>Hebrew</add>”</p>
            <p>and I feel assured that you think with<lb/> me in this respect and I should be
                pleased<lb/> if you think well of it to publish your<lb/> sentiments on the subject
                I will keep<lb/> you posted on all matters of any interest<lb/> Both congregations
                were well attended in<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>. I am told that <persName>Dr Cohn</persName> delivered a<lb/> very
                impressive sermon in confirming a<lb/> number of Boys and Girls upon the new
                System<lb/> in the Reform World. My sermon I will send<lb/> you and judge for
                yourself my folks were very much<lb/> pleased. We had a Boy <add>Hebrew</add> on the
                        <date>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi></date> day of</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">/5</p>
            <p><add>Hebrew</add>. And read the <add>Hebrew</add> in the<lb/> old Orthodox Style to a
                crowded auditory<lb/> which gave great satisfaction. I still and<lb/> will adhere to
                our good old times and<lb/> will suffer no innovation, and I am happy<lb/> to say
                that with few exceptions my <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> support me in this respect,
                altho' at<lb/> times I have to go into the Battle field<lb/> but I will and do not
                flinch. The Gleaner<lb/> being the only Jewish Organ here sometimes<lb/> rouses up
                one or two who go abroad<lb/> and say this is old and out of tune and<lb/> that
                causes mischief. I heed them not<lb/> and when I reason with them they are<lb/>
                silenced. I am so far fortunate that the<lb/> Board of Trustees tho' individually
                not<lb/> very ultra Orthodox yet they will not allow<lb/> any one to interfere with
                me in the synagogue<lb/> service, at the head of them is our <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                an Englishman who has held office for<lb/> many years who is really a stanch
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> and who never neglects to be in<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> whenever service is performed<lb/> our <add>Hebrew</add> is opened
                every <add>Hebrew</add> and<lb/> three times an <add>Hebrew</add> and there you
                find<lb/> the <add>Hebrew</add> at his port and this has a</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>powerful influence with the congregation<lb/> in general when they see the
                President<lb/> setting the good example the old adage<lb/> “<add>Hebrew</add>”<lb/>
                The charitable Institutions among us<lb/> are flourishing and do much good<lb/> the
                people are certainly ready at all times<lb/> to dispense charity and that too
                liberally.<lb/> I believe now my dear sir I have<lb/> exhausted all my sources of
                information<lb/> and I hope I have not exhausted<lb/> your patience to read my long
                epistle<lb/> but I suppose you are like me at<lb/> times glad to get something fresh
                from<lb/> abroad however trifling</p>
            <p>I leave you now in the hope that<lb/> this will reach you in health of mind<lb/> and
                Body and expect to hear from<lb/> you soon</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Believe me</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">H. A. Henry</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
