<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF6_3</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Montreal, Canada</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f6_0003_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f6_0003_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f6_0003_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f6_0003_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>

								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Montreal</placeName> <add>Hebrew</add></p>
				<p><addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Dear Friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Having a few minutes leisure before<lb/> synagogue I embrace it gladly to reply to your last which<lb/> for my inclination has remained too long unanswered. I regret<lb/> much that you did not order my article to be altered as I requested<lb/> you&#44; since it will force me to continue the said article to a greater<lb/> length than agreeable to me. But as you say it was unavoidably so<lb/> I must be content.  You are mistaken however if you think I don&#39;t<lb/> know what inconvenience it causes to alter a form. I have seen<lb/> a great deal of printing in my time and have corrected more than<lb/> one proof for the press. My dear <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> you must not again<lb/> write me &#8220;I am a little tired of a work that brings me nothing<lb/> but vexation&#8221; You are yet too young in your vocation to cry<lb/> with <persName>Solomon</persName> &#8212; <add>Hebrew</add> nor can<lb/> you with any truth say with him <add>Hebrew</add> no such<lb/> thing&#44; dear friend&#44; you <hi rend="underline">are</hi> appreciated if not by <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; yet by<lb/> all those whose good <add>&#63;</add> is worth having. You&#44; no doubt&#44;<lb/> with me&#44; think one roar of the lion more agreeable than 50 brays<lb/> of the jackass. And these roars of the lions &#40;not of <placeName>New York</placeName> or<lb/> <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#41; you have. What more then do you want&#63; Is it assistance&#44;<lb/> look through your vol. 6&#44; and see whether I have not done<lb/> my share.  I never asked any other return than what you chose<lb/> to give me. Your favorable opinion was enough for me.<lb/> You are not a Saxon&#44; don&#39;t be a grumbler then but continue<lb/> like a good boy at your task. If you continue to perform it as<lb/> properly as heretofore&#44; the <hi rend="underline">Sugarphim</hi><add>&#63;</add> shall not be long in coming</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>neglect it and expect to receive what we used to style in our<lb/> Hebrew school &#8212; palackas.  I promise you that the first one<lb/> you get shall be from from the hand &#40;if it be alive&#41; that is now<lb/> perusing these words.  So look out. Now I shall give you a little<lb/> more vexation in respect to the Occident &#224; la <persName>Carondle<add>&#63;</add></persName>&#59; A pretty Editor<lb/> you are <persName>Mr. I.</persName>  I should like to know how you expect to keep<lb/> a subscriber when you send your numbers so irregularly. Here is the<lb/> half of <date>April</date> over and your Canadian subscribers have not yet<lb/> received either their <date>March</date> or <date>April</date> numbers. Pretty <add>&#63;</add> truly.<lb/>  I <hi rend="underline">guess</hi> your news will be pretty stale to them&#44; And then the<lb/> circular that was to go with them&#44; why how can we know what&#39;s<lb/> going on. The Proposed assembly may be no longer a proposed assembly<lb/> but have already taken place to and we poor unfortunate neglected<lb/> and abandoned creatures know nothing of it If this isn&#39;t enough<lb/> to make a person swear I don&#39;t know what is. Take care<lb/> your eyes for if they get near my nails <persName>Mr I</persName> I don&#39;t know<lb/> what the consequences might not be &#8212; but really you<lb/> must be a little more regular in sending them i.e. in getting<lb/> your agent in <placeName>New York</placeName> to do so&#44; for I hear it is his fault.<lb/>  It is doubly disagreeable for a correspondent to receive them so<lb/> late as there might be some Er<add>&#63;</add> to be made in his<lb/> article which he would like to send forth next number.<lb/>  I shall say no more about it now because I hope that you<lb/> will take steps to let us have them in future by the <date>6th</date> or <date>7th</date> of<lb/> the month. I shall write to <placeName>England</placeName> the<add>&#63;</add> endeavor to press the<lb/> sale of these. I don&#39;t think you have a good agent in <persName>Mrs Joel</persName><lb/>  She lives in <placeName>F<add>&#63;</add>  Street</placeName> which is entirely out of the world<lb/> and especially out of the Jewish world. I think <persName>Sam&#39;<lb/> Solomons</persName> of <placeName>Bevis Marks</placeName> would be able to push the sale</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>better. Did you ever try him&#63;  Not having received the <date>March</date><lb/> Occident I have not seen the circular.  As soon as received I shall<lb/> call a meeting of the congregation and we will doubtless not be<lb/> needful.  I am a <hi rend="underline">little vext</hi> at the delay of the Occident this <add>&#63;</add><lb/> There is no other congregation in <placeName>Canada</placeName> but the <add>&#63;</add> in <placeName>Montreal</placeName><lb/> and the German one that formerly existed <hi rend="underline">is on its last legs</hi>. They<lb/> were but a poor and troublesome set who lately composed it<lb/> neither ornamental nor useful in a synagogue above all in a<lb/> Portuguese synagogue the <add>Hebrew</add> of which they &#8220;<add>&#63;</add>.&#8221;<lb/>  As for my long being inclined to support the assembly without<lb/> being able to say <add>&#63;</add> with <persName>Dr. Cantwell</persName> I can lead the<lb/> poor deluded men where I please&#8221; I think I shall be able to<lb/> induce within them a <sic>favourable</sic> opinion on these matters.<lb/> If you don&#39;t go to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> I shall expect you in <placeName>Canada</placeName><lb/> this summer. Let me know whether you come  and I will<lb/> prepare a room for you in my house which is next door<lb/> to <persName>Mrs Josephs</persName>.  <persName>Mr and Mrs JHJ</persName>  and <persName>Miss Sarah J</persName> start<lb/> <date>Sunday</date>&#44; I believe for the <placeName>States</placeName>. Is it true that <persName>Nathan</persName><lb/> has given up his situation in <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> and is now in <placeName>New<lb/> Orleans</placeName> with <persName>Carillon<add>&#63;</add></persName> also.  That this letter worthy who<lb/> is required by all as a madman should care to look for<lb/> another nest&#44; I am not at all surprised for he has made the<lb/> <placeName>West Indies</placeName> &#8220;too hot to hold him&#8221; but <persName>Mr. Nathan</persName> what<lb/> does he run about for.  I can&#39;t help thinking that it is<lb/> a great pity he ever gave up his situation in <placeName>Kingston</placeName>. I<lb/> sincerely hope that those congregations wanting a Hazan in<lb/> the <placeName>States</placeName> will be especially carefully of <persName>Carillon<add>&#63;</add></persName>.  He has<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> discord wherever he has been &#8212; and will continue to<lb/> do so wherever he goes. And then his principles&#44; as <sic>accomodating</sic></p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>as the weather cock to every puff of wind. I hope that you<lb/> will keep your eye upon him&#44; and <hi rend="underline">look to the interests</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">of our cause</hi>. You will understand me. I never saw <persName>Carillon</persName><lb/> in my life have never corresponded with him but what I do<lb/> know of him as a Rabbi and Teacher I can&#39;t admire. And more<lb/>  I ask you keep your eye on him. With respect to the situation<lb/> at <placeName>Richmond</placeName> I have written to <persName>Mr. Hyman</persName> for farther particulars but<lb/> I confess more with the intention of ascertaining whether the situation<lb/> as worthy the acceptance of my brother in law Hazan <persName>Mendes</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Montego Bay</placeName>.  He is a most worthy &#38;  talented young man&#44; a gentleman<lb/> and scholar and quite orthodox. I would like him to be near me<lb/> I did not mention names to <persName>Mr. Hyman</persName> nor does <persName>Mr Mendes</persName> know<lb/> that I have written. I need scarcely tell you then that the name<lb/> is to continue <add>Hebrew</add>.  I am glad to see that I have not been too severe<lb/> in forming my estimate of the attainments of <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> of <placeName>New York</placeName><lb/> I agree with you in considering that the &#40;his brother I <sic>dont</sic> know<lb/> is not one who ought to be at the head of a Congregation in the<lb/> present state of things. His surprising land<add>&#63;</add> I say with all my<lb/> heart&#44; most lamentable that with such a field before him he has<lb/> not done more to make our religion more respectable among his<lb/> flock. I asked you to insert my sermon in your <add>&#63;</add> because it would have<lb/> been read with more interest with the <date>Passover</date> but do with<lb/> it what you please. It is not so formidable thing to write a sermon<lb/> Having now replied to your letter in full I shall send you one or two<lb/> news items if indeed you have not already received them.<lb/> I expected<add>&#63;</add> writing you more fully but I must break off<lb/> I milk will write by <persName>Mr Joseph</persName> wishing you all blessings and prosperity</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Believe me yours ever faithfully</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
