<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF11_2</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0002_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0002_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0002_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0002_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Methinks I hear you say what<lb/> a miserable correspondent my friend has become<lb/> or has the scythe of time <add>&#63;</add> down her<lb/> energies or has absence rendered her indifferent<lb/> to her old friends.  Neither kind sir&#44; but Sickness<lb/> which is beyond our control has made me a delin<lb/>quent in every thing but sincerity. I have had many<lb/> of my immediate family confined to the bed with sickness<lb/> &#38; have been ill myself &#38; have continued to feel its<lb/> debilitating influence.  But as <persName>Mrs Chick</persName> says in <persName>Dombey</persName><lb/> &#8220;I must make an effort&#8221; or my friends will lay me<lb/> aside as a thing that has been&#33;  In truth I begin to<lb/> think <placeName>Charleston</placeName> does not agree with me spiritually or<lb/> bodily in a city ones thoughts turn naturally into the<lb/> channels in which flows the thoughts of those around them<lb/> In the country what one hears &#38; sees suggests entirely dif<lb/>ferent mediations The universal harmony of nature<lb/> stills our fretted passions all the eye rests on speaks<lb/> of infinite wisdom &#38; providential care &#38; we feel<lb/> that we can commune with nature &#38; with natures<lb/> God with more deep devotion &#38; more pious faith<lb/> my Son has been confined for a month &#38; required<lb/> my sole attendance &#38; as <persName>Sarah</persName> <add>&#63;</add> was absent I had<lb/> every thing devolving on myself.  My daughter has<lb/> returned &#38; although not well is much improved &#38;<lb/> <persName>Philip</persName> is again at his business.  So &#8220;<persName>Richard</persName> is himself<lb/> again&#8221;</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>you have had my friend &#38; cousin <persName>A Moise</persName> with you he<lb/> wrote you were pleased to name me in warm terms<lb/> of friendship for which accept my thanks. The approba<lb/>tion of the world pleasant but a thousand times<lb/> more so is the commendation of an enlightened &#38; intelligent<lb/> friend &#8212; I heard with deep regret that my friend <persName>R Hart</persName> had<lb/> been ill&#44; tender her my warmest sympathies tell her<lb/> I will write as soon as I can&#44; without the form of a reply<lb/> to my last. I often wish I could in more powerful language<lb/> than profession&#44; manifest my deep affection for that pure<lb/> &#38; meritorious couple&#33; but that could jade makes me<lb/> niggard in all but affection. Adversity is a shrewd<lb/> taskmistress&#44; a mighty moral <sic>leveller</sic>&#44; how it teaches us to appre&#45;<lb/>ciate kindness &#38; to discover friends where we had only<lb/> discerned inferiors&#33;  It is the Jewel <sic>shiek</sic> out of the<lb/> ugliness &#38; venom of the heart. I have not tasted of<lb/> the draught as <hi rend="underline">deeply</hi> as many more <hi rend="underline">deserving</hi> but<lb/> sufficiently so to value those friends who love me<lb/> for the little merit I posses &#38; not for the gilding<lb/> that adorns the picture&#33;  I am happy in writing that<lb/> my sister is enjoying good health after so much of<lb/> bodily &#38; mental suffering. She has not yet recovered<lb/> her spirits her deep seated affection for our departed<lb/> brother&#44; still renders her indifferent to society in fact<lb/> it is so painful for her even to come &#38; pass a day <lb/> with me that except in sickness I do not eseach<add>&#63;</add><lb/> it the full check &#38; the sparkling eye of early youth do<lb/> not tell their tale of suffering like the worn fea&#45;<lb/>tures of after years <add>&#63;</add> although Sis is not old yet</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>sorrow has left its withering influence on her mind&#33;<lb/> Well <persName>Mr. Tobias</persName> has another daughter engaged <persName>Priscilla</persName><lb/> the devotee to forms &#38; ceremonies has o&#39;er leaped them<lb/> all&#33; &#38; engaged herself to <persName>L Myers</persName> such are the inconsisten<lb/>cies of human beings&#59; at her time of life there is not the<lb/> excuse of passion subduing reason &#38; I expect there was<lb/> more <hi rend="underline">matter</hi> than <hi rend="underline">mind</hi>&#44; in the compact which<lb/> holds them together. She represents him par excellen<lb/>ce as the man of piety &#38; love for a religion. She knows<lb/> nothing of this is &#40;entre nous&#41; as I am intimate with<lb/> the family &#38; fond of them &#38; would not willingly hurt<lb/> their feelings. I do hope &#38; pray that the Holy Shrine<lb/> of Home&#44; which should be wreathed with blossoms<lb/> may not be heaped with ice &#38; the only garland which<lb/> renders it attractive&#44; beaten out of cold &#38; sordid gold<lb/> I presume among the <add>&#63;</add> you have heard of the application<lb/> we have had to fill the place of our valued minister<lb/> from his own &#38; the <persName>Rabbi Guiste&#39;s</persName> recommendation he is<lb/> par  parenthese the very beau ideal of all that hum&#45;<lb/>an desire could covet but I am perfectly content<lb/> with the one we have &#38; desire no change &#8212; still<lb/> I remain <hi rend="underline">quiet</hi> as if I am not so small a <hi rend="underline">fish</hi> as to move<lb/> among my adversaries without threatening the water<lb/> If you desire further information relative to this <add>&#63;</add><lb/> of the <date>19th century</date> I will give it you in my next<lb/> I do pray that if he comes among us he will inspire<lb/> more <hi rend="underline">zeal</hi> than now exists among the Jews of <placeName>Charles<lb/>&#45;ton</placeName> it seems to me they aim at doing the least<lb/> possible <hi rend="underline">good</hi> in the longest <hi rend="underline">possible time</hi>.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>my remarks are not to be handed about as a relish for<lb/> the tea table for I <hi rend="underline">aim</hi> at being <hi rend="underline">good</hi>&#44; but by some<lb/> unfortunate propensity I sometimes forget the character<lb/> I wish to be &#38; shew the one I am &#38; a little of the<lb/> venom of frail nature will shew itself although<lb/> regret comes as soon as it is expressed &#38; therefore<lb/> I am more cautious in society than in writing. For<lb/> custom has placed a padlock on the lips of women<lb/> of which society keeps the key &#38; therefore we must not<lb/> say all we feel or think.  My family both white &#38; <sic>coloured</sic><lb/> seem to suffer by the change from <placeName>Georgia</placeName> to <placeName>Carolina</placeName><lb/> I hope after this summer their health will be better<lb/> my own health has been delicate all summer &#38; I<lb/> crave change of air &#38; scene in fact I require repose of<lb/> mind &#38; body for the duties which devolve on me are<lb/> no sincere  I assure you.  I have a great big <add>&#63;</add> of<lb/> hope which sustains me &#38; hope on hope ever is my<lb/> motto &#38; the world I suppose think my path should<lb/> with Rose leaves &#38; as appearances are the current<lb/> coin of the World I watch over them as the miser<lb/> watches his hoarded gold&#44; while scribbling this I have<lb/> had so many interruptions that I must close<lb/> an <add>&#63;</add> after assuring you of the regards<lb/> of family &#38; the sincerity of your friend.</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">R. C. Moise</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
