<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Wolff, A.</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>Box 1, FF4</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF4_1</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Wolff, A.</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1847-7" source="" attested="yes">2 July 1847</dateLet>
              
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0001_1r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0001_1v.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0001_2r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0001_2v.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0002_1r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0002_1v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p>Wax seal</p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
		<text>
		<body>
		<pb n="1"/>
		
		<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>St Thomas</placeName> <date>2 July 1847</date>  private</p>
		<p><addressee>Revd Mr Leeser</addressee></p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Phila</placeName></p>
		  <p rend="indent(2)">Dr Sir</p>
		  <p rend="indent(3)">Your letter of <date>12 Nov&#44; 11 Dec &amp; 4 Jany</date> are<lb/> before me  I would have been[&#63;] replied to before this but really I<lb/> have been &amp; am still so occupied that I could not spare time<lb/> before&#44; the affairs of our Congregation have been extremely<lb/> heavy for me as you shall find&#44; I will firstly reply to your<lb/> letter of <date>Dec.</date>  You are quite correct when you state that I<lb/> am interested for you.  I have always been&#44; &amp; am so still&#44; this<lb/> has been the reason of my always writing you in the <sic>stile</sic> I do.<lb/>  I regret to find that you had been so indisposed.  I <sic>hurt</sic> that<lb/> your health has since been perfectly re&#45;established.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr Nans.[&#63;]</persName> and myself are at variance&#44; because at<lb/> his arrival I placed every confidence in him as an old friend<lb/> &amp; a man being alike friendly to myself as well as to the party<lb/> appeared to me&#44; &amp; one to when I considered devoted the duty of<lb/> interfering &amp; reconciling all the evils of the <sic>hart</sic>&#44; but in<lb/> stead of that<lb/> he inserted[&#63;] himself under the banner and did<lb/> all he could to annoy &amp; vex <del>him</del> me&#44; being then in appearance<lb/> friendly disposed&#44; he concocted a letter which <persName>Dr Peixotto</persName> signed as President<lb/> Addressed to the head of the Commission for framing the new laws<lb/> in which he reviled me shamefully.  I attacked him upon it<lb/> &amp; he acknowledged it&#59; for this &amp; other reasons I withdrew from him<lb/> &amp; not only myself but other highly respectable members of the<lb/> congregation lost the opinion they held of him&#44; he then became<lb/> a leader of the party&#59; &amp; continued to do all he could to annoy&#44;<lb/> this led him to be in[&#63;] agreement <persName>M Nathan</persName> as well as to<lb/> myself&#44; making use of no measured language&#44; calling him a<lb/> Counting Priest &amp;c.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">I have written you so fully in the benefits</p>
		

		<pb n="2"/>
		
		<p>of confirmation that I will add what has really come<lb/> under my notice&#44; there was 3 entire families here&#44; who previously<lb/> to <persName>Mr Carillons [&#63;]</persName>&#44; &amp; were on the eve of apostatizing&#44; his<lb/> instructions for the confirmation &amp; private arguments completely<lb/> brought them back to their duty.  I have since had the pleasure<lb/> of beholding its Moral &amp; Religious effects upon the Young<lb/> people who now venerate their religion because they begin to<lb/> understand it.  it is only a few whose opinions are lax<lb/> and are desirous of helping their children in ignorance of true<lb/> religion that are so violently opposed to it because they are<lb/> afraid that their children will reproach them for not keeping<lb/> the <date>Sabbath</date> &amp; holy days which is strictly enforced in the<lb/> Catechism&#44; the proof that it is well received is&#44; that <persName>Mr<lb/> Nathan</persName> will confirm 14 young people in <date>Passover</date>.  I am sorry<lb/> that we do not agree upon this point&#44; for experience has confined<lb/> my opinion of its benefits &amp; I am resolved to promote it with<lb/> all my might.  <persName>Mr Nathan</persName> would have replied but the<lb/> man has been so annoyed by the conduct of <persName>Simmonds</persName> &amp; his<lb/> party that I do not for the life of me know how he could<lb/> get thro&#39; his duties as well as he did&#44; added to it&#44; we<lb/> have a heavy task to get through the new laws&#44; the heaviest<lb/> part falling upon himself &amp; myself;&#8211;I saw him last night&#44;<lb/> he promises to reply very soon.&#8211;By the Bye I have never<lb/> secured the Occident for <date>September</date>.  Please to forward it.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">I now come to our Congregational Matters under the<lb/> Administration of <persName>Simmonds</persName> &amp; his friends.  I informed you of<lb/> the abuses of power in some cases&#44; these continued so<lb/> long&#44; &amp; new ones were added that enacted[&#63;] a great stir in the<lb/> Congregation &amp; very many that had been opposed to me&#44; now<lb/> saw that the reports they were against me were false&#59; at<lb/> length <persName>Simmonds</persName> quitted the Island for the purpose of<lb/> marrying her Brother with a lady at <placeName><sic>Caracao </sic></placeName>&#44; by which the</p>
		

		<pb n="3"/>
		
		<p>the administration of the Synagogue was only left in the<lb/> hands of 4 instead of 7 persons&#8212;5 of the body forming a<lb/> quorum&#44; two of the members at the election refused to act &amp;<lb/> never did as long as the Quorum was complete no one opposed<lb/> the legality.&#8211;but at <persName>Simmonds</persName> leaving&#44; he with the 4 others<lb/> balloted [&#63;] out of 2 instead of 4 Wardens as the law orders<lb/> to fill the place of President&#59; now previous to balloting for<lb/> a new the old President must resign&#44; as soon as he did<lb/> this&#44; the body was reduced to 4 which were not a quorum &amp;<lb/> had not the power of doing any business&#44; consequently the<lb/> balloting was illegal&#59; the most respectable members of<lb/> the Congregation represented the business to [&#63;] &amp; showed<lb/> the necessity of the Government of the Congregation being filled<lb/> up &amp; of a new election for that purpose &#40;the laws of the<lb/> Congregation does not provide for such a state of things&#44;&#41;<lb/> the Government who knew I were heartily disgusted with<lb/> all the proceedings of the entire party since the affair<lb/> with <persName>Carellion</persName> who saw how every thing had gone to [&#63;]<lb/>[&#63;]&#44; &amp; who know that these people were improper ones to<lb/> be in the Government&#44; appointed me President &amp; Messrs<lb/> O[&#63;] &amp; <persName>Fidangree[&#63;]</persName> Wardens&#44; &amp; then ordered an entire new<lb/> election of 7. this the 4 Remaining of <persName>Simmonds</persName> Administration<lb/> protested against&#44; &amp; as the were the majority I could not carry<lb/> out the Government order&#44; I informed Government of it &amp; sent in<lb/> the protest&#44; the Governor immediately dismissed them from their<lb/> offices &amp; placed <persName>Miss Rothschild</persName>&#44; <persName>Dr DeCortz</persName>&#44; <persName>Dr Monsato</persName><lb/> &amp; <persName>Isaac Pritt[&#63;]</persName> in their stead the Board to  continue until<lb/> further orders&#58;&#8211;we found the affairs in a very bad &amp;<lb/> neglected state&#44; the circular they published was proved to be<lb/> incorrect in all its parts&#44; the Synagogue was in need of repair<lb/> the [&#63;] at the Burial Ground in a very bad state&#44; and<lb/> [&#63;] the minister &amp; every other officer in credit.  The Minister</p>
		

		<pb n="4"/>
		
		<p>for 6 months pay as well as the other officers&#44; we required<lb/> $1200 over &amp; above the Taxes to make the Synagogue clear&#44;<lb/> in consequence we determined to call a meeting of the<lb/> congregation &amp; lay before the members an expose &#40;I could<lb/> get the sum required by [&#63;] pay $250 per year&#41; previous<lb/> to having any idea of calling a general meeting&#44; I wrote<lb/> a letter to <persName>Nans</persName> proposing a reconciliation of all that had<lb/> passed &amp; asking him to use his influence with those over<lb/> whom I know he had influence to forget &amp; bury the past<lb/> remote[&#63;] for the general good.  I did this for the common<lb/> good&#44; with no view to my particular standing&#44; because I<lb/> was already at the head of the Congregation placed there by<lb/> government&#44; &amp; consequently not in need of the suffrages of<lb/> any one&#8212;the act was purely religious&#8212;his reply was of<lb/> a nature that in time will make him feel regret &amp; a<lb/> refusal; except upon terms that could never have been<lb/> acceded to by any will in either of the congregation&#44; he<lb/> wanted us to go back&#8212;only have Readers without pulpit<lb/> instruction&#44; to do away with Taxes &amp; substitute offerings<lb/> to them upon the religiously inclined the whole <sic>burthen</sic> of<lb/> maintaining the establishment&#44; at length the meeting<lb/> took place at that meeting he and the arguments quoted<lb/> which was met by a vote of 3 to 1&#44; against him&#44; &amp; his party<lb/> of 10 persons&#44; he promises that affairs shall be worse than</p>
		

		<pb n="5"/>
		
		<p>ever&#44; then you see his conduct&#44; the Governor being very<lb/> much displeased with his &amp; <del>his</del> party&#39; doings did not invite<lb/> any one of them to a Ball he gave for some Dutch Naval<lb/> Officers&#44; this has made him more furious&#44; but thank God<lb/> he cannot injure altho he may annoy&#44; you can form no<lb/> idea of the trouble I have had to re&#45;arrange the affairs.<lb/>  the Synagogue is under repair&#44; the Burial House will be&#44; the<lb/> people beg me to pay their taxes.  <persName>Mr Nathan</persName> has consented<lb/> to leave his Salary &amp; in a little time the Sunday School will<lb/> be again alone&#8212;in spite of the distractions</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">Pray send me the [&#63;] Volume of the Pentateuch in<lb/> place of the one that was injured &amp; returned we shall soon<lb/> require it.  The new Laws will go into Government in the<lb/> Month.  I have no time to recapitulate all the insults to<lb/> <persName>Mr Nathan</persName>&#44; <persName>Mr Bay</persName> had a circumcision at his house&#44; he<lb/> wrote to inform me &amp; stated that he did not require the<lb/> services of the Minister&#44; insulting him thus publicly.  <persName>Bay</persName> is<lb/> <persName>Naan</persName> son in law</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">I regret to state that my son <persName>Moses</persName> has been<lb/> obliged to take his name off of the list of subscribers to the<lb/> Occident for the ensuing Year&#44; business having gone bad with<lb/> him&#44; 3d [&#63;] <persName>Naan</persName> refused to pay his tax yesterday.  I<lb/> will not enforce it by law as I am determined to do the<lb/> opposite of that which he &amp; party desire.  I will be moderate<lb/> &amp; put up with their opposition as far as I can without<lb/> creating more bad feeling&#44; it is awful to live among such<lb/> bad spirits&#59;&#8211;you can suppose that neither himself for any of<lb/> his party of 10 came to the Synagogue&#44; they cannot be accused<lb/> of having done often previously&#8211;</p>
		  <p rend="indent(2)">With best wishes I am My Dr Sir</p>
		  <p rend="indent(3)">Yours truly</p>
		  <p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">A Wolff</persName></p>
		

		<pb n="6"/>
		
		<p><addressee>Revd Mr Leeser</addressee></p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philada</placeName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>