<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Miller, M. R.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx9FF14_8</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Miller, M. R.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1851-01" source="" attested="yes">15 January 1851</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_2r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_2v.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>acceptable penitent&#59; and&#44; thirdly&#44; the improbability that the law will<lb/> free the transgressor from its curse merely on the ground that he<lb/> has repented.  The inquiry now is What is the round of merit or of<lb/> satisfaction&#44; on which according to the Sacred Scriptures God pardons<lb/> sin&#63;  If the threatened penalty cannot be dispensed with&#44; either we<lb/> must suffer it ourselves or some other must suffer in our<lb/> place.  If the first threatening that in the day of the eating of the<lb/> forbidden fruit <persName>Adam</persName> should die&#44; exhibits the standard measure of<lb/> all the penalties of disobedience&#44; or if we may discover the common<lb/> measure in the appointment that the man who should eat the for&#61;<lb/>bidden bread during the <date>Passover</date> should be cut off from the con&#61;<lb/>gregation of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; or if the penalty of each of the ten command&#61;<lb/>ments is death&#44; we cannot suffer for ourselves the penalty&#44; except in<lb/> our hopeless death or moral ruin.  The cup of the wrath of God is<lb/> not to be exhausted by our sinful lips.  It is the challenge of God to<lb/> every impenitent sinner&#58; &#8220;Can thine heart endure&#44; or can thine hands<lb/> be strong&#44; in the days that I will deal with thee&#63;&#8221;  <persName>Ezek.</persName> 22&#58;14.<lb/>  The higher our views of the justice holiness and truth of God&#44; the<lb/> deeper and despair in view of our own sin.  Can any one then take<lb/> our place and die for us&#63;  The substitute must himself be without<lb/> sin&#44; and under no obligation to suffer for himself.  Further&#44; God<lb/> would not accept a substitute who is unable for our place&#44; who&#44; in<lb/> suffering for us&#44; would himself be ruined.  A suitable substitute<lb/> must have power to lay down his life and to take it again.<lb/>  This power&#44; <persName>Jesus</persName> claimed.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Hebrew Scriptures give us many solemn lessons on<lb/> atonement by death.  The blood was sacredly set apart and forbid&#61;<lb/>den in common use&#44; it being that part of the living system through<lb/> which an atonement for the soul was made upon the altar.  Hence<lb/> it is a saying of the <sic>Rabbies</sic>&#44; <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> the essential matter of atonement is in the blood.  This doctrine<lb/> never became obsolete among the prophets&#59; on the contrary&#44; it grew<lb/> and ripened.  It is in the last prophecies &#8220;Seventy weeks are deter&#61;<lb/>mined&#8222; upon thy people&#44; and upon thy holy city&#8221;&#8212;so we read in <persName>Dan&#61;<lb/>iel</persName>&#44;&#8212; &#8220;to finish the transgression&#44; and to make an end of sins&#44;<lb/> and to make atonement for iniquity&#44; and to bring in everlas&#61;<lb/>ting righteousness&#44; and to seal up the vision and prophecy&#44;<lb/> and to anoint a holy of holies.&#8221;  Hebrew and Christian<lb/> commentators agree that here a period of years is designated<lb/> which must have come to an end in the first century of the<lb/> Christian Era.  But&#44; notwithstanding this agreement&#44; there is<lb/> a wide difference in the interpretations.  The Christian beholds<lb/> in these events predicted by <persName>Daniel</persName>&#44; the expiatory and all&#45;sufficient<lb/> sufferings of his Messiah&#44; the everlasting righteousness in which<lb/> the sinner may be accepted&#44; the restraint laid on the condemning<lb/> power of sin&#44; the grand <sic>fulfilment</sic> of visions and prophecies&#44;<lb/> and the spiritual consecration of a new sanctuary and commu&#61;<lb/>nity of worshipers.  The Christian finds this prophecy full of<lb/> consolation&#58; on the contrary&#44; in the Jewish interpretation&#44;</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>it loses all its features of promise.  This finishing of trans&#61;<lb/>gression is the full preparation through hardness of heart un&#61;<lb/>belief and immorality&#44; for the captivity of the last eighteen hun&#61;<lb/>dred years&#59; this end of sins is the swelling of the flood of<lb/> sin to the highest measure&#59; this atonement for iniquity commen&#61;<lb/>ces and continues in the captivity which still exists&#59; the bringing<lb/> in of everlasting righteousness may be either the process of becom&#61;<lb/>ing externally righteous through the present captivity&#44; or the sup&#61;<lb/>pression of the righteousness of the fathers and prophets&#59; the seal&#61;<lb/>ing up of the visions of prophets is a lamentable termination&#44; not<lb/> a grand consummation&#59; the anointing of a holy of holies is the<lb/> shutting up of the temple by the anointed.  When <persName>Ezra</persName> is the com&#61;<lb/>mentator whom I here have before me.  How bright and com&#61;<lb/>forting this passage to the Christian&#33;  How dark to the Jew.<lb/>  it is like the cloud that gave light to the Israelites&#44; and was<lb/> darkness to the Egyptians.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">According to the preceding views&#44; the transgressor needs a<lb/> more holy nature that he may be capable of repenting&#44; and an atone&#61;<lb/>ment by blood that he may be delivered from the curse.  The gos&#61;<lb/>pel meets the first need in the sanctification which the Holy<lb/> Spirit works&#44; and the second need in the atonement of <persName>Christ</persName><lb/> It appears to us that if ever an anxious self&#45;condemned despair&#61;<lb/>ing Jew derived consolation from the fact that the blood of his<lb/> victim on the altar was appointed his atonement&#44; we may<lb/> derive still greater consolation from the atonement of <persName>Christ</persName>.<lb/>  No wonder&#44; however&#44; that the latter is foolishness to those who<lb/> feel that they stand in no need of an atonement.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In conclusion&#44; let one attend to your appeal to remove some<lb/> difficulties.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">On 1 <persName>John</persName> 5&#58;7&#44; I have no desire to enter into any discussion.<lb/>  You may decide as you please on the genuineness.&#8212;Unless you force<lb/> into the following passage a change of the speaker&#44; it is as clear on<lb/> the doctrine of the Trinity as the above disputed verse.  Is. 48&#58;15.<lb/>16.  &#8220;I&#44; even I&#44; have spoken&#59; yea&#44; I have called him&#59; I have brought<lb/> him&#44; and he shall make his way prosperous.  Come near unto me&#44; hear<lb/> ye this&#59; I have not spoken in secret from the beginning&#59; from the time<lb/> that it was&#44; there am I&#58; <hi rend="underline">and now the Lord God hath sent me and</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">his Spirit</hi>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You find a difficulty in the verse&#58; &#8220;And when all things shall be<lb/> subdued unto him&#44; then shall the Son also himself be subject unto<lb/> him that put all things under him&#44; that God may be all in all.&#8221;<lb/>  We do not contend that <persName>Christ</persName> will continue eternally in his office<lb/> of high&#45;priest and intercessor.  He represents himself as the way<lb/> to the Father&#44; but this way will be eventually closed&#59; and<lb/> then woe to those who have despised the last and only means<lb/> of reconciliation to God.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The opposition to Christianity and its abuse have fulfilled<lb/> the prediction of the sending of the sword among men.  <persName>Jesus</persName> never</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>intimated that if all men would become his true followers&#44; they could<lb/> not live together without the sword.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">From my childhood my impression has always been that <persName>Mat&#45;<lb/>thew</persName> and <persName>Luke</persName> tell different parts of one consistent narrative in<lb/> relation to the end of <persName>Judas</persName>.  He first strangled or hanged him&#61;<lb/>self&#58; in this condition he fell and was crushed&#44; as <persName>Luke</persName><lb/> describes.  Where is the contradiction&#63;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Detestable Presbyterianism&#33;  &#8220;A distinguished Presbyterian<lb/> divine has said &#8220;<hi rend="underline">Hell is paved with the skulls of infants</hi>.&#8221;  Pos&#61;<lb/>sibly you were never more surprised in your life than you will<lb/> be when you see it here asserted that we Presbyterians do not<lb/> hold every thing which our ministers say&#44; as proceeding from di&#61;<lb/>vine inspiration.  There is&#44; however&#44; one sentence which we hold<lb/> to be inspired&#58; please direct your next attack against it.<lb/>  &#8220;Suffer little children to come unto me and forbid them not&#44; for<lb/> of such is the kingdom of heaven.&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is a mystery why you propose difficulties which a child can<lb/> answer.  I once put the question to an Israelite&#44; if he would not<lb/> be willing to sacrifice all that he has&#44; even his own life&#44; to know<lb/> the truth of Christianity&#44; it is true.  He gave me a very<lb/> evasive answer&#58; his conscience appeared to whisper that he knew<lb/> himself not to be anxious on the point&#44; and that he had best not<lb/> dissemble.&#8212;Prejudice makes us blind.  In our prejudice we are<lb/> not true to our own highest interests.</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)">Yours most respectfully&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">M. R. Miller</persName></p>
				<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date>Jan. 16&#44; 1851</date>.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p><addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I send you the following subscribers for the<lb/> next volume of the Occident.  &#42;They are good pay.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr Gains Fenn</persName> <placeName>New Haven. Connecticut</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Rev. H. M. Willson</persName> <placeName>251 Elizabeth st. N. Y.</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Rev. David M. Holliday</persName> <placeName>Peckskill N. Y.</placeName></p>
				<p>I shall try to get you more subscribers as I have opportunity&#44;<lb/> and I will be a subscriber for your <del>daily paper</del> weekly paper.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In relation to your notes on my last.  I suppose I need not<lb/> inform you of the extreme difficulty in persuading Christians that<lb/> our Heavenly Father makes such a difference between Jews and<lb/> Christians that what would be idolatry to the former is allowable<lb/> to the latter.  The Christian will not cease to think that if he has<lb/> the same light which the Jew has&#44; he is under the same obligations<lb/> of obedience and reverence to our common Father.  And why<lb/> should it not be so&#63;  God may say to the Jews&#44; Let other nations<lb/> go after their gods&#44; but do you follow me&#44; just as a father<lb/> may say to one of his sons.  Let the other children go on&#44; but do you obey me&#44;&#8212;this however would signify no approval of the<lb/> disobedient.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You understand this as a private remark&#44; not intended<lb/> for any public notice.</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">Your friend truly</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">M. R. Miller</persName>.</p>
				<p><addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>. </p>
				<p>&#42; To commence with the <date>April</date> No.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
