<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Marcuson, Menachem</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF10_1</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Marcuson, Menachem</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>Pittsburgh, PA</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1853-01" source="" attested="unk">8 January 1853</dateLet>
              <dateLet when="1853-01" source="" attested="yes">8 Tebet 5613</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f10_0001_1r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f10_0001_1v.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f10_0001_2r.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>7 pages on 6 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
          <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
      
		<pb n="1"/>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">Revd Sir</p>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
		<pb n="2"/>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<p>I could not stay in <placeName>Charleston</placeName>&#44; because I was afraid for the <sic>yelow</sic> fever<lb/> it was there. To bring your book I will send you the book you lend it to me with the first<lb/> opportunity&#44; the few <sic>dolars</sic> you spent for me also&#44; I hope you<lb/> will not do&#44; as the former did&#44; to write any thing&#44; without to<lb/> know if their opinion are true or false&#44; because why should<lb/> you make me to write against you to&#44; that make no difference<lb/> we may <sic>belive</sic> every one what we <sic>belive</sic> though I may under<lb/> sign your friend</p>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
		<pb n="3"/>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
		<pb n="4"/>
          <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Pittsburgh</placeName>&#44; <date>Friday&#44; 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Tebet &#40;January&#41; 1853</date></p>
			<p>Rev. Sir&#58;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I hope that you will excuse me only this once&#44; for troubling you so fre&#45;<lb/>quently. I hope this is enough also for the letters that may still come. Yes&#45;<lb/>terday about 12 midnight&#44; <persName>Mr. Yaroslausky</persName> read for me the letter of <persName>Mr.<lb/> Oliver</persName>. To be brief&#8212;with regard to the food that I ate along with him&#44; that<lb/> is true. But what was it we were eating&#63; Last time when I sent my resigna&#45;<lb/>tion to the congregation and accepted the position in the synagogue&#44; as I have written to<lb/> you several times before&#44; I asked him where I should be until I went there<lb/> whereupon&#44; he replied that his wife and family are in the country and that he<lb/> himself had to depart that night or early the next morning&#44; but that I could<lb/> leave my luggage with him. He left at home only one black man who went<lb/> to work every day to earn his bread. There was no other maid servant in the<lb/> house. I brought my things there. We talked until quite late at night. It<lb/> was about midnight when I said&#44; &#8220;I&#39;m quite hungry&#8221;. He replied&#44; &#8220;The<lb/> house is quite empty&#8212;not even bread.&#8221; Nevertheless&#44; he sent his negro who<lb/> got some milk and bread. That is what we ate together. Now you can see<lb/> how lies begin with truth. What can I say in reply&#63; Before dawn&#44; he had to leave<lb/> at one time he had recommended me to one of his friends who had asked<lb/> me to pay him a visit. I came to him once but found him out. I spent<lb/> more than two hours there&#44; because of the many books which he possessed<lb/> but could not wait for him. I left and never came to him again<lb/> and never saw him. How I conducted myself afterwards&#44; I have al&#45;<lb/>ready told you. I asked the people of <placeName>Montgomery</placeName> on several occasions to<lb/> come out and see and convince themselves.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">With regard to shaving. The fact is that all the observant people<lb/> do so here&#44; but I don&#39;t want to boast. You can convince yourself through<lb/> <persName>Mr. Block</persName>&#44; one of the congregation of <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>. He once came out to<lb/> the slaughter house&#44; which is about two miles out of town&#44; in order to speak to<lb/> the butcher. He found that I had trimmed my beard with a scissors&#44; a<lb/> thing I always used to in the slaughter house in order to save time&#44; for<lb/> when I am in the city I wanted to study&#44; for I have very little time<lb/> for myself there. So you see I was not doing it in order to fool anybody<lb/> Here no one comes. I did not know this man was coming. I wasn&#39;t<lb/> doing it for the sake of the two negroes who do the slaughtering here. And<lb/> if you suppose that I did not shave myself because I had no razor&#44;<lb/> you can convince through <persName>Mr. Sahling</persName> of <placeName>Augusta</placeName> that at one time<lb/> I came to his house and his wife said&#44; &#8220;Oh&#44; I just wanted to send</p>
		<pb n="5"/>
			<p>some chickens to you to be slaughtered. Now you are here.&#8221;<lb/> I said&#44; &#8220;I did not bring the slaughtering knife&#8221;&#44; whereupon she<lb/> replied&#44; &#8220;Our clerk used to be a schochet. He has a slaughtering<lb/> knife as well as a sharpening stone.&#8221; The clerk showed me a<lb/> razor which he had fixed up for a slaughtering knife. I then said<lb/> &#8220;I shall not slaughter here with this knife unless you make<lb/> me a present of it.&#8221; Thereupon&#44; he gave it to me&#44; and I still<lb/> have it.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">With regard to the day of conversion&#44; about which <persName>Mr. Yeroslausky</persName><lb/> tells me&#44; I understand nothing. The church from which <persName>Mr. Oliver</persName> came<lb/> has a school&#44; and the church from which <persName>Mr. Davis</persName> comes&#44; has a school. Now&#44;<lb/> <del>both</del> each of these says that I adopted his faith. In this he was<lb/> all wrong. At one time we discussed the various peculiarities of their belief<lb/> We spoke about the Presbyterians&#44; who believe that man has no choice of<lb/> good or evil&#44; for everything is already predestined by God. I said that<lb/> where there is no freedom of choice&#44; there can be no reward and<lb/> punishment&#44; for reward and punishment can be only where there<lb/> is freedom of choice. That is why I could not understand<lb/> that belief at all&#44; and that&#44; from that point of view&#44; there belief<lb/> was superior. But I have quite forgotten one point&#44; namely&#44; just<lb/> what I said about their faith as to why it must be false.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">With regard to the first chapter of <hi rend="underline">Matthew</hi>&#63;&#44; <persName>Mr. Yaroslausky</persName><lb/> tells me what he writes&#44; and I am very much surprised. I assure you<lb/> that we discussed it once. This is an old question. The generations<lb/> are not properly written down&#44; but I also asked him this&#58; It is true<lb/> that when you speak of God&#44; you believe there is only one God&#44; but when<lb/> you mention the name of his person he seems to be three&#44; namely&#44;<lb/> Father&#44; Son&#44; and Holy Ghost. Thus when you speak of the Father<lb/> and mention the son&#44; the son must be the Son of the person whom you call<lb/> Father. In Matthew&#44; however&#44; it is written that the angel had told<lb/> <persName>Joseph</persName> that <persName>Mary</persName> would become pregnant through the Holy Ghost. Then<lb/> how is that&#63; To this he answered that Father and Holy Ghost are the same<lb/> Then I again said &#8220;Are they there then two or one&#63;&#8221; To this he has<lb/> not given me any answer to this day. You can rest assured that if<lb/> I was surprised&#44; which I do not remember any more&#44; my surprise<lb/> was due to the stupidity of the people who believe this. With regard to<lb/> the case of the &#36;70&#44; I answer you that I once spoke to <persName>Mr. Davis</persName></p>
		<pb n="6"/>
			<p>when he asked me what my salary was here in <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>&#44; I tell<lb/> him it was &#36;500. He said to me&#44; you should have doubled that if<lb/> you came over to us. And then&#44; casually&#44; I said&#44; &#8220;Would you do this<lb/> and give &#36;1000 for this&#63; And he said&#44; &#8220;Yes&#44; certainly&#44; if only you say<lb/> that you are coming over.&#8221; Then I said&#44; &#8220;It might be right for a man<lb/> to change after having brought his mind upon the right road with regard<lb/> to eternity&#44; but when he receives money for it&#44; then he has already re&#45;<lb/>ceived his rewards here&#44; and he cannot&#44; therefore&#44; come to eternity. But<lb/> you do your work completely without thought. It is one thing to lead a<lb/> man away from his religion&#44; but another to destroy him&#8212;a thing which<lb/> are forbidden to do&#8221;. The &#36;70 I counted for two persons for three<lb/> months&#39; instruction&#8212;a lesson a day except <date>Saturday</date> and <date>Sunday</date></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">The said <persName>Mr. Oliver</persName> once met me on the street. He asked<lb/> me from where I was coming. I told him I was in a house of one of<lb/> my congregation. He asked me to go with him to a church where he<lb/> was going&#44; but I refused. Then he asked me whether Jews were for&#45;<lb/>bidden to enter a church. I told him that we may&#44; &#8220;but because<lb/> you ask me&#44; I don&#39;t do it&#44; and that you may never persuade me to do<lb/> it&#44; even if you ask me a great deal.&#8221; Outside of that one time of<lb/> which I have already spoken.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">And now&#44; my friend&#44; I leave it to you. Do what you<lb/> think best. If you speak about the Jewish law&#44; then according to Jewish<lb/> law&#44; I should be believed. For there are now no Jews who say any&#45;<lb/>thing or who can say anything against me. But 3 shall now appear<lb/> to no law and no justice. Do yourself in accordance with your own<lb/> thoughts&#44; only consider the matter. You are dealing with me now in a<lb/> matter that concerns life. All I have to say is&#44; &#8220;I know that&#42;<lb/> my redeemer liveth&#8221;. This is my only hope&#44; and I am sure<lb/> of the kindness of God who has not forsaken me to this day. He<lb/> will broaden my path&#44; and my knees will not hand. He will<lb/> set me up on my feet and make me ride upon the altars of my<lb/> enemies. I shall see vengeance upon those that hate me and shall<lb/> not fear&#44; for God is with me to help me&#44; even though there are many<lb/> who fight against me. They have all made a flat<add>&#63;</add> to decide<lb/> how and what to do&#44; but there are many more with me&#44; with the help of<lb/> God&#44; than are with them. For the God of truth&#44; the God of life will support<lb/> me with this righteous right hand. For I look for His mercy</p>
			<p>&#42;Job</p>
		<pb n="7"/>
          <p rend="indent(1)">Aside from this&#44; if I omitted &#40;to refute&#41; anything on that letter&#44; it<lb/> is only because I had to have it read before me. Naturally it is<lb/> better to be able to read it for oneself.</p>
          <p rend="indent(8)"><persName role="author">Menachem&#8212;&#8212;Marcuson</persName></p>
			<p><hi rend="underline">This I have written to <persName>Bernheim</persName>&#160;&#160;English</hi></p>
			<p>It is also a lie that I have received commission for being a<lb/> missionary.</p>
          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>