<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF7_3</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1850-02" source="" attested="yes">12 February 1850</dateLet>
              <dateLet when="1850-02" source="" attested="yes">12 February 5610</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0003_1r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0003_1v.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0003_2r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0003_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
      
		<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date>12 Feby. 5610 &#40;1850&#41;</date></p>
			<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
          <p rend="indent(2)">My dear friend.</p>
          <p rend="indent(4)">I have been too much occupied since<lb/> my arrival with matters connected with the congregation receiving<lb/> and returning the numerous visits of its members&#44; and my own personal<lb/> affairs&#44; to write you&#59; and not wishing to keep you&#44; who have shown so<lb/> much interest for the progress of Judaism in this quarter&#44; uninformed<lb/> as to a single particular of all that has taken place&#44; I delayed addressing<lb/> you until I had sufficient leisure to give you all the information on<lb/> the subject. Having now arranged the preliminaries satisfactorily<lb/> I hasten to acquit myself of the pleasing duty</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I left <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> on the <date>23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Decr.</date> I was detained at <placeName>Havan&#45;<lb/>nah</placeName> waiting the arrival of the steamer from the <date>26<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> to the <date>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Jany.</date> As<lb/> I did not wish to go to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> and <placeName>Jampico</placeName> in her&#44; and no direct<lb/> opportunity offering for <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#44; I was forced to go to <placeName>Savannah</placeName>&#44;<lb/> and thence by stage&#44; steam&#44; and rail road&#59; at length arriving here hap&#45;<lb/>pily on the <date>19<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> ult just <hi rend="underline">28</hi> days after my departure from <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>.<lb/> The only pleasing incident&#44; worth mentioning&#44; in my travels&#44; is the<lb/> <date>Friday</date> &#38; <date>Sabbath</date> spent at <placeName>Savannah</placeName>. We had divine service evening<lb/> and morning&#44; and I preached to a numerous auditory&#44; considering<lb/> the number of our people who are settled there. <persName>Messrs. Delamotta</persName> and<lb/> <persName>S. Cohen</persName> promised to give you all particulars of what transpired&#44;<lb/> it is therefore needless for me to do so. I was exceedingly well received<lb/> and most hospitably entertained. Your name was often mentioned&#44; and the<lb/> value and magnitude of your labours acknowledged and discussed.<lb/> always enthusiastic in the cause of my friends&#44; your reputation<lb/> and services suffered nothing from my being present. There is a fine</p>
		<pb n="2"/>
			<p>opening at <placeName><sic>Savanah</sic></placeName> for a Good Jewish minister I think such a<lb/> man as <persName>Mr. DaSola</persName> would answer. There is a feeling of true piety and<lb/> zeal both among the ladies and gentlemen of that place&#44; which&#44; properly<lb/> directed by a faithful and energetic spiritual guide&#44; would make the <placeName><sic>Savanah</sic></placeName><lb/> Synagogue one of the best regulated and most conspicuous in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName><lb/> Had I not been detained so long on the way&#44; I should have liked<lb/> to have spent a week or two among such agreeable people as <persName>messrs<lb/> S Cohen</persName>&#44; <persName>Delamotta</persName>&#44; <persName>Isaac Cohen</persName> &#38;c.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I expected to find every thing in readiness on my arrival<lb/> and was surprised to hear that even the donation of the synagogue had<lb/> not yet been made. Our mutual friend <persName>Mr. Touro</persName> is a man deliberate<lb/> and cautious in his plans and movements. It is natural at his advanced<lb/> age. However the property is now in the hands of the congregation. The<lb/> good old man signed the act&#44; which gave away &#36;150&#44;000. for such is the<lb/> value of the land and buildings&#44; as calmly and coolly as tho&#39; it were an<lb/> ordinary transaction&#44; I am convinced that the idea&#44; of having thus handed<lb/> his name down to posterity as a munificent and princely upholder of<lb/> the institutions of his people&#44; never crossed his mind. He is without<lb/> exception&#44; one of the most single&#45;hearted men I ever encountered. His<lb/> ruling thought is filial reverence&#59; and the gift of the synagogue arises<lb/> <del>more</del> as much from a desire to do honor to the memory of his father <del>than</del> as any other.<lb/> Such a man deserves some testimonial expressive of his coreligionists&#39;<lb/> esteem. It has occupied the thoughts of many here&#44; but he is so retiring<lb/> unostentatious&#44; and modest&#44; as to preclude the hope of his willingness<lb/> to receive any mark of regard. When you come on&#44; we should have the benefit of your<lb/> counsel&#59; for something must be done to save us from the charge of<lb/> ingratitude&#44; or not properly appreciating his disinterestedness and<lb/> patriotism. He has further designs for the promotion and diffusion<lb/> of religious instruction among the rising generation&#44; which will in time<lb/> be matured and perfected. He holds you in great esteem&#44; and has<lb/> already put by the funds for paying your expenses to witness the conse</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><date>2&#45;12&#45;1850B</date></p>
		<pb n="3"/>
			<p>cration. My engagement is for life&#44; i e&#45;during good behaviour and<lb/> ability to discharge my duties&#44; temporary sickness excepted. The salary<lb/> &#36;2500 p ann.&#44; a large sum apparently&#44; but really small when the extravagant<lb/> cost of every thing here is considered. I shall not keep a school&#44; but<lb/> only have classes for children for Hebrew and religious instruction. An<lb/> assistant had been engaged&#44; a <persName>Mr. DaSilva</persName>&#44; who formerly officiated at<lb/> <placeName>Mobile</placeName>&#44; at &#36;1200. He will act as Shamash&#44; collector&#44; messenger &#38; assistant<lb/> Reader. <persName>Mr. Isaac Soria</persName> continues the secretaryship.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">The consecration will not take place before the middle of<lb/> <date>May</date>&#44; say the <date>15<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date>&#44; at which&#44; altho&#39; <date>Shebungot</date> may see you absent from<lb/> your congregation&#44; you <hi rend="underline">must</hi> appear&#44; as one of the bright stars<lb/> of our Jewish hemisphere. I beg of you&#44; as a mark of favor on your<lb/> part towards <hi rend="underline">me</hi>&#44; independently of the Congregation&#44; to consider the<lb/> pulpit as your own the <date>Sabbath</date> after the consecration&#44; or rather<lb/> the <date>Friday</date> after&#44; being the first day of <date>Shebungot</date><add>&#63;</add>. As I shall leave<lb/> this on the <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> Inst. for <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>&#44; and not return until the <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi></date> or <date>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> May</date><lb/> you will please communicate with our friend <persName>G. Kursheedt</persName>&#44; and say<lb/> whether you will be here. Surely your congregation will spare you on<lb/> such an occasion and must feel delighted at the high respect<lb/> evinced towards their their pastor. Your share in the consecration service<lb/> I have not yet determined on&#59; but it will be my delight to show you<lb/> the honor you so well merit. Consider these sentiments&#44; my dear friend&#44;<lb/> as heartfelt&#59; I have no other <add>&#63;</add> than&#44; as an Israelite&#44; to join in doing<lb/> homage to that talent&#44; whose energetic exercise has mainly con&#45;<lb/>tributed to that progress&#44; now fermenting and leavening in our Congrega&#45;<lb/>tions. It will be a sad disappointment to <persName>Mr. Touro</persName> and myself<lb/> if you be absent on an occasion so honorable to him&#44; so interesting<lb/> to you. Our officers will write you specially.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">It was originally intended to celebrate the consecration<lb/> before I returned to <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>&#44; but this idea was abandoned&#59; and<lb/> I objected to it for several reasons&#44; one of which was&#44; tho&#39; I did</p>
		<pb n="4"/>
			<p>not express it to any one but <persName>Mr. Touro</persName>&#44; that <hi rend="underline">you</hi> could not<lb/> be here. From a letter received from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#44; it appears there<lb/> was an impression of your having been ill&#45;treated by the Congregation&#44;<lb/> here&#44; after you had bestirred yourself so much in personally attending<lb/> to the announcement and quick dispatch of articles ordered for<lb/> the synagogue. If such an idea entered your mind&#44; the plain<lb/> statement in this letter of the true facts will remove its and satisfy<lb/> you on this head. Nor must you interpret <persName>G. Kursheedt&#39;s</persName> silence<lb/> to any neglect or forgetfulness on his part. Had I not been an eye&#45;<lb/>witness of the way in which he is pestered with every minute affair<lb/> relating to both congregations&#44; together with the amount of business he<lb/> has to transact in his own office&#44; I might have been induced to suppose<lb/> that his silence as a correspondent arose from disinclination to<lb/> write. It is impossible for you to conceive the dilatory manner things<lb/> are managed here. Business absorbs men&#39;s attention from morn till night&#44;<lb/> and from that they will not budge. He has enough of that to occupy<lb/> him the whole day&#59; therefore when he is consulted besides on all<lb/> <hi rend="underline">spiritual</hi> matters&#44; for which <persName>Mr. Guttheim</persName> &#38; I have given him the title<lb/> of <add>Hebrew</add> and he is constituted by general consent&#44; as well perhaps as<lb/> by inclucation&#44; the umpize<add>&#63;</add> and arbitration of both synagogues&#44; you can<lb/> then form a notion that he is a hard working man as well as yourself.<lb/> I am induced to say this much in his <sic>defence</sic>&#44; he having charged me<lb/> to assign a satisfactory reason for not visiting you.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">Your friend <persName>Mr. Gutheim</persName> and I are upon the best of terms.<lb/> I esteem him much as a scholar and a gentleman&#44; and shall do my<lb/> best to establish the friendship which now exists between us on the<lb/> firmest basis. Our mutual aim must be&#44; the advancement of Judaism<lb/> and in accomplishing it&#44; union and harmony should exist between the<lb/> ministers of the two congregations. I see nothing to prevent the reciprocation<lb/> of regard and kindness.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I must now close this long letter with the hope of<lb/> its meeting you in good health. I shall count the days till I<lb/> have the pleasure of welcoming you to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#44; and giving you<lb/> a cordial and hearty greeting. Meanwhile remember me kindly to<lb/> all friends and believe me&#44; as ever your friend &#38; well wisher</p>
          <p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName></p>
			<p>Did you receive my letter from <placeName>Jamaica</placeName><lb/> on the subject of coming here &#38;c&#63;</p>
          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>