<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Oliver, C. D.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Oliver, C. D.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Montgomery, AL</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1852-10">20 October 1852</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0016_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0016_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0016_2r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)"><date>Oct 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1852</date>.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir. Having recently gotten hold of the last issue of<lb/> the “Occident” I was
                much surprised on finding in it an article<lb/> from <persName>Mr E.
                    Marcussohn</persName> denying his ever having abjured<lb/> Judaism. Now it may
                be proposed to state what I know of this<lb/> gentleman, as the Editor of the
                Occident seems to solicit information<lb/> concerning him.</p>
            <p><persName>Mr Marcussohn</persName> was introduced to me at my house by
                    <persName>Rev<lb/> Mr Bonhomme</persName> (a gentleman long and favorably
                known.)<lb/> He appeared a little awkward from his want of a ready use of<lb/> the
                English language, for this he apologized, and expressed a<lb/> desire to enter upon
                the study of it. Thereupon I proposed that<lb/> he should instruct me in Hebrew and
                I would in turn teach him<lb/> English. In order to carry out this arrangement he
                was to visit<lb/> me at a certain <del>period</del> hour every morning (That is when
                his<lb/> engagements or mine did not otherwise prevent). For several<lb/> weeks he
                continued to come, when together we would read the<lb/> Old and New Testaments
                frequently <sic>stoping</sic> while reading to<lb/> comment upon some passage. He
                appeared greatly interested in<lb/> the New Testament especially with those portions
                found in the<lb/> first chapters of <persName>Mark</persName>, embracing the
                Savior's sermon on the<lb/>
                <placeName>Mount</placeName>. He observed the most profound <sic>reverance</sic> in
                speaking<lb/> of <persName>Christ</persName>. He acknowledged the importance of a
                Mediator in our<lb/> approaches to the Father. Spoke of the <sic>ineficiency</sic>
                of the law to justify<lb/> the sinner. Told me that he prayed to God to pardon his
                sins, and that he<lb/> felt that he had received pardon. I spoke plainly with him
                touching<lb/> the witness of the spirit, &amp; the inward peace consequent upon
                the<lb/> forgiveness of sins. He remarked that he felt that he had received
                this<lb/> witness &amp; this peace. I felt anxious for <persName>Mr M.</persName> to
                be placed beyond all doubt<lb/> in regard to his spiritual change, &amp; hence I
                often conversed with him<lb/> upon the subject of the new birth—or scripture
                religion. He expressed great<lb/> dissatisfaction with the duties laid upon him as
                Teacher of the Jewish faith,<lb/> Complained of his brethren, their want of
                enlightenment &amp; so on. Said he<lb/> was receiving from them $500.00 a year as a
                salary, that they paid him at<lb/> fixed times, said that one installment would be
                due him in a few weeks,</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>but that he felt that he could not remain with them up to that time as it<lb/> would
                be acting the part of the hypocrite. This he mentioned more than once,<lb/> Of
                course I could but sympathize with him, in what I conceived to be the honest<lb/>
                <sic>struglings</sic> of conscience.</p>
            <p>On the <date>5th July</date> according to my best recollection, he made his
                appearance at my<lb/> house, greatly agitated. Said that he had given up his church
                &amp; had declared<lb/> in favor of Christianity. He stated at the same time that he
                need money, &amp; had<lb/> no means of paying it, as the Jews whom he had been
                serving would no doubt<lb/> withhold that portion of his salary which was due him.
                Seeing him in<lb/> this unpleasant dilemma, I advanced him $70 which he said
                would<lb/> be sufficient to pay him out of debt. He now left his boarding
                house,<lb/> and moved his trunks to my house and lived with me. I noticed in
                him<lb/> a perfect conformity to Gentile customs.</p>
            <p>When he first visited me he would not take a drink of water except<lb/> with his hat
                on, if it was not at hand, he would leave his seat and go in<lb/> search of it.
                After he came to my house to live, he gave up this custom, indeed<lb/> he gave it up
                before.</p>
            <p>Again he sat at my table and ate whatever I did, and what without any apparent
                scruple<lb/> I was a little surprised when he asked me the loan of my razor, and
                stated that<lb/> he had never put a razor upon his face, but that he had been
                accustomed to clip<lb/> his beard with a kind of scissors. He handled the razor very
                awkwardly but<lb/> made out to sh<add>?</add>. Since then I think he has used this
                instrument altogether<lb/> especially during his <hi rend="underline">Conversion to
                    Christianity</hi></p>
            <p>In regard to his church <sic>preferances</sic>, he said that they were with the
                Methodist, that he<lb/> believed in their doctrines, &amp; desired to unite with
                them. The time when I was to receive<lb/> him by baptism into the church was
                appointed but owing to some circumstance it was<lb/>
                <sic>defered</sic>. In the meantime <persName>Rev. Mr Davis</persName> &amp; myself
                had an interview upon the subject of<lb/> his uniting with the church, Our claims
                upon him were about equal, &amp; we agreed that<lb/> neither of us would receive
                him, or in any way influence him to become a member of our<lb/> respective
                communions, but that we would leave him to make up deliberately his own<lb/> mind
                &amp; decide for himself.</p>
            <p>After this I was compelled to be absent from my station for several days and
                consequently<lb/> procured for <persName>Mr M.</persName> another home, which was at
                the house of one of my members, where he was<lb/> well cared for and fed. He showed
                while here no anti-swine disposition but</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>ate this kind of flesh with a gusto. Since I disposed of <persName>Mr M.</persName>
                as<lb/> alluded to, I have not seen him up to the present time. The particulars<lb/>
                touching his history from thence to his setting out for <placeName>Charleston S.
                    C.</placeName><lb/>
                <persName>Rev. Mr Davis</persName> can give you. (We both honestly endeavored to
                benefit a<lb/> man who shewd himself in our way for instruction &amp; guidance,
                if<lb/> we have been deceived it is not any guilt of ours. We feel
                    <sic>acquited</sic><lb/> before God and at the bar of our own consciences. The
                religion which<lb/> we profess teaches us to forgive those who wrong us. So did our
                divine<lb/> Master before us, &amp; so do we. In conclusion I humbly recommend friend<lb/>
                <persName>Marcussohn</persName> if he has never known <persName>Christ</persName> to
                seek him with all his<lb/> heart, &amp; when he has truly found him he will never
                disown him, but<lb/> like his noble countryman &amp; brother after the flesh
                    <persName>Paul</persName> he can say<lb/> “God forbid that I should glory save
                in the cross of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>” &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yours truly, <hi rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">C. D. Oliver</persName>
                    Pastor of M. E.</hi></p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">Church, <placeName>Montgomery, Ala.</placeName></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
