<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">K. O. M.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx2FF7_17</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">K. O. M.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Augusta, GA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1860-04" source="" attested="yes">8 April [1860]</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b2f7_0017_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b2f7_0017_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b2f7_0017_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b2f7_0017_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><date>April 8th</date></p>
				<p><addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Imagination fertile in ways of<lb/> tormenting as well as in ways of blessing&#44; has fitted my<lb/> mind with many fears as to the construction you would<lb/> place on my silence&#59; &#38; therefore has caused me to be silent<lb/> when duty &#38; inclination both prompted me to reply.<lb/>  You seem to think that I have much leisure at command<lb/> but you are mistaken I often cannot command an hour in<lb/> the 24 to appropriate to myself &#38; truly when your letter<lb/> arrived I had mind &#38; body so much occupied &#40;&#38; not pleasantly<lb/> either&#41; that I <sic>defered</sic> writing until I was in a better frame<lb/> of mind &#38; when I could I felt like a guilty one that had<lb/> not firmness to confess her fault.  Better feelings have come over<lb/> me &#38; if you will accept the Assurance that indifference did<lb/> not <sic>actuated</sic> me &#38; that I will do better in future.  I will<lb/> be again the punctual correspondent you were wont to call<lb/> me.  When you judge I have a great deal of leisure you<lb/> no doubt identify in me a Southern Woman &#38; one of<lb/> easy circumstances&#59; now let me undeceive you I <hi rend="underline">am neither</hi>&#44;<lb/> although born&#44; at the <placeName>South</placeName>&#59; I have none of the indolence<lb/> unjustly attributed to us&#8212;nor the means to indulge in it&#44; if<lb/> I wished.  I have the charge of a large family&#44; have many<lb/> responsibilities&#44; besides&#59; have many pecuniary troubles&#44; Educate<lb/> two children at home&#44; do all my own needle work&#59; but<lb/> above all&#58; am in a society far above my means &#38; among<lb/> the like of <placeName>Augusta</placeName>.  This latter circumstance&#44; obliges me</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>to fritter away many hours that might be more profitably<lb/> employed&#59; and I am only reconciled to doing so&#44; from the reflection<lb/> that I neglect no duty &#40;for writing you is a pleasure&#41; my business<lb/> correspondents all find me punctual &#38; I should deprive my<lb/> children of much pleasure &#38; many advantages did I seclude<lb/> myself from the world&#33;  You cannot tell&#44; you cannot comprehend<lb/> what sacrifices a <add>&#63;</add> mother is capable of making for<lb/> her offspring&#33;  Besides you know I love reading &#38; mine is a most<lb/> <sic>heterogenous</sic> mass&#33;  I have injured my eyes so much&#44; by reading<lb/> late at night&#44; that I now have to use glasses.  I can honestly<lb/> affirm&#44; that unless in society that from 6 in the morning until<lb/> 10 at night &#38; some times 12 I am never unoccupied.  I have been<lb/> thus explanatory&#44; for your letter would infer&#44; that I plead an<lb/> excuse for my indolence&#33;  Now that is not my besetting sin<lb/> I assure you&#33;  What it is&#44; I shall leave one of your pendration<lb/> to discover.  My two daughters are gone to <placeName>Charleston</placeName>&#44; <persName>Set</persName> to<lb/> be bridesmaid&#44; at her cousins wedding &#38; <persName>Rose</persName> to pass some time<lb/> with her grandparents.  <persName>Set</persName> intended replying to your letter but<lb/> preparations for her departure have prevented&#59; she will<lb/> write you from <placeName>Charleston</placeName>.  The criticism on the dying Hebrew<lb/> will I fear deter the young aspirant from other communication<lb/> for the present.  I do not doubt their justice but few have energy<lb/> to  bear up against the criticism of one so capable as your<lb/>&#45;self.  Why have no numbers but the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> &#38; 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> of the miscellany<lb/> been published&#63;  I am glad&#44; that you have completed the 2<lb/> last numbers of the Pentateuch.  Believe me my dear friend<lb/> poverty&#44; brings no deeper sting to me&#44; than in depriving<lb/> me of <sic>allmost</sic> all the religious works of the present days for I<lb/> prize those I possess so highly&#59; that I deeply regret I cannot<lb/> increase my stock of Jewish publications.  We have an excellent</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>collection of books&#44; but at the time I was able to purchase a Library<lb/> the Jews had sunk too deep in sloth &#38; indifference to benefit their<lb/> people.  The Occident &#38; miscellany are the only two I feel able to sub&#45;<lb/>scribe to&#44; <persName>Mrs Hart</persName> sends me on the Voice of Jacob &#40;&#38; while<lb/> I think of it&#41; do say to her I have received no numbers since <date>Octo<lb/>ber</date>.  <persName>Mrs Henry</persName> gets hers &#38; therefore I am no sufferer.  Our Sunday<lb/> School does not increase&#44; in numbers&#44; although <persName>Mrs Henry</persName> is<lb/> indefatigable &#38; I use every effort to promote its well doing.  Out of 8<lb/> families I have relinquished sending their two children&#44; not I believe<lb/> from any cause&#44; but because they are not strong in faith.  The Jews<lb/> certainly are a stiffnecked race &#38; want much of that piety of heart&#44;<lb/> which would bear against worldly considerations.  Will you tell me&#44;<lb/> whence we take the institution of having godfathers &#38; mothers&#58; as I<lb/> can find no example in the bible.  Do you consider it no harm to att<lb/>end the <sic>Theatre</sic> or a Ball or any other public amusement on the<lb/> <date>Sabbath</date>&#63;  Do you judge the <date>Sabbath</date> properly kept when spent<lb/> in gossiping from one house to another after the duty of Public<lb/> Worship is over&#63;  By what form are Jewesses allowed to become<lb/> members of the Synagogue &#38; at what age&#63;  If they are not allowed<lb/> to join <hi rend="underline">at all</hi>&#44; there can be no religious <hi rend="underline">form</hi>&#44; which gives man the<lb/> <hi rend="underline">right</hi>&#59; for certainly in no part of the Sacred book&#44; do we find women<lb/> deprived of the hope of eternal salvation &#38; the same course that would<lb/> fit man for a celestial abode would I should hope entitle<lb/> women.  Do you know a <persName>Miss Hendricks</persName> from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> she lives with<lb/> her aunt <persName>Mrs Levy</persName>&#44; her family reside here&#44; she seems to be ladylike<lb/> &#38; industrious &#38; has much capacity for earning a support She has with<lb/> her sister opened a fancy store on a small scale but will I hope<lb/> do well we are much interested for her.  She is a regular attendant<lb/> of the Sabbath School&#44; where we assemble &#38; <persName>Mrs Henry</persName> &#38; myself<lb/> read the morning Service.  We adopted this course because we found</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>it would collect together the few Jewesses here &#38; the children would<lb/> be more deeply impressed by preparing them to attend at a given place<lb/> to hear the service read than in their own houses.  Another motive<lb/> influenced us living among gentiles we were subject to interruptions<lb/> &#40;which although I never allowed to interfere with me&#41; were unpleasant</p>
				<p>I hope as soon as the duties of the <date>Passover</date> are finished you will<lb/> <sic>will</sic> write me a long pleasant letter to convince me the mantle<lb/> of Charity is always thrown over the faults of your friends<lb/> What a purifying festival this is if we would only cleanse our<lb/> internal house as we do our worldly abode there would be but<lb/> little fear of a blessed hereafter.  Your sincere friend <persName role="author">KOM</persName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways in the center of the page"></p>
				<p><addressee>Revnd Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
				<p rend="The letter continues written sideways at the top of page 1"></p>
				<p>I have written in such haste &#38; so badly that I would like to destroy this but then I<lb/> might delay it<lb/> for a while so with<lb/> all its imperfections<lb/> let it go.  Remember<lb/> me to my friends<lb/> my son will soon<lb/> collect yr subscrip<lb/>tion money &#38; forward<lb/> it.  My son <persName>Philip</persName><lb/> has located in <placeName>La<lb/> Grange</placeName> a small<lb/> town in <placeName>Georgia</placeName><lb/> he has opened a<lb/> Drug Store &#38; is read<lb/>&#45;ing medicine<lb/> during his leisure hours.  I am<lb/> so pleased that<lb/> he is in the same<lb/> state with me<lb/> that although 250 miles se<lb/>perate us I dare<lb/> not murmur.<lb/>  We have it quite<lb/> cold &#38; rainy our<lb/> winter has been<lb/> very severe</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
