<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">B. E.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx9FF14_3</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">B. E.</author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>London, United Kingdom</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1844-03" source="" attested="yes">28 March 1844</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_2r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_2v.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>To The Editor of the Occident</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Reverend Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Having read the <persName>Rev. Mr Carillon&#39;s</persName><lb/> letter addressed to you in the Occident No 11. I beg leave through your<lb/> valuable columns respectfully to ask the Rev gentleman how<lb/> he reconciles the celebration of the double festivals with his<lb/> condemnation of <hi rend="underline">human laws</hi>&#44; when added to the divine<lb/> code&#63;  These are <persName>Mr Carillon&#39;s</persName> words &#8220;God forbid that any<lb/> Jews should commit rebellion against the God of our fathers&#8222;<lb/> by adding human laws&#44; to the divine&#44; pure and perfect code &#38;c<lb/>  Now in reference to some of our festivals&#44; it is enjoined that<lb/> the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> and <hi rend="underline">seventh</hi> day be holy convocations&#58; is it not then<lb/> to fly in the very face of this divine command to add&#44; <hi rend="underline">voluntarily</hi><lb/> to these two days&#44; a <hi rend="underline">second</hi> and an <hi rend="underline">eighth</hi> day&#63;  is it not an open<lb/> violation of the precept <add>Hebrew</add> &#8220;Thou shalt neither<lb/> add to nor diminish from it &#91;the law&#93;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is worthy remark&#44; that from the observance of<lb/> these double festivals we give utterance in our prayers to expressions<lb/> both untrue and contradictory.  For instance&#44; one of these interpolated<lb/> festivals &#40;<add>Hebrew</add>&#41; kept on a <hi rend="underline">ninth</hi> day&#44; we&#44; in our solemn prayer&#44;<lb/> call <add>Hebrew</add> &#40;&#8220;This <date><hi rend="underline">eighth</hi> day of solemn assembly</date> Again&#59;<lb/> on the second day of <add>Hebrew</add> &#40;<date>new year</date>&#41; we repeat <add>Hebrew</add> &#40;&#8220;The<lb/> world was brought into existence <hi rend="underline">this</hi> day&#41; which cannot be predicated<lb/> of <hi rend="underline">both</hi> days&#44; for one is evidently a negation of the other.  But much<lb/> more objectionable is that highly <sic>irreverend</sic> disregard of holy truth&#44;<lb/> which&#44; on the double festivals&#8212;additions made by <hi rend="underline">mortal man</hi>&#8212;<lb/> proclaims <add>Hebrew</add> &#40;&#8220;These are the festivals of the Lord&#44;<lb/> holy convocations&#8221;&#41;.  Now as all these double festivals&#44; including <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> are confessedly<hi rend="underline"> &#8220;human laws&#44;&#8221;</hi> called by <persName>Maimonides</persName> <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#40;words or institutions of the scribes&#41; I would then respectfully ask<lb/> <persName>Mr Carrillon</persName> in the name of that holy religion we both reverence&#44;<lb/> whether these <hi rend="underline">human</hi> ordinances&#44; added to the &#8220;divine code&#8221; do not<lb/> come under the category of the sins he so emphatically denounces&#63;<lb/>  Antiquity of custom&#44; in the present case&#44; is unentitled to the slightest<lb/> weight&#44; because&#44; this custom&#44; the offspring of sheer necessity with which<lb/> it should have ceased&#44; is a positive transgression of God&#39;s law.  Let it<lb/> be imagined that necessity had compelled our ancestors to diminish<lb/> <hi rend="underline">from</hi> instead of adding <hi rend="underline">to</hi> the divine code&#8212;had compelled them to<lb/> keep only six instead of seven days <date>Passover</date>&#59; would future generations<lb/> of Jews&#44; in the supposed cases&#44; be justified by veneration of antiquity<lb/> to continue to sin voluntarily&#44; because their ancestors had thus acted<lb/> from compulsion&#63;  &#8220;No&#8221; replies Holy Writ &#8220;Thou shalt neither<lb/> <hi rend="underline">add</hi> to nor diminish <hi rend="underline">from</hi> the law&#8221;  Should it be asked in case<lb/> of the abolition of the second day <add>Hebrew</add> what is to be done</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>when the <date>first day of Tishri</date> falls upon the <date>Sabbath</date> I answer&#44; <hi rend="underline">Obey</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">God</hi> and blow the <add>Hebrew</add> as <persName>Joshua</persName> did &#91;Chap 6&#93; for it were impious to<lb/> suppose that wrong&#44; which God commands and this command is as<lb/> irrespective of place and time as that of circumcision so frequently performed<lb/> on the <date>Sabbath</date>&#59; <hi rend="underline">in fact&#44; no tyranny of custom&#44; it matters not how old&#44; can</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">make void the word of the living God</hi></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">These double festivals&#44; with the exception of &#42;<add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#40;and even that festival was not always kept two days&#41; were never observed<lb/> in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>&#44; simply because its inhabitants had no doubt as to the<lb/> precise days on which the three festivals &#40;<add>Hebrew</add>&#41; were to be celebrated<lb/> and this example&#44; one would think should be an all&#45;sufficient reason<lb/> with modern Jews&#44; who possess an unerring calendar to abolish the<lb/> Custom</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">From the observations of <persName>Maimonides</persName> on this subject in his<lb/> Yad Hachazaka &#40;in Hilch Kidd Hachodesh and Hilch Yom Tob&#41;<lb/> it may be legitimately inferred that our great talmudical teacher<lb/> himself&#44; when he abstracts from the then state of things de facto&#44; and<lb/> addresses himself to the question de jure&#44; is no advocate for the perpetuity<lb/> of these supplemental days.  <persName>Maimonides</persName> not only calls the institution<lb/> of them a&#8212;<add>Hebrew</add>&#8212;<hi rend="underline">a fashion</hi> &#40;&#8220;Our celebration of the second day of these<lb/> festivals is a <hi rend="underline">fashion</hi> introduced by the sayings of the scribes&#44; an<lb/> innovation due to the state of dispersion&#8221; <add>&#63;</add> Yom Tob Ch 1 rule 21&#41;<lb/> but he says <hi rend="underline">totidem verbis</hi> that by rights the second day ought to be abolished.<lb/>  Here follow his words</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">&#8220;Now a days when there is no Sanhedrin&#44; and when the Beth Din<lb/> of <add>Hebrew</add> follows the actual calculation&#44; it would be just to have only <hi rend="underline">one</hi><lb/> holiday in <hi rend="underline">all</hi> places&#44; <hi rend="underline">even in those removed from <placeName>Palestine</placeName></hi>&#44; as well as<lb/> those in <add>Hebrew</add> in as much as they all rely on <hi rend="underline">one</hi> calculation&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">As the abolition of these supplemental days forms the most<lb/> salient point of difference between the Congregation of the <placeName>West<lb/> London</placeName> Synagogue of British Jews and their coreligionists&#44; and as<lb/> <persName>Mr Carillon</persName> has introduced several reforms into his own synagogue&#44;</p>
				<p>&#42;In those times it was requisite to observe two days <add>Hebrew</add> for the<lb/> messengers who were sent out upon the high places to watch the heavens<lb/> for the appearance of the new moon might have been impeded<lb/> in their observations by the state of the atmosphere and their<lb/> return to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> on the <date>thirtieth of Elul</date> been thereby prevented<lb/>&#59; in such case&#44; and <hi rend="underline">not otherwise</hi>&#44; if I rightly understand <persName>Maimonides</persName>&#44;<lb/> two days <add>Hebrew</add> were kept in the capital of <add>Hebrew</add>.  Further&#59;<lb/> as the feast of <add>Hebrew</add> is held on the <date>first day Tishri</date> there would<lb/> have been no opportunity to correct any error into which the messen&#45;<lb/>gers might have fallen&#44; if only one day had been observed</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>I have therefore dwelt the longer on this religiously important subject&#44;<lb/> which I now submit to the calm consideration of the reverend<lb/> gentleman</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I trust I shall not trespass too much on the valuable<lb/> and impartial pages of the Occident if I take this opportunity to<lb/> set <persName>Mr Carillon</persName> right as to the opinion entertained of the Talmud<lb/> by the <persName>Rev D. W. Harks</persName>.  Never did this gentleman unqualifiedly<lb/> deny its authority or speak disparagingly of the traditions contained<lb/> therein&#59; on the contrary&#44; he spake in terms highly eulogistic and<lb/> reverential of the authors of that work.  He did indeed say that the<lb/> Talmud was not so infallible a guide for the Israelites as the &#8220;One<lb/> immutable Law&#8221; contained in Holy Writ&#44; but let these words be taken<lb/> in <sic>connexion</sic> with the antecedent praise and with the whole paragraphs<lb/> of which they form a part and no unprejudiced person&#44; I am<lb/> bold to say&#44; will see in them aught that is not religiously true&#33;  And<lb/> here to enable the reader to judge for himself I subjoin the paragraph<lb/> in question extracted from the Discourse delivered in the <placeName>West London</placeName><lb/> Synagogue on the day of its consecration &#40;Vide Discourse p 748&#41;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">&#8220;Now let it not be supposed that it is the intention<lb/> of myself&#44; or of any member of this Congregation&#44; whose humble<lb/> organ I am&#44; to vilify&#44; in any way&#44; the character of the traditional<lb/> records.  ON the contrary&#44; we recognize in them a valuable aid for the<lb/> elucidation of many passages in scripture&#59; we feel proud of them as<lb/> a monument of the zeal and mental activity of our ancestors&#44; we<lb/> hold it our duty to reverence the sayings of men who&#44; we are convinced&#44;<lb/> would have sacrificed their lives for the maintenance of that Law<lb/> which God has vouchsafed to deliver unto us&#59; but we must &#40;as our<lb/> conviction urges us&#41; solemnly deny&#44; that a belief in the <hi rend="underline">divinity</hi> of<lb/> those traditions written in the Mishna and the <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and<lb/> Babylonian Talmuds&#44; is of equal obligation to the Israelite with the<lb/> faith in the divinity of the law of <persName>Moses</persName>.  WE know that these<lb/> books are human compositions&#59; and though we are content to accept<lb/> with reverence from our post&#45;biblical ancestors&#44; advice&#44; and instruction&#44;<lb/> we cannot <hi rend="underline">unconditionally</hi> accept their Laws.  For Israelites&#44; there<lb/> is but one immutable Law the sacred volume of the scriptures<lb/> commanded by God to be written down for the unerring guidance of his<lb/> people until the end of time&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is not unessential to observe&#44; that even these mild&#44;<lb/> measured remarks were not gratuitous&#44; but absolutely called for as the<lb/> Minister was then addressing his Congregation for the first time<lb/> after himself and they had been excommunicated under the charge<lb/> &#40;<hi rend="underline">utterly groundless by the bye</hi>&#41; of having denied the divinity of the Oral<lb/> Law...I hope I do not offend <persName>Mr Carillon</persName> by supposing that he</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>under parallel circumstances&#44; would not have expressed himself more<lb/> respectfully of the Talmud than his brother Minister spoke of it</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am most anxious to avail myself of the present opportunity<lb/> to inform <persName>Mr Henry Goldsmith</persName>&#44; that the charge &#40;Occident No 8&#41; he has<lb/> brought against the members of the <placeName>Burton Street</placeName> Synagogue of having<lb/> repudiated the wearing of Tephilin is wholly devoid of truth.  I<lb/> unhesitatingly acquit <persName>Mr Goldsmith</persName> of <sic>wilful</sic> misrepresentation and<lb/> refer him to the first volume No 12 of the Voice of Jacob page 89 where<lb/> he will find that a &#8220;<hi rend="underline">rumour</hi>&#8221; had reached its editor that the &#8220;Secession<lb/> Congregation&#8221; had determined by a majority of two in <hi rend="underline">favor of</hi> not against&#44; the wearing of <add>Hebrew</add> The following note from the Editor shows that there<lb/> was not a scintilla of truth even in the above &#8220;rumour&#8221; hence I trust<lb/> <persName>Mr Goldsmith</persName> will in future&#44; exercise a little wholesome <sic>scepticism</sic> &#40;not<lb/> inaptly called one of the nerves of wisdom&#41; when reports again reach him<lb/> as to the proceedings of the <placeName>Burton Street</placeName> Synagogue.  The Editor&#39;s note<lb/> alluded to is as follows &#8220;This rumour referred to the obligation of<lb/> wearing <add>Hebrew</add>.  After we had gone to press&#44; an authorized explanation<lb/> reached us&#44; that this particular question was not put to the vote.  It was&#44; on the<lb/> contrary&#44; an understanding&#44; that the <add>Hebrew</add> should be worn during<lb/> the service of every day on which they were worn in the established synagogues.<lb/>  On the morning of <add>Hebrew</add> those who could not conscientiously comply with<lb/> this understanding were absent from service&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I return to the subject of the double festivals as<lb/> I wish to observe before I conclude that if I had supposed Talmudic<lb/> knowledge essential to the proper understanding of the question at<lb/> issue&#44; then&#44; most assuredly&#44; I had not been so presumptuous as to discuss<lb/> a matter so transcendently important&#44; but&#44; I rely with some confidence<lb/> on arguments&#44; which&#44; seem to me&#44; to rest on the force of truth&#44; the energy<lb/> of common sense and upon the all&#45;sustaining pillars of Holy Writ</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Reverend Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Yours very respectfully</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)"><persName role="author">B. E.</persName></p>
				<p><placeName>Upper Beaford Place</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Russell Square</placeName></p>
				<p><placeName>London</placeName> <date>March 28th 1844</date></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
