<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF4_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola,
                            Abraham</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Montreal, Canada</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1857-02">19 February 1857</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1857-02">19 February 5617</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0013_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0013_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0013_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f4_0013_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Montreal</placeName>
                <date>19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. 5617</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Dear Sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">I have had no time to notice yours<lb/> of <date>1<hi rend="sup"
                        >st</hi></date> ult till now. There are one or two remarks I think it<lb/>
                right to make. You seem to be under the impression that I<lb/> required a public
                apology from you in the matter of the <placeName>Phila</placeName><lb/> election and
                the article you wrote about my testimonials.<lb/> But this is wrong. As you write so
                do I. I was and am willing<lb/> to drop it. If you have my last letter, refer to it,
                you will find<lb/> I say “let this pass” I merely required that did I write for
                the<lb/> Advocate or any other publication edited by you you should<lb/> make the
                amende honorable for your <hi rend="underline">short</hi> (as you <add>?</add><lb/>
                criticize of <persName>Pennoch</persName> by indirectly (I believe this was the
                term<lb/> employed) recalling your charge—expressed or implied—no matter<lb/>
                which—in said critique—that I was not <add>?</add> safe &amp; etc. This<lb/> was all
                &amp; it surely was not asking much for your industrious<lb/> and unsparing
                dissection of the Catechism. About remuneration<lb/> there will be no difficulty—you
                revert again to the election at <placeName>Phila</placeName><lb/> and say (I make a
                few comments en parenthese) you have it<lb/> in your power to prove that your
                interference with me [I<lb/> never interfered with you] was owing to letters recd
                from <placeName>Phil</placeName><lb/> [I <hi rend="underline">have</hi> letters to
                prove that ll<add>?</add> your friends justified my <add>?</add><lb/> ministers
                included—though same were with you <add>אחד בפה ואחד בלב</add>]<lb/> “Why not do so?
                You continue, send on the letters you owe the<lb/> scamps that deceived you no favor
                [Cui bono? I was near showing<lb/> you the letters when you were here but I took the
                second and</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>better thought why should not my word be sufficient? Why embitter<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L.</persName>
                <del>still</del> more against them, they against him by raking up old<lb/>
                grievances. No! <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> will one day be <add>?</add> and find that<lb/>
                <persName role="author">A.D.S.</persName> Is not so black as he paints him] “and no
                principle of<lb/> honor can bind you in respect to them. Here again I take a<lb/>
                leaf out of your own book and say I cannot allow any one<lb/> to dictate to me the
                code of honor. It is as accessible to me as<lb/> to others, and having equal right
                to put my own interpretation<lb/> on its requirements, I always have done so and
                intend please<lb/> God always yet to do so. What you write about my editing<lb/> a
                periodical connecting myself with <persName>Dr. R.L</persName>
                <persName>Dr L L.</persName> (By the<lb/> way <add>?</add> made the latter a Dr I
                thought he was only Mr)<lb/> in publishing—a thing I never contemplated yet—your
                cautious<lb/> about looking out carefully—uncertainty <add>?</add>
                profit—estimate<lb/> of popularity—inconvenience of losing money—to all these
                    <add>?</add><lb/> I do not deem it necessary to reply. If I desired to publish
                a<lb/> magazine tomorrow I do not see why I should stop to ask <persName>Messrs<lb/>
                    Lyons</persName>
                <persName>Wise</persName> &amp; <persName>Isaacs</persName> their consent more than
                any good Christian<lb/> would ask leave of any brother respected in the flesh. You
                would<lb/> not require me to ask you, for you say so. I notice your advice<lb/> not
                to <hi rend="underline">attack</hi> you should I edit or assist in editing this<lb/>
                imaginary paper. Why should I do this even in the land of dreams<lb/> without
                    <add>?</add> I may say that when I <add>?</add> provocation<lb/> enough, I feel
                courage enough to attack any one and defend<lb/> myself from any one, though they be
                the giants, &amp; I the <sic>pigmy</sic>.<lb/> But seriously, what is the use our
                exchanging letters all<lb/> about visionary nothings, and old old topics. Let
                them<lb/> go to the tomb of all the 6 amulets In future I promise I shall<lb/> be
                more business like when I shall have occasion to write<lb/> you. In writing upon
                other topics you forgot<lb/> to say the list for the Advocate came to hand. This
                list</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>however small, would not show I had any idea of <hi rend="underline"
                >warring</hi><lb/> with you. If I mistake you, you also mistake me. I<lb/> patiently
                assure you I am no covert enemy of yours; but I<lb/> do not write on the orthodox
                side to please you—God forbid<lb/> and if I wished to enter into a disagreeable
                topic I would call<lb/> offensive that part of your letter wherein you
                    <sic>advise</sic> me not to<lb/> write for the Israelite or Asmonean. “I would
                not have your<lb/> enemies” hear of such advice, and i must again say that I<lb/> am
                convicted enough to use my own judgment in this matter.<lb/> My father never advised
                me thus much, simply because he<lb/> has a better opinion of me than you seem to
                have or perhaps<lb/> than your letters imply. But you cannot put me out of<lb/>
                conceit with you. I do not easily throw aside old acquaintances<lb/> Your last was
                written in a very bitter spirit and in any one<lb/> else I should have treated it as
                a piece of very great impertinence<lb/> but I have never lost for you feelings of
                true respect and regard<lb/> even in our most inimical moments—even when you
                have<lb/> been most surly and ill-humored, and I the model of<lb/> patience and
                consideration thought you had treated me<lb/> harshly and ungenerously, for I have
                always accepted as<lb/> true your assurance that if in your labors you have had<lb/>
                successes you have had more disappointments &amp; unpleasantness<lb/>—I was truly
                sorry to notice your announcement of a fire again in<lb/> the bindery—I trust you
                are no loser.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In conclusion please notice what it was I<lb/> really required of
                you in my last and how very easily my<lb/> injured honor would be satisfied and
                sullied reputation<lb/> restored to its pristine purity &amp; brilliancy by you,
                should<lb/> it be deemed desirable by either of us to write in any</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>enterprise. Trusting that from this day forward<lb/> somos buenos amigos <add>רעים
                    אהודים</add> sine el <add>חמץ</add> les otras dias</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I remain as ever yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName>
            </p>
            <p>Oblige me by handing the<lb/> enclosed to <persName>Miss Gratz.</persName> If
                not<lb/> troubling you too much I would<lb/> prefer your giving it yourself<lb/>
                rather than sending.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
