<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Miller, M. R.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Miller, M. R.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-01">15 January 1851</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0008_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>acceptable penitent; and, thirdly, the improbability that the law will<lb/> free the
                transgressor from its curse merely on the ground that he<lb/> has repented. The
                inquiry now is What is the round of merit or of<lb/> satisfaction, on which
                according to the Sacred Scriptures God pardons<lb/> sin? If the threatened penalty
                cannot be dispensed with, either we<lb/> must suffer it ourselves or some other must
                suffer in our<lb/> place. If the first threatening that in the day of the eating of
                the<lb/> forbidden fruit <persName>Adam</persName> should die, exhibits the standard
                measure of<lb/> all the penalties of disobedience, or if we may discover the
                common<lb/> measure in the appointment that the man who should eat the
                for=<lb/>bidden bread during the <date>Passover</date> should be cut off from the
                con=<lb/>gregation of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, or if the penalty of each of
                the ten command=<lb/>ments is death, we cannot suffer for ourselves the penalty,
                except in<lb/> our hopeless death or moral ruin. The cup of the wrath of God is<lb/>
                not to be exhausted by our sinful lips. It is the challenge of God to<lb/> every
                impenitent sinner: “Can thine heart endure, or can thine hands<lb/> be strong, in
                the days that I will deal with thee?” <persName>Ezek.</persName> 22:14.<lb/> The
                higher our views of the justice holiness and truth of God, the<lb/> deeper and
                despair in view of our own sin. Can any one then take<lb/> our place and die for us?
                The substitute must himself be without<lb/> sin, and under no obligation to suffer
                for himself. Further, God<lb/> would not accept a substitute who is unable for our
                place, who, in<lb/> suffering for us, would himself be ruined. A suitable
                substitute<lb/> must have power to lay down his life and to take it again.<lb/> This
                power, <persName>Jesus</persName> claimed.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Hebrew Scriptures give us many solemn lessons on<lb/> atonement
                by death. The blood was sacredly set apart and forbid=<lb/>den in common use, it
                being that part of the living system through<lb/> which an atonement for the soul
                was made upon the altar. Hence<lb/> it is a saying of the <sic>Rabbies</sic>,
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> the essential matter of atonement is in the blood. This
                doctrine<lb/> never became obsolete among the prophets; on the contrary, it
                grew<lb/> and ripened. It is in the last prophecies “Seventy weeks are
                deter=<lb/>mined„ upon thy people, and upon thy holy city”—so we read in
                    <persName>Dan=<lb/>iel</persName>,— “to finish the transgression, and to make an
                end of sins,<lb/> and to make atonement for iniquity, and to bring in
                everlas=<lb/>ting righteousness, and to seal up the vision and prophecy,<lb/> and to
                anoint a holy of holies.” Hebrew and Christian<lb/> commentators agree that here a
                period of years is designated<lb/> which must have come to an end in the first
                century of the<lb/> Christian Era. But, notwithstanding this agreement, there
                is<lb/> a wide difference in the interpretations. The Christian beholds<lb/> in
                these events predicted by <persName>Daniel</persName>, the expiatory and
                all-sufficient<lb/> sufferings of his Messiah, the everlasting righteousness in
                which<lb/> the sinner may be accepted, the restraint laid on the condemning<lb/>
                power of sin, the grand <sic>fulfilment</sic> of visions and prophecies,<lb/> and
                the spiritual consecration of a new sanctuary and commu=<lb/>nity of worshipers. The
                Christian finds this prophecy full of<lb/> consolation: on the contrary, in the
                Jewish interpretation,</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>it loses all its features of promise. This finishing of trans=<lb/>gression is the
                full preparation through hardness of heart un=<lb/>belief and immorality, for the
                captivity of the last eighteen hun=<lb/>dred years; this end of sins is the swelling
                of the flood of<lb/> sin to the highest measure; this atonement for iniquity
                commen=<lb/>ces and continues in the captivity which still exists; the bringing<lb/>
                in of everlasting righteousness may be either the process of becom=<lb/>ing
                externally righteous through the present captivity, or the sup=<lb/>pression of the
                righteousness of the fathers and prophets; the seal=<lb/>ing up of the visions of
                prophets is a lamentable termination, not<lb/> a grand consummation; the anointing
                of a holy of holies is the<lb/> shutting up of the temple by the anointed. When
                    <persName>Ezra</persName> is the com=<lb/>mentator whom I here have before me.
                How bright and com=<lb/>forting this passage to the Christian! How dark to the
                Jew.<lb/> it is like the cloud that gave light to the Israelites, and was<lb/>
                darkness to the Egyptians.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">According to the preceding views, the transgressor needs a<lb/> more
                holy nature that he may be capable of repenting, and an atone=<lb/>ment by blood
                that he may be delivered from the curse. The gos=<lb/>pel meets the first need in
                the sanctification which the Holy<lb/> Spirit works, and the second need in the
                atonement of <persName>Christ</persName><lb/> It appears to us that if ever an
                anxious self-condemned despair=<lb/>ing Jew derived consolation from the fact that
                the blood of his<lb/> victim on the altar was appointed his atonement, we may<lb/>
                derive still greater consolation from the atonement of
                <persName>Christ</persName>.<lb/> No wonder, however, that the latter is foolishness
                to those who<lb/> feel that they stand in no need of an atonement.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In conclusion, let one attend to your appeal to remove some<lb/>
                difficulties.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">On 1 <persName>John</persName> 5:7, I have no desire to enter into
                any discussion.<lb/> You may decide as you please on the genuineness.—Unless you
                force<lb/> into the following passage a change of the speaker, it is as clear
                on<lb/> the doctrine of the Trinity as the above disputed verse. Is. 48:15.<lb/>16.
                “I, even I, have spoken; yea, I have called him; I have brought<lb/> him, and he
                shall make his way prosperous. Come near unto me, hear<lb/> ye this; I have not
                spoken in secret from the beginning; from the time<lb/> that it was, there am I: <hi
                    rend="underline">and now the Lord God hath sent me and</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">his Spirit</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You find a difficulty in the verse: “And when all things shall
                be<lb/> subdued unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subject unto<lb/> him
                that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.”<lb/> We do not contend
                that <persName>Christ</persName> will continue eternally in his office<lb/> of
                high-priest and intercessor. He represents himself as the way<lb/> to the Father,
                but this way will be eventually closed; and<lb/> then woe to those who have despised
                the last and only means<lb/> of reconciliation to God.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The opposition to Christianity and its abuse have fulfilled<lb/> the
                prediction of the sending of the sword among men. <persName>Jesus</persName>
                never</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>intimated that if all men would become his true followers, they could<lb/> not live
                together without the sword.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">From my childhood my impression has always been that
                    <persName>Mat-<lb/>thew</persName> and <persName>Luke</persName> tell different
                parts of one consistent narrative in<lb/> relation to the end of
                    <persName>Judas</persName>. He first strangled or hanged him=<lb/>self: in this
                condition he fell and was crushed, as <persName>Luke</persName><lb/> describes.
                Where is the contradiction?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Detestable Presbyterianism! “A distinguished Presbyterian<lb/>
                divine has said “<hi rend="underline">Hell is paved with the skulls of
                infants</hi>.” Pos=<lb/>sibly you were never more surprised in your life than you
                will<lb/> be when you see it here asserted that we Presbyterians do not<lb/> hold
                every thing which our ministers say, as proceeding from di=<lb/>vine inspiration.
                There is, however, one sentence which we hold<lb/> to be inspired: please direct
                your next attack against it.<lb/> “Suffer little children to come unto me and forbid
                them not, for<lb/> of such is the kingdom of heaven.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is a mystery why you propose difficulties which a child can<lb/>
                answer. I once put the question to an Israelite, if he would not<lb/> be willing to
                sacrifice all that he has, even his own life, to know<lb/> the truth of
                Christianity, it is true. He gave me a very<lb/> evasive answer: his conscience
                appeared to whisper that he knew<lb/> himself not to be anxious on the point, and
                that he had best not<lb/> dissemble.—Prejudice makes us blind. In our prejudice we
                are<lb/> not true to our own highest interests.</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours most respectfully,</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <persName role="author">M. R. Miller</persName>
            </p>
            <p><placeName>New York</placeName>
                <date>Jan. 16, 1851</date>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>
                <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I send you the following subscribers for the<lb/> next volume of the
                Occident. *They are good pay.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr Gains Fenn</persName>
                <placeName>New Haven. Connecticut</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <persName>Rev. H. M. Willson</persName>
                <placeName>251 Elizabeth st. N. Y.</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <persName>Rev. David M. Holliday</persName>
                <placeName>Peckskill N. Y.</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>I shall try to get you more subscribers as I have opportunity,<lb/> and I will be a
                subscriber for your <del>daily paper</del> weekly paper.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In relation to your notes on my last. I suppose I need not<lb/>
                inform you of the extreme difficulty in persuading Christians that<lb/> our Heavenly
                Father makes such a difference between Jews and<lb/> Christians that what would be
                idolatry to the former is allowable<lb/> to the latter. The Christian will not cease
                to think that if he has<lb/> the same light which the Jew has, he is under the same
                obligations<lb/> of obedience and reverence to our common Father. And why<lb/>
                should it not be so? God may say to the Jews, Let other nations<lb/> go after their
                gods, but do you follow me, just as a father<lb/> may say to one of his sons. Let
                the other children go on, but do you obey me,—this however would signify no approval
                of the<lb/> disobedient.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You understand this as a private remark, not intended<lb/> for any
                public notice.</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">Your friend truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">M. R. Miller</persName>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>. </p>
            <p>* To commence with the <date>April</date> No.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
