<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Wise, Isaac M.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF17_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Wise, Isaac
                            M.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_3v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_4r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false">Fragile</condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Small Pin No 4.<lb/>4/</p>
            <p>Principles of Judaism<lb/> No 12</p>
            <p>Occident copy<lb/>
                <date>July</date></p>
            <p>1.</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">To the Editor of the Occident.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The object of this letter is to<lb/> continue my objections against
                the dogma<lb/> of the <sic>resurection</sic> of the body, and to<lb/> vindicate the
                doctrine of the immortality<lb/> of the soul; wherefore you will excuse me,<lb/>
                that I at once commence without <del>all fashionable</del> any farther<lb/>
                    preface<del>s</del>. The process of life is a continual<lb/> struggle of the
                principle of life with <del>the</del><lb/> organic matter; that principle of life
                puts in this manner<lb/> the organic machine <del>thus</del> in such a rapid
                and<lb/> uninterrupted motion, that the latter is<lb/> so much impaired and
                enfeebled, that the<lb/> former <del>might</del> would make its escape, if the
                mate=<lb/>rial machine <del>be</del> were not strengthened by rest,<lb/> and
                nutritious food. So we see the<lb/> principle of life always active
                    <add>struggling</add> to escape from<lb/> its organic prison, which calls to our
                mind<lb/> the words of an ancient sage <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> “thou livest against
                thy will.” Still we <del>feel sorry</del> experience regret<lb/> when the hour of
                departure comes; the<lb/> principle of life has <del>thus</del> been so long
                accustomed <del>itself</del><lb/> to its organic companion, that the hour<lb/> of
                separation is an hour of agony and pain; wherefore said the ancient sage<lb/> “thou
                diest against thy null” <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <del>said the ancient sage.</del> There is no man who is as<lb/> pious and
                    <del>so</del> righteous, so virtuous and good<lb/> as he could be; none has ever
                done as much good as<lb/> he <del>could</del> might have done; none
                    <sic>developes</sic> his mental faculties<lb/> capacities to <del>that</del> the
                highest degree which they are<lb/> capable of attaining; consequently every man<lb/>
                has his faults, his infirmities, his sins,<lb/> which he <del>like so very
                    much</del> is exceedingly anxious to cover with<lb/> the veil of obscurity and
                forgetfulness.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>But notwithstanding all this, <del>Still</del> we know that above us is the eye,
                which<lb/> sees every thing; an Ear which hears every thing<lb/> and all our
                transactions are recorded in the<lb/> book<del>s</del> of everlasting memorial; we
                still <del>we</del><lb/> must give account before a Judge who knows<lb/> the
                thoughts of the heart, although we wish<lb/> to have our transactions covered and forgotten<lb/>
                <del>„thou sh wilt</del><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> Thou will have to give an account „of thy deeds against they
                will.”<lb/> Life in general is a chain of <del>antiteses</del>
                opposites<add>?</add>, of<lb/> struggles, of sacrifices, of self-denial, of
                temp=<lb/>tations; such is the life of the virtuous, while<lb/> that of the vicious
                is a series of miseries, of<lb/> calamities and self-contempt, wherefore
                an-<lb/>other ancient sage said <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> “It <del>is</del> would have
                been better for man not to <del>be born</del> have been created than to <del>be
                    born</del> have been.”<lb/> After I have now lived against my will, and<lb/>
                sacrificed my joys and pleasures, born the<lb/> persecutions, the
                    <del>wounding</del> scoff, the ironic<lb/> satire, the <del>hellish</del>
                malignity of men; after<lb/> I <del>went</del> have gone f<del>r</del>orth
                triumphantly from all tempta=<lb/>tions and <del>irritations</del> excitement; after
                I have died and have<lb/> given account of my acts; after the truth has become<lb/>
                mine, and I am permitted to live in the<lb/> company of <del>adequate</del>
                congenial spirits, ravished and<lb/> satisfied with the glory <del>of the
                    Glory</del> of the<lb/> Most High, <del>I</del> shall I be forced to live
                again<lb/> on this earth? No, that is impossible,<lb/> I think too much of the
                goodness of God,<lb/> that <del>I could think</del> the should inflict <del>such
                    a</del> so horrible a wrong<lb/>
                <del>done by God himself</del> on his creatures.</p>
            <p>Hence we must <del>consider</del> keep in mind that God said<lb/> to
                    <persName>Adam</persName>, “In the sweat of thy face shalt thou<lb/> eat bread,
                till thou return unto the ground, for<lb/> out of it wast thou taken; for dust thou
                art</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and unto dust shalt thou return.” (Genesis 3. 19.)<lb/>
                <persName>Abigail</persName> said to <persName>David</persName>, “But the soul of
                my<lb/> lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with<lb/> the Lord thy God” (I
                    <persName>Samuel</persName> 25. 29). <persName>David</persName><lb/> said, “For
                thou wilt not <del>cead</del> gild my soul to the<lb/> grave, thou wilt not suffer
                thy pious one to see<lb/>
                <sic>distruction</sic>; thou <sic>wist</sic> make known unto me<lb/> the path of
                life, the <sic>fulness</sic> of joy (which is)<lb/> with thy presence, (and) the
                pleasures (which are)<lb/> at thy right hand for evermore” (Psalm 16. 10,11.)<lb/>
                We do not see, how any one can torture these passages to <add>?</add><lb/> into a
                resurrection of the body.</p>
            <p>If a general resurrection of the body will take place, the question<lb/>
                <del>it is to be asked,</del> arises will <del>the arisen ones</del> the revived die
                again<lb/> or not? in case they die again, another general<lb/> resurrection must
                take place, and then an-<lb/>other one, and another one and so forth <del>into</del>
                to an<lb/> infinity of resurrections; but in case they die not,<lb/> then it will be
                a new creation, but not these<lb/> very same bodies which have died; for they are
                so<lb/> composed, that they continually change their state<lb/> and particles,
                dimensions, form and colour,<lb/> consequently they must die. Hence, what use
                is<lb/> in the resurrection of the body? If our opponents<lb/> say, the soul cannot
                perfectly exist, enjoy the purest<lb/> pleasures &amp; live in the happiest manner
                before<lb/> God in the <del>chorus</del> assembly of Angels and <del>adequate</del>
                congenial<lb/> spirits then they must first deny the doctrines<lb/> of Judaism,
                which <del>makes</del> teaches God to be a<lb/> pure, and absolute spirit, and as
                God exists<lb/> without the aid of a body, just as well the<lb/> disembodied human
                spirit which is the <sic>immage</sic> of God, <del>can</del> exist with<lb/> all
                    <del>his</del> its excellencies and <del>all his</del> faculties:<lb/> And if
                they admit this <del>thesis</del> portion, <del>then</del> they must<lb/> confess,
                that the soul not only derives no</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>advantage from a <sic>resurection</sic> of <del>his</del> the body, but<lb/> he is
                again forced into a piece of clay <del>of clay</del>,<lb/> which enfeebles
                    <del>his</del> its faculties, and deprives <del>him</del><lb/> it of the highest
                joy, to be with God, to<lb/> know the truth. I <sic>recieved</sic> lately a book,
                of<lb/> which a very few copies exist, viz: The book<lb/> of <add>Hebrew</add>
                <persName>Tobias</persName> the Physician the grandson of the author of<lb/>
                “Beginning of Wisdom” <add>Hebrew</add>, in which a great deal of Kabbalah and<lb/>
                physical matters are mingled in the same<lb/> manner that his grandfather has
                    <del>intermixed</del> mixed up<lb/>
                <del>the</del> Kabbalah with the most sublime moral<lb/> philosophy. One passage of
                this book is<lb/> remarkable and has a strong bearing upon<lb/> our subject,
                wherefore I shall give you an<lb/> epitome of it; bear in mind, the author was<lb/>
                a Kabbalist of the dark ages: “The principle of<lb/>
                <persName>Rabbi Jacob Yakof</persName> (Kiddushin Vol 39) <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                “the reward to virtue is not in this world” (but<lb/> in a world to come) has met
                with decided<lb/> opposition among the Rabbis and among<lb/> the doctors of our age;
                they supposed, the<lb/> soul <del>is</del> in a pure state is unfit to
                    <sic>recieve</sic><lb/> either reward or punishment, wherefore<lb/> they said a
                resurrection of the body must<lb/> take place; and since so many Jews died<lb/> for
                their faith, or pined away in oppression<lb/> and distress because of their
                Religion, they<lb/> say, the resurrection must take place shortly after<lb/> the
                coming of the messiah, that those pious<lb/> martyrs may be rewarded and enabled to
                rejoice in the<lb/> final triumph of Judaism; but as to those<lb/> who adhere to the
                principle of <persName>Rabbi Jacob Yakof</persName><lb/> the doctrine of a
                resurrection of the body is<lb/> altogether superfluous.” I hope my opponents<lb/>
                will not excommunicate this old <del>author</del> writer.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">fol. 3.</p>
            <p><del>wherefor they painted the</del> would called by them <add>Hebrew</add> or also<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> with such splendid colours; but<lb/> others made <del>the</del> a
                mistake <del>to take</del> in assuming this <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> for the future
                state of life of the same human<lb/> beings, which produced the
                    <sic>phantastic</sic> doctrine<lb/> of the resurrection of the body. And even
                if<lb/> we take for granted, that this world will be<lb/> destroyed and re-created,
                still the resurrection<lb/> is an impossibility. In the crust of the earth we<lb/>
                see, that the former destructions of organic life<lb/>
                <del>was</del> were effected by water, as the remains of marine<lb/> animals in all
                parts of the globe plainly show;<lb/> the water stood very long over the whole
                globe,<lb/> which the thick strata having settled down from<lb/> standing water
                plainly indicate; the organic<lb/> beings were buried under the mud, which the<lb/>
                water was mixed with, and after the <sic>seperation</sic><lb/> of land and water,
                volcanic eruptions threw<lb/> the organic matter upon the surface of the earth,<lb/>
                as some volcanoes do even in our times, and<lb/> of which the surface of the earth
                bears evidence; after which<lb/>
                <del>then</del> a new creation of organic being commen,<lb/>ced. No seed, no egg, no
                being of former<lb/> kingdoms of life could escape the general<lb/> destruction, nor
                remain uncorrupted for so<lb/> long a period of time in the dissolving water<lb/> of
                the sea; consequently each successive <del>creation</del> change<lb/> was an
                independent <del>one</del>, entirely new, a creation.<lb/> It cannot be called a
                gradual transition; for<lb/> each successive creation represents a greater
                variety<lb/> of kinds, more <del>accomplished</del> complicated and more artful<lb/>
                organizations, so that only the inorganic matter<lb/> was improved by the previous
                creations, but the<lb/> animate beings themselves were always created<lb/> anew and
                independent of these former existing.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>This destructive and re-creative process we meet<lb/> with six times in the crust of
                the earth (remember<lb/> the six days of creation) consequently we are bound to<lb/>
                say “these are the laws of nature established by the will of<lb/> God for such
                revolutions.” If now the world<lb/> should be destroyed and re-created once
                more,<lb/> it must certainly be in the same way as formerly;<lb/> all bodies must be
                dissolved, the organic matter improved,<lb/> which will be thrown up by
                    <del>thrown</del> volcanic eruptions<lb/> of the earth's surface, and a new and
                independent<lb/> creation be commenced. Now it would <del>it</del> be possible<lb/>
                enough, that the same souls with their devel-<lb/>oped capacities, acquired
                abilities, increased ener<lb/>gies and pure, consciousness of their former<lb/>
                state be re-clothed in an improved organic<lb/> body, and live again a human life
                though<lb/> of a higher order; still this very body in which<lb/> we are clothed now
                cannot resurrect to be<lb/> once more our garment as the old doctrine<lb/> of
                resurrection asserts; then it must therefore be a new<lb/> creation and no such
                thing as a resurrection.<lb/> I hope you will confess, that I seriously<lb/>
                reflected on my subject, and that I can in<lb/> some measure account for that fatal
                “no,”<lb/> which I uttered in <placeName>Charleston</placeName>; I must tell<lb/>
                you if my opponents can give as much<lb/> ground for their “yes” I am perfectly<lb/>
                satisfied; But still if you can prove<lb/> by the bible, that I am bound to
                believe<lb/> a literal resurrection of the body, I shall<lb/> calmly lay aside all
                these insurmountable<lb/> difficulties, and—believe. I am now<lb/> about writing an
                Essay on immortality, which<lb/> I trust, since it is a reading matter to every<lb/>
                man and not merely to the Jew, will be</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>published next summer, and I hope, it will<lb/> diffuse better views on that
                important sub<lb/>ject, than those entertained now.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Assuring you of my best friendship</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">and esteem I am always</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">truly yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">Isaac M. Wise</persName> DD</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
