<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">"A Looker-on"</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF1_52</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">"A Looker-on"</author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1866-12" source="" attested="yes">9 December 1866</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_2v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0052_3r.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>5 pages on 5 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Jewish Ministry</placeName></p>
				<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
				<p rend="align(right)">Editor of the Occident</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">If ever I have felt enhanced the interest with<lb/> which I peruse the pages of the &#8220;Occident&#8221;it was on <sic>successeively</sic><lb/> reading the leaders in your <sic>isseues</sic> of <date>June</date> <date>July</date> &#38; <date>August</date> &#38; I feel<lb/> how very inadequately I am permitted to applaud you for thus con&#45;<lb/>vincingly demonstrating the necessity of a Jewish Theological high<lb/> school whence may come forth men earnest in the cause of<lb/> God to teach the unlettered &#38; thus contribute their portion to the<lb/> welfare of their fellow creatures.  I may in the way of<lb/> preface remark &#8212; altho&#39; by the bye preambles are not part of my<lb/> habits&#44; on the contrary&#44; I am known to introduce myself unawares<lb/> even at the risk of meeting an unwelcome&#44; in the way of preface<lb/> however&#44; I must say that altho&#39; I entirely coincide with you in the<lb/> basis of your dissertation there are points commented upon by<lb/> you in which there is an honest difference in our views.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It would be affectation to attempt if even a mild insinuation<lb/> that Judaism does not feel the want of pious teachers&#44; men who will<lb/> undertake to instruct the people the tenets of their faith as held by<lb/> our father <persName>Abraham</persName> of blessed memory&#44; &#45; we are happily not with&#45;<lb/>out a few such but as unfortunately the number is small&#44; there<lb/> is a pressing <del>a</del> demand to afford the means that <del>their <add>&#63;</add> is <add>&#63;</add> </del> <lb/> it may increase I wish not to be understood as speaking dis&#45;<lb/>paragingly of those who have sacrificed their time to the cause of their<lb/> faith&#44; on the contrary they are the bright specks<add>&#63;</add> on which the mind<lb/> loves to reflect &#38; the only regret which the reflections bring forth<lb/> is that the entire ministry is not so well composed.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The mission of the Minister is not fully applied <add>by those who undertake it</add> &#38; thus it<lb/> is that the love of gain&#44; a prevailing defect let us admit it&#44; &#38; the ambi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">2</p>
				<p>of being at the head of a congregation&#44; thereby recuring<add>&#63;</add> a respec&#45;<lb/>table position&#44; sometimes for life time have brought forth as<lb/> God&#39;s messengers men&#44; who not being of the right stamp have com&#45;<lb/>pletely failed in the work&#44; where in piety &#38;  sincerity were upper&#45;<lb/>most a perfect success would have been the consequence. You<lb/> rightly observe Sir &#8220;if he wishes to do his whole duty&#8221; &#38; here is the<lb/> hinge of a great many of the differences &#38; dissensions which we so often<lb/> experience in the ranks of religion. A minister&#39;s duties&#33; <sic>how</sic><lb/> varied they are&#44; to what material benefit they would tend if piously<lb/> fulfilled&#44; how honorable the profession if sincerity was made the<lb/> leading trait &#38; of what blessings it would prove if rightly <sic>practised</sic>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Let us suppose Sir &#8212; but no&#44; it is not supposition the writer<lb/> of this has such a personal experience &#8212; that a minister in private<lb/> conversation repeatedly admits a certain principle which he<lb/> thinks practicable &#38; recommends the means to attain the deside&#45;<lb/>ratum &#38; when  the parties thus instructed are preparing them&#45;<lb/>selves for the task&#44; their guide ascends the pulpit &#38; there&#44; where no hu&#45;<lb/>man voice can contradict him he advances notions diametri&#45;<lb/>cally opposed to what he had agreed upon &#38; emits the thunders of<lb/> his vatican on those who believe &#38; are prepared to act in the man&#45;<lb/>ner which he impressed <add>on</add> them to be his belief &#38; his readiness to act.<lb/> Now Sir&#44; can any genuine honor he attached to such a host &#38; can<lb/> the man who thus deceives lay claim to that deference which<lb/> ennobles him who knows to whom to grant it&#63;  I know<lb/> your reuse of right &#38; I imagine I see you shuddering at the state&#45;<lb/>ment I have made I imagine hearing you exclaim<lb/> Oh&#33; That such pretended advocates of Truth could be laid aside &#38; if<lb/> for the glory of our religion they cannot reform&#44; could they be made<lb/> to be quiet whilst they are among the people &#38; holding there an exal&#45;<lb/>ted office. Whether the words which escape the lips of</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">3</p>
				<p>such an individual be the choicest&#44; or whether he be versed in rhe&#45;<lb/>toric &#38; knows all the mimics  particular to oratory&#44; it is <sic>imposseible</sic><lb/> for his exhortations to have the desired effect on those who know that<lb/> the lips beguile the heart true&#33;  There may be some who<lb/> imagine that their favorite preacher<lb/> is the personification of truth&#44; he is all that can be desired&#44; he may<lb/> even be supposed to be unlike his specie&#44; frail &#38; erring. But of course<lb/> such conclusions are not the result of calm &#38; deliberate reflection<lb/> &#38; they are only mentioned here as forming a connecting link<lb/> to the moral weakness which is so general. There is perhaps no<lb/> occupation in life from which more honor &#38; satisfaction could<lb/> be attained than the ministry&#44; but of course it has its solemn respon&#45;<lb/>sibilites &#38; if there are sacrifices it is but natural to picture that shame<lb/> &#38; disgrace will ensue. The Jewish minister&#39;s chief aim should<lb/> be to establish peace in his congregation &#38; by no means should he<lb/> be found fanning the flame which may unfortunately exist&#44; but<lb/> always holding the olive branch&#44; it is his mission to propagate<lb/> peace &#38; be the medium of reconciling those who are divided&#44; he<lb/> should make his flock one large family of which he is appointed<lb/> to act as father&#44; <sic>counsellor</sic> &#38; guide&#44; he is to be their judge &#38; with<lb/> the scale of Justice weighing in equal poise he is to arrange what&#45;<lb/>ever differences arise. Oh what an opportunity for a<lb/> faithful &#38; sincere heart to manifest its throbbings&#44; of what high<lb/> importance would such a chief be in truth could it be said of<lb/> him that his value exceedeth that of rubies. Identifying him&#45;<lb/>self with the being of his flock&#44; he is to partake of their pleasures &#38;<lb/> mourn with them over their sorrows&#44; a true friend&#44; he proves him&#45;<lb/>self as such in the time of need. With satisfaction he joins<lb/> them in the events when gladness pervades their home&#44; &#38; with</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">4</p>
				<p>the experiences which should naturally characterize his post he<lb/> warns them of the uncertainty of the duration of earthly pleasures<lb/> in kindress it <sic>behoves</sic> him to say to them &#8220;boast not of to&#45;day&#8221;<lb/> and likewise when the ills of life from which none are excluded<lb/> embitter their existence it is the spiritual guide whose office again<lb/> becomes necessary &#38; whilst he condoles with them in their be&#45;<lb/>reavement he kindly offers a balm to the blow over which they<lb/> weep&#44; he soothes their sorrows &#38; removes every impression which<lb/> might heighten affliction &#38; how unlike his high calling would be<lb/> the minister who performs not this duty&#44; how base in him to increase<lb/> their afflictions with allusions foreign to the circumstances. It is<lb/> indeed in the hours of distress when sickness prostrates us &#38; when the<lb/> work of death has cast gloom &#38; desolation in our homes that the faith&#45;<lb/>ful friend&#44; such as the pastor is expected to be&#44; mediates with kindness<lb/> &#38; endeavors to relieve the overburdened heart of its griefs. There is no circum<lb/>stance to justify his absence from the house of mourning&#44; nothing<lb/> to extenuate such an utter neglect of the minister&#39;s most solemn<lb/> privilege. But it is not to be expected that the compact<lb/> between Pastor &#38; flock imposes obligations on the former only&#44; &#45; no<lb/> the Congregation has also its share of duties equally high &#38; impor&#45;<lb/>tant&#44;  &#38; at the door of such as discard them blame must inevita<lb/>bly be attached&#44; the minister&#39;s love &#38; kindness must find their coun&#45;<lb/>terpart among his people &#38; cheerfully should they return <hi rend="underline">the treat&#45;</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">ment </hi>which he extends to them. The world&#39;s history<lb/> points to times when priesthood as a mass have been a curse to hu&#45;<lb/>manity when they have stained their mission by their vices&#44; their<lb/> ignorance &#38; tyranny&#44; the prospects are that such such time are not<lb/> to return&#44; still however it is our duty to check the growth of evil where&#45;<lb/>ever it shows itself. The entire ministry is not yet what it<lb/> should be&#44; still no one will deny its necessity &#38; that its influence<lb/> can be made most beneficial.</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">5</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I therefore heartily approve of the suggestions cast forth by<lb/> you of establishing a Theological high school&#44; &#38; whenever the work<lb/> is undertaken I offer to contribute my  mite towards its proper<lb/> establishment&#44; being convinced that it would prove of the highest<lb/> benefit to our religion &#38; finally be the means of adding pious &#38;<lb/> sincere ministers of the small number that we never have among<lb/> us. I trust not to have encroached on your valuable space &#38; that<lb/> my remarks hastily sketched will meet your approval&#44; in fact<lb/> I know sufficient of you to be convinced that in your estimation<lb/> I have not overacted the duties of  spiritual guide.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">With my renewed wishes for your welfare</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">I am yours</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Very Sincerely</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">A. Looker&#45;on</persName>.</p>
				<p><placeName>St. Thomas W I</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><date>9th December 1866</date></p>
				<p>Postscript</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The foregoing was written about two months ago&#44; but<lb/> owing to indisposition I could not before then&#44; attend to its forwar&#45;<lb/>ding.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
