<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF6_9</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>Montreal, Canada</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1849-02" source="" attested="yes">1 February 1849</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f6_0009_1r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f6_0009_1v.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f6_0009_2r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f6_0009_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
      
		<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Montreal</placeName> <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Feby &#47;49</date></p>
			<p>Dear Friend&#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent(2)">I have somewhat altered my mind as regards the<lb/> article I lately sent you for the Occident. As I have not heard from<lb/> you on this subject up to present date&#44; I conclude you intend publishing<lb/> it. I have determined however&#44; if you have not yet published it&#44; not<lb/> to let it remain as first written and therefore must beg you to make<lb/> the following alterations in it &#40;i. e. if you want it&#41;. I was so bothered<lb/> when I sent it you that I had but little time or attention to bestow<lb/> on the Introductory observations &#40;which alone are not old papers&#44; for<lb/> I believe I told you that the quotation from Pentsal<add>&#63;</add> with some&#44; nearly<lb/> all&#44; indeed of the notes I had lying by for some time waiting to be dressed<lb/> The <sic>consequense</sic> of my writing hastily was as I afterwards recollected<lb/> that I made a kind of promise to furnish several <add>&#63;</add> pieces&#44; how<lb/> I shall be very happy to do so but I don&#39;t want to bind myself to write<lb/> in any one particular style or in any one particular subject&#44; Hence<lb/> I now cry <add>&#63;</add> and I want to alter my faux pas if it be<lb/> one&#44; in manner following. Problem. The Ed&#95;<add>&#63;</add> had an article on Hebrews<lb/> and their opponents signed ADS&#44; it is necessary to make an alteration in<lb/> the same. If this be printed it is required that it be printed as written from<lb/> the commencement down till the end &#40;in the Introductory remarks&#41; of <persName>Dr.<lb/> Mc Cauls</persName> vindication. After the passage or sentence which commences &#8220;We leave<lb/> it with the reader to determine how far <persName>Dr Mc Caul</persName> in the above extent<lb/> refutes the <add>&#63;</add> &#40;I <sic>dont</sic> remember the exact words as I didn&#39;t keep a<lb/> copy&#41; insert this &#8220;With such testimony&#44; the testimony of an<lb/> adversary&#44; it were unnecessary &#40;at this word insert at bottom the<lb/> note which speaks<add>&#63;</add> of translations of some Hebrew authors already</p>
		<pb n="2"/>
			<p>writing such as the Hebrew Review Bible &#38;c Let the note begin &#8220;Unnecessary<lb/> because the&#8212;&#41; to produce in refutation <add>&#63;</add> the good things they have written out &#38;c &#38;c. Immediately<lb/> add at the end of this sentence leaving out what I have already written<lb/> &#8220;But perhaps it would be no improfitable <del>&#63;</del> did the contributors<lb/> to the Jewish periodical literature of the day devote their attention<lb/> occasionally to these charges which may almost be considered as<lb/> stereotyped&#44; since they are produced every day&#44; in a new dress it may<lb/> be&#44; by those whose ignorance and prejudice will not allow them to<lb/> know better. Leaving to other and abler pens this &#40;as we humbly<lb/> conceive&#41; desirable occupation we would <sic>commense</sic> the campaign of<lb/> vindication by defending from severe and unmerited attack a portion<lb/> of <hi rend="underline">The Cosmography of R. Abraham Peitsal</hi><add>&#63;</add> of which work as a<lb/> whole we however offer no opinion&#44; <del>as chiefly</del> because we are not called upon to do &#38;c&#8212;<lb/> the charges against it being but partial&#59; yet&#44; thus much we will say&#44;<lb/> that books refer many reasons&#44; claims the most attentive and respectful<lb/> consideration &#8220;of both the Jewish and Christian student&#8221; Then continue<lb/> new Par. &#8220;This work thought not so well known &#38;tc&#44; and all the rest<lb/> as sent. &#40;Q.E.D.&#41; Now my dear friend can I depend upon your<lb/> making these alterations just as I have directed so that no inconsistency<lb/> or contradiction exists in the article. I am sorry indeed to prove<lb/> so troublesome a correspondent&#44; but it <sic>canno</sic> be helped.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I told you we had formed a Sunday School here. Perhaps you<lb/> would like a little information as to our doings. I asked a meeting<lb/> at my <add>&#63;</add> of the ladies of the congregation&#44; during <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; when I showed<lb/> them the necessity for some <add>&#63;</add> being made for the more efficient<lb/> religious instruction of the young etc. In the usual course it was proposed<lb/> and carried to establish a SS after the model of that established<lb/> by the estimable <persName>Miss Gratz</persName> of your city. I was elected superintendent<lb/> tho&#39; I would have preferred that the truth had been confided</p>
		<pb n="3"/>
			<p>to a <placeName>Montreal</placeName> <persName>Miss Gratz</persName>&#8212;but it was necessary I should accept<lb/> and I did so. The young ladies of the Cong. were elected teachers <del>and are</del><lb/> <add>&#63;</add> to act when required. The present teachers are <persName>Miss Phoebe David</persName><lb/> who is also secretary. <persName>Miss Rebekah Joseph</persName>&#44; and <persName>Miss Sarah Solomon</persName>.<lb/> The pupils the first day were <del>27 an</del> 21 and have so continued.<lb/> Books used&#8212;Pykes&#8212;Peichotto&#44; and elder &#40;boys&#41; Solomons Mosaic System<lb/> a copy of which was presented me in <placeName>New York</placeName>. I need not add further<lb/> particulars as these would be common to all such schools.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I am sorry to find you are not to inquire now of the Proposed assembly<lb/> coming to something speedily. I hope you are deceived <persName>J. H. Isaacs</persName> letter<lb/> surprised me a little&#8212;he should not have <add>&#63;</add> of difficulties and differences<lb/> of opinion I still insist upon the <add>&#63;</add> I forwarded you being<lb/> correct that they will not be found in the copy&#8212;and it is the fault<lb/> of the printers. I have yet a copy of the article which I would send<lb/> if necessary. The serious errors such as making the Jews settle in <placeName>Rome</placeName><add>&#63;</add><lb/> instead of <placeName>England</placeName> were I am quite confident the faults of your barberous<lb/> named compositors. I beg to acknowledge the Voice of Jacob and<lb/> return you many thanks for your prompt attention to my request. The<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> magazine has been discontinued and I hear it is to reappear<lb/> in the reform interest. I know the two L<add>&#63;</add>s and am not much<lb/> surprised by this. Since <persName>Dr B</persName><add>&#63;</add> retired from the Editorship of the V&#95;it<lb/> and its followers have changed their colors like the chameleon.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I gave your receipts to the <persName>Messrs Benjamin</persName>. The think they<lb/> <sic>dont</sic> owe so much but will refer to their books. I will pay<lb/> over the money to your agent as soon as I can <add>&#63;</add> it.<lb/> Of course you know that you said agent is a Paper. <persName>Mrs J<lb/> H J</persName> has a daughter. <persName>Mr J.</persName> altho&#39; formerly &#40;i. e. before I came<lb/> out&#41; one of the warmest &#38; best supporters of the Synagogue&#44; from<lb/> some reason or other&#44; cannot&#44; unfortunately be persuaded to</p>
		<pb n="4"/>
			<p>belong thereto. But all this occurred before I came to <placeName>Canada</placeName> as I before<lb/> said&#8212;else I would have acted as mediator&#8212;now it is a different<lb/> matter to bring things around. If it had been a <add>&#63;</add>&#44; the Cong had<lb/> determined to make him pay handsomely&#8212;even his relations. As it<lb/> is don&#39;t be surprised if you have to name the young one in the<lb/> <add>&#63;</add>&#8212;of course all I have said of this affair is sub<add>&#63;</add><lb/> My dear fellow&#44; you appear just as anxious as you would represent<lb/> me to appear&#44; to demonstrate that you have no claims on<lb/> the ladies we have discovered about. Claims&#63; Who said you had&#63;<lb/> Have you any <hi rend="underline">old Orients</hi> &#38;tc which you could let me have&#44; as their<lb/> perusal would be some benefit to me in rubbing up what little I know<lb/> of Deutsch. You would oblige me much by lending them me as you<lb/> receive them&#44; you might send them by opportunity and so I would<lb/> return them. My father receives them all&#44; but it would be difficult<lb/> and expensive to receive them from <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I trust that having written you so frequently lately that<lb/> you will not be quite so cheery with your correspondence but let<lb/> me hear from you soon and fully. One half the topics I write you<lb/> on you never deign to answer <add>&#63;</add> I insert you an invitation<lb/> to come in here in the summer.&#8212;<add>Hebrew</add>&#33; Wait till I ask you<lb/> again. I asked you&#44; &#8220;are you going to publish Peril<add>&#63;</add> <add>Hebrew</add>&#33; You<lb/> are certainly a civil gentleman to say the least of you&#44; still I conclude nevertheless<lb/> with health and prosperity to you&#44; wishing you may enjoy every&#44;<lb/> happiness that I wish</p>
          <p rend="indent(7)">Yours very sincerely</p>
          <p rend="indent(8)"><persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName></p>
			<p><addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p><persName>Miss Catherine Vallentine</persName> died <date>Wed&#44; 17 Jany</date></p>
			<p> she was sister to <persName>Mr Valentine</persName> One of</p>
			<p>the founders of the Syn. Does she deserve</p>
			<p>an obituary in the Oc. or are these paid for&#8212;</p>
			<p> She was a truly&#44; religious and charitable person.</p>
          <p><persName>Jacob</persName> send you some of my article till</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I hear from you.</p>

			          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>