<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF14_64</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0114.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0115.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0116.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0117.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>
                <add>Hebrew</add>
            </p>
            <p>“Now there arose up a new king over <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, who knew not
                    <persName>Joseph</persName>.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">(Exod: 1. 8.)</p>
            <p>
                <add>Hebrew</add>
            </p>
            <p>“Who knew not: He pretended not to know him.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">(<persName>Rashi's</persName> commentary)</p>
            <p>Dear Sir.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Though it is but a few weeks since I became person<lb/>ally
                acquainted with you, I have been for many years<lb/> an admirer of your ably
                conducted periodical, and but<lb/> for the oftentimes too ready admission of
                articles of<lb/> rather questionable qualifications and a general<lb/> tendency to
                overrate the <hi rend="underline">mediocre</hi> and to compliment<lb/> the
                undeserving, I think the <sic>jewish</sic> public will<lb/> coincide in my
                assertion, that it stands unexcelled<lb/>
                <del>either for</del> by any religious periodical in this country,<lb/> either for
                earnestness of purpose, or for the learning,<lb/> consistency, unvaried politeness
                and decorum<lb/> of its editor. A full approbation of your<lb/> labours in the cause
                of <placeName>Israel</placeName> might have perhaps<lb/> been more agreeable to you,
                but it would have tar<lb/>nished the sincerity of my views on the subject,
                parti<lb/>cularly as my remark in reference to misapplied<lb/> courtesy, has of late
                been so amply verified.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As long as you were seated in the editorial<lb/> chair of the
                Occident, for many years the only</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p><sic>jewish</sic> paper in <placeName>America</placeName>, as long as you were
                known<lb/> as an author, a correct translator of several <sic>hebrew</sic><lb/>
                works and the <hi rend="underline">only</hi> preacher in the vernacular<lb/> in this
                country, the sheaves (and from what I know<lb/> many empty-headed ones) were, like
                those in <persName>Joseph's</persName><lb/> dream, bowing and making obeisance to
                you, and<lb/> many a dog that barks <hi rend="underline">now</hi> at your heels, was<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">then</hi> ready to lick your hand.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">However “Tempora mutantur &amp;ca”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now there arose up a new Editor in<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName>, whose superior education according to his<lb/> own
                record in the Asmonean of <date>6th</date> inst. “had<lb/> led him into the presence
                of the sovereign of one<lb/> of the mightiest of Empires” yet who knew not,
                either<lb/> the polished manners of the courtiers, or the ceremonious
                politeness<lb/> of the Chinese. If I understand him right (which<lb/> task is rather
                a difficult one) he claims for his<lb/> paper the avowed object of furthering the
                cause<lb/> of our sacred faith by elevating the mind of its<lb/> followers and by
                preaching Union to <placeName>Israel</placeName>.<lb/> How far he has generally
                succeeded, I feel no<lb/> inclination to investigate, but as an individual,<lb/> who
                is not indifferent to the fair fame of his<lb/> fellow-believers, I claim the right
                to <sic>enquire</sic><lb/> whether the article headed “<hi rend="underline">The
                    Occident, and</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">the Asmonean</hi>”, published in the latter on<lb/> the
                    <date>13th</date> instant, is befitting a periodical devoted<lb/> to a high and
                holy purpose, and whether such<lb/> low abuse in the columns of a religious
                paper</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>is calculated to elevate the character of the Jews, their<lb/> press and the standing
                of its supporters and subscribers?<lb/> Language like that, is even unbecoming
                the<lb/> columns of a political country paper, and the<lb/> scurrilous, vulgar and
                disrespectful epithets used<lb/> in that publication against a former
                functionary<lb/> of our faith and a preacher of its doctrines, must<lb/> certainly
                tend to exclude it from the table of every<lb/> respectable family. Yet the author
                seems to entertain<lb/> a different opinion in regard to his productions, and<lb/>
                by appending his initials to it, he appears anxious<lb/> to proclaim his paternity,
                which likely might<lb/> have been questioned by a discriminating public<lb/> since
                the arrivals of the pictorial part of the Asmonean with<lb/> the Motto “Two are
                better than one” were practi<lb/>cally substituted by adding a correcting hand<lb/>
                to the grammatical department of the paper.<lb/> If <persName>R. L.</persName>,
                however had been conversant with<lb/> the <sic>latin</sic> quotation “<hi
                    rend="underline">Ex ungue leonem</hi>”, he<lb/> might have saved himself that
                trouble.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Though I am fully acquainted with<lb/> the particulars of the origin
                of your difficulty<lb/> with the <hi rend="underline">Magnus
                        <persName>Apollo</persName></hi> of the Asmonean,<lb/> I do not consider it
                my province to enlarge<lb/> upon the subject; sufficient it is to know, and
                such<lb/> every one does know, that you have neither<lb/> published nor caused to be
                published aught,<lb/> which could have deserved such a virulent and<lb/> atrocious
                attack from that quarter;</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and even if you had offended the dignity of the self-<lb/>constituted organ of the
                Jews in <placeName>America</placeName>, it<lb/> is more than questionable, whether
                the mode selected<lb/> and adopted by him was a justifiable and<lb/> proper one.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your labours in <placeName>Israel</placeName> certainly entitle
                you<lb/> to a better treatment at the hands of your<lb/> co-religionists, in
                consideration of which and<lb/> of the many services you have for a number of years
                rendered to that cause, I concluded<lb/> that the Asmonean's article should not
                pass<lb/> without some comment; and as the columns<lb/> of the Occident, from the
                obvious reason that<lb/> its editor is a party to the controversy, cannot<lb/> with
                propriety be opened to a more extended<lb/> review, and no proper medium for its
                pub=<lb/>lication being presently available, I am<lb/> constrained for the moment to
                restrict the<lb/> same to its present dimension.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As a man of experience you will,<lb/> however, not be surprised when
                you find<lb/> that the world ill requites favours, that<lb/> have been received,
                when there is a supposition<lb/> that additional ones can no more be obtained;<lb/>
                and as for the strictures of the Asmonean,<lb/> you may console yourself, if
                consolation<lb/> be required, that you share them with</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
