<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Melodola, David</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF8_42</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Melodola, David</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>London, United Kingdom</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1851-05" source="" attested="yes">9 May 1851</dateLet>
              <dateLet when="1851-05" source="" attested="yes">7 Iyar 5611</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f8_0036_1r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f8_0036_1v.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f8_0036_2r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f8_0036_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p>Wax seal</p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
			<language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
      
		<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>London</placeName> <date>9th May 7th Iyar 5611</date></p>
			<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee> <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
          <p rend="indent(2)">My Dear Friend&#160;&#160;Yours <date>27th veadar</date> and <date>12th nisan</date> I acknowledge&#44;<lb/> and did not do so before in consequence of pressure of business &#40;on that I should not have cared&#41;<lb/> but my dear mother&#39;s illness which has been the cause&#44; as well as in some of my past letters to<lb/> you have been rather in a confused state&#44; she has been ever since <date>17th veadar</date> &#40;<date>Friday</date> I wrote to<lb/> you in a dangerous state&#41; your subject and affair was of that importance to me that I could<lb/> not allow a port to pass over me&#44; I should be telling the greatest falsehood in the presence of God<lb/> were I to say to the contrary <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; I was not at all <hi rend="underline">disappointed</hi> in the case itself&#44; the<lb/> <hi rend="underline">result</hi> and its proceedings. I was sure that such would be the end&#44; and fully convinced that it would so<lb/> happen as I will explain. The only <hi rend="underline">disappointment</hi> came from you to me was&#44; by your knowing better than I do the<lb/> place and people that you should have said in one of your letters so positively &#34;<persName>Mr. M</persName>&#34; does not stand the <hi rend="underline">remotest</hi><lb/> chance&#44;&#34; and in the last by your assigning the number of votes &#38;c. this and this only made me have doubts&#59;<lb/> on the <date>Saturday</date> previous to the arrival of the news I called with <persName>Mr. Piza</persName> to pay a visit to a <persName>Mr. Cohen</persName><lb/> from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> &#40;as you may suppose my great anxiety&#41; to learn <hi rend="underline">verbally</hi> and <hi rend="underline">personally</hi> how<lb/> matters stood&#44; he was out&#44; but very politely he called on me on the <date>Sunday</date>&#44; I told him most openly and<lb/> candidly that I did not know you personally&#44; but the &#34;<hi rend="underline">truth &#38; justice</hi>&#34;&#59; you did not deserve such<lb/> treatment after 21 years and with all our <hi rend="underline">noise</hi> here&#44; we had not your <hi rend="underline">equal</hi>&#44; and as we knew each other<lb/> as neighbours from young he coincided and I believe spoke the truth that he was sure you would not<lb/> get it as he knew the number of opponents you had and&#44; as for <persName>Revd&#58; Rosenfeld</persName> he actually named 6 to 7 and<lb/> that <persName>Morais</persName> sure would have it&#44; such was all that passed between us&#44; so that I almost made up my<lb/> mind fully to such result&#44; when on the <date>Tuesday</date> the news were known by thy Packet&#59; what could be<lb/> expected from a number who gather and assemble and are <hi rend="underline">determined</hi> in all manners and ways to<lb/> cast down a man&#44; every trick&#44; every effort&#44; manure&#44; will be used&#44; and in opposition any <hi rend="underline">log</hi> would<lb/> save&#44; you are Theologian enough &#40;and indeed more than they ever deserved&#41; to know <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> and in a case of <hi rend="underline">opposition</hi> <add>Hebrew</add> these sentiments of the Prophet &#38;c. will <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> fully corroborate your expressions &#34;<hi rend="underline">after this any one can succeed</hi>&#44;&#34; what must you say then when you hear<lb/> this <hi rend="underline">original spare sentiments</hi> compiled by <hi rend="underline">himself</hi>&#44; and not sent <del>by</del> from elsewhere&#44; or prepared by others&#44;<lb/> and do so on in every other respect.&#8212;<add>Hebrew</add>&#8212;I am greatly astonished at <persName>Mr. Harts</persName> conduct&#44; I wrote to<lb/> him not only as Parnas but considering him your <hi rend="underline">friend</hi> that he should suggest to me some plan or way<lb/> to bring matters to a conclusion in your favour I <sic>considerd</sic> I was writing to a Gentleman and that<lb/> he would have acted as such&#44; had he <sic>shewn</sic> my first letter to his colleagues which he ought to<lb/> have done&#44; I flatter myself it was well written argued and really a feeling one&#44; that it would have<lb/> changed many &#44; as you say &#34;<hi rend="underline">my letter to <persName>Mr. Hart</persName> was not read</hi>&#44;&#34; and more by <hi rend="underline">keeping my letter</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">from the generality of the congregation</hi>.&#34; if so&#44; which I do not doubt you for a moment&#44; It is the act of any<lb/> thing but justice&#44; and far from a friend&#44; but on the contrary&#59; I must confess I did not like on such<lb/> important subject the delay of reply&#44; the petty excuse of pressure of business is a poor &#34;got off&#44;&#34; and a<lb/> very miserable and frivolous one&#44; when we ought to exert ourselves for <del>a</del> such a friend as you&#44; and on<lb/> such a <hi rend="underline">rascally</hi> treatment&#44; I call it&#58; <add>Hebrew</add> and so it ought to be&#44; look at my doings<lb/> I did not neglect replying you in the <date><sic>friday</sic> 21st <sic>march</sic></date> wherein I wrote I was rather confined as my dear and<lb/> beloved mother was taken with a Paralytic stroke her <sic>speach</sic> &#38; right side effected on that morning<lb/> early&#44; had the house full of Doctors&#44; her life hung and depended on a <add>Hebrew</add> still I followed up my<lb/> duty towards a friend&#44; &#38; thanks to God she is something better&#41; I believe such ought to be done by all <hi rend="underline">friends</hi><lb/> I must let you know that I replied on the <date>19th Adar</date> to <persName>Mr. A&#58; Hart&#39;s</persName> letter and must confess that it was</p>
			<p>&#42;when I say rascally I mean on the <sic>anonimous</sic> pamphlet which is<lb/> the act of a coward.</p>
		<pb n="2"/>
			<p>well written and conducive leaving me no doubt that if he was <hi rend="underline">a friend</hi> it all must have finished to<lb/> an amicable re&#45;instatement of yourself to office and on that and that only did all my hopes depend&#59;<lb/> moreso&#44; that I had no reply from him&#44; I made it sure he was at work in favor of the cause&#44; at last I had<lb/> the pleasure of receiving an answer nearly 11 weeks after&#8212;<hi rend="underline">when all the Dance and Farce was over</hi>&#44; shall<lb/> please God <add>Hebrew</add> reply to him for had he in due time wrote to me his suggestions&#44; I might have<lb/> written them to you&#44; perhaps you might have taken my advice and things might have alter&#39;d&#59; you<lb/> shall have at foot extracts of that it relates you&#44; and you will be a better judge. the letter reached me<lb/> last <date>monday</date> &#38; the <date>tuesday</date> before the news of the election reached here. I have no <hi rend="underline">direct</hi> news<lb/> of the young man <persName>Morais</persName> neither of his arrival nor of his election&#44; it is no more than I fully<lb/> expected&#44; unfortunately all my lifetime I devoted to lender services &#38; favors in which places<lb/> I have ever been correspondent with ungratefulness&#44; he dined with me on the <date>Tuesday</date> tete<lb/>tete a true friendly dinner&#44; on the <date>Thursday</date> morning among all his friends none accompanied<lb/> him to the terminus but myself &#38; the person with whom he lodged&#44; I was also the first who <sic>opend</sic><lb/> his arms when he came from <placeName>Leghorn</placeName> &#40;though my repl<add>&#63;</add> was on the field&#41; and found him&#44;<lb/> he having brought me a letter from his Rabbi or teacher with whom he was more of a messenger<lb/> in the house&#59; his master <persName>Piperno</persName> being almost the last of that class with whom from<lb/> our childhood we corresponded &#38; when at <placeName>Leghorn</placeName> we were more than brothers always together&#44; I appreciated<lb/> his <sic>reccomendation</sic> and corresponded it&#44; but I found him on several occasions not open or sincere.<lb/> this I can only attribute to it either as he know very well for I told him <sic>wen</sic> on the day of the dinner openly&#44;<lb/> I wished him success in any other way&#44; but wished to hear <persName><hi rend="underline">Leeser</hi></persName> re&#45;instated as it was but<lb/> just. I also hinted to him a little of my opinion &#40;for I was born at <placeName>Leghorn</placeName> &#38; my forefathers<lb/> who were all at service of the Synagogue <add>Hebrew</add> ever since the first stone was laid down<lb/> to that City knowing his weight in full to a grain of his <hi rend="underline">genuine value</hi>&#41; he would be <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi> after you. I do not<lb/> take away any of his merits as a fit Hazan religious principles&#44; and well understanding his<lb/> prayers&#44; further as a good <add>Hebrew</add> of the first rudiments of the Hebrew &#38; Bible&#44; he may yet write when he<lb/> gets a little more used to money&#58; with respect to your Bible there is no doubt it will be something<lb/> great coming from you&#44; but am sorry to say you are ignorant of the state of the present <hi rend="underline">Sephardim</hi><lb/> congregation&#8212;the true <hi rend="underline">flower&#44; gentry</hi> by birth&#44; right&#44; men of talent&#44; <hi rend="underline">gentlemen promoters</hi> of <hi rend="underline">literature</hi><lb/> have left us in the affair of the Sehim<add>&#63;</add>&#8212;all the <persName>mocattas</persName>&#44; <persName>Henriques</persName>&#44; <persName>H Montofire</persName>&#44; all of<lb/> them my friends and supporters&#44; four <persName>DeCastro</persName> &#40;<persName>Hanand</persName>&#41; who was like them I remain with<lb/> us died in prime of life&#58; this day in candour with the exception of <persName>Sir Moses</persName> we have not a second<lb/> person a few new ones&#44; boys who cares for nothing and doubt the Bible much more the translation of it<lb/> Judaism to them is a farce&#44; it is all left in the hands of a few barbarian from <placeName>Canbury Gibraltar</placeName> &#38;c<lb/> who are <sic>bigotted</sic> to the greatest extreme carried with the deepest ignorance and any thing in that<lb/> way of opening eyes <sic>enlightment</sic> or expending <hi rend="underline">one</hi> farthing would be <add>Hebrew</add> they are in themselves<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add>&#8212;and really <add>Hebrew</add>. My advice would be send me some copies of a well<lb/> made up Prospectus of the work I will send them among my friends &#38; Christians and will<lb/> personally call and forward it to obtain subscriptions&#44; I care no trouble to serve you and depend<lb/> on this to be agreeable to the <sic>curtin</sic> of the place&#44; the best &#38; sure plan to succeed&#44; my name<lb/> is great &#40;to our shame&#41; more among the learned Christians with respect to the synagogue still there<lb/> is a talk I am little acquainted with matters or I have abandoned frequenting Jews houses<lb/> after my avocations I devote it at home to study in my next I shall give you precise<lb/> particulars. Wishing you most heartily every success <add>Hebrew</add> from yours sincerely<lb/> <persName role="author">David Melodola</persName></p>
			<p>When you have nothing better to do write to me for I am<lb/> ever glad to hear from you&#44; I beg to remind you confidence of the above particularly<lb/> about <persName>Morais</persName> let it be secret&#8212;<add>Hebrew</add> as he might write here and</p>
			<p rend="line continues on page 3">as I said there are always many to look out and place me in disturbance which I must <add>&#63;</add>.<lb/> &#8212;<add>Hebrew</add></p>
		<pb n="3"/>
			<p>&#34;The following is the whole of <persName>Mr. A. H.</persName> letter which refers your affair dated <date>April 8th nisan 6th</date><lb/> with a P. S. outside &#34;This letter having been detained in consequence of being too late for the last<lb/> steamer. I have to announce the election of <persName>Mr. S&#58; Morais</persName> for 3 years <persName>A&#58; H&#58;</persName><lb/> it reached me <date>Monday last 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May&#45;3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Izar</date>&#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">&#34;I have noted the contents of your letter very faithfully and thank you for your<lb/> acknowledgments therein contained&#44; and I fear there will be very little chance for<lb/> <persName>Mr. Leesers</persName> re&#45;election &#40;whom I highly esteem for his talents and the good he has done for<lb/> our people&#41; as he has not abated as yet a single one of the several stipulations he demanded<lb/> care of his again being elected Hazan of our congregation&#44; and the congregation have refused by a<lb/> decided vote to alter their rules or regulations&#8212;and the election is to take place next<lb/> <date>Sunday 11th Nisan</date>.&#41; There are two candidates who appear to give great satisfaction to the<lb/> &#34;members in their reading of the Hebrew&#44; viz <persName>Revd Jacob Rosenfeld</persName> of <placeName>Charleston S. Carolina</placeName><lb/> &#34;and <persName>Mr. Morais</persName> from <placeName>London</placeName> &#40;the testimonials of the latter being highly satisfactory&#41; and<lb/> &#34;the content will be between them and <persName>Mr. Leeser&#39;s</persName> friends who will vote for him I understand<lb/> &#34;if even he is not a candidate. I can assure you that I regret exceedingly the loss of<lb/> &#34;<persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> to our congregation but under the circumstances I do not see how our<lb/> &#34;congregation could have submitted to <persName>Mr. Leeser&#39;s</persName> demands that they should alter their<lb/> &#34;By laws&#44; and rules&#44; under which he has served for 21 years without any oppression<lb/> &#34;towards himself&#44; besides having been told before he made the demands&#44; that it would<lb/> &#34;result as it has but he would not be advised&#8212;unless he comes forward with some<lb/> &#34;modifications of his terms on the day of election&#44; I think that either of the strangers<lb/> &#34;aforenamed will be elected. I trust that ere long he will learn that however<lb/> &#34;hard he may think of me for not resigning the office of Parnass at<lb/> &#34;the time that this congregation refused to elect him for an indefinite<lb/> &#34;period and without signing the contract &#38;c. that I acted according to<lb/> &#34;Principle <add>&#63;</add> altho&#39; I wished his election at that time I could not condemn the<lb/> &#34;congregation over which I presided for adhering to the terms &#38;c. which had<lb/> previously existed between them and <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>. &#40;had he asked the alterations<lb/> &#34;courteously instead of demanding them <hi rend="underline">at the time.</hi> I think the congregation would<lb/> &#34;have acceeded&#44; but they were not willing to be driven&#44; when they could have been<lb/> &#34;led gently.&#41;&#34; He expresses very politely at the beginning of his letter&#34; a heavy press<lb/> of business is my only excuse for not earlier acknowledging<lb/> the same.&#34;</p>
			<p>I must apologize for the state of my letters to you in the writing <add>&#63;</add>. I am very<lb/> short sighted and must stop more than I ought&#44; and in no way whatever<lb/> could use myself to glasses. I have this moment learnt that the great <persName>Dr. Frankel</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Dresden</placeName> is here.</p>
		<pb n="4"/>
          <p rend="indent(10)">Paid</p>
			<p><addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>America</placeName></p>
          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>