<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Kursheedt, Gershom</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx9FF18a_8</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Kursheedt, Gershom</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1849-01" source="" attested="yes">1 January 1849</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1849-01" source="" attested="yes">5609</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f18a_0008_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f18a_0008_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f18a_0008_2r.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date>Jany 1. 5609</date>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">My revd &#38; dear friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">I have been waiting on <persName>Mr Touro</persName><lb/> or rather in hopes of receiving his orders&#44; to break the protrac<lb/>ted silence which has too long ruled between us.  And now<lb/> anticipating early cause for writing you again I still essay<lb/> to explain in part the reasons for my late neglect towards<lb/> you.  Heavy blows have been <sic>levelled</sic> at your humble<lb/> friend since this pleasure was lastly indulged in&#59; wrongs<lb/> have borne down in unmeasured strides &#38; at times my<lb/> very spirit has failed me.  But the Lord is merciful &#38; altho&#39;<lb/> my trials have been moulded into an ordinary casting&#44; yet an<lb/> eluding faith&#44; &#38; resignation to what is permitted in the<lb/> infinite wisdom of God&#44; have enabled me thus far to rise<lb/> superior to the machinations of the evil.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Presuming that you have heard of the<lb/> treachery of my late partner who has acted like the most<lb/> heartless <sic>vilain</sic> &#40;for I consider him beyond comparison<lb/> with anything that I have ever seen or heard or read of&#41; robbing<lb/> me of thousands&#44; most inhumanly too&#44; I hope that you<lb/> have made great allowances for the lack of exhibition<lb/> of that respect which had previously been my wont in<lb/> my intercourse with you.  Verily my good friend I have<lb/> suffered but thanks to the Supreme&#44; my national Jewish<lb/> feeling has held firm midst incessant whirlwinds &#38; storms<lb/> which&#44; each&#44; as they arise&#44; seemed to bring inevitable destruc<lb/>tion to my every hope in life.  You will doubtless excuse<lb/> this awkward introduction to a letter which was intended<lb/> to be altogether in a different strain&#44; but&#44; &#8220;from the fullness<lb/> of the heart the mouth speaketh&#8221; &#38; even now a great deal remains<lb/> to be done&#44; ere I can feel safe from the fowlers snare&#44; the accomplish<lb/>ment of which God in his mercy grant unto me&#8212;</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>With regard to congregational affairs I have little new<lb/> to state.  When I was about to write to you to procure<lb/> some of the inside furniture &#38;c I discovered that the<lb/> ceiling of the building was so defective as to be really<lb/> dangerous &#38; after some weeks lost in convincing<lb/> <persName>Mr Touro</persName> of this he acceded to my wish to have<lb/> it taken down.  For seven weeks past we have had<lb/> incessant rains &#38; therefore could not plaster.  The appear<lb/>ance of the cholera &#40;which I am happy to say is now in the<lb/> decline&#41; made workmen very scarce&#44; &#38; now I think we<lb/> can not consecrate the building before <date>March</date> or <date>April</date><lb/> I hope ere many days that <persName>Mr Touro</persName> will tell me<lb/> to order out what we require&#44; but he is dreadfully slow<lb/> &#38; the concern has cost him so much already that he<lb/> is perhaps to be excused for holding back&#44; particularly<lb/> as he gets no very low estimate of the cost of &#8220;<hi rend="underline">Sepharim</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">Bells</hi> &#38;c &#38;c from me.  Yet all will come right in time<lb/> and you must be patient as I have learned to be.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">After frequent letters between <persName>M N Nathan</persName><lb/> &#38; myself I find that he has altered some parts<lb/> of the service at <placeName>St Thomas</placeName>&#44; nothing of great impor<lb/>tance&#44; &#38; that he desires more ecclesiastical power<lb/> than is generally allowed a Hazan.  I have finally<lb/> written him offering him &#36;1600 a year &#38; a house<lb/> equal to 8 or 900 more thus making his salary equiva<lb/>lent to 24 to 2500 a year.  I offer to yield certain privileges<lb/> &#38; if possible thus to compromise his demands regarding<lb/> the trifling innovations in the service.  The only point<lb/> that strikes me of any consequence is in his omitting<lb/> the repetition of the <hi rend="underline">Anudale</hi><add>&#63;</add>.  All his improvements<lb/> as to order regular <sic>attendence</sic>&#44; a choir &#38;c &#38;c I approve</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">By the bye I have at last succeeded in getting the organ<lb/> taken away from the church &#38; think I shall be able to keep</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>it out altogether&#44; in view of which <add>&#63;</add><lb/> making the consecration very plain.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Right Reverent <persName>Rabbi <hi rend="underline">Carillion</hi></persName> is here<lb/> offering his services &#38; starting to <add>&#63;</add> his way<lb/> I think he will find however that he has<lb/> come across the wrong man in me.  I am<lb/> really afraid of this man&#39;s being at the head<lb/> of anything&#44; he seems to have given trouble where<lb/>ver he has gone what do you know or think<lb/> of him&#63; write me as I write you this&#44; in<lb/> confidence.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">All my leisure time is devoted to the interests<lb/> of the congregation &#38; still they do not seem satisfied.<lb/>  So help me God if I err it is from too great a desire<lb/> to make everything right.  You can not imagine what<lb/> an incessant tax it is on me &#38; bothered as I have<lb/> been to death with my own troubles &#38; having the labor<lb/> of three men to perform in my paper I have been<lb/> at times almost crazy &#38; heartily sick of the whole<lb/> concern.  But please God I&#39;ll stick to it &#38; work it into shape<lb/> before I retire from office.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Now my good Sir I have fairly stolen the time<lb/> required to indite this &#38; it has been at the sacrifice of<lb/> attending to other <sic>judaic</sic> matters.  I wish we had a proper<lb/> minister here for I am bored to death with liberal minded<lb/> &#8220;Goyim&#8221; who want information &#38; which in fact I am scarcely<lb/> able to give them.  I have had to day to play the &#8220;<hi rend="underline">Roff</hi>&#8221; to <sic>jew</sic> &#38; gentile<lb/> &#38; what with weddings&#44; circumcisions&#44; funerals &#38;c I am ever<lb/> in the go.  Besides in an epidemic there are several poor of our<lb/> faith who depend on me.  I informed the Howard Association of this<lb/> fact &#38; stated frankly that I could only aid that society among those<lb/> taken with cholera in my immediate neighborhood.  Oh if I had<lb/> you here how I would bother you with one half of my duties</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p><add>&#63;</add> fit <persName>Judge Womac</persName> of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName> is here<lb/> giving Lecture at the University &#38; wants me to give<lb/> him an explanation of all our laws.  I take<lb/> him to a wedding on <date>Wednesday</date> &#38; then I have to<lb/> edify him on the &#8220;Jurisprudence of the Jews&#8221;<lb/> what a business for a pen devil like myself<lb/> The worst of it is that every body here knows me<lb/> to be a Jew &#38; <sic>unfotunately</sic> I pass off for one of the<lb/> enlightened &#38; well read.  Every great man that comes<lb/> here by some means or other I am brought into contact<lb/> with &#38; invariably conversation turns to the nation.<lb/>  At all events my dear <persName>Leeser</persName> I strive to bring no disgrace<lb/> &#38; always state that I speak for myself &#38; not for the Nation<lb/> that I am very ignorant &#38; rusty formal <add>&#63;</add> from<lb/> a congregation since my 18th year.  Almost every scientific<lb/> man who comes here brings letters to me from some friend or<lb/> acquaintance who kindly volunteers to make me know&#44; but<lb/> if they knew him I try to keep quietly in my <hi rend="underline">sanctum</hi><lb/> &#38; do my day&#39;s &#38; night&#39;s work they would probably hesitate.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But this is an abominably egotistical letter &#38; yet it is<lb/> just such a <add>&#63;</add>ear I would naturally write to one whom I<lb/> know as I do you&#44; all I can say is write me in the same way<lb/> &#38; then we will be even.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Will you give my fondest love to my dear little Aunt when<lb/> you see her.  Tell her her good husband always calls for me at night<lb/> on his way home &#38; I see him constantly through the day.  He is well<lb/> &#38; will be with me ere long.  I have taken advantage of a holiday to write<lb/> you although I have been interrupted twenty times since beginning this.  My<lb/> family are always anxious to hear of your good health &#38; no less so is<lb/> your devoted although lately unheard from friend</p>
				<p><persName role="author">Gershom K</persName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways down the left side of the page."></p>
				<p><add>&#63;</add>ink this is very handsomely written for me&#8212;can you do as well&#63;</p>
				<p><add>&#63;</add> no visits to day excepting to widows &#38; orphans.  No fashionable heartless calls &#38; I had no sweetheart to kiss on the occasion.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
