<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF4_13</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Marcuson, Mr.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_2r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4_0013_2v.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p><addressee>Mr Marcusson</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">To the Editor of the Jewish Chronicle of <placeName>New York</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I met with you <date>August</date> <add>&#63;</add> at the house of one of my friends which&#44; in<lb/> perusing I came to an article headed &#8220;Conversion<add>&#63;</add>&#44;&#8221; which speaking of the conversion<lb/> of certain Jews to Christianity&#44; embraces my name among others&#44; to my<lb/> grief&#44; <sic>surprize</sic> &#38; astonishment.  My indignation might have been less&#44; had<lb/> I given the least assent to your doctrines in the conversation I had<lb/> with some of your faith in <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>.  But as I deem the whole system<lb/> of Christian faith little better than a dream&#44; awaking fancy perhaps&#44; and<lb/> nothing more&#44; I am at less to imagine how you <add>&#63;</add> could<lb/> do me the injustice to state I had changed my faith&#44; one as <add>&#63;</add><lb/><add>&#63;</add> as the God who first bestowed it on us through his servant<lb/> <persName>Moses</persName>.  To a Jew nothing can be more disgraceful than being charged<lb/> with deserting his religion&#59; and this disgrace this injustice you have<lb/> fastened on me in your unauthorized publication.  In selecting <add>&#63;</add><lb/> on his people God through his prophet called on a stiff necked genera<lb/>tion&#59; but also He styled us a &#8220;Great nation&#44; having wisdom &#38; understand<lb/>ing&#44; which two elements are necessary in a rational religion&#44; so as to<lb/> prevent us from believing every idle tale &#38; fiction which may be retold<add>&#63;</add><lb/> to us.  I give you this information for your guidance&#44; that you may not so<lb/> readily believe in time to come if you hear of the conversion<add>&#63;</add> of a Jew&#44; espe<lb/>cially if he be one who has learned something&#59; since Sir you may be sure&#44;<lb/> that you hear a thing which slight not to be believed&#44; or that he is one of the<lb/> most ignorant of his people.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Now the only way I can account for the origin of the report is as follows&#58;<lb/> the <del>person</del> missionary who sent you the letter in the <add>&#63;</add> of the above number came several<lb/> times to my residence&#44; and we had several communications about religious mat<lb/>ters&#44; and <add>&#63;</add> he had the worst of the argument&#44; as he will I hope<lb/> have the cand<add>&#63;</add> to acknowledge for every interview we had he failed to answer</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>my objections&#59; and once when we had argued before many people his best<lb/> reply was that <add>&#63;</add> all the doctrine of the trinity is a <add>&#63;</add>&#59; &#8220;but it is<lb/> very plain to us&#44;&#8221; I replied&#44; and so it is&#44; thank God&#44; for we know that it<lb/> is not founded in fact nor revelation.  After this he told me that<lb/> the minister of the city wished to become acquainted with me&#44; and that they<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> to learn Hebrew for which they would pay me&#59; and so he recom<lb/>mended me to them.  After I became a little better acquainted with them&#44;<lb/> we often spoke together about religion&#44; but I always had the last word&#44;<lb/> they failing to maintain their side.  On one occasion&#44; after conversing<lb/> for some time&#44; one of them took the liberty to tell me <del>&#63;</del> on finding<lb/> himself unable to contend any farther with me&#44; after this f<add>&#63;</add>&#58; &#8220;All<lb/> that you say is so high &#38; deep&#59; but in religious matters it is only necess<lb/>ary to have faith &#40;i.e. Only to believe whether there are good reasons for so<lb/> doing or not&#41;&#59; and the only reason why you Jews do not believe in <persName>Jesus</persName><lb/> &#40;I do not want to call him <persName>Christ</persName>&#44; because he never was this and<lb/> never will be&#41; is because you do not take the Bible in the true light&#44;<lb/> and you are cursed that you shall have ears &#38; not hear&#44; eyes &#38;<lb/> not see&#44; a head and not understand.&#8221;  This assertion hurt my<lb/> feelings deeply&#44; and my heart was made sick&#44; and I replied to him<lb/> &#8220;We were the first to whom the Almighty God delivered the Bible by the hands of<lb/> <persName>Moses</persName>&#44; and you have obtained it solely from us&#59; and if therefore if<lb/> you hear it&#44; we hear it be a certainty&#59; and still you dare to say<lb/> that you understand it in its true light&#33; and have a better knowledge of<lb/> its contents than we&#33;&#8221;  After this I began to show them that not only<lb/> have they not the true light&#44; but they have no light at all&#59; and I proved<lb/> to them that <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Dr. Clarke</persName> in his commentaries was in error&#44; and did<lb/> not understand the true sense of the Hebrew.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Most of their conversation was about the Trinity&#59; and the manner in which</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>they attempted to explain it to my understanding was truly ridiculous&#59; and<lb/> I showed them that even of their own faith they do not know enough to help themselves&#44;<lb/> and I was able to give them better reasons than theirs&#59; but I proved to them<lb/> at the same time that their belief is false&#44; and that it is not possible to believe<lb/> in three persons as the Deity&#59; and if their <add>&#63;</add> holds good&#44; they either<lb/> believe in four or two gods&#59; but three can never be one.  I also demonstrated<lb/> to them that <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Dr. Clarke</persName> established a plural in the <add>&#63;</add><lb/> with the name of God&#44; that he did not understand the meaning of the<lb/> words at all.  I also explained to them in a correct manner the mean<lb/>ing of the word Shiloh &#40;Gen. XIIX 101&#41;&#59; let them repeat to you my answer&#59;<lb/> and if they are not able to do so because it is &#8220;too high or deep&#8221; I will do<lb/> myself<lb/> so with pleasure at a later period&#44; if God pleases to spare me</p>
				<p>In speaking of the crucifixion&#44; I asked where this was predicted in the<lb/> Old Testament&#63;  The therefore presented me with a little book&#44; &#40;which<lb/> I shall carefully preserve&#44;&#41; wherein I read that this important event is<lb/> foretold in Deuteronomy XXI 22&#44; 23&#59; to which I <add>&#63;</add> that if this be<lb/> so&#44; I could frame no objection to this position.  But I pray you to read<lb/> the first referred to&#59; and I am sure you will agree with me&#44;<lb/> that no Christian argument can be derived from it.  The second<lb/> passage could in the one relating to the brazen serpent which <persName>Moses</persName><lb/> was ordered to make in the desert&#44; of which it is said that it is a sign&#44;<lb/> that &#8220;as the serpent was lifted up&#44; so was <persName>Jesus</persName> to be crucified.&#8221;<lb/>  I then asked them whether they were satisfied to take the whole<lb/> history of the brazen serpent as a sign of <persName>Jesus</persName>&#59; since it would be im<lb/>proper to take the half only.  They answered&#58; &#8220;To be sure&#44; we take the<lb/> whole history.&#8221;  I expressed myself perfectly satisfied with this&#59; but as I gave<lb/> them no reason for this&#44; they perhaps thought that I was not able to an<lb/>swer&#59; yet this however&#44; thank God&#44; is not the case&#59; the reason for my</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>not saying more was&#44; that the thing was too trifling to require<lb/> farther illustration.  But as it seems that I was misunderstood&#44;<lb/>  I will now enter into farther details.  In saying <hi rend="underline">the whole</hi> history&#44;<lb/> I meant that of the lifting up of the serpent by <persName>Moses</persName> was a sign<lb/> of <persName>Jesus</persName>&#44; the destruction of the serpent by the <persName>King Hezekiah</persName> in 2 Kings<lb/> XVIII 4 must also be a sign of him&#44; as after he had been crucified<lb/> he was buried and became dust like the rest of mankind.  You<lb/> can find no more signs that either the serpent or its type arose<lb/> after this&#59; and <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Hezekiah</persName> called it &#8220;Nehushtan&#44;&#8221; which<lb/> in your version <del>if</del> is left untranslated&#59; but I will tell you what<lb/> it means&#44; it is a Hebrew word&#44; and signifies a piece of brass<lb/> or copper.  Now you can see who takes the Bible in a true light&#44;<lb/> the Christians of the jews.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Now I beg you do not make any more mistakes&#59; I can show<lb/> you many things&#59; but I do not wish to have a controversy&#44; if<lb/> you do not provoke me again.  I shall be perfectly satisfied with<lb/> this course&#59; but if you like warfare better&#44; I am ready to meet<lb/> you&#59; but I advise you to take care that you do not provoke me<lb/> to write myself some of these days a commentary on the New<lb/> Testament&#59; which I hope will be better than <persName>Dr. Clarke&#39;s</persName> at least it<lb/> shall be more in accordance with truth.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Your reporter says that I shall become a faithful missionary&#59;<lb/> certainly not in the sense which he wishes you to understand this&#58;<lb/> but if you want <hi rend="underline">light</hi>&#44; I am prepared to give it to you to the best of<lb/> my abilities&#44; if you will but open your heart and mind to receive the<lb/> truth.  And do not say that the Jews do not understand the scriptures<lb/> in their true light.  I can refer you to <add>&#63;</add> as regards<lb/> my qualifications&#59; but after all I pray you to let me rest.  I wish to live<lb/> in the faith of our <hi rend="underline">ancient</hi> heavenly Father &#38; I desire to follow his<lb/> commandments&#59; and though you say&#44; &#8220;The law condemn us&#59;&#8221; still do I<lb/> say&#44; that it is the truth and everlasting life.  Do you <add>&#63;</add><lb/> as many persons as you like&#59; I will call on the only true God<lb/> alone&#44; for He is the sole saving Person&#44; as He is the sole Creator<add>&#63;</add>.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
