<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF11_5</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes">5 October</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_2v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_3r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_3v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 3 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Augusta</placeName> <date>October 5th</date></p>
				<p><addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">I was anxious to reply to yours of <date>16th</date><lb/> immediately on its receit<add>&#63;</add> &#38; to thank you for putting me in conceit<lb/> with myself but a variety of domestic arrangements &#38; some family letters<lb/> of importance compell&#39;d me to delay replying to your very flattering favor.<lb/>  Tis very pleasant when out of humor with the world &#38; yourself to break<lb/> the seal of a letter &#40;from a kind of friend in a quiet corner of the world&#41;<lb/> which excites yourself love &#38; throws a little rose colour on the dark<lb/> tints of life. In a constant intercourse with the world I have had<lb/> much to mortify &#38; distress me but as yet my sincerity in friendship has<lb/> never been doubted &#38; you do me only justice my kind friend&#44; in<lb/> judging that I am as <hi rend="underline">jealous</hi>&#44; in your cause&#44; as you have found<lb/> me in that of newer friends. Think not you are alone in receiving<lb/> censure where you expected approbation. Although not a public<lb/> character&#44; my motives are often misconstrued &#38; wrong interpre<lb/>tations given to them even by some very dear to me&#44; I regret<lb/> it but sorrow not&#44; as one without hope&#59; for I know ere a little<lb/> while&#44; all that appears dark&#44; in my actions&#44; will be illumed<lb/> by the light of truth&#33;  The task is a painful one to extract<lb/> the sweet from the bitter  which the hand of malevolence is too apt<lb/> to surround us with&#44; but I should feel prouder of you&#44; my respected<lb/> friend&#44; if there was less of the human &#38; more of the <hi rend="underline">humane</hi> feeling<lb/> in your expression of discontent towards the fair dames of <placeName>Charleston</placeName><lb/> remember &#8220;To these who suffer much&#44; much shall be given&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">For patience wears the brightest wealth in Heaven.&#8221;<lb/> God has endowed you with so much deeper knowledge than your</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>fellow&#44; has gifted you with perception so far superior to ours&#59; has inspired<lb/> you with power to illumine the path of your benighted people&#44; has<lb/> blessed you with the power of elevating the Jewish character so as<lb/> to place it &#40;if not superior&#41; on a level with the religionists of other<lb/> faith that we marvel when we find<del>ing</del> you entering into the<lb/> sarcasms of those inferior to you in mental blessings &#8212; methin<lb/>ks I hear you exclaim &#8220;But does <persName>Mrs Moise</persName> think&#44; because I am<lb/> more endowed with intellectual resources&#44; more deeply versed in<lb/> a knowledge of God &#38; his perfectibility than those around me I am<lb/> exempt from human passions &#38; human weaknesses &#38; by no<lb/> means my dear Sir&#44; but that you have the ability to root out<lb/> with a stronger hand&#44; the tares that spring up among your wheat<lb/> &#38; when we find you wanting where are we to look for examples<lb/> to pattern by. Our letters of late have all contained&#44; something<lb/> relative to <persName>Mr. P</persName>&#44; let us by mutual consent&#44; banish him&#44; for<lb/> I wish at this distance&#44; to see none of the dark shades thrown<lb/> around your portrait &#38; I fear he can never be introduced<lb/> without producing frowns&#44; where I desire smiles&#44; I have read the<lb/> poems of the <persName>Misses Moise</persName> some years ago &#38; was much pleased<lb/> with them&#44; as they gave much promise of a rich poetic fancy accompani&#45;<lb/>ed by the freshness of youth&#44; you are happy in having such contributors<lb/> to your labors &#38; I should be most happy to enlist as a subaltern<lb/> even in your company&#44; had I the time to devote to literary pursuits<lb/>  In bygone days I had leisure &#38; would have repaid your patronage<lb/> by a promise of future usefulness but alas now I must check<lb/> all ambitious aspirations &#38; plodd on in the every day walks of life<lb/> satisfied&#44; if I can as an accountable being&#44; act my part in my path in life<lb/> amidst its trials &#38; its duties &#38; reconcile myself with the reflect&#45;<lb/>ion that the soul is invigorated by the difficulties&#44; &#38; purified</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>by the trials it meets &#38; overcomes in the journey of life &#8212; I have<lb/> 3 or 4 unfinished communications which have been commen<lb/>ced since your Occident but I have not the time nor desire<lb/> to appear before the public under your scrutinizing eye.<lb/>  I have had much lately to distract my mind from gleaning<lb/> any of the honors you are ready to bestow on humble aspir<lb/>ants in the cause of <placeName>Israel</placeName>. A beloved brother who I always<lb/> viewed as a pattern of piety who I was proud of for his beauty&#44; his<lb/> talents &#38; filial piety has doomed me to despair &#38; his parents<lb/> to sorrow by marrying gentile woman&#59; had he in youth<lb/> allowed his fancy to get the better of all those lessons inculcated<lb/> with a mothers watchfulness I would have pitied &#38; forgiven but<lb/> when at the age of 40 when the passions are cooled by reason<lb/> when reflection must awaken the decree issued against<lb/> all who marry with the heathens how can I excuse him&#33;<lb/>  He was my favorite brother my pride &#38; glory &#38; how has he<lb/> disappointed my fondest hopes&#59; yet if God will forgive him <add>&#63;</add><lb/><add>&#63;</add> surely ought &#38; yet I feel it hard to write the word<lb/> my son too my first born is about to leave the home of his<lb/> fathers &#38; seek his future in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> he will not go<lb/> without my consent &#38; I have given it because I know that<lb/> when our influence fails opposition will avail naught.<lb/> his object is to render his mother&#39;s &#38; orphan sisters &#38; broth<lb/>ers life more affluent&#44; but I am selfish &#38; would rather<lb/> have a scanty pittance surrounded by my children &#38; bring<lb/>ing the sunshine of their love than the wealth of <placeName>indies</placeName><lb/> I fear that absence may do its work of forgetfulness<lb/> &#38; what would life be to me without the certainty of<lb/> being beloved &#38; having something to love on earth</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>you say I am impulsive therefore you must not scrutinize<lb/> my letters&#44; for as my thoughts pious so do I pen them &#38; you<lb/> must be thankful that my pen cannot fly as swiftly as they<lb/> do or what a heterogeneous mass you would be taxed to read<lb/> But I have some correspondents&#44; that I have to compose<lb/> my letters for&#44; &#38; they are anything but agreeable ones&#59; but to<lb/> those whose friendship I can depend on&#44; I throw them<lb/> on paper&#44; as they rush to my mind without any regard to<lb/> style penmanship or order. I have read several numbers of<lb/> the women of <placeName>Israel</placeName> &#38; am much pleased with them <persName>Miss<lb/> A</persName> with a happy talent imparts interest &#38; character to many<lb/> which in the sacred book are only remarkable as the wives of<lb/> good &#38; great men &#38; as being mothers of the Jewish family. We<lb/> have bought it for our Library thereby enabling those scholars<lb/> who can appreciate them to read them&#44; as well as children of a<lb/> larger <add>&#63;</add> I often sigh&#44; that my means&#44; will not<lb/> sanction&#44; my indulgence in possessing&#44; every book that<lb/> comes out&#44; relative to our people. I am a great admirer of<lb/> <persName>Charlotte Elizabeth</persName>&#44; but have just finished a little work<lb/> &#40;sent to <persName>Rosalie</persName> by a gentile friend&#41; that savors quite too<lb/> much of the Saviour to suit my taste &#8212; I shall not allow<lb/> her to read it&#44; as I cannot expunge&#44; what is objectionable<lb/> which I often do&#44; in works sent to her&#44; there being such as connec<lb/>tion as to render it quite unintelligible by so doing &#8212; Aprospos<lb/> do you know what her real name is&#63; Have you heard that<lb/> <persName>Miss Henry Myers</persName> is married to <persName>Tuckerman</persName> the <add>&#63;</add> And<lb/> <persName>Charlotte</persName> to <persName>Griswold</persName> the authors Intermarriages are bad<lb/> enough when the young &#38; thoughtless enter into them&#44; but</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p>when women who are in the <add>paper ripped</add> &#38; yellow leaf of time enter<lb/> into such engagements what can they hope for.<lb/> The report of <persName>Miss H&#39;s</persName> marriage has only reached me but <persName>Mrs H</persName><lb/> has received a letter from <persName>Charlotte</persName> informing her&#44; of her marriage<lb/> I have a pretty piece of poetry&#44; called the &#8220;Dying Hebrew&#8221; if you<lb/> will receive it&#44; without the authors name I will forward it<lb/> our weather is cool &#38; delightful&#44; the autumnal leaves have not yet<lb/> begun to fall &#38; remind us&#44; of our departure from this beautiful<lb/> world&#59; and we will have no depressing heat to render our appro&#45;<lb/>aching fast&#44; uncomfortable&#44; may you be written<lb/> in the book of a happy &#38; prosperous life&#44; is my fervent prayers<lb/> and at the intercession of the good&#44; for their fallen &#38; sinful<lb/> sisters&#44; avails much I hope you will not be unmindful<lb/> of one&#44; who stands much in need of forgiveness for positive<lb/> as well as negative sins &#8212; My daughter &#38; son both desire their<lb/> regards&#44; they have a pleasant circle &#38; enjoy all the benefits<lb/> of the best society&#44; although I often ask myself&#44; if my precepts are<lb/> sufficiently impressed to prevent their marrying with the stranger<lb/> God must watch over them&#59; cut off from their own people<lb/> I cannot deprive them of the charms of society &#8212; I found my<lb/>&#45;self on the 5th side without being aware with this mom<lb/>ent how I am taxing your time &#38; patience. Let me soon<lb/> hear from you &#38; do inform me if there is more union among<lb/> your congregation than in <date>1840</date> &#8212; Remember me to my Cousins<lb/> good fortune seems to <del>some</del> to follow them through life&#59; few<lb/> are more deserving&#44; but if we judge only by the prosperity of our<lb/> friends of their goodness&#44; what a sorry chance some of us will<lb/> have &#8212; I cry you mercy &#38; will subscribe my self</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">your friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)"><persName role="author">R C Moise</persName></p>
			<pb n="6"/>
			<p rend="indent(4)">Mail</p>
				<p><addressee>Revd I. Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><placeName>Pa</placeName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written upside down at the top of the page.">The books are recd &#8212; will write<lb/> in relation to them when the money<lb/> is collected. Yours &#38;c <persName>Thos S Moise</persName><lb/> Many thanks in for the <date>Saturday</date> post<lb/> it afforded amusement to many<lb/> of us &#38; <persName>S A</persName> says her scrap books<lb/> has <sic>benefitted</sic> materially by it.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
