<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Hayyim, Son of Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF1_67</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Hayyim, Son of
                            Jacob</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Dulmen, Germany</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-07">12 July 1854</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-07">16 Tammuz</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url=""/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 6 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>
                <add><hi rend="underline">Yiddish</hi>-German</add>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Dülmen</placeName>, <date>Wednesday</date>,</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><date>(16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Tammuz), July 12,
                1854</date>.</p>
            <p>Dearest cousin:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your letter of the <date>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Iyar
                    (May)</date>,<lb/> which came to me by way of
                <placeName>Magdeburg</placeName>,<lb/> delighted me all the more in that I saw in
                it<lb/> your warm family devotion and especially your<lb/> interest and concern and
                love for me.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Were I still unmarried I would,<lb/> without further thought,
                consent to your<lb/> request to obtain for myself the position at<lb/>
                <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>. I would also and aside from<lb/> the success
                or failure of this plan, gladly<lb/> have accepted your invitation to make a<lb/>
                holiday trip to you. This I could have<lb/> done without losing my position here,
                for it<lb/> would have given me great pleasure to spend<lb/> some time with a
                beloved relative, whose name<lb/> has become famous far off, and who has<lb/>
                accomplished worthwhile things in <placeName>America</placeName> in<lb/> the
                interests of our holy faith. However,<lb/> since about a year ago I am happily
                married<lb/> and I must take into consideration the<lb/> wishes of my beloved wife
                and not journey</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2.</p>
            <p>with her quite so far away to a place from<lb/> which she would presumably not have
                the<lb/> opportunity again to see her aged parents.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But even if I cannot take into consider<lb/>ation the problematical
                position, nevertheless, I<lb/> can answer your questions with regard to a
                friend<lb/> who has ambitions of that sort. His name<lb/> is <persName>David
                    Steinberg</persName>, and he is, at the present<lb/> time, teacher in the Jewish
                seminary at <placeName>Münster</placeName>.<lb/> The day before yesterday he paid me
                a visit. From<lb/> two letters of his friend <persName>Guttheim</persName>, I
                noticed<lb/> that the latter recently paid you a visit,<lb/> furthermore, that he
                asked <persName>Steinberg</persName> to<lb/> take steps with regard to the position
                in <placeName>San<lb/> Francisco</placeName>. He asked me, therefore, to <del>let
                    you</del><lb/>
                <del>know</del> request of you to send a word of<lb/> recommendation for him to that place.<lb/>
                <persName>Steinberg</persName> has, in addition to a decided philo<lb/>logical bent,
                devoted to a thorough study of the<lb/> classics. At this very time he is about to
                take his<lb/> doctoral examination. He told me that he is<lb/> thoroughly acquainted
                with the French language<lb/> &amp; English, however, he has not made any
                further<lb/> progress than to understand the “Vicar of<lb/> Wakefield” without
                having done much further</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">3.</p>
            <p>reading. With his thorough philological<lb/> knowledge, however it will not be
                difficult for him to) make great<lb/> progress in this respect. The chief thing,
                however,<lb/> is that it was always his great desire he<lb/> is now 34 years old—to
                devote himself to<lb/> the education of the young. In all the com-<lb/>munities in
                which he acted as teacher, until<lb/> now, as well as in all his general
                relationships,<lb/> he has enjoyed general respect and love,<lb/> both with regard
                to his thoroughness as well<lb/> as his honorable moral character. As regards<lb/>
                religious and ceremonial life, his present<lb/> position insures that he lead a
                ceremonial-<lb/>ly Jewish life, if only not to suffer criticism.<lb/> Nevertheless,
                I don't want to overlook the<lb/> fact that in this respect he inclines towards<lb/>
                * a mild reform. However, in matters that<lb/> concern the fundamentals of our
                holy<lb/> faith, I can safely say that, in so far as I can<lb/> judge human beings,
                that he is a Jew with<lb/> a sincerely Jewish heart.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Steinberg</persName> thinks that if it is possible he<lb/>
                would prefer that another man be given the<lb/> position of chazan while he devote
                himself to<lb/> preaching and religious instruction of the<lb/> young. This he
                desires, not because he lacks</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">4.</p>
            <p>the aptitude for such work but because the<lb/> combination of all these activities
                in one person, es-<lb/>pecially in so large a community, might be too<lb/>
                exhausting. He would gladly give up a portion of<lb/> his salary if a chazan were
                appointed separately.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1851</date>, the second part of my<lb/> Hebrew
                study and exercise book appeared. I sent it<lb/> to you through an emigrant but I
                don't know<lb/> whether it has been delivered to you. The reviews,<lb/> of this
                book, seem very favorable. It is also<lb/> having a seemingly good sale. Although
                it<lb/> was written originally for Jewish schools, it has been<lb/> introduced also
                in some German<lb/> gymnasia. Unfortunately, a large number<lb/> of our Jewish
                teachers are either too ignorant of<lb/> Hebrew or too indifferent to make practical
                use<lb/> of this book. On the other hand, some highly re-<lb/>spected and excellent
                colleagues have let<lb/> me know by letter that since the introduction of<lb/> my
                book in their schools, the instruction in<lb/> Hebrew has taken a new upward swing
                and<lb/> has <del>caused a</del> made Hebrew a popular subject, on the<lb/> part of
                the spiritually awakened children. Such<lb/> men, however, are exceptional, for
                most<lb/> Jewish teachers are merely “hewers of wood<lb/> in the house of God.” They
                limit them-<lb/>selves to the most essential. Generally<lb/> speaking, Hebrew
                teaching is torture for<lb/> them, since they themselves are ignorant</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">5.</p>
            <p>of it. Most guilty is the “Münstersche Ver-*<lb/>einschule” which does not produce
                sufficient<lb/> results in this respect, and in spite of the en-<lb/>closed program
                of studies which has been<lb/> acclaimed throughout the classes of the
                com-<lb/>munity, it has not until now, improved<lb/> any. The chief fault lies in
                the unsatisfactory<lb/> method of the good, but elderly, seminary<lb/> teacher,
                    <persName>Cohen</persName>, who has no understanding<lb/> of how an interest for
                such studies can be<lb/> planted in his pupils.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For our needy brothers in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>,<lb/>
                collections have been taken up rather diligently<lb/> here also.
                    <placeName>Dülmen</placeName> for example contributed<lb/> 18 ½ Reichstaler.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Finally, several family news items.<lb/>
                <persName>Lippman</persName> is married since <date>1847</date>.
                    <persName>Selig</persName><lb/> since a year ago. The former has four<lb/>
                children. Both conduct a business in corn<lb/> in —<add>?</add>, which is really flourishing.<lb/>
                <persName>Probka</persName> is, for the last five years, married<lb/> to one of the
                most important — in <placeName>Essen</placeName>,<lb/>
                <persName>Jamgon Gottschelk</persName>, and has four children.<lb/>
                <persName>Hindlke</persName>, who three years ago married the<lb/> oldest son of
                    <persName>Uncle Isaac</persName>, in <placeName>Lünen</placeName>,
                un-<lb/>fortunately died in childbirth. The little<lb/> son which she left, is thank
                God, in good<lb/> health. <persName>Zanvil</persName> has a good<lb/> medical
                practice in <placeName>Herzfeld</placeName>,</p>
            <p>* The community school<lb/> of <placeName>Münster</placeName></p>
            <p rend="The following is written in the left margin of the page">either <hi
                    rend="underline">butcher</hi><lb/> or <hi rend="underline">miller</hi> or<lb/>
                something else.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">6.</p>
            <p>near <placeName>Loest<add>?</add></placeName>
                <persName>Lazar</persName> and <persName>Gittlesche</persName> are<lb/> still in the
                old peoples' home. My dear<lb/> mother is, thank God, still in good health,<lb/> and
                is at present on a visit at <persName>Procha's</persName>.<lb/> Everyone sends you
                hearty greetings. I<lb/> am very happy with my beloved wife<lb/>
                <persName>Shanetta</persName>. She is very religious, kind-<lb/>hearted, and a good
                housekeeper. In spite<lb/> of our meager income she knows how to<lb/> manage so that
                we get along very nicely<lb/> in a respectable manner of living. In<lb/> order to
                improve our situation, I intend<lb/> to establish a store, which my wife, who
                is<lb/> used to such things from her home, will<lb/> have in charge.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And now, my dear cousin, <del>write</del> it is<lb/> your turn to
                write to me about your private<lb/> situation. A short while ago I heard you<lb/>
                had given up your position. Is that really<lb/> so? Good luck, many blessings to
                you<lb/> and your work. With unchangeable, loyal<lb/> friendship and love, I remain,
                your cousin</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">Hayyim</persName>, son of
                    <persName>Jacob</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
