<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF1_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Anytown, Ottoman Palestine</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-01">January 1854</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-01">Tebeth 5614</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_3v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_4r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f1_0007_4v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="true"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Vol XI</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">No 10</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <date>Tebeth 5614 January 1854</date>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Palestine</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Writer in the <add>?</add> whether sought for in the <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/> or in
                natural causes the fact is undoubted that <placeName>Palestine</placeName> has ever
                been<lb/> that and of affection to all believers in the Bible. The <del>Monkes</del>
                Mohamedan<lb/> has his Al-Charria<add>?</add>, the Christian possess their various
                churches &amp;<lb/> shrines; and they all <add>?</add> less than us attach the
                highest earthly society<lb/> to the spots consecrated by the remarkable <add>?</add>
                of patriarchal &amp; biblical<lb/> history. It may be a fanatical error as some
                would <sic>characterise</sic> it<lb/> for Jews to cluster round those places where
                where formerly they were the<lb/> lords<add>?</add> but no little better than slaves
                and beggars and subject to our<lb/> bearing and tyrannical master. But so they have
                been from the<lb/> day the temple fell a sacrifice to the flames whether the
                    <add>?</add> were<lb/> the Romans, the Arabs, the crusaders, the Egyptians, or
                the Turks.<lb/> At not time for eighteen centuries, and were before the emblem of
                our<lb/> national glory fell, were <add>?</add> the norm than earlier on our own
                soil;<lb/> still <placeName>Palestine</placeName> was the land of our hope, the
                country of our desire.<lb/> But let those who blame the deviant for this feeling
                tell us why<lb/> it should not be so? are we so well treated in more civilized
                countries?<lb/> are we so regarded as equals in many lands? How many
                    <placeName>Americas</placeName><lb/> are there in the world? how many
                    <placeName>Hollands</placeName>, <placeName>Belgiums</placeName> &amp;
                    <placeName>France</placeName>?<lb/> Tell us where are all the liberties which
                our du<add>?</add> of a <add>?</add><lb/> have obtained in
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <add>?</add>, <placeName>Hungary</placeName>
                &amp; <placeName>Poland</placeName>? Where? Dissipated<lb/> to the <add>?</add> and
                    <add>?</add>; and the partial light which dawned six years<lb/> ago, and which
                    <add>?</add> to be the harbinger of a brighter day, has<lb/> left us in greater
                obscurity and the loosening of the chains of political<lb/> and religious slavery,
                has caused us to feel the lightening of the <add>?</add> with</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>a thousandfold redoubled painlessness, for dreamers, where is your<lb/>
                <add>?</add> reign? where is your universal <add>?</add>? where the
                <add>?</add><lb/> I am of the Lamb and the wolf together? The wars of oppression
                against<lb/> freedom still continue, and the wolf yet <add>?</add> his teeth
                against<lb/> the unoffending lamb that is unable to have his prey. Letting go
                where<lb/> we will, <add>?</add> countries where there live in all less than a half
                a<lb/> million of our brethren, the body of political slavery and degre-<lb/>dation
                is still ours, as are yet excluded from all places of profit<lb/> and preferment;
                and even the eight<add>?</add> to a share in the possession of<lb/> the lands of
                    <add>?</add> is denied us in many lands. Oh! what a<lb/> freedom this is! What a
                state that is to satisfy the longing of the<lb/> Jewish patriot for happier days for
                a time when the land of<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> is again to be ours, to be occupied by sons of freedom
                and industry,<lb/> sitting each under his own vine<add>?</add> and each his own fig
                tree with<lb/> none to make him afraid. Whatever others may do, we do not blame<lb/>
                the oppressed, not even the free, in all lands who look toward their<lb/>
                    ancestral<add>?</add> home or the true country of <placeName>Israel</placeName>,
                where the<lb/> religion promulgated through <persName>Moses</persName> is ultimately
                to stand proud<add>?</add><lb/> on the light and life of the world, guiding all
                mankind to universal<lb/> freedom, teaching them all a perfect, pure, un<add>?</add>
                faith, and<lb/> alone undying in the spirit, for the Creator of all things.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">'Hence we say, could a numerous agricultural
                population<add>?</add><lb/> be drawn <del>toward</del> to
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, we should not only contribute to towards<lb/>
                the permanent relief of these residing there already, but we should<lb/> open an
                    <add>?</add> for many who now know of <add>?</add> only as<lb/> a
                <add>?</add>ionary and received a sacrifice as <add>?</add> them out on
                tranquil<lb/> days, of which they and their father, before them have <add>?</add>
                the true<lb/> signification. If it could be accomplished, that the <add>?</add> of men<lb/>
                <add>?</add> Israelites of <placeName>Poland</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Russia</placeName>, <add>?</add> and <placeName>Hungary</placeName>
                &amp; <placeName>Turkey</placeName></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>should be planted in agricultural colonies in the callings of the land<lb/> of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, under the protection of the present energetic
                    <persName>Sultan Abdul<lb/> Medjed<add>?</add></persName> with full liberty to
                organize municipal corporations,<lb/> permitted to bear arms and fully empowered to
                use of them<lb/> in case of an attack from without; we should do much to<lb/>
                ameliorate the abject condition of European communities who<lb/> now are daily
                exposed to insult and <add>?</add> of their arrogant<lb/> and proud oppressors. If
                his home should become intolerable to<lb/> an Israelite, he would know whether he
                could resort and<lb/> find the means of self support without the danger of being led
                away<lb/> from the path of duty, which now alas! is too often the case with
                those<lb/> who go to <placeName>England</placeName>, <placeName>France</placeName>,
                    <placeName>America</placeName><add>?</add> from other countries<lb/> simply to
                follow the only pursuit which seems to promise them<lb/> a speedy return,
                    <add>?</add> trading in one of its many <del>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del><lb/> shapes, all other employments being inacceptable to a stranger<lb/> who
                is unacquainted with the language &amp; customs of the lands<lb/> he just arrives
                in. But now <placeName>Palestine</placeName> once open to receive Jewish<lb/>
                immigrants; <del>where</del> were its agricultural wealth once more acceptable<lb/>
                to our faith; <del>wh</del> were its fields once more fertile and its cities<lb/>
                rebuilt anew: not alone that many could unite themselves<lb/> to its inhabitants to
                cultivate the soil, sure of a speedy and rich<lb/> return for their labors; but then
                who have the genius and lust<lb/> for business could carry on profitable commerce
                with all<lb/> parts of the world in exchange for the varied products of the<lb/>
                fields and vineyards, and perhaps the many rich muses<add>?</add> of resonan<lb/>ce
                which now lie unused and unknown, <del>with</del> against <add>?</add><lb/> is
                raised from the soil and <add>?</add> skill and labors<lb/> in every other country.
                This is no mere dream, the realization<lb/> of what is beyond the range of
                possibility; but the same spectacle</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>was witnessed in ancient times when the <add>?</add> of<lb/>
                <placeName>Giza</placeName> &amp; <persName>Gideon</persName> contained the commerce
                of the world; when<lb/>
                <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was filled with the wares of all climes and
                when<lb/> prosperity and elegance smiled in every city o the prosperous<lb/>
                commonwealth. If we revert to the description of <persName>Jacob</persName> and
                    <persName>Ezekiel</persName><lb/> of the prosperity and elegance of <add>?</add>
                and Jews alone we may indeed wonder at<lb/> the awful desolation which now presides
                over them &amp; <add>?</add> of<lb/> musical <add>?</add> &amp; refreshment; but at
                the time it leads us to the<lb/> condition that under similar circumstances similar
                results<lb/> may be <add>?</add> at some future, if ever distant, day. If the<lb/>
                weak places should be built up; if the broken <add>?</add> should<lb/> be repaired;
                if the now dry aqueducts should be restored; if the<lb/>
                <add>?</add> of the inhabitants should be converted into thrift<lb/> and industry;
                it cannot be otherwise than that the articles of<lb/> import would be multiplied
                beyond calculation. The <add>?</add><lb/> in the wilderness of
                    <placeName>Syria</placeName> and <placeName>Judea</placeName> would afford food
                for<lb/> millions of sheep, whose fleece could readily rival and<lb/> exist perhaps
                under that happy sky, <add>?</add>, serenity<lb/> on that eastern fairyland, the
                best mariners of <placeName>Spain</placeName> and<lb/>
                <placeName>Saxony</placeName>; that <add>?</add> could readily be made to wear on
                his<lb/> shroud of the purest fibre after being abundantly fed till the<lb/> day of
                his <add>?</add> with the healthful <add>?</add> of the whole<lb/> mulberry which
                would grow there in abundance <add>?</add> the<lb/> commonest care be taken; the
                bulk of the worth could yield<lb/> abundant supply of the purest olive oil, for a
                    <add>?</add> they were<lb/>
                <add>?</add> from us; the <add>?</add> of <persName>Judah</persName> would
                again<lb/> be laden with the fruit of the vine, and the valleys of
                    <placeName>Jezreal</placeName><lb/> and <placeName>Sharon</placeName>, and
                    <placeName>Carmel</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Tabor</placeName>, and the plains
                of <placeName>Jericho</placeName><lb/> &amp; of the <placeName>Great Sea</placeName>
                would again be <del>bad</del>
                <add>?</add>dened with the</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>immense harvests, the hundredfold yield, which <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add> them. Cotton too, and hemp, and fruit of various<lb/> kinds, the Indian
                corn, the potato, the yam, the banana,<lb/> and other products anciently unknown in
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName> could be readily intro-<lb/>duced and yield
                their increase in unexampled plenty, if the<lb/> labourers were used there to
                prepare the soil for their reception.<lb/> And can it be doubted that so many
                articles what in their<lb/> raw or manufactures state would feed<add>?</add> a ready
                demand in other<lb/> countries, <add>?</add> not soon enrich their producers,
                and<lb/> elevate them, as successful commerce always does, to a<lb/> high state of
                refinement and elegance?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The ruinous cities would soon be rebuilt; the books<lb/> of the
                timid billers of tillers of the soil who now fear, to work diseasing<lb/> the
                assault of the maraud<add>?</add>
                <add>?</add>, would soon make place<lb/> for <del>the</del> compatible
                    farm-<add>?</add>; the pastures now desolate<lb/> would resound with the bells
                of the returning flocks and hearts<lb/>
                <del>at evening</del> led <del>forth</del> home by the little and gay shepherds,
                as<lb/> in ancient times; the parts which are now rarely visited by the<lb/> ships
                of foreign nations, because there is so little for them to<lb/> carry away would
                soon be filled with vessels displaying the<lb/> flag of every country; and the roads
                on which now painfully<add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add> the camel of the caravan in its slow progress, would<lb/> be made
                noiseful by the thundering steam car in its impa<lb/>tient <add>?</add> to reach the
                place of its destination; and<lb/> all because industry once more <del>should</del>
                would have breathed life<lb/> &amp; vigour into the listless indolent <del>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del> few that now vegetate<lb/> not live, starve and not enjoy life in a land
                which formerly<lb/> nourished the millions of men and cattle, and now produces<lb/>
                scarcely enough to feed its <del>remnants</del> handful of persons coming as they
                have</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>done from many climes without concert of action without any cohesion<lb/> or unity of
                purpose. The Turks are merely the rulers, and are not, we<lb/> should judge our
                    <add>?</add> the Arabs are too indolent to make good<lb/> farmers, and totally
                unacquainted with the improved state of European<lb/> agriculture, or are given to
                    <add>?</add> and <add>?</add> true to their ancient<lb/> national character so
                that from the <add>?</add> population not<lb/> much can be expected, unless they
                    ref<add>?</add> their customs altogether<lb/> which is not likely to take place
                in centuries to come, unless some<lb/> now <add>?</add> revolution should compel
                them thereto. The Christian<lb/> inhabitants are not many, and being either
                    <sic>mountaineous</sic>, who have<add>?</add><lb/> isolated from civilization or
                    <add>?</add> and connected with monastic and<lb/> other religious
                establishments; if we have understood correctly the<lb/> accounts of
                    <sic>travellers</sic>, are not likely to contribute much to<lb/> the improvement
                of the land. The Jewish population, which may<lb/> reach twenty thousand in all is
                too few, and for that matter<lb/> too ignorant of manual labors to do any thing for
                their own<lb/> advancement. Is it therefore wonderful that
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName> presents<lb/> to the eye of the stranger so
                little of what is <add>?</add>, and im<lb/>measurate with the description which we
                have received of its<lb/> former popul<add>?</add>ness and magnificence? Nay it is
                at most<lb/> a wonder that a vestige has been left, after all the battles<lb/> and
                earthquakes and other causes of desolation, to show<lb/> that
                        <placeName><sic>Baalbec</sic></placeName>, and <add>?</add> and
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> were at one<lb/> time such cities as but few of
                modern times can com-<lb/>pare with; and if something is not done to restore them
                the<lb/> few fragments of ancient days must crumble away in the<lb/> cause of coming
                generations and leave not a wreck behind.<lb/> If therefore a new life could be
                infused in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>; if a new population<lb/> industrious
                and inured to toil could be gradually infused on the stagnant</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>masses which now encumber its surface, there can be no question<lb/> but that
                proportionate good results would be speedily brought to view; for<lb/> the indolent,
                seeing the superior advantage of industry, the happy affects<lb/> of independence
                through labour, would naturally be <add>?</add> either to<lb/> the village of the
                soil or to the mechanical pursuits required<lb/> to supply the many wants of a
                farming population. This again<lb/> would react or commence, goods from foreign
                lands would<lb/> have to be brought in to furnish the requirements for the
                work<lb/>ship, the manufacturing and the <add>?</add> of the table; and this
                would<lb/> again be the <add>?</add>runner of internal improvements, by high
                ways<lb/> canals and rail roads, to bring the fruits of <add>?</add><lb/> the reach
                of our <add>?</add> and to enable to producers<add>?</add> to dispose of<lb/> his
                surplus where it is needed.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">There is no conceivable reason why <placeName>Palestine</placeName>
                &amp; <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName><lb/> should be given over to sterility and
                    <sic>disolution</sic> when in former<lb/> ages they were not alone the misery of
                mankind, but the seat<lb/>
                <add>?</add> knowledge and religion were scattered all over the<lb/> earth.
                    <placeName>Egypt</placeName> may have been the home of early architecture and
                the<lb/> priests who guarded a secret knowledge of a purer <add>?</add> of by<lb/>
                than the majority of the people possessed; but it was nevertheless<lb/> from the
                inhabitants of the first mentioned lands that the religions<lb/> which now govern
                the world were derived; and through them taught<lb/> at first in Arabic <del>and
                        <persName>Mohamed</persName> was a rather of the same land</del><lb/> it was
                only from <placeName>Palestine</placeName> that his system advanced under
                various<lb/> guises as the conquering system, destined to ever <add>?</add> others
                in<lb/> to <add>?</add>less <add>?</add> to universal dimension. Fine
                P<add>?</add><lb/> too, it is assisted, that the system of alphabetical writing
                was<lb/> first carried into eastern <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and <add>?</add>
                is in result a higher<lb/> philosophy notwithstanding the corruption of the Greek
                &amp; Romans</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>than was known among them before that time, and savage<lb/> lords were thereby
                connected into elegant and refined communi<lb/>ties. And shall it be so forever that
                all their lands shall<lb/> be only desolate and without the foot of man and beast
                to<lb/> pass through them? It is true that the Scriptures have recorded<lb/> a
                fearful <add>?</add> over the lands of these who relying on their<lb/> strength and
                wisdom <add>?</add> of the law of God<lb/> and walked after their imaginations of
                their own &amp; unbridled<lb/> heart. But it is likewise true that the same
                authority<lb/> promises consolation and a restoring of the ancient glory; and
                the<lb/> only question is how this is to be accomplished. We will not at
                pre-<lb/>sent enter into a reception of the prophecies bearing on this topic;<lb/>
                nor investigate how far we should rely on a sudden development<lb/> of the divine
                policy which is to affect the great and <add>?</add> predictions<lb/> of
                    <placeName>Israels</placeName> sun; but it surely cannot be wrong for us to
                endeav-<lb/>our to promote the happy future by some exertions of my own.<lb/> It may
                be that all efforts will be in vain; it is possible that<lb/> a curse doth rest on
                the land which it is not yet the time to<lb/> have removed; it is possible enough
                that the <hi rend="underline">man</hi> is yet wanted<lb/> who could be a leader in
                this blissful regeneration. Still we think<lb/> that it is worthwhile to make an
                effort to aid our brothers <add>?</add><lb/><add>?</add> on the spot with the means
                to <del>make our effort not</del> realize our self ameliora<lb/>tion which they are
                now anxious to effect, bring sick at heart<lb/> of the life of paupers; <add>?</add>
                which is a never ending always recom<lb/>mencing service of <add>?</add>, &amp; is
                indeed a pity that hitherto the<lb/> very love for our religion has been made the
                moving principle<lb/> of fastening <add>?</add> on the land of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. “To offer for the love of<lb/> the
                    <placeName>holy land</placeName> “was and is considered highly meritorious; to
                main<lb/>tain a deed <add>?</add> praiseworthy and salutory; whereas all<lb/> this
                must only <sic>perpetiate</sic> the <add>?</add> which the pious thought they</p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_11_10.pdf">The above text refers to Occident
                        Volume 11 No. 10 pages 477 through 486. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
