<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Bernheim, G. D.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF14_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Bernheim, G.
                            D.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f14_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">For the Occident.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev. Mr. Leeser</addressee>; I read in the <date>October</date> number of
                the Occident<lb/> an account given by yourself &amp; <persName>Mr. E.
                    Marcussohn</persName> in<lb/> which he makes statements, which utterly &amp;
                entirely deny<lb/> the fact, that he had left the Jewish faith &amp; united
                himself<lb/> with, or at least had been amongst Christians, also denying some<lb/>
                statements made as to his conversion in the <date>August</date> number<lb/> of the
                Jewish Chronicle, declaring <persName>Rev. Mr. Bonhomme</persName>, and<lb/> several
                other ministers in <placeName>Montgomery</placeName> as those that had<lb/> spread
                base falsehoods concerning him.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now if <persName>Mr Marcussohn's</persName> account be true, &amp;
                such<lb/> really is the case, he has suffered severely &amp; suffered
                inno-<lb/>cently, and nothing rejoices me more than that such<lb/> foul deeds were
                so openly and deservedly exposed to be<lb/> detested by every virtuous man. However,
                there are<lb/> some things that I cannot fully understand, as they<lb/> are “too
                high and too deep” for me, and therefore I wish<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Marcussohn</persName>, who certainly is an erudite and an<lb/>
                honourable man, to explain them for me; we ministers,<lb/> down
                    <placeName>South</placeName> here, are such common &amp; plain folks, that<lb/>
                we cannot fully comprehend the conduct of <persName>Mr. E.<lb/>
                    Marcussohn</persName>, I would wish him then to explain<lb/> unto me the
                following circumstances: -</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">1stly. If <persName>Mr. M.</persName> had never left the Jewish
                faith<lb/> why should he tell me &amp; others, that he had publicly re-<lb/>nounced
                that faith before the congregation which he<lb/> served as Chazan or Shochet in the
                city of <placeName>Montgomery<lb/> Ala.</placeName> 2Ndly. Why should he try to
                prove his sincerity</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>in having done so, as he stated, by telling me that in so<lb/> doing he lost an
                excellent annual salary, part of which<lb/> had already been earned by several
                months service ren-<lb/>dered the Jewish congregation in
                    <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>, &amp; for which<lb/> he did not receive a
                cent on account of his having left<lb/> the Jewish faith. 3dly Why should he come to
                me in<lb/> the character of a converted Israelite, staying in my house<lb/> for two
                weeks, instead of shunning me as a Christian<lb/> minister, and go amongst his
                Jewish brethren.</p>
            <p>4thly Why also should he have necessity to shave him-<lb/>self in our house, since as
                a sincere Jew, and withal a<lb/> Jewish Rabbi or Chazan, it was not lawful for him
                to do<lb/> so; en passant; will you just be so kind <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>;
                &amp;<lb/> ask him to show you the nice set of shaving appara-<lb/>tus I presented
                unto him. 5thly Why should he<lb/> want of me a commission to labour as a
                missionary<lb/> to the Jews, and went with that intention to <placeName>Columbia,
                    S.C.</placeName></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">6thly Why did he ask me, and also make me promise<lb/> to come to
                    <placeName>Columbia</placeName> in a week after he left
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>, &amp;<lb/> be present to witness initiation
                into the Christian<lb/> church by baptism, which I also would have done, had<lb/>
                not our family been taken sick with the Yellow fever<lb/> about that time, having
                also been afflicted with the loss<lb/> of a dear mother with that disease. Will you
                also please<lb/> ask him to let you see the letter of introduction to the<lb/>
                <persName>Revd E. B. Hart</persName> of <placeName>Columbia</placeName>, which I
                gave him.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">7thly It was also his misfortune that he should have re-<lb/>ceived
                some money from me, for which I hold his receipt,<lb/> &amp; which, so he says in
                his last letter to me from <placeName>Philada.</placeName></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>dated the <date>12 of Septr 1852</date>, he will refund, besides that which<lb/> the
                Christian friends in <placeName>Montgomery</placeName> have given him, when<lb/> I
                know, that, had he never given up his Jewish faith the<lb/> truly benevolent
                Israelites in <placeName>Charleston</placeName>, who never yet have<lb/> refused a
                worthy applicant for aid, and who lately were so<lb/> kind to the poor Jews during
                the past prevailing epidemic,<lb/> would certainly have assisted him in his
                distress; thus<lb/> saving him the trouble of going amongst Christians for<lb/>
                pecuniary assistance. 8thly Why also, if <persName>Mr. M.</persName><lb/> had never
                left that faith, did he beg me in his last letter,<lb/> not to write anything
                concerning him. Ah! I am fearful<lb/> that he knew I might mention some few
                circumstances, which<lb/> in a slight degree would contradict a few statements made
                by<lb/> him in the Occident, and thus the faith, as to the truth of<lb/> his
                statements, which his Jewish brethren would have, might<lb/> slightly be impaired.
                9thly You state, <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>; that <persName>Mr.<lb/>
                    Marcussohn</persName> remarked that his sole reason for going
                    <placeName>North</placeName><lb/> was to contradict the statements made in the
                Jewish Chronicle<lb/> as to his conversion. Now I would readily believe this, for<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. M.</persName> is certainly an honourable man, if it were provable<lb/>
                that an upright man would travel over 1000 miles for this<lb/> sole purpose,
                spending nearly $100.00 expenses collecting money<lb/> for this sole reason among
                Christians by false statements, taking a <sic>circuituous</sic><lb/> route; when all
                might be accomplished by simply publish-<lb/>ing a letter in the Occident, which he
                might have sent you.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">10thly If that were his sole reason for going
                    <placeName>North</placeName>, then he<lb/> must have had a vision in
                    <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>, that those statements<lb/> would be published
                in the Jewish Chronicle about conver-<lb/>sion, for his first saw them at my house,
                when he had</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>already performed nearly one half of his journey to the
                <placeName>North</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now I might go on still further in giving you more<lb/> facts,
                either of which, as either of the others which I have<lb/> given, would confirm the
                statements made in the Jewish<lb/> Chronicle, viz; that <persName>Mr. E.
                    Marcussohn</persName> did renounce the<lb/> Jewish faith; but these are
                sufficient to convince any<lb/> candid mind; however of the circumstances connected
                with<lb/> his conversion, I know nothing, as I do not reside in<lb/>
                <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>, and was not present at that time, I only
                give,<lb/> an inquiring public what I do know &amp; no more.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It may also be alleged, that as <persName>Mr. M</persName> was not
                baptized<lb/> he did not renounce his faith in Judaism, but that does<lb/> not
                follow at all, Baptism can only be considered as con-<lb/>firming his former acts
                &amp; conduct publicly declared by him-<lb/>self baptism alone will make no man a
                Christian; one<lb/> thing, however, is certain, that <persName>Mr. M.</persName> did
                renounce the Jewish<lb/> faith, but had not formally accepted of the Christian
                faith;<lb/> God alone must judge his motives for acting so strangely.<lb/> Upon the
                whole <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>, I come to this conclusion,<lb/> that if all
                Jews, especially converted Jews, were like <persName>Mr. E.<lb/>
                    Marcussohn</persName>, I would truly believe with you, that there<lb/> would be
                very little hope of doing any good, in our way of<lb/> thinking, among the children
                of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, therefore it follows, that<lb/> we need not regret
                that he has turned back to the Jews again.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yours sincerely</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">G. S. Bernheim</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">son of a converted Israelite</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">who died in the Christian faith</p>
            <p>N. B. If what I have now written<lb/> is not sufficient for <persName>Mr.
                    Marcussohn</persName>, &amp; he wishes to continue<lb/> the controversy, I will
                in my next give to the public some<lb/> things which he might not relish so
                well.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
