<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>Box 1, FF4</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF4_18</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>Montreal, Canada</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1847-11" source="" attested="yes">24 November 1847</dateLet>
              
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0020_1r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0020_1v.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0020_2r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f4_0020_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false">Fragile</condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
		  <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
		<text>
		<body>
		<pb n="1"/>
		
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>1 Presde Ville Place</placeName></p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Montreal</placeName></p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><date>Nov 24 1847</date></p>
			<p><addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>

		  <p rend="indent(2)">My dear Friend</p>
		  <p rend="indent(3)">You flatter me much when you say<lb/> you will be happy to count me among the few you favor with<lb/> an interchange of communication.  Though I am pleased to stand in<lb/> correspondence with the <persName>Rev Isaac Leeser</persName> Minister of the <sic>Portugese</sic> Israelites<lb/> in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> I am much more pleased to communicate with the Editor<lb/> of the Occident&#44; and the author of the &#34;Jewish Discourses&#44;&#34; and of the &#34;Mosaic<lb/> Law&#34;  If therefore I am at any time not to remedy in answering your favors<lb/> as this feeling would prompt&#44; do not impute it to neglect but to its<lb/> true cause inability.  It has been inability that has prevented my answering<lb/> yours of the <date>16th</date> till the present moment&#44; and it has been inability that<lb/> has forbidden my sending you by opportunity of <persName>Mr Joseph</persName> an article which<lb/> I have but just now been able to commence&#44; and which I promised you<lb/> in my last.  I know not whether it will suit the Occident&#44; because<lb/> although a Jewish subject&#44; it is likely to prove more interesting to the readers<lb/> of a British Periodical&#44; it may be called an Essay or <sic>Enquiry</sic> into the first<lb/> settlement of Jews in <placeName>England</placeName>.  When in <placeName>London</placeName> I took some little trouble<lb/> in collecting materials for the subject and in the above form they<lb/> are much at the service of yourself and of the readers of the Occident<lb/>  Please let me know by earliest opportunity whether you [&#63;] to<lb/> receive it.   I would have sent you sermon for publication but<lb/> suppose that even now you would be unable to insert it from<lb/> the number you have on hand.  Will my father&#39;s be among those<lb/> you intend publishing.  English news would lead one to believe</p>

		<pb n="2"/>
		
			<p>that its remarks are as pertinent now as when delivered.  News from<lb/> here I can send you but little&#44; A friend who lately paid us a visit&#44; and still<lb/> more lately visits <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> &#40;I believe&#41; is pleased to say &#34;altho we Canadians do not<lb/> form &#40;here&#41; one of the largest and most influential congregations we prove that<lb/> we sufficiently understand what is [&#63;] to the respectability of Synagogue worship<lb/> &#34;The building is most striking for its very neat &amp; pretty appearance&#44; marked decorum<lb/> pervaded the assembled&#44; and an utter absence of that boisterousness&#44; sometimes<lb/> unfortunately prevailing in our larger Synagogues was observable xxx The prayers<lb/> were read by the [Hebrew] <add>[&#63;]</add> with an apparent desire to avoid that style which<lb/> reminds one so much of the opera and which for time and place is alike<lb/> objectionable xxxx  It must be highly gratifying to you to know that your<lb/> discourses&#44; and general services as reader and teacher are highly spoken of &#40;dont[&#63;]<lb/> you think dear friend I have some excuse if I grow vain&#63;&#41; My friend &#40;[&#63;]&#41; continues&#44;<lb/> But what pleased me most was to see your pupil &#40;Mouther[&#63;] I <persName>Ascher the son<lb/> of the Parnass</persName>&#41; called us <persName>Maphlir[&#63;]</persName>&#44; The very correct and pleasing name of<lb/> his reading afforded me much pleasure.&#34;  If you wish to give us all a fond<lb/> character here you can insert it in your news Items.  The name of the writer &#40;tho&#39;<lb/> perhaps known to you shall be provided if you require it editorially tho&#39;<lb/> I am not sure he would like it &#40;his name&#41; to appear in the Occident for All he says is&#8211;&#34;If<lb/> you choose&#44; write <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> what a <hi rend="underline">first rate</hi> character stranger gives<lb/> you.&#34;  All the news I can give you of us &#40;should you pronounce that <hi rend="underline">no</hi><lb/> news&#41; is that our Parnas is <persName>Mr Ascher</persName> whose inde[&#63;]able services as Parnas&#44; and<lb/> whose jealous endeavors to promote the welfare and quiet of the community<lb/> with his <sic>colleage</sic> <persName>Dr David</persName> <del>the</del> President are mentioned by all in the highest<lb/> terms.  They all have been unanimously re&#45;elected.  The formation[&#63;] of the new Board of Trustees has <del>also</del> caused general satisfaction<lb/> among <del>to</del> the members.  These are <persName>Messrs S. Benjamin</persName>&#44; <persName>Simon Hart</persName>&#44; and <persName>Jesse Joseph</persName>&#44;<lb/> Treasurer <persName>John Levy</persName> &#40;re&#45;elected&#41; and <persName>Levy Myer Solomons</persName> &#40;also re&#45;elected.&#41;  During<lb/> the late summer an unprecedented[&#63;] number of German Jewish Emigrants visited<lb/> <placeName>Canada</placeName>&#44; Indigent&#44; and in many cases sick&#33;  They provide most services<lb/> drain on the funds of our Infant Philanthropic Society&#44; About Thirty<lb/> unfortunate persons many with families besides one noatbly[&#63;] pensioner&#44; were<lb/> recipients.  On [&#63;] that the committee contemplated a Benefit Ball<lb/> but have not yet held any [&#63;] of [&#63;].  Should they determine<lb/> upon this&#44; they will no doubt make it known in the Occident.<lb/>  This dear friend is all the news I can scrape together concerning<lb/> our precious selves&#44; and I have preferred giving you most of it as<lb/> an &#34;Extract from a private communication&#34; because if I had myself</p>

		<pb n="3"/>
		
			<p>undertaken to &#34;give characters&#34; I should altho&#39; finding much to praise<lb/> still find a little to censure&#8211;But to other matters.  I received last<lb/> week a letter from my friend <persName>D Benisk</persName> now Editor of the Voice of Jews<lb/>  He writes me that it is to be considerably enlarged and the whole to be<lb/> under his management.  This last would imply&#44; strange fingers in the Free<lb/> and I think this has been the case with the late [&#63;] articles contend<lb/> in the Voice.  In a letter received from my father the same mail he writes<lb/> &#34;I hear that it is the intention of your friend <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> to visit old<lb/> <placeName>England</placeName>&#8211;Do you know whether this is really the case&#44; I should be most<lb/> happy to have it in my power to exercise my great esteem for him.&#34;<lb/>  What am I to reply&#44; dear friend&#63;  I hear this for the fist time.  He<lb/> encloses me a prospectus of <persName>Mayer&#39;s</persName> projected publication&#8211;What do<lb/> you think of this.  There is no doubt I should say that as far as abilities&#44;<lb/> Rabbinical and general knowledge so&#44; there is not a man&#44; christian or Jew<lb/> who is better able to answer <persName>Mr C[&#63;]</persName> than this said <persName>Hoya</persName>.  As a<lb/> Hebraist he has not I firmly believe his equal.  Witness his [Hebrew]<lb/> and Hebrew Translation of <persName>Mr Cauls</persName> Old Paths.  Some attribute<lb/> the Heb version of the Christian Common Prayer to him but looking<lb/> at the style of that sublime composition I should doubt this much<lb/>  His last articles too in the <placeName>London</placeName> Jewish Chronicle are&#8211;to make<lb/> use of a mysterious old saying &#34;not to be sneezed at.  I am more<lb/> anxious to see his 1st no.  The [&#63;] of state [&#63;] I suppose has<lb/> retired purposely to make room for the &#34;faithful missionary&#34; who<lb/> will doubtless occupy much room on the tables of the religious<lb/> reading world&#44; but the Jewish &amp; Christian&#44; altho&#39; the same apathy<lb/> unfortunately exist to [&#63;] [Hebrew] here&#44; as on the subject of an<lb/> efficient ministry.  With respect to this last the observation<lb/> of my father very often seems occurs to me.  He very dryly observed one day<lb/> &#34;The [Hebrew] to sail them must be [Hebrew] [&#63;]&#34;<lb/> and I think he is right.  But I sincerely hope this unhealthy<lb/> state of things will give way to more worthy &amp; [&#63;] notions<lb/>  It has done so in many cases let us hope that its <sic>observence</sic><lb/> will soon be universal.</p>
			<p>I informed <persName>Mrs Ascher</persName> of your invitation not to charge for<lb/> the nos&#44; and she denies to acknowledge your politeness&#8211;</p>

		<pb n="4"/>
		
			<p>So you are a reformer.  I have not yet seen your <date>November</date> number<lb/> but doubt well that the reforms there propounded will shock<lb/> orthodox susceptibility but little&#44; and that they are of a practiced<lb/> and [&#63;].  I too am a reformer as far as endeavours<lb/> which I believe to be <hi rend="underline">consistent</hi> and legal&#44; in improving the manner<lb/> of Synagogue worship are concerned.  I don&#39;t think the cause of<lb/> orthodoxy would suffer much did conservative Synagogues introduce<lb/> quiet &amp; respectability in their services.  Orthodoxy by nature<lb/> by age&#44; and by character is respectable.  Absurd and inconsistent<lb/> novelty in the Synagogue is disrefutable in its very essence<lb/> and it appears therefore a serious &amp; cruel anomaly that while<lb/> all that care [&#63;] devotional feelings prevail in the new [&#63;]<lb/> in the old&#44; very much that is calculated to excite disgust<lb/> worldly and impure feelings is there observable.  But my dear<lb/> friend [Hebrew]&#44; continue to sound in the unwilling ears<lb/> of the [Hebrew]&#44; and [&#63;] success <hi rend="underline">must</hi> one day follow.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">&#34;Prata albicaul camis friunis&#34; Our Canadian winter<lb/> approaches in the shape of a few slight snow storms.  See too<lb/> looks more plentiful in the streets than it did in summer&#44; But<lb/> with all its severity speaking from last winters experienced<lb/> I like the winter here much.  There is a [&#63;] the cold [&#63;]<lb/> clearness of atmosphere that renders the season here much more<lb/> agreeable and healthy than in <placeName>London</placeName>.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(1)">I must now bid you good bye dear friend for<lb/> the present.  Hoping you will write me very soon&#44; and<lb/> [&#63;] and that you may receive this [Hebrew]&#33;</p>
		  <p rend="indent(6)">I am My dear Friend</p>
		  <p rend="indent(6)">Yours very sincerely</p>
		  <p rend="indent(6)"><persName role="author">Abraham deSola</persName></p>
			<p><persName>Mrs Joseph</persName> &amp; daughters desire</p>
			<p>me to remember them to you</p>
			<p>with comforts.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>