<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF3_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1856-06">1 June 1856</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0015_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0015_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0015_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0015_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="true"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <date>June 1. 1856</date>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">Dear Sir/ It was not<lb/> forgetfulness or neglect that has hitherto
                prevented me from<lb/> answering your kind letter of <date>February 12</date> last,
                but circum-<lb/>stances alone, the explanations of which, here following, must<lb/>
                be ample apology for me. When I received your letter, you<lb/> were on your way to
                    <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, wherefore I had to await for<lb/> your
                return. Then I read in the Occident that <persName>Rev. Mr Jacobs</persName><lb/>
                had sent you a reply to my last letter in your periodical, when<lb/> I again thought
                to await its publication. Afterwards I was<lb/> so busily engaged in the most
                various occupations and duties,<lb/> that, besides having been unwell for the last 3
                months, I could<lb/> barely find time to write the most urgent private letters.
                In<lb/> the meanwhile, when I intended again to do my duty, and reply<lb/> to yours
                above mentioned, I heard that <persName>Rev. Mr Jacobs</persName> had<lb/> sent you
                a communication—like that to the Israelite—condemnatory<lb/> of my reading a Psalm
                in the church, in consequence of<lb/> which I thought it proper again to defer my
                reply, with the<lb/> view of avoiding even the least appearance of my intention<lb/>
                to bias you by a private letter. Now, as <persName>Mr J.'s</persName> letter
                must<lb/> be <del>publish</del> in the Occident, so that I can no longer
                exercise<lb/> any influence, I may <del>say</del> after all, write with all
                impunity.<lb/> This much also I may add, with regard to this affair, that I
                hope,<lb/> as a matter of simple justice, you have in your “<hi rend="underline"
                    >Note</hi>” not al-<lb/>together disregarded my explanation in the Israelite,
                nor forgotten<lb/> that whatever <persName>Mr J.</persName> now writes about me, is
                tinctured with a good</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>deal of animosity, vindictiveness and hatred. And here let me relate to you<lb/> the
                whole history of <persName>Mr J.'s</persName> relation to me, which I have hitherto
                from delicacy<lb/> withheld from you. When <persName>Mr. J.</persName> arrived here,
                I immediately called upon him, as<lb/> common courtesy demands it, and told him at
                once: Let us be friends, al-<lb/>though our religious views diverge; you preach
                orthodoxy and I, reform,<lb/> don't you attack my congregation, as I intend never to
                make my<lb/> reference to yours; especially let us meet each other in society
                with<lb/> that <sic>collegial</sic> friendship, as ought ever exist between
                gentlemen; such a<lb/> cause will have a good impression not only upon the Jews, but
                upon the<lb/> society at large, and is calculated to raise the Jewish character in
                the<lb/> eyes of the Public. <persName>Mr J.</persName> made all the promises I
                could expect. But<lb/> already on the following <date>Sabbath</date>, he <hi
                    rend="underline">directly</hi> attacked us in the most<lb/> venomous manner; of
                course, at that time, when the “honeymoon” was<lb/> not yet over, he could do such
                things with impunity; you must know<lb/> this yourself, for at the same time he
                treated you in the same arrog-<lb/>ant manner. He neither returned my visit, nor
                that of many of my<lb/> conregators who had likewise called upon him. Yet, I cared
                not about<lb/> all that; I continued to treat him with the most marked
                courtesy.<lb/> During the summer of <date>1853</date> he came to me to borrow a
                book, the<lb/>
                <add>מורה נבוכים</add>, but told me <hi rend="underline">in my room</hi>, that I
                should not look upon<lb/> his coming as a visit, as he had merely come to borrow
                that book. My<lb/> answer was: My library is at all times at your disposal. I even
                had<lb/> him invited to my wedding; he neither came, nor acknowledged the
                in-<lb/>vitation, nor ever congratulated me. yet, I continued to treat him with
                <lb/>courtesy, until in <date>November 54</date> he charged me, in a conversation we
                had<lb/> near the Post-Office with having perverted<add>?</add> a passage in the
                Shulchan A-<lb/>such, when I coolly answered, “he only retorted in this manner,
                because<lb/> he felt that I had proven his inconsistency,” upon which he flatly
                called<lb/> me “ignorant;” when I told him, that it was below my dignity to
                answer</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to such an important speech. The breach was thus made. Soon afterwards<lb/> the
                presentation to <persName>Mr Valentine</persName> (Occident viii, 37) took place,
                when it so happened<lb/> that I attended, for the first and only time—the meeting of
                the Chebrah preceding<lb/> the presentation. During that meeting, <persName>Mr
                    J.</persName> insulted me 5 times, in the most<lb/> outrageous manner, while I
                merely smiled. He had then forgotten that<lb/> his star had greatly waned.
                    <persName>Mr. V.</persName> called him thrice to order, and ordered<lb/> him at
                last to sit down; nay! And this point it is particularly that ex<lb/>asperated
                    <persName>Mr J.</persName> mostly—declared before the society, that my
                complaint,<lb/> that during my absence several poor strangers had been buried
                without<lb/> ministerial attendance, was true, although <persName>Mr. J.</persName>
                had, in the course of<lb/> his insults, denied the fact. Not one of his long
                    regators<add>?</add> was then found<lb/> who did not confess that <persName>Mr.
                    J.</persName> acted in a most ungentlemanly &amp; <add>?</add>-<lb/>ness &amp;
                amiability. From that time <persName>Mr. J.</persName> took his speech from
                    <persName>Mr<lb/> V.</persName> &amp; <persName>N. Levin</persName>—During the
                same winter he saw himself induced<lb/> to resign in consequence of repeated
                complaints having been made by Congreg<lb/>ators of his, of his undignified
                deportment in society, of his leaving<lb/> the synagogue during the reading of the
                Haphtorah to taste a <hi rend="underline">drink</hi>,<lb/> &amp;c. &amp;c.; nay!
                even before <hi rend="underline">his</hi> Board it was remarked, that there was<lb/>
                such a wide difference between his deportment &amp; mine. He was <hi
                    rend="underline">permitted</hi>,<lb/> upon his <hi rend="underline"
                >request</hi>, and after an apology from the pulpit, to withdraw his<lb/>
                resignation. Yet he must give vent to his wrath, I was no longer ap-<lb/>proachable,
                and this he most outrageously insulted <persName>Mr Valentine</persName>, on<lb/>
                <add>פסח</add>
                <date>5615</date>, <hi rend="underline">during Public Service</hi>, which
                    <add>?</add> caused an irremediable breach<lb/> between these two, and a great
                reserve with others. Add to this, that I am<lb/> on a most friendly with most, and
                intimate with many of his congregation,<lb/> and you can understand the rest.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Last summer, you must remember, he began to write against
                    <persName>Kalish</persName> &amp;<lb/>
                <persName>Wise</persName>, on “Ladies' singing &amp;c”, when he wanted books of
                reference, which has not,</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>since his whole Hebrew library consists of about ½ dozen Volumes, the <add>תנ"ך</add>
                included.<lb/> But too proud, to send to me, although I had all along sent him word,
                that my<lb/> library was at his disposal, even for Articles against myself, he
                resorted to<lb/> a trick. A Polish Jew often visited me with the pretext to “<hi
                    rend="underline"><add>?</add></hi>,”<lb/> and made extracts from the Talmud,
                Maimonides &amp;c. I know at once<lb/> for whom he “learned.” But having made it a
                rule, to allow people to dupe<lb/> me, until a good opportunity enables me to show
                them, that they are the dupes,<lb/> not I, I permitted the man to act as he chose.
                One day, after reading for<lb/> some time, he requested me, to let him take a volume
                of <add>רמב"ם</add> home, when<lb/> I coolly answered: “Tell <persName>Mr
                    Jacobs</persName>, whenever he wants a book from my library,<lb/> he must either
                come himself, or send in his own name; I do not allow my<lb/> books to be borrowed
                in such a clandestine way!” The man burst into<lb/> a laughter; &amp; said, “you are
                keen, the book was intended for <persName>Mr. Jacobs</persName>.”<lb/> Between
                    <add>י"כ</add> &amp; <add>ר"ה</add>
                <persName>Mr J.</persName> met me at a funeral, and—made up<lb/> against my Article.
                I answered, I should be glad of it, only requested him to<lb/> abstain from all
                scurvilities &amp; personalities, as a <hi rend="underline">friendly</hi>
                controversy could be<lb/> productive only of good. He promised all. And when his
                first Article ap-<lb/>peared, some of <hi rend="underline">his admirers</hi>
                expressed to me their astonishment at this,<lb/> that he could write so calmly. They
                were soon cured of their astonish-<lb/>ment. Since the publication of my answer, to
                spit out whenever he meets me.<lb/> Nay! he went even so far, to recite, at a
                nuptial festival, a Hebrew<lb/> poem, extracted from some work, but given out by him
                as his own, to ridicule<lb/> me, thus making himself also, besides being the
                officiating minister, the<lb/> Possenmacher. And hence: <hi rend="underline">illae
                    lacrumae</hi>. You may now<lb/> judge how impartial he must <add>?</add>,
                whenever I am concerned. I assure<lb/> you, that I deeply regret this state of
                things, for his sake, for so far,<lb/> he has been the loser in every respect.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In your last editorial you give me also “a lick at the tailor.”
                And<lb/> yet you owe me thanks; for it was I, who forced <persName>Drs W.</persName>
                &amp; <persName>L.</persName> to declare them-<lb/>selves, and I would be very much
                obliged to you for telling me: whether you<lb/>
                <sic>indorse</sic> their explanations of the ii Article, or not; and whether they
                spoke<lb/> in the same manner before the conference. I am inclined to think,
                they<lb/> then deluded you, or, as you will have it, themselves. That is of
                little<lb/> difference to the Public; this much we have gained, that we now
                understand<lb/> what they wanted. And if you will let me have the use of your pages,
                I<lb/> will “shed” a little more ink, and write “commentaries” on their
                expositions.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
