<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Jonah of the house of
                    Bondi</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF4a_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Jonah of the house of
                            Bondi</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-05">21 May 1863</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4a_0001_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4a_0001_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4a_0001_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4a_0001_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f4a_0001_3r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="true"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><date>Tuesday, Rosh Hodesh Sivan(May), 1863</date>.</p>
            <p>Peace and all that is good, forever:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If some cure were found for my weak nerves, my low<lb/> spirits, and
                for my bitter feelings, it would be a letter from you,<lb/> you, an appointed
                officer and honored in your place. But when you<lb/> begin to complain even more
                what shall I say ? Unfortunately,<lb/> you have no insight.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am very grateful to you for your frankness when you<lb/> say that
                    <persName>Pappe</persName> is my friend. I did not expect anything else.
                Not<lb/> because of my mitzvoth, nor because of my situation, but a learned<lb/> man
                like me is revolted by such pseudo-learning. Unfortunately,<lb/> this type of
                    <sic>Cnazan</sic> constitutes the majority of conservative Ju-<lb/>daism.
                Orthodoxy is an artificial, a Jesuitical thing. I am<lb/> proud to say that I spurn
                orthodoxy, for I want the true Judaism,<lb/> such as our sages have received and
                transmitted through the Oral<lb/> Law, and such as our children should receive, as I
                said last <date>Sun-<lb/>day</date> at a meeting for the establishment of a Sunday
                school. You<lb/> must admit that through the work of such people, who do nothing
                for<lb/> the education of the children, must have as a result that Judaism<lb/> will
                die with us. Will <persName>Pappe's</persName> children know anything about a
                Tal-<lb/>mud? Will they know what the mitzvoth from the Torah are? Or<lb/> mitzvoth
                of the rabbis? Is it not a great, brazenness on the part<lb/> of <sic>sucha</sic>
                man to rely purely upon customs and to stick his head be-<lb/>tween hills and
                mountains while the learned and righteous people<lb/> of the world in
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName> are astonished at my work? Does he
                under-<lb/>stand anything, even with regard to ordinary meanings of the Talmud,<lb/>
                the Mishnah, idol-worship? Yes, I consider myself among those<lb/> about whom our
                sages, may their memory be for a blessing, said, “All<lb/> that a good student is
                destined to being forth as a novelty, etc.” I<lb/> insist upon holding on to the
                old, but in order to save something<lb/> from the shipwreck which may at all
                possibly be saved, I shall, if</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>necessary, always go as far as our <hi rend="underline">Shulchan Aruch </hi>and
                    <persName>Maimonides</persName> go.<lb/> That is the boundary, As far as which
                I, as a learned man who under-<lb/>stands to read between the lines, must follow
                with his spirit. That<lb/> is self-evident. I tell you if nothing happens for
                Conservative Ju-<lb/>daism, everything is lost, and all, except those who now life
                in fear<lb/> of eternal punishment, will go over to the camp of the enemy.
                Inside<lb/> the synagogue, they want to be called pious. Inside their houses,<lb/>
                they eat trefah and violate the <date>Sabbath</date>. Here it is a terrible
                thing<lb/> to see. Unfortunately, people do not understand how to “increase the<lb/>
                Torah and glorify it”. You, too, refused to understand how to proceed<lb/> with
                wisdom and intelligence. If you do understand how to accomplish<lb/> much, it does
                not seem to be on the practical side. Unfortunately,<lb/> the statement of the great
                    <persName>Rabba</persName> is not sufficiently well-known.<lb/> “He who forgoes
                his own qualities, all his sins are removed.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When people who do not know the words of our sages, mis-<lb/>take
                the unessential for the essential„ I do not hold it against them.<lb/> They know no
                better. It is preferable that they should hold on to<lb/> the unessential in order
                that he essential should not be forgotten.<lb/> But when one sees that the important
                ones of <placeName>Israel</placeName> throw the Torah<lb/> overboard and maintain
                silly customs only for the sake of gain, only<lb/> to act hypocritically, then one
                must weep for the destruction of our<lb/> holy Torah. These people do not know and
                do not understand what it<lb/> means, “Desecrate one <date>Sabbath</date> in order
                that you may be able to observe<lb/> many <date>Sabbaths</date>”. I can tell you for
                your own satisfaction, you, the<lb/> Portuguese who has cast aside the comments of
                    <persName>Rabbi Moses Isserlein</persName><lb/> (RaMA) which are holy to me,
                that in my small community, <hi rend="underline">Emunei Israel</hi>,<lb/> I have had
                recited the counting of the <hi rend="underline">Omer</hi>.... on the other hand,
                I<lb/> insist that there be no idle conversation, no business talk, and such<lb/>
                like.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I will not say about myself that I have a fuller insight</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2.</p>
            <p>in the learning that God granted me. I say “The fear of thy teacher, etc.”<lb/> “The
                Torah of my teachers and my superiors” — “The fear of heaven” —<lb/> “A man's
                livelihood is set for him”. And so I trust in God and must<lb/> complain that a man
                like you who is known as a God-fearing man should<lb/> have so little influence. I
                may be writing to a good friend and I ex-<lb/>pect that you will deal kindly with
                me... but it is not possible to<lb/> remain inactive.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I should like you to send this letter to <persName>Jacob
                    Friedman</persName>,<lb/> the Mohel. You will receive through the post either
                one set of holi-<lb/>day prayer books or <sic>??</sic>. The house is easy to find.
                    <persName>Pappe</persName> knows it.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Your servant ready to serve you,</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">Jonah of the house of Bondi</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="On the margin of the first page">I am adding a report about the meeting for the
                Sunday school.<lb/> Please publish it</p>
            <pb n="Envelope"/>
            <p>
                <persName>Rev. Isaac Leeser</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <placeName>Penn</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>1227. Walnut St</placeName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
