<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M., Dr.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF3_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M.,
                            Dr.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1856-06">10 June 1856</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0017_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0017_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0017_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0017_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Charleston</placeName>, <date>June 10
                1856</date>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev: Isaac Leeser</addressee>, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">Dear Sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">Your kind<lb/> letter, dated <date>June 5</date>, reached me
                yesterday, and I hasten to reply<lb/> to it at once, in order to remove all
                unfavorable impressions from your<lb/> mind, which, judging from the contents of
                your letter, seems to rest<lb/> thereon.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Let me begin with the passage in my correspondence to <persName>Dr
                    Ph's</persName><lb/> “Zeitung des Judenthums.” When I read your remarks in the
                letter<lb/> to me, I laughed very heartily; but perceiving afterwards, at the<lb/>
                perusal of your Editorial in the <date>June</date> number of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Occident</hi>, that<lb/> you took the affair more than serious,
                I at once determined to make<lb/> some explanations to you, as I do not wish to be
                misjudged by you.<lb/> Know then, the clause “<add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add>,” is not mine, but <persName>Dr Ph's</persName>. The sentence
                con-<lb/>tained in my manuscript, runs thus: “mit <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add>.” It appears to<lb/> me that <persName>Dr Ph.</persName> Made this
                change, which, by the way, I do not approve,<lb/> with the view of having
                    <persName>R. Hirsch</persName> kept out of the controversy. I<lb/> hope that his
                candid explanation will satisfy you; since it can<lb/> be no discredit to you, to be
                compared with <persName>R. Hirsch</persName>, whose<lb/> sincerity of principles and
                honesty of purpose, no one, not even<lb/> his fiercest opponents can question. But
                here I must<lb/> complain of your translation. In rendering the clause, “In<lb/>
                <add>?</add>,” by “I will admit, with<lb/> sincerity,” you did not do justice to the
                spirit of my words. My</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>intention was, most emphatically to repeat what I have often told you and<lb/>
                others, that you belong to those very few in our midst, <del>that</del> who are
                sin-<lb/>cerely &amp; honestly orthodox; to use your own words: “whose practice
                does<lb/> not belie their theory.” But your translation of my words does<lb/> not
                convey the emphasis and sincerity contained therein; as it shows,<lb/> it admits the
                construction of ambiguity, even sarcasm and irony.<lb/> I should have translated in
                this way: “which, however, are in-<lb/>deed sincere.” Now, I do not only authorize
                but even request you<lb/> to notice my explanation in your next issue, as I am never
                so<lb/> self-conceited or proud, to give explanations, where justice demands<lb/>
                them; besides, the picture which you have drawn of a Polish<lb/> Rabbi would
                certainly be such a reflection on you, as I would<lb/> be indeed the last to
                conceive or <sic>indorse</sic>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You speak, furthermore, of scurrilous remarks having been<lb/> made
                before about you in <persName>dr Ph's</persName>. Gazette. You later under a
                great<lb/> mistake I have never found any. On the contrary; <persName>Dr
                    Phs.</persName> in<lb/> not<add>?</add> your Bible, rebutted those that had
                indulged in<lb/> such remarks in this country, especially <persName>Mr.
                    Kalish</persName>, as I wrote<lb/> you at the time; upon which you told me, that
                you showed <persName>Dr<lb/> Ph's</persName>. Remarks to the former, and took him
                thus by surprise, so<lb/> that he did know what to say.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I think you are wrong in not publishing my report; for the<lb/>
                reasons you give, hold not good. You forget that the works are<lb/> not those of
                    <persName>Dr Ph.</persName>, but of the “<hi rend="underline">Institute</hi>,”
                and he has no<lb/> right to dispose of them, as he can do with his own; I
                regard<lb/> this “<add>?</add>” as a real national affair, which every Jew<lb/>
                ought to <sic>patronise</sic>. I have myself to pay subscription,<lb/> although I am
                the agent for <placeName>America</placeName>. And so had <persName>Dr<lb/>
                    Einhorn</persName> to pay his $1.65.__Apropos of <persName>Dr E.</persName>
                <hi rend="underline">You</hi> have</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>certainly no right to complain of his not visiting any synagogue in<lb/>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>; pray, have you ever passed the threshold of a
                “Temple?”<lb/> Besides, <persName>Dr E.</persName> was but once in
                    <placeName>Phila.</placeName> since his arrival at
                    <placeName>Balti-<lb/>more</placeName>, and then only on account of the death of
                a niece of his. You<lb/> see that it is not right, to judge so harshly. He is
                certainly as<lb/> sincere &amp; consistent in his views, as you, in yours; and
                such<lb/> qualities we ought to respect in <hi rend="underline">every one</hi>. Now,
                that I am<lb/> liberal, I proved again on the <date>2d</date> day of <add>פסח</add>,
                when I visited<lb/> the new Polish Synagogue in this city, and read the
                    <add>הפטרה</add>!<lb/> Can you assert such liberality on your part?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As regards <persName>Mr J's</persName> Articles, he may write as
                long as he pleases,<lb/> I do not even glance at them; I do not even hold him in
                contempt,<lb/> I pity the man, he has fallen so deep, that he is no longer<lb/>
                within my reach.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="underline">Several</hi> copies of your small bible have
                been purchased for our<lb/> Sunday-School, and more will be bought, when the funds
                allow it;<lb/> for I am determined, that the Christian version should be
                banished<lb/> from the school. Any how, we bought more, than the <hi
                    rend="underline">Orthodox</hi> Con-<lb/>gregation, that has no more a
                Sabbath-School, thanks, as I<lb/> was told, to the praiseworthy exertions of the
                orthodox <persName>Mr. Jacobs</persName>.<lb/> I myself bought the <hi
                    rend="underline">first</hi> copy from <persName>Mr Hart</persName> for my
                own<lb/> private use, and urge, on every occasion, upon my Congregat-<lb/>ors, to
                relinquish the common Bibles, and buy yours. And<lb/> I think, several have followed
                my advice.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When I told you that I deferred my reply to your letter of
                    <date>Febr.</date>,<lb/> because I <del>did not</del> wished to avoid the
                appearance of influencing<lb/> you, I meant to say, that I did not wish, <hi
                    rend="underline">you</hi> should think that<lb/> I <hi rend="underline"
                    >intended</hi> to influence you, altho' I <hi rend="underline">knew</hi> very
                well, that no man<lb/> could do it. But, again, I did not wish, that you should <hi
                    rend="underline">think</hi> of such</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>an attempt on my part.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As regards the gentlemen in <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, I
                certainly know them as<lb/> well as you do, &amp; perhaps a little better, which is
                also the reason<lb/> why I am anxious to force them to explanations or show the
                people<lb/> who &amp; what they are. I have followed them very closely, and
                attentively<lb/> studied their history. The could not bear that I, too, should
                have<lb/> come out against them; they forgot that nothing on earth can
                in-<lb/>fluence me, when Truth &amp; Justice are concerned. “Fiat justitia,<lb/>
                pereat mundus” is my principle.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The <sic>inclosed</sic> book is sent to <persName>Rev. Mr Isaac
                    Leeser</persName>, not the<lb/> Editor of the Occident. The collection consists
                partially of original compos-<lb/>itions, partially translations, furnished by
                members of the congregation &amp;<lb/>
                <del><hi rend="underline">yourself</hi></del> your humble servant. Whatever may be
                your opinions<lb/> with regard to the use of English hymns in the synagogue you<lb/>
                will find nothing un-Jewish in this book, which I hope, tho'<lb/> it be
                    <add>חזק</add> in your eyes, will not be regarded as unworthy of a<lb/> place in
                your library.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As you have concluded your letter with a Latin salutation, I
                must<lb/> conclude mine in Greek,</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <add>Greek</add>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">Dr M Mayer</persName>
            </p>
            <p>P. S. Please send me 2 copies of <persName>Mendelsohn's</persName> Jerusalem.<lb/> I
                shall settle with you, <add>אי"ה</add>, in <date>July</date>, when I intend visiting the<lb/>
                <placeName>North</placeName>, and, of course, seeing you in
                    <placeName>Philada.</placeName></p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">M</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
