<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">a descendant of
                    Israel</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">a descendant of
                            Israel</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1846-08">16 August 1846</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_3v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_4r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0004_4v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Small Pica.</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">No 6.</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">Denning.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">To the Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>St Thomas</placeName>
                <date>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> August 1846</date>
            </p>
            <p>Revd Sir.—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I know the deep sympathy and interest<lb/> which you feel in all
                that concerns your coreligionists<lb/> wherever they may be found, I therefore
                without apology<lb/> take the liberty of occupying your attention with some<lb/>
                remarks on a subject that ought to engage the attention<lb/> of every friend to the
                Faith; I know not what your<lb/> views may be with respect to the various
                Innovations<lb/> which tender the title of “Reform” are finding their way<lb/> into
                the Ritual and Ceremonies of the Jews of the present<lb/> day; but I think I know
                    sufficient<del>ly</del> of you, in order to<lb/> be assured that whatever your
                opinions may be, you will<lb/> not object to hear and to give publicity in your
                valuable<lb/> periodical (the Occident) to the opinions of others however<lb/> they
                may differ from yours.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It may be necessary to premise that the Indivi=<lb/>=dual who now
                addresses you thinks that the form of the<lb/> religious worship of the Jews may be
                favorably amended,<lb/> some of their customs may without injury or impropriety<lb/>
                be dispensed with; but he must confess himself not<lb/> sufficiently learned to
                point at any particular one,<lb/> and to say so with <hi rend="underline"
                    >certainty</hi>; therefore for himself, tho' a<lb/> reformer, he would rather
                yield allegiance to long<lb/> established customs than indiscreetly to have them
                chang'd;<lb/> but another more powerful reason which induces him<lb/> to object to
                the innovations alluded to is that they are<lb/> not the result of combined and
                general understanding<lb/> by the Jews throughout the World: Individuals, who<lb/>
                claim to be the descendants of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, who believe in
                the<lb/> revelations of the Old Testament and look for the<lb/>
                <sic>fulfilment</sic> of the promises declared thereby should consider<lb/> that an
                obligation rests upon them of a different character</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>to that which belongs to mere religious Sectarians; on<lb/> them devolves the duty of
                seeking for the national<lb/> regeneration of the house of
                    <persName>Jacob</persName>, and by every means<lb/> should they endeavor to
                hasten the approach of the gathering<lb/> in of the faithful; will they do so by
                destroying their<lb/> individuality or by object and servile imitations of the<lb/>
                customs of the Gentiles, who on their part have on induce-<lb/>ment, no object in
                preserving that unity, which whilst<lb/> it gives strength, vigor and consistency to
                the worship is at<lb/> the same time a type of the object of the adoration and
                hope<lb/> of the Jew; <hi rend="underline">One only true and all powerful
                God</hi>?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If our forms be defective, our ceremonies not congenial<lb/> to the
                spirit of the times, in Heaven's name let them be<lb/> changed; but let the change
                be the result of some combin'd<lb/> purpose, let it be based upon the united wisdom
                of<lb/> competent persons selected by the parties interested; I am<lb/> for change,
                but for such a change as will not destroy the<lb/> unity, the individuality and
                harmony of a people who<lb/> claim to the chosen of God: I am led to these<lb/>
                reflections Mr Editor by having witnessed a ceremony<lb/> performed in the Synagogue
                of this <placeName>Island</placeName> under the<lb/> title of “Confirmation”; what
                the Hebrew term is I do<lb/> not know, nor do I think there is any, invented as
                yet,<lb/> for I believe the origin of this grave ceremony does not go<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">quite so</hi> far back as when the Hebrew Language was the<lb/>
                Vernacular of the Jews; but perhaps when I describe it<lb/> your learning may devise
                some Hebrew word applicable<lb/> to it; and really I wish you would, for the
                term<lb/> Confirmation reminds one too forcibly of the “laying on<lb/> of hands” of
                the “Lord's spiritual” the “Vice Gerents of their<lb/> Lord and Master
                    <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>;” In order to be appreciated<lb/> by a Jewish
                congregation I will briefly describe the<lb/> ceremony as it was “enacted” here.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The confirmanté having undergone a course of<lb/> instruction and
                preparation and being perfect in their<lb/> parts, a procession composed of the
                confirmants (the</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>girls dressed in white with white veils covering their heads<lb/> and faces, the Boys
                in their holiday suits) walking in<lb/> pairs and succeeded by the Reader of the
                congregation<lb/> dressed in his Robes, proceeded from the residence of the<lb/>
                Reader to the Synagogue, arriving there the Service of the<lb/> Evening (eve of
                    <date>Shebungot</date>) was commenced, at the<lb/> appropriate time the Reader
                ascended the pulpit and<lb/> delivered a discourse in English, the confirmants
                and<lb/> their parents were then placed around the front of the<lb/> Ark in two
                Ranks, the former in front and the latter in<lb/> the rear, the Reader taking his
                stand on the platform<lb/> of the ark, then interrogated the confirmants on the
                Decalogue<lb/> and the thirteen articles of Faith alternately in Hebrew<lb/> and in
                English, the responses being all correctly made in<lb/> accordance with an
                established formula; the ark was<lb/> opened and three Scrolls of the Law were taken
                out and<lb/> held by the dignitaries of the congregation, the confirmants<lb/> then
                approached and placed their hands upon the Scrolls<lb/> they repeated a solemn
                pledge and promise that they (the<lb/> confirmants) will always believe in what they
                have<lb/> learned and repeated; and will never change their Religion,<lb/> (or words
                to that effect) the confirmants <sic>ascented</sic> thereto,<lb/> and the Parents
                then laid their hands on the heads of the<lb/> confirmants and a blessing was
                invoked by the Reader;<lb/> after this an exhortation was delivered and the service
                was<lb/> concluded. Now Sir! I ask, and would respectfully<lb/> ask you to answer,
                has such a ceremony ever been performed<lb/> in any Synagogue of Jews previous to
                the establishment<lb/> of what are termed “reformed congregations” in
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName>?<lb/> is it to be found in the formula of Jewish
                worship<lb/> ordained by Rabbinical authority since the dispersion?<lb/> is it to be
                found in the ceremonial established for the<lb/> Israelites by
                    <persName>Moses</persName>? if not, then I feel constrained to<lb/> say that it
                is a presumptuous uncalled for innovation<lb/> without warrant from any acknowledged
                Jewish<lb/> authority and as such should be discountenanced and</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>rejected.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The creed of the Jews as I have understood it consists in<lb/> the
                emphatic Declaration “<hi rend="underline">Hear O <placeName>Israel</placeName> the
                    Lord our <del>thy</del></hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">God is One</hi>” it begins and it ends with that single<lb/>
                comprehensible and undisputed Idea. But in the ceremony<lb/> of confirmation as it
                was performed here this great Truth<lb/> is joined to what are termed the
                    13<del>th</del> Articles of Faith, all<lb/> of which the confirmants are made to
                    <del>believe</del> declare they<lb/> “believe with a firm faith.” thus by
                confounding a plain and<lb/> evident truth, designed as the basis of the Jewish
                faith<lb/> with a collection of questionable deductions drawn from<lb/> the writings
                of the Prophets and the Sages of the Bible;<lb/> the foundation for discussions,
                divisions and dispersions<lb/> is laid which is to be feared will lead to the same
                consequences<lb/> as have resulted to the Christian Church; But independent<lb/> of
                this, I would ask, Is it either wise or proper to cause<lb/> or even to permit young
                inexperienced persons to make<lb/> a solemn pledge before God and the world, always to<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">believe</hi> what they have been taught and always to <hi
                    rend="underline">act</hi> in<lb/> conformity to that belief? In my humble
                opinion it is a<lb/> species of subornation of perjury and the promoter of<lb/>
                deception; Sir! is a man's belief under his own control?<lb/> can he lock up his
                mind? can he close his senses to the<lb/> evidences and power of Reason? the idea of
                pledging<lb/> oneself to any given <hi rend="underline">belief</hi>, appears to be
                such a perfect<lb/> absurdity and is so much at variance with what every<lb/> man, a
                fraction beyond an Idiot in intellect must<lb/> himself have observed of himself,
                that nothing but the<lb/> quintessence of Bigotry could ever have imagined it—<lb/>
                the pledge with respect to action is not quite so absurd;<lb/> but what does it lead
                to? A child is pledged to a certain<lb/> religious practice, with the increase of
                years and experience<lb/> he finds them to be erroneous and of course wishes to<lb/>
                change them; but he remembers his pledge, what then?<lb/> Either he continues to do
                what he <hi rend="underline">believes to be wrong</hi>; or<lb/> he argues upon the
                nonliability to an engagement into</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>which he was forced or betrayed; and he forfeits his pledge.<lb/> If the former, what
                have not his wise teachers to answer for?<lb/> if the latter, what is the value of
                his pledge?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But Sir let us look upon this subject in another<lb/> point of view
                free form speculation and founded upon<lb/> facts either having occurred or likely
                to occur. The<lb/> Communicant is under his pledge bound to observe the Laws<lb/> of
                the Decalogue among these is the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> “Remember to keep<lb/> holy
                the <date>Sabbath day</date> &amp;c”, he repeats the imperative command,<lb/> he is
                told that it comes from God himself, that God in whose<lb/> presence he stands, on
                whose holy word his hand is placed,<lb/> he then repeats the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                command “Honor thy father and thy<lb/> mother”, that father's hand is on his head,
                he feels its pressure<lb/> and with it he remembers that that father openly and
                    <sic>wilfully</sic><lb/> infringes the command which he brings him there to<lb/>
                pledge himself to observe! the father is a <date>Sabbath</date> breaker!!<lb/> what
                a solemn mockery is not this!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Mr Editor, numberless are the reflections which<lb/> press on my
                mind at this moment; yet I dare not<lb/> impose upon your indulgence in giving vent
                to them, But<lb/> permit me a few words more; I shall be brief. This<lb/>
                <placeName>Island</placeName> you know is one of the Colonies of
                    <placeName>Denmark</placeName>; under<lb/> the benevolent protection of its late
                and present Sovereigns,<lb/> the Jews here have enjoyed not only a free toleration
                of<lb/> their religion but their congregation has been endowed<lb/> with special and
                valuable privileges; they prospered under<lb/> them; their worship was upheld; and
                notwithstanding the<lb/> regulations under which their coreligionists of
                    <placeName>Denmark</placeName><lb/> were governed, they were free to govern
                themselves; But the<lb/> spirit of absolutism and Bigotry could not let “well<lb/>
                enough” alone, it must control men's consciences; there<lb/> was too much freedom of
                action, too much liberty of thought.<lb/> In the year <date>1814</date> an ordinance
                of the <persName>King</persName> had provided<lb/> for the religious education of
                the Jews in <placeName>Denmark</placeName> and<lb/> in order to enforce it, it was
                ordained that the children<lb/> at 14 years of age should undergo an examination
                and</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>“depose their Religion” and make a promise “never with their<lb/> free will to act
                contrary to the principles which they<lb/> acknowledged” under the <hi
                    rend="underline">penalty</hi> of not being permitted<lb/> “to <hi
                    rend="underline">make oath</hi>, to <hi rend="underline">enter into
                    marriage</hi>, to <hi rend="underline">enter as journeymen</hi><lb/> “<hi
                    rend="underline">in any corporation</hi>, to be <hi rend="underline">made
                    Burghers in any town</hi>, to<lb/> “<hi rend="underline">keep any trade</hi>, to
                    <hi rend="underline">enter among the students</hi>, or to <hi rend="underline"
                    >be their</hi><lb/> “<hi rend="underline">own guardians</hi>” all this was
                specially provided, for the<lb/> people of the “Mosaic Communion” residing or such
                as<lb/> might hereafter be permitted to reside in <hi rend="underline"
                        ><placeName>Denmark</placeName></hi>., well<lb/> Sir! nothing of this was
                ever applied or intended for the<lb/> Jews of this place, they enjoyed their civil
                and religious<lb/> rights to the fullest extent; what think you then of the<lb/>
                fatuity of the men who could seek to disturb so happy<lb/> a state of things? what
                think you of the Individuals<lb/> who could apply to the Colonial Government for
                permission<lb/> to enforce the regulations alluded to upon their
                coreligionists,<lb/> residents of this <placeName>island</placeName> to enslave
                their consciences! to make the <del>employment</del> enjoyment<lb/> of their civil
                rights dependent upon a pledge to shackle<lb/> the freedom of thought and of
                religious conviction!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Can it be that these men are the descendants of the<lb/> people who
                for ages have endured persecutions and obloquy<lb/> without surrendering an Iota of
                their right to worship<lb/> God after the dictates of their own Hearts? They are
                so,<lb/> they are Jews who have done this deed, strange<lb/> inconsistency! the
                persecuted whilst yet groaning<lb/> under the effects of persecution seek themselves
                to be<lb/>
                <sic>persecuters</sic>!! but Sir they say their intention is<lb/> good, they fear
                that without some restraint of this<lb/> kind the Jewish religion will be lost, that
                there have<lb/> been a few <sic>seceders</sic> and there might be more—and is<lb/>
                it so? is the Jewish religion so weak a fabric as to<lb/> be held together with
                chains and cords? is its foundation<lb/> gone? has the Glory departed from
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">These men add insult to injury; Sir you are<lb/> one of the watchmen
                on the outer tower; to you I<lb/> appeal for a warning, tell these men that in
                seeking</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to uphold that they destroy; tell them that the Great <add>?</add><lb/> of the
                Universe has given to man free will to choose<lb/> between good and evil, let them
                not pretend to be<lb/> wiser than their Creator.</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours in the Faith</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <hi rend="underline">
                    <persName role="author">a descendant of <placeName>Israel</placeName></persName>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">L. P.</persName>
            </p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Note By the Editor</hi>. Our valued correspondent, whom we have
                known and esteemed<lb/> for a number of years, wields a stray pen; and though we
                think that he <add>?</add><lb/> highly on all generous minds do when an object of
                interest is presented to them<lb/> still in the <sic>believe</sic> that there is a
                great cause for serious thought upon<lb/> the subjects embraced in his
                communication. Our friend could not have been aware<lb/> when speaking of the
                ceremony of confirmation that we had noticed it already in<lb/> an
                    <date>August</date> number, from information derived from three various
                sources<lb/> who all approved of the new institution, whilst we appended upon
                remarks<lb/> qualifying our assent to the institution thereof we said: “Though so
                much is<lb/> told of this child of modern days, we are for our part not yet
                satisfied of<lb/> its usefulness and though not opposed to its being resorted to,
                however<lb/> might except to some of the details, we have not yet seen enough to
                satisfy<lb/> our own judgment of the propriety of its introduction.” It will thus be
                seen<lb/> that we do not assent to the necessity, and consequently to the propriety
                of<lb/> holding a public religious institution, as has been recommended by some
                of<lb/> our correspondents in common with many others, for readers need not be
                sur-<lb/>prised that we allow others to advocate in our pages what we do not
                think<lb/> either useful or necessary; we have always endeavoured to invite free
                discussion,<lb/> not the least doubting that we too may obtain thereby convictions
                not otherwise attain-<lb/>able. Truth can only gain by discussion; error alone must
                be crouched<lb/> in darkness for fear of exposure. So with the confirmation, we
                permitted its<lb/> advocacy, and will now let others if they think proper discuss it
                according to<lb/> its merits as then on one or the other side. We for our fact, deem
                it a<lb/> harmless thing; but still an innovation upon our ancient customs;<lb/>
                Just in former days knew nothing of it; it is borrowed from the protestants<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName>, if we mistake not, and is akin to the first
                communion among<lb/> the catholics, for which the children are prefaced by a long
                course of study,<lb/> so that they may be able to be cleverly catochind<add>?</add>
                by the examining clergy<lb/> men when the to them important day arrives for their
                    expression<add>?</add> to<lb/> the <hi rend="underline">grace</hi> of the
                church. Christians as our readers know, think the <add>?</add><lb/>king of the bread
                and wine of the communion of the highest importance</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>
                <persName>Revd Isc Leeser</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Editor of the Occident</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
