<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1847-01">January 1847</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1847-01">Shebat 5607</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0005_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0005_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0005_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0005_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>To the Editor of the Occident <hi rend="underline">Education and the
                Ministry</hi></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Rev Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)"><del>?</del>
                <date>Shebat 5607</date>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)"><date>January 1847</date>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Both your articles in No 36 and 46 of your valuable<lb/> Periodical
                I have carefully read and reflected upon. Would<lb/> every American Israelite do so,
                and especially if those who<lb/> form our German Congregations could or would read
                the latter<lb/> article, headed: “Education for the ministry.” in the last number of
                the<lb/> Occident; and if in doing so, they would pay to it that close
                attention<lb/> and just regard, which it truly deserves—then, I am sure, it
                can<lb/>not fail to effect their own good, and to impress on the minds of the<lb/>
                people the dangers to which they are or will be exposed, through the<lb/> snares of
                treacherous minds, false tongues and deceitful hearts<lb/> under the disguise of
                Religion</p>
            <p>But I am sorry to say, in regard to the realization of your plan or<lb/> the
                establishment of a high school I can entertain but faint hopes,<lb/> when I consider
                the little encouragement <del>granted</del> extended at present to established<lb/>
                schools for religious instruction, and the total absence of such in many<lb/> of our
                oldest and wealthiest congregations.—And these, I venture<lb/> to say, are the very
                places, where all the attainments, which a High<lb/> School can promise, could be
                easily obtained, if the people at large,<lb/> particularly the wealthy classes would
                earnestly wish and take<lb/> measures that their children <del>may</del> might know
                of it a little more than the<lb/> chaunting of a Haphtorah or perhaps also the
                translation of a Yigdal.<lb/> Nay, that high respect and earnest desire for the
                knowledge of wisdom,<lb/> that pure energy for the cause of religion which the Law
                commands, and<lb/> you wish to see, I am not able to find it; it appears not to be
                in the minds<lb/> of the people.—And should the generous examples, which
                noble-<lb/>-hearted men have offered to you, arouse others for imitation and give
                success to<lb/> the good cause:—then we must not be too rash in the estimation of
                its good<lb/> results.—No matter how high it be, “when we quit the School, we are
                but<lb/> Schoolboys and no more”—it is (generally speaking) a truth, not
                understood<lb/> by either the youth, or the <sic>publick</sic> at large, but which
                every man of some<lb/> proficiency in any science or art would readily admit; and
                how will then<lb/> that treasure, which is more than all the treasures on earth—“the
                sacred Law”—<lb/> be safe in the hands of an American Schoolboy? <del>?</del>
                who</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>2</p>
            <p>is so little acquainted with living examples of holy and virtuous men<lb/> learned
                    <del>of</del> in the Law, and who perhaps <del>but for</del> except his
                schoolbooks, never yet has<lb/> seen the title of another Hebrew book? And should I
                go too far in<lb/> underrating our American youth, I am surely not too
                scrupulous<lb/> in apprehending that the boys placed on the pulpit will soon
                defy<lb/> the holy lessons of their teachers and their teachers' teachers, and<lb/>
                they might become “Shepherds that cannot understand and<lb/> Pastors” “that destroy
                and scatter the Sheep of the<lb/> pasture.” Let the history of foreigners and
                foreign ministry be a<lb/> warning example to <placeName>America</placeName>. On
                exposing some dangers in the<lb/> nature of your plan, I intend by no means to
                disparage its<lb/> value and import and, but on the contrary, our consciousness of
                such<lb/> dangers, will induce and prepare us to act with the greater caution<lb/>
                and prudence, that we might the better insure good success and<lb/> glorious results
                to the holy cause of Judaism.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My remarks thus far concern the latter pages of your article, and
                are<lb/> anticipated here, because I preferred to answer first to points on the
                substance of<lb/> which we both would easily agree—But what concerns the first pages
                of your<lb/> “Educ. for the ministry” I candidly confess to you, that in reading
                them I<lb/> felt grieved to the bottom of my heart.—To any sincere and religious
                Jewish mind<lb/> it must appear as <del>be</del> a horrible cruelty to see
                persecution, oppression, contempt and scorn<lb/>
                <sic>practised</sic> on men, many of whom the Law of God might call the Pillars of
                Judaism<lb/> in <placeName>America</placeName>!!—We have men in
                    <placeName>America</placeName>, who from their cradle <del>off</del> have been
                brought<lb/> up in piety and learning, men who have “a knowledge of moral
                philosophy, of hebrew<lb/> in all its branches, biblical comments, mishnah, Talmud,
                Jewish history and<lb/> “antiquity, Algebra, French, German, general History and
                Geography”<lb/> and who are “not unacquainted with English Literature and Grammar”
                (or in<lb/> saying this I have made use only of the same order and terms wherewith
                you described<lb/> the studies of a High School) [page A76.] would I make any
                addition instead of “a<lb/> knowledge” on many heads I would have said “Eminence and
                erudition” I would<lb/> have also said, men of logical and sound reasoning and
                argument and of considerable<lb/> experience; and what is <del>the</del> more than
                all, personally known to us for a number of years as<lb/> men who know no disguise,
                who are peaceful virtuous, pure and firm in principle and<lb/> practice of religion,
                strict <del>for</del> as regards themselves and tolerant towards others—There
                are<lb/> also others of whom we would but partly speak in the above terms, and
                perhaps not<lb/> at all apply the latter additions; but after all no more indulgence
                than actually<lb/> occasionally used in <placeName>America</placeName>, might be
                needed in their behalf.—“And where</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3</p>
            <p>can we find these men”?<del>?</del> I have seen them in a “little Grocery,”<lb/> a
                “Slaughterhouse,” a “Coalyard,” a “Tavern,” a “Cigar-or other shop,”<lb/> such and
                the like are the places, whither the <del>worthy</del> men <del>to</del> worthy to
                grow the ministry<lb/> have been pushed back by the Errors of the multitude, and
                ____ — - —!</p>
            <p>“And for God's sake, how is it them possible, that all this be true and be still<lb/>
                inconsistency with your statements about the lamentations of the people<lb/> “of the
                nearly total absence of qualified men for the office of duly educated<lb/> “<hi
                    rend="underline">religious teachers</hi>”?</p>
            <p>“of the great want of intelligent persons, wanted for the ministry,<lb/> “in manner
                that the <hi rend="underline">Word of God</hi> may be <hi rend="underline"
                    >expounded</hi> to the<lb/> “people”? How is it consistent with your saying: “we
                know of<lb/> “no candidates (for <hi rend="underline">religious Teachers</hi>) or
                persons likely to become so<lb/> “to supply new Congregations or to take the place
                of the <hi rend="underline">ministers</hi> now<lb/> “officiating.”?</p>
            <p>Part of my statements I could easily verify to every reader by only referring<lb/>
                him to former volumes of the Occident, and therefore I need not be plainer<lb/>
                about that—and as to your's Sir! I say, So “and <del>tell</del> show my people<lb/>
                “their transgression, and the house of <persName>Jacob</persName> their sins” they
                are<lb/> “speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving from the heart words of<lb/>
                “falsehood” tell them to call things by their right names, to say what<lb/> they
                mean and to mean what they say, and this will <del>dissolve matters and</del><lb/>
                show forth the truth.— “A man whose voice pleases, or one whose speech suits<lb/>
                his publick” is, with few exceptions, the general definition of Jewish ministry in<lb/>
                <placeName>America</placeName>; and the people would rarely call a man fit
                    <del>for</del> to be minister, if his<lb/> voice do not please their taste.—Let
                them thus not cry out for want of<lb/> “<hi rend="underline">ministers</hi>” “<hi
                    rend="underline">Religious Teachers</hi>” “men who know <hi rend="underline">to
                    expound</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">the Law of God</hi> to the people” let them not use false words
                and call<lb/> the name of God: “Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy<lb/>
                God in vain”—And only this much we say, but we do neither conjure<lb/> the good
                policy nor dispute the just purpose and beneficial results of having such<lb/>
                officers in large communities, for the people will say, that it confers on them
                a<lb/> signified pleasure, that it arouses their feelings of devotion, and that it
                gives<lb/> solemnity to worship, just at the proper place and time—during the
                service<lb/> in the Synagogue—And to deliver a discourse from the pulpit, will
                that<lb/> really <del>say to</del> be <hi rend="underline">expounding the Law of
                    God</hi>? will it strike the mind and teach it<lb/> “to know wisdom and
                instruction, to understand the words of the wise and<lb/> “their dark sayings”? or
                will it rather strike our senses, deceive our hearts</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>4</p>
            <p>dazzle our eyes, and at the end make us Sin and forget the divine command:<lb/> “ye
                shall not seek after your own hearts and your own eyes”?<lb/> (vis Talmud Berachott
                    <add>?</add> 12) These and more questions one might ask and<lb/> perhaps
                    <persName>Blair's</persName> Rhetorick itself and daily experience might
                argue<lb/> in his favour, but in one word I would answer him: “All depends<lb/> on
                the man,” it will do good from a good man, and in the words of<lb/> the royal
                Psalmist let us say: “Lord, who shall abide in thy tabernacle?<lb/> ....“he that
                walketh uprightly, and worketh righteousness, and<lb/> “speaketh the truth in his
                heart, he that backbiteth not with his<lb/> “tongue, nor <hi rend="underline">doeth
                    evil to his neighbour</hi>, <hi rend="underline">nor taketh up a</hi><lb/> “<hi
                    rend="underline">reproach against his neighbour</hi>—<hi rend="underline">he
                    that honoreth them</hi><lb/> “<hi rend="underline">that fear the Lord</hi>.__.he
                    <hi rend="underline">that not taketh bribery against the</hi><lb/> “<hi
                    rend="underline">innocent</hi>” (Psalm 15.); and if we do not know, or rather
                know the man<lb/> not to be so, we again apply the words of that holy book: “But
                unto<lb/> “the wicked God saith, what hast thou to do to declare my<lb/> “statutes,
                then givest thy mouth to evil, and thy tongue frameth<lb/> „deceit.” (Psalm 50. 16,
                19.)</p>
            <p>Thus the more I consider and reflect upon the state of Judaism amongst<lb/> us, the
                more I am convinced, that something must be done for the<lb/> good, some remedy must
                be sought for; independent therefore of your<lb/> plan, I offer you herewith my
                suggestions, which at once may form<lb/> the conclusion of this letter.__In my
                estimation this evil, and<lb/> some others say in the organization of the
                Congregations, (<add>?</add>wel here<lb/> as in other countries perhaps, but I
                merely speak of <placeName>America</placeName>) and that is the<lb/> quarter the
                remedy must come from.—Instead of that prejudicial show<lb/> of superiority and
                empty domination, which creates favorite <add>?</add><lb/> and supports men in
                indolence <del>and wantonness, instead of that</del> let us in future promote<lb/>
                and elevate religion and virtue, <del>study,</del> learning and talent—To be<lb/>
                plainer on the subject: Let every Congregation, newly to be formed, abolish<lb/> the
                office of Shamas (Sexton) as an office of the Congregation; but let all its
                lower<lb/> duties, including those <del>of attending</del> required during service,
                be done for real on able wages<lb/> by a suitable person hired or appointed by the
                trustees as a messenger. <del>or</del><lb/>
                <del>carrier</del>—And should there be any thing <del>be</del> that belongs to
                ceremony or decorum<lb/> during service, any honorable member or trustee might be
                expected voluntarily<lb/> to act for the benefit of the community, and in this way
                saving part of the<lb/> salary, rent, collection and other revenues of that office,
                a Congregation<lb/> will be enabled to have two clerical officers, let them both me
                ministers<lb/> or Elders, and if the one be more able to <del>the</del> gratify
                    <del>cation</del> of the members and the<lb/> solemnity of the service by his
                agreeable voice, let the other be more to <del>?</del> superintend our
                children's<lb/> instruction <del>and edification</del> and to add to the
                edifications of the adults; for I wish the one and the other to be religious
                teachers not<lb/> merely Schoolmasters. From my observations communicated to
                you<lb/> it might be inferred that we will find in this country suitable men
                qualified in English<lb/> for that station, let us then place worthy men in
                    <del>worthy</del> places worthy of them and we might<lb/>
                <del>also</del> expect them to become after a time <del>at once</del> also good
                pulpit orators <del>on the pulpit</del> in<lb/> places where the public might wish
                for it. Again by engaging a number</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
