<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">B. E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">B. E.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>London, United Kingdom</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1844-03">28 March 1844</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0003_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>To The Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Reverend Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Having read the <persName>Rev. Mr Carillon's</persName><lb/> letter
                addressed to you in the Occident No 11. I beg leave through your<lb/> valuable
                columns respectfully to ask the Rev gentleman how<lb/> he reconciles the celebration
                of the double festivals with his<lb/> condemnation of <hi rend="underline">human
                    laws</hi>, when added to the divine<lb/> code? These are <persName>Mr
                    Carillon's</persName> words “God forbid that any<lb/> Jews should commit
                rebellion against the God of our fathers„<lb/> by adding human laws, to the divine,
                pure and perfect code &amp;c<lb/> Now in reference to some of our festivals, it is
                enjoined that<lb/> the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> and <hi rend="underline"
                    >seventh</hi> day be holy convocations: is it not then<lb/> to fly in the very
                face of this divine command to add, <hi rend="underline">voluntarily</hi><lb/> to
                these two days, a <hi rend="underline">second</hi> and an <hi rend="underline"
                    >eighth</hi> day? is it not an open<lb/> violation of the precept
                    <add>Hebrew</add> “Thou shalt neither<lb/> add to nor diminish from it [the
                law]</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is worthy remark, that from the observance of<lb/> these double
                festivals we give utterance in our prayers to expressions<lb/> both untrue and
                contradictory. For instance, one of these interpolated<lb/> festivals
                    (<add>Hebrew</add>) kept on a <hi rend="underline">ninth</hi> day, we, in our
                solemn prayer,<lb/> call <add>Hebrew</add> (“This <date><hi rend="underline"
                        >eighth</hi> day of solemn assembly</date> Again;<lb/> on the second day of
                    <add>Hebrew</add> (<date>new year</date>) we repeat <add>Hebrew</add> (“The<lb/>
                world was brought into existence <hi rend="underline">this</hi> day) which cannot be
                predicated<lb/> of <hi rend="underline">both</hi> days, for one is evidently a
                negation of the other. But much<lb/> more objectionable is that highly
                    <sic>irreverend</sic> disregard of holy truth,<lb/> which, on the double
                festivals—additions made by <hi rend="underline">mortal man</hi>—<lb/> proclaims
                    <add>Hebrew</add> (“These are the festivals of the Lord,<lb/> holy
                convocations”). Now as all these double festivals, including <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                are confessedly<hi rend="underline"> “human laws,”</hi> called by
                    <persName>Maimonides</persName>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> (words or institutions of the scribes) I would then
                respectfully ask<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Carrillon</persName> in the name of that holy religion we both
                reverence,<lb/> whether these <hi rend="underline">human</hi> ordinances, added to
                the “divine code” do not<lb/> come under the category of the sins he so emphatically
                denounces?<lb/> Antiquity of custom, in the present case, is unentitled to the
                slightest<lb/> weight, because, this custom, the offspring of sheer necessity with
                which<lb/> it should have ceased, is a positive transgression of God's law. Let
                it<lb/> be imagined that necessity had compelled our ancestors to diminish<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">from</hi> instead of adding <hi rend="underline">to</hi> the
                divine code—had compelled them to<lb/> keep only six instead of seven days
                    <date>Passover</date>; would future generations<lb/> of Jews, in the supposed
                cases, be justified by veneration of antiquity<lb/> to continue to sin voluntarily,
                because their ancestors had thus acted<lb/> from compulsion? “No” replies Holy Writ
                “Thou shalt neither<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">add</hi> to nor diminish <hi rend="underline">from</hi> the
                law” Should it be asked in case<lb/> of the abolition of the second day
                    <add>Hebrew</add> what is to be done</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>when the <date>first day of Tishri</date> falls upon the <date>Sabbath</date> I
                answer, <hi rend="underline">Obey</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">God</hi> and blow the <add>Hebrew</add> as
                    <persName>Joshua</persName> did [Chap 6] for it were impious to<lb/> suppose
                that wrong, which God commands and this command is as<lb/> irrespective of place and
                time as that of circumcision so frequently performed<lb/> on the
                    <date>Sabbath</date>; <hi rend="underline">in fact, no tyranny of custom, it
                    matters not how old, can</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">make void the word of the living God</hi></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">These double festivals, with the exception of
                *<add>Hebrew</add><lb/> (and even that festival was not always kept two days) were
                never observed<lb/> in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, simply because its
                inhabitants had no doubt as to the<lb/> precise days on which the three festivals
                    (<add>Hebrew</add>) were to be celebrated<lb/> and this example, one would think
                should be an all-sufficient reason<lb/> with modern Jews, who possess an unerring
                calendar to abolish the<lb/> Custom</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">From the observations of <persName>Maimonides</persName> on this
                subject in his<lb/> Yad Hachazaka (in Hilch Kidd Hachodesh and Hilch Yom Tob)<lb/>
                it may be legitimately inferred that our great talmudical teacher<lb/> himself, when
                he abstracts from the then state of things de facto, and<lb/> addresses himself to
                the question de jure, is no advocate for the perpetuity<lb/> of these supplemental
                days. <persName>Maimonides</persName> not only calls the institution<lb/> of them
                    a—<add>Hebrew</add>—<hi rend="underline">a fashion</hi> (“Our celebration of the
                second day of these<lb/> festivals is a <hi rend="underline">fashion</hi> introduced
                by the sayings of the scribes, an<lb/> innovation due to the state of dispersion”
                    <add>?</add> Yom Tob Ch 1 rule 21)<lb/> but he says <hi rend="underline">totidem
                    verbis</hi> that by rights the second day ought to be abolished.<lb/> Here
                follow his words</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">“Now a days when there is no Sanhedrin, and when the Beth Din<lb/>
                of <add>Hebrew</add> follows the actual calculation, it would be just to have only
                    <hi rend="underline">one</hi><lb/> holiday in <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
                places, <hi rend="underline">even in those removed from
                        <placeName>Palestine</placeName></hi>, as well as<lb/> those in
                    <add>Hebrew</add> in as much as they all rely on <hi rend="underline">one</hi>
                calculation”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As the abolition of these supplemental days forms the most<lb/>
                salient point of difference between the Congregation of the <placeName>West<lb/>
                    London</placeName> Synagogue of British Jews and their coreligionists, and as<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Carillon</persName> has introduced several reforms into his own
                synagogue,</p>
            <p>*In those times it was requisite to observe two days <add>Hebrew</add> for the<lb/>
                messengers who were sent out upon the high places to watch the heavens<lb/> for the
                appearance of the new moon might have been impeded<lb/> in their observations by the
                state of the atmosphere and their<lb/> return to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> on
                the <date>thirtieth of Elul</date> been thereby prevented<lb/>; in such case, and
                    <hi rend="underline">not otherwise</hi>, if I rightly understand
                    <persName>Maimonides</persName>,<lb/> two days <add>Hebrew</add> were kept in
                the capital of <add>Hebrew</add>. Further;<lb/> as the feast of <add>Hebrew</add> is
                held on the <date>first day Tishri</date> there would<lb/> have been no opportunity
                to correct any error into which the messen-<lb/>gers might have fallen, if only one
                day had been observed</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I have therefore dwelt the longer on this religiously important subject,<lb/> which I
                now submit to the calm consideration of the reverend<lb/> gentleman</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I trust I shall not trespass too much on the valuable<lb/> and
                impartial pages of the Occident if I take this opportunity to<lb/> set <persName>Mr
                    Carillon</persName> right as to the opinion entertained of the Talmud<lb/> by
                the <persName>Rev D. W. Harks</persName>. Never did this gentleman
                unqualifiedly<lb/> deny its authority or speak disparagingly of the traditions
                contained<lb/> therein; on the contrary, he spake in terms highly eulogistic
                and<lb/> reverential of the authors of that work. He did indeed say that the<lb/>
                Talmud was not so infallible a guide for the Israelites as the “One<lb/> immutable
                Law” contained in Holy Writ, but let these words be taken<lb/> in
                    <sic>connexion</sic> with the antecedent praise and with the whole
                paragraphs<lb/> of which they form a part and no unprejudiced person, I am<lb/> bold
                to say, will see in them aught that is not religiously true! And<lb/> here to enable
                the reader to judge for himself I subjoin the paragraph<lb/> in question extracted
                from the Discourse delivered in the <placeName>West London</placeName><lb/>
                Synagogue on the day of its consecration (Vide Discourse p 748)</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">“Now let it not be supposed that it is the intention<lb/> of myself,
                or of any member of this Congregation, whose humble<lb/> organ I am, to vilify, in
                any way, the character of the traditional<lb/> records. ON the contrary, we
                recognize in them a valuable aid for the<lb/> elucidation of many passages in
                scripture; we feel proud of them as<lb/> a monument of the zeal and mental activity
                of our ancestors, we<lb/> hold it our duty to reverence the sayings of men who, we
                are convinced,<lb/> would have sacrificed their lives for the maintenance of that
                Law<lb/> which God has vouchsafed to deliver unto us; but we must (as our<lb/>
                conviction urges us) solemnly deny, that a belief in the <hi rend="underline"
                    >divinity</hi> of<lb/> those traditions written in the Mishna and the
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and<lb/> Babylonian Talmuds, is of equal
                obligation to the Israelite with the<lb/> faith in the divinity of the law of
                    <persName>Moses</persName>. WE know that these<lb/> books are human
                compositions; and though we are content to accept<lb/> with reverence from our
                post-biblical ancestors, advice, and instruction,<lb/> we cannot <hi
                    rend="underline">unconditionally</hi> accept their Laws. For Israelites,
                there<lb/> is but one immutable Law the sacred volume of the scriptures<lb/>
                commanded by God to be written down for the unerring guidance of his<lb/> people
                until the end of time”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is not unessential to observe, that even these mild,<lb/>
                measured remarks were not gratuitous, but absolutely called for as the<lb/> Minister
                was then addressing his Congregation for the first time<lb/> after himself and they
                had been excommunicated under the charge<lb/> (<hi rend="underline">utterly
                    groundless by the bye</hi>) of having denied the divinity of the Oral<lb/>
                Law...I hope I do not offend <persName>Mr Carillon</persName> by supposing that
                he</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>under parallel circumstances, would not have expressed himself more<lb/> respectfully
                of the Talmud than his brother Minister spoke of it</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am most anxious to avail myself of the present opportunity<lb/> to
                inform <persName>Mr Henry Goldsmith</persName>, that the charge (Occident No 8) he
                has<lb/> brought against the members of the <placeName>Burton Street</placeName>
                Synagogue of having<lb/> repudiated the wearing of Tephilin is wholly devoid of
                truth. I<lb/> unhesitatingly acquit <persName>Mr Goldsmith</persName> of
                    <sic>wilful</sic> misrepresentation and<lb/> refer him to the first volume No 12
                of the Voice of Jacob page 89 where<lb/> he will find that a “<hi rend="underline"
                    >rumour</hi>” had reached its editor that the “Secession<lb/> Congregation” had
                determined by a majority of two in <hi rend="underline">favor of</hi> not against,
                the wearing of <add>Hebrew</add> The following note from the Editor shows that
                there<lb/> was not a scintilla of truth even in the above “rumour” hence I trust<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Goldsmith</persName> will in future, exercise a little wholesome
                    <sic>scepticism</sic> (not<lb/> inaptly called one of the nerves of wisdom) when
                reports again reach him<lb/> as to the proceedings of the <placeName>Burton
                    Street</placeName> Synagogue. The Editor's note<lb/> alluded to is as follows
                “This rumour referred to the obligation of<lb/> wearing <add>Hebrew</add>. After we
                had gone to press, an authorized explanation<lb/> reached us, that this particular
                question was not put to the vote. It was, on the<lb/> contrary, an understanding,
                that the <add>Hebrew</add> should be worn during<lb/> the service of every day on
                which they were worn in the established synagogues.<lb/> On the morning of
                    <add>Hebrew</add> those who could not conscientiously comply with<lb/> this
                understanding were absent from service”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I return to the subject of the double festivals as<lb/> I wish to
                observe before I conclude that if I had supposed Talmudic<lb/> knowledge essential
                to the proper understanding of the question at<lb/> issue, then, most assuredly, I
                had not been so presumptuous as to discuss<lb/> a matter so transcendently
                important, but, I rely with some confidence<lb/> on arguments, which, seem to me, to
                rest on the force of truth, the energy<lb/> of common sense and upon the
                all-sustaining pillars of Holy Writ</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Reverend Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">Yours very respectfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">
                <persName role="author">B. E.</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <placeName>Upper Beaford Place</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Russell Square</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
                <date>March 28th 1844</date>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
