<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">O.</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>Box 1, FF5</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF5_1</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">O.</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="unk" accepted="unk"></addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>London, United Kingdom</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1847-1" source="" attested="yes">3 January 1847</dateLet>
              <dateLet when="1847-1" source="" attested="yes">January 5607</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f5_0001_1r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f5_0001_1v.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f5_0001_2r.jpg"/>
					<graphic url="ilcajs_b1f5_0001_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item>Freemasons</item>
              <item>Politics Great Britain</item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
		<text>
		<body>
		<pb n="1"/>
		
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>London</placeName>&#59; <date>3 Jany 1847 &#40;5607&#41;</date></p>
			<p><persName>Sir Moses Montefire</persName> has consented to sit for his portrait in compliance<lb/> with a requisition from the Portuguese Elders <sic>conserning</sic> which I informed<lb/> you in my last.  <persName>Sir Hart Esqr</persName> R A&#44; a Jewish painter&#44; who has<lb/> raised himself to considerable distinction by his numerous successful per&#45;<lb/>formances has been very appropriately selected as artist for this under&#45;<lb/>taking.&#8211;A similar compliment to <persName>Lady Montefire</persName> has been<lb/> suggested in recognition of the eminent share which she is known to<lb/> have taken in all the noble enterprises of her distinguished partner<lb/> In the last No but one of the &#34;Voice of <persName>Jacob</persName>&#34; this subject has been ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;gued very warmly.  but I do not learn as yet that it has been<lb/> &#45;suitably responded to by the Jewish public generally.&#8211;</p>
			<p>Her Majesty has been pleased to confer the title of Baronet on<lb/> another eminent member of our faith&#44; the <persName>Baron Anthony de Roth&#45;</persName><lb/><persName>schild</persName> as announced a few days ago in the official Gazette<lb/>&#8211;A Metropolitan Evening journal announces the name of the<lb/> <persName>Baron Lionel de Rothschild</persName> among the list of liberal candi&#45;<lb/>dates for the next general election for the city.  I am not aware<lb/> if this announcement has any foundation in truth&#44; &#40;it has not<lb/> been as yet contradicted&#41;&#44; but as it is contemplated to make a<lb/> [&#63;] movement in favor of the complete emancipation of the<lb/> Jews of this country&#44; there is little doubt but that <del>&#63;</del><lb/> this great city will take the initiative in the [&#63;]<lb/> of so important a question.&#8211;<del>the consessions to Jewish political</del><lb/> The &#34;removal of the Jew&#39;s disabilities bill&#34; which was passed in<lb/> the last session has already led to the election of a Jewish citizen<lb/> of <placeName>London</placeName>.&#44; <persName>B Phillips Esqr</persName> of <placeName>Newgate St.</placeName> to the municipal office<lb/> of Common Councilman for one of the most extensive and pop&#45;<lb/>ulous wards of the city&#44; this gentleman who is much and deserved&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly respected obtained his appointment by a very large majority.  The fact that this is<lb/> <del>being</del> the first Jew returned to a municipal<lb/> office in this city renders the circumstance one of great interest<lb/> and importance to both Jew &amp; Christian.</p>
			<p>The <placeName>West London</placeName> synagogue of British Jews in <placeName>Burten St</placeName><lb/> has at length been recognized as a religious</p>

		<pb n="2"/>
		
			<p>place of worship&#44; and is now therefore duly registered <del>&#63;</del><lb/> as a building wherein marriages can in future be legally solemnized<lb/> The following very interesting extracts are taken from<lb/> a number of the &#34;Free Mason&#39;s Quarterly review&#34; being part of a<lb/> letter from the <persName>Rt Hon the Earl of Zetland</persName> Grand<lb/> Master of the Freemasons of <placeName>Great Britain</placeName> to the Grand Master<lb/> of <placeName>Prussia</placeName>&#44; on account of the Jewish Free masons being excluded from<lb/> visiting any of the Lodges in that country notwithstanding they<lb/> may be possessed of authentic certificates from the Grand Lodge<lb/> of <placeName>England</placeName>&#8211;&#34;the letter proceeds to say&#8211;&#34;The M W. Grand<lb/> Master of <placeName>England</placeName> the <persName>Rt Hon the Earl of Zetland</persName>&#44; received with<lb/> the deepest feelings of grief the reply made by the R W brother <persName>Bier</persName><lb/> the Grand secretary&#44; on behalf of the Grand L R Y of friendship<lb/> <placeName>Berlin</placeName> to the communications of his Lordship of the <date>15th Decb</date> last in<lb/> as much as that reply announces&#44; that by the existing laws of the Gr L R Y<lb/> of <placeName>Prussia</placeName> none but Christians and duly legitimated brethren of recognized<lb/> Lodges are allowed access to the labors&#8211;To this law&#44; it appears that<lb/> all subordinate Lodges are bound to confirm&#44; and to include as visitation<lb/> brethren of the Jewish faith&#44; notwithstanding such brothers may take with<lb/> them the certificate of the G L of <placeName>England</placeName>&#44; and be in every respect&#44; as<lb/> to character unenceptimable[&#63;]&#59; the religious creed being alone the ground<lb/> of refusal.  The G L of <placeName>England</placeName>&#44; by the earliest history and tradition<lb/> [&#63;] always declared and observed the universality of Freemasonry&#44; ma<lb/>&#45;king no distinctions or exclusions on the score of religious faith&#44; a matter<lb/> into which she never enquires&#44; beyond the point in which all men<lb/> agree.  It is for this reason that she does not sanction or <sic>recognise</sic> meeting<lb/> which in some places are holden by assemblies of particular religionists.<lb/>  With these the G L of <placeName>E</placeName> does not interfere but she strictly guards by<lb/> her laws and her practice against the introduction into her lodges<lb/> of any emblems or decorations which are indicative of particular creeds<lb/> deeming them liable to be taken as offensive demonstrations at variance<lb/> with the true spirit of Free Masonry x x x But when members<lb/> of English Lodges&#44; lawfully admitted and bearing diplomas from the<lb/> Gr Lodge of <placeName>England</placeName> duly authenticated under her &#40;[&#41;seal are not<lb/> recognised and on the contrary are rejected merely on account of their<lb/> particular faith&#44; it becomes the imperative duly of the Gr Master<lb/> to vindicate the nights the honor and the integrity of the body</p>

		<pb n="3"/>
		
			<p>over which he has been called to preside whose branches extend to every quarter<lb/> of the habitable globe.&#8211;In the discharge of that duty then the grand<lb/> Master of <placeName>England</placeName> protest against the refusal which  has been made<lb/> to acknowledge the legitimate children of a lawfully constituted En&#45;<lb/>glish Lodge.  and at the same time is constrained to recall from his<lb/> post the R W mother the <persName>Chev Esser</persName> as the representative of <placeName>England</placeName> in<lb/> the G L R Y of <placeName>Russia</placeName> at <placeName>Berlin</placeName> x x x x x x The Grand Master com&#45;<lb/>mands me to add that he has communicated to the G L the<lb/> sentiments here conveyed&#44; as well as the cause he felt compelled to<lb/> adopt and that the G L with one record declared its full accents<lb/> x x x x x he laments the occurrences which for a time&#44; unfortu&#45;<lb/>nately impede the wanted intercourse x x x x dated <placeName>London</placeName> <date>4 Sept 1846</date><lb/> &#40;[&#41;The periodical from which the above is extracted among other very liberal<lb/> and pertinent remarks in this noble letter and the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> reply<lb/> observes &#34;The letter itself&#34; &#40;meaning the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> reply&#41; &#34;occupying 4 <sic>Loges</sic> is<lb/> not worth recording and we have no wish to <del>plase upon record that it</del> promulgate so<lb/> unmasonic a <del>record</del> document&#44; nor do we wish to place upon record<lb/> that which we know the Prussian Freemasons are ashamed of &#34;x x x x<lb/> In the meantime it it affords us great pleasure to be able to state<lb/> that the members of the Pilgrim Lodge of <placeName>London</placeName> No 289 which works<lb/> in the German Language and of which the late Prussian representative<lb/> brother <persName>Hebeler</persName> was master have since the publicity given to the anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;masonic Prussian doctrine altered their mode of initiation and do not<lb/> now compel the candidate to make a declaration of his religion<lb/> previously to his being admitted&#44; we were surprised at its not being<lb/> altered before&#44; considering the immediate P G R of <placeName>England</placeName> is a mem&#45;<lb/>ber of the Lodge.&#8211;The Most Worshipful Master&#39;s determined conduct<lb/> has already produced a good effect.  All honor to him&#44; as well as to<lb/> brother <persName>Henry Faudel</persName> the stalwart champion of the Jewish Free&#45;<lb/>masons&#34;&#8211;&#40;[&#41;It is proper to add that this gentleman&#44; &#40;<persName>Henry Faudel</persName>&#41;<lb/> is himself a Jew partner &amp; brotherinlaw to <del>the</del> <persName>Mr B Phillips</persName> the<lb/> recently elected common Council man of whose appointment I have<lb/> furnished you with an account above.  <del>The</del></p>
			<p>The Great Synagogue Dukes place has had the liberality and good<lb/> taste to vote <del>the &#63;</del> an increase of <del>the</del> salary<lb/> to the Chief Rabbi&#44; &amp; the other German synagogues are expected to<lb/> contribute in their due proportions.&#8211;It is proposed also to augment</p>

		<pb n="4"/>
		
			<p>the present inadequate stipends of the Dayanim who considering<lb/> the dignity and importance of their respective duties have hitherto&#8211;<lb/>been but very indifferently hard.&#8211;The &#34;Jewish Chronicle&#34; gives<lb/> a very ample and interesting report of an <del>very</del> important meeting<lb/> held at Liverpool to celebrate the anniversary of the &#34;Hebrew Phil<lb/>anthropic Society&#34; at which some very eloquent speeches men made<lb/> on the subject of Jewish Emancipation by the <persName>Revd Dr Raphael</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Birmingham</placeName>&#44; <persName>H I Atkinson Esquire</persName> an eminent Barrister &amp; several<lb/> other distinguished Jews &amp; Christians.  the great length to which I<lb/> have already entered this communication precludes the possible<lb/> of my making any extract but as I presume you regularly re&#45;<lb/>ceive the Anglo Jewish periodicals I beg to call your attention<lb/> to this report as contained in the &#34;Jewish Chronicle.&#34;&#8211;</p>
			<p>The committee of the Jews &amp; General Literary &amp; Scientific Institution<lb/> have put forth a very tempting programme for their anniversary<lb/> fete which will come off on the 20th Inst.  I shall endeavour<lb/> to give you some account of it in my next.  The Portuguese<lb/> Beth Holim Hospital Ball will take place the night succeeding<lb/> they are both deserving objects&#8211;and will I trust meet with the<lb/> best encouragement.&#8211;This is also the season for holiding<lb/> the anniversaries of several other Jewish Institutions namely<lb/> the Blind Asylum&#44; Infant School &amp; Orphan Asylum each<lb/> of which is celebrated by a grand Public Ball.&#8211;I shall refer<lb/> more particularly to some of these Charities in my future cor&#45;<lb/>respondence <del>also</del>.</p>
		  <p rend="indent(11)"><persName role="author">O.</persName></p>
		  
		  <div>
		    <p><ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_4_10.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume 4 No. 10 pages 515 through 516. Click here to view.</ref></p>
		  </div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>