<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF3_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola,
                            Abraham</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, I.,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Montreal, Canada</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1856-06">22 June 1856</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1856-06">22 June 5616</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0020_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0020_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f3_0020_2r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Montreal</placeName>
                <date>22 June 5616</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Rev. I. Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Dear sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">You will think I have quite forgotten your favor<lb/> of <date>5<hi
                        rend="sup">th</hi></date> inst. which I received the day after
                    <add>שבועות</add>, but however<lb/> improbable it may appear to you, I have not
                had a minute<lb/> for letter writing since the holy days. You know I teach<lb/> the
                children Hebrew, and the number has greatly increased-<lb/>-but you do not wish to
                know how I have been employed</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You need not thank me for the almost nothing<lb/> I have done, &amp;
                would do for any one under the same circumstances.<lb/> The two Daily Prayers sent
                will I presume soon go, but<lb/> not the Catechisms. If I am to collect the
                amounts<lb/> due you for Bibles &amp;c you had better enclose me a slip<lb/> which
                you can send with the next Occidents, something<lb/> in this form. I hereby request
                &amp; <sic>authorise</sic>
                <persName>NDS</persName> to<lb/> collect <add>?</add> It is useless to refer in this
                again to what<lb/> has so long passed, but I am not the only one who<lb/> thinks I
                had cause to be disappointed in your<lb/> course towards me. You stated in the
                Occident I had done you<lb/> wrong. I deny this as emphatically now as ever<lb/> My
                conduct towards you was honest fair and above<lb/> board, although I know you
                conveyed a different</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>impression to mutual friends, upon whom however<lb/> it had no effect. I yet think
                were you to review all<lb/> you would find I had some good grounds for my
                opinion.<lb/> Had matters so turned out with any other than yourself<lb/> I should
                long since have ceased to think of that with<lb/> derision and contempt; but it was
                a hard thing to be<lb/> branded as something mean and vile by one whose good<lb/>
                opinion had ever been so prized by me, and which had<lb/> ever been so flattering. I
                always am prepared to admit<lb/> that misrepresentation, antagonism &amp; jealousy
                of you<lb/> were rife, but I deny before my maker that these<lb/> feelings ever
                actuated me; that I did or said anything<lb/> that after the best reflection I
                thought calculated to<lb/> injure you or your chances of re-election on your<lb/>
                own terms, or that I ever had any feelings towards<lb/> you but of respect &amp;
                esteem. You will never<lb/> know how, even since the appointment of your<lb/>
                succession to office, I have been invited from <hi rend="underline">other</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">quarters than <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></hi> (let me
                add this, for I<lb/> would not wish you even to suppose for a minute<lb/> that your
                successor was one) to engage, humble as<lb/> my position is, in various things which
                could only<lb/> be injurious to you. I do not desire to embitter<lb/> your
                intercourse with those men in office with<lb/> whom you must even if occasionally
                only come<lb/> in contact, but I have convincing proof of</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>my having been <del>charged</del> deemed guilty of insincerity by you<lb/> without
                cause. I at one moment was on the point of<lb/> showing you this, but second &amp;
                better thoughts came.<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">You had already publicly pronounced your opinion</hi>,
                though<lb/> as a sincere friend you had no right to condemn me<lb/> so quickly &amp;
                unheard, <add>שמוע דין אחיכם</add>, and <add>הוכח תוכיח</add> you<lb/> had
                forgotten. When a line from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> would have<lb/>
                settled all, your dignity would not permit you to realize<lb/> that if there is
                    <add>עת לחשות לחכות</add> there is also <add>עת לדבר</add>. I had<lb/> never
                thought to have written, at least not to day<lb/> on this subject, one so fruitless
                of result, as it necessarily<lb/> must be, but as it is written it must go.
                Perhaps<lb/> were we living in the same city, some good result<lb/> might be arrived
                at. At present I think of <add>הצועק על מה שעבר וגוער</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Had I had time I would have written you before<lb/> to tell you of
                my fathers having informed me a few weeks<lb/> since of your <add>?</add> to him
                about the Prayer Books.<lb/> He writes me he would address you by the same
                packet<lb/> so you will learn from himself the reasons for declining<lb/> I would
                have told you myself of his going on as far as<lb/> his third vol. The first has
                been for some time<lb/> in <placeName>Montreal</placeName>, &amp; last
                    <date>August</date> I saw it in <placeName>New York</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Apropos des <hi rend="underline">bottes</hi>, what else but an
                obstructive<lb/> policy did you expect there, unless a little or small policy<lb/> I
                hope the <add>דרשן</add> may find not duly <del>find</del> a field of<lb/>
                usefulness sans obstructions but also a bed of roses<lb/>-not <add>שושנה בן
                    החוחים</add>-though I feel disposed sagely<lb/> to shake my head &amp; say I
                have my doubts.</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">I remain yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">
                <persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
