<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>[no title given]</title>
          <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Lyon, Rob.</author>
          <editor></editor>
          <sponsor></sponsor>
          <funder></funder>
          <principal></principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp></resp>
            <name></name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <p>Not part of a series</p>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <note></note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <biblStruct>
            <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
            <monogr>
              <imprint>
                <dateLet></dateLet>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <region>PA</region>
              <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
              <institution></institution>
              <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
              <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
              <idno>LSDCBx1FF7_24</idno>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
              <msName></msName>
            </msIdentifier>
            <head></head>
            <letHeading>
              <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Lyon, Rob.</author>
              <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac, Rev.</addressee>
              <deliverer></deliverer>
              <respStmt>
                <resp></resp>
                <name></name>
              </respStmt>
              <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
              <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
              <dateLet when="1850-09" source="" attested="yes">25 September 1850</dateLet>
            </letHeading>
            <msContents>
              <msItem>
                <author></author>
                <editor></editor>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp></resp>
                  <name></name>
                </respStmt>
                <title></title>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
                <listBibl>
                  <bibl></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <filiation></filiation>
                <textLang></textLang>
                <figure>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0024_1r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0024_1v.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0024_2r.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="ilcajs_b1f7_0024_2v.jpg"/>
                </figure>
              </msItem>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <supportDesc>
                  <support>
                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
                  </support>
                  <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
                    <dimensions></dimensions>
                  </extent>
                  <foliation></foliation>
                  <collation></collation>
                  <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                  <layout></layout>
                </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              <handDesc script="manuscript">
                  <handNote></handNote>
              </handDesc>
              <decoDesc>
                <decoNote></decoNote>
              </decoDesc>
              <additions></additions>
              <bindingDesc>
                <binding>
                  <decoNote></decoNote>
                </binding>
              </bindingDesc>
              <sealDesc>
                <seal>
                  <p></p>
                </seal>
              </sealDesc>
              <accMat></accMat>
              <envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
            </physDesc>
            <history>
              <origin></origin>
              <provenance></provenance>
              <acquisition></acquisition>
            </history>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <recordHist>
                  <source></source>
                  <change></change>
                </recordHist>
                <availability status="free">
                  <p>Unrestricted</p>
                </availability>
                <custodialHist>
                  <custEvent></custEvent>
                </custodialHist>
              </adminInfo>
              <surrogates></surrogates>
              <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </additional>
            <msPart>
              <altIdentifier>
                <idno></idno>
              </altIdentifier>
            </msPart>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p></p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p></p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
          <correction>
            <p></p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p></p>
          </normalization>
          <quotation>
            <p></p>
          </quotation>
          <hyphenation>
            <p></p>
          </hyphenation>
          <segmentation>
            <p></p>
          </segmentation>
          <stdVals>
            <p></p>
          </stdVals>
          <interpretation>
            <p></p>
          </interpretation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
          <rendition></rendition>
          <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
          </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit=""/>
        </refsDecl>
        <classDecl>
          <taxonomy>
            <category>
              <catDesc></catDesc>
            </category>
          </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <appInfo>
          <application ident="" version="">
            <desc></desc>
            <label></label>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <creation></creation>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <textClass>
          <keywords scheme="unknown">
            <list>
              <item></item>
              <item></item>
            </list>
          </keywords>
          <classCode scheme=""></classCode>
          <catRef/>
        </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change></change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
      
		<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>140 Nassau St New York</placeName></p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><date>25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Sepr 1850</date></p>
			<p>The <addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
          <p rend="indent(4)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
          <p rend="indent(2)">In reply to yours of the <date>19<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> instant&#44; I find the explanation<lb/> you have given of the observations which appeared in the <date>Sepr.</date> number of<lb/> the Occident totally unsatisfactory you say&#58;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">&#8220;In regard to your inquiry about the <add>&#63;</add> of the Asmonean&#44; I have to<lb/> tell you frankly that if it is true that you charged the people at<lb/> <placeName>Albany</placeName> ten dollars for inserting a reply to <persName>Mr Spanier</persName> and then<lb/> refuse doing it nevertheless&#44; it does not look well&#44; and this<lb/> is what they asked me to print&#44; together with some reflections<lb/> which I thought it not <del>to</del> my business to make public. My<lb/> correspondent writes &#34; The Asmonean was directed to insert it and<lb/> answered in a letter in our possession now to give it insertion as<lb/> an Editorial for ten dollars. But one day after this the Asmonean<lb/> came out with an abusive language and its wise editorial remarks.&#8221;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">Now for the life of me&#44; I cannot discern form this statement<lb/> whether the people at <placeName>Albany</placeName> say&#44; or you believe&#44; that I charged<lb/> them ten dollars under <sic>pretence</sic> of giving insertion to what you<lb/> now call a <hi rend="underline">reply</hi> to <persName>Mr Spanier</persName> and that I afterwards refused to<lb/> print it notwithstanding they had so paid for it. Inexplicable<lb/> as is your letter to me&#44; your statement in the Occident assumed<lb/> the truth&#44; without your having troubled yourself to test your<lb/> correspondents veracity. However let us look at the facts.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">After having refused to notice the <placeName>Albany</placeName> quarrel or to side<lb/> with either party&#44; the Asmonean of <date>July the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> published the</p>
		<pb n="2"/>
			<p>card from <persName>Mr. Spanier</persName>&#44; but an early post I was favored with a letter<lb/> enclosing what purported to be a report of a meeting whereat the<lb/> members of the congregation Beth El were present who passed certain<lb/> resolutions therein set forth&#59; the letter requested that I would publish<lb/> the enclosed report. I replied in two ways firstly by letter probably to one<lb/> or two persons referred to&#44; and secondly&#44; in the columns of the Asmonean of<lb/> the <date>26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of July</date>. My letter to <persName>Mr Beckel</persName> stated&#44; &#8220;I must decline giving<lb/> insertion to the report in its present form. Justly I have refused&#39;<lb/> insertion to communications containing personalities against <persName>Dr Wise</persName><lb/> hence I must reject attacks upon the other side Secondly&#44; the whole<lb/> of the <add>&#63;</add> resolutions are couched in language unfit for publication<lb/> and totally inadmissible into the columns of the Asmonean &#8220;x x<lb/> xxxxxxxxxxxxx&#39; The seventh to the twelfth resolution<lb/> with a slight revision of the language would be inserted.&#8221;</p>
			<p>&#8220;Should you see fit to withdraw the objectionable matter and substitute<lb/> that now suggested&#8221; &#8220;the charge for its insertion in the editorial<lb/> columns of the Asmonean will be 12 cents p line and as it<lb/> will num to eighty lines the price would be ten dollars which you will<lb/> please to remit when you forward your instructions <add>&#63;</add> the same&#8221;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">It must be understood that the first six resolutions those to which<lb/> I imperatively refused insertion were a libellous attack upon <persName>Mr Spanier.</persName><lb/> The next resolutions laudatory of <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> and <del>of</del> exposing the meetings<lb/> confidence in him as a Preacher &#38;c I offered to insert upon slightly <add>&#63;</add><lb/> the language &#40;making it english&#41;. And I <add>&#63;</add> the entire report as a<lb/> personal matter&#44; issued for party ends and personal gratification&#59; hence<lb/> it was an advertisement and to be paid for as such.</p>
		<pb n="3"/>
          <p rend="indent(1)">From having been assailed in the pages of the Occident. I desire<lb/> that the same channel should be used to remove the <del>expression</del> aspersion&#44;<lb/> therefore&#44; I furnish you&#44; as its Editor&#44; with the above Extract from my letter<lb/> book requesting that you will in the next number&#44; give place in your<lb/> own name&#44; to a lucid and satisfactory explanation&#44; for you must<lb/> readily perceive&#44; and acknowledge&#44; how indiscreet was the statement&#44;<lb/> and arrogant the assumption expressed by you&#44; when you stated<lb/> &#8220;that the publication of the <add>&#63;</add> of the Editor of the Asmonean would<lb/> injure him&#44; and increase your circulation.&#8221;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">I shall not deign to comment on the evident bad taste which<lb/> induced you&#44; a professor of Divinity&#44; to pen the following &#8220;a charge which<lb/> we do not care <hi rend="underline">just now</hi> to bring down upon us&#8221; the words undeserved<lb/> by me&#44; may possibly have reference to your present hostile position<lb/> with your congregation&#44; or may prospectively regard the forthcoming &#8220;Jewish<lb/> Advocate&#8221; but ere the Editor of the Occident wrote <hi rend="underline">just now</hi> he<lb/> should have recollected&#44; that I&#44; as the Editor of the Asmonean&#44; did<lb/> through its agent at <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> <persName>Mr Michael Allen</persName>&#44; place its columns<lb/> at the service of the <persName>Rev Isaac Leeser</persName> to answer and refute the charges<lb/> of his opponents. And further that I am in possession of two notes<lb/> wherein <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> writes &#8220;that he is greatly obliged to the Editor<lb/> of the Asmonean for his dignified notice of A Review&#59; and in the<lb/> second <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> requests a notice&#44; and remarks &#8220;that he is not<lb/> ungrateful for favors conferred&#8221;</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">It matters little to me&#44; how you act with respect to notices or<lb/> reports&#59; the Asmonean while under my charge will be conducted as<lb/> I deem fit&#44; but if you refer to an editorial of mine published</p>
		<pb n="4"/>
			<p><date>July the fifth</date> you will perceive that I publicly announced that matters<lb/> of public import or general interest would be inserted gratis&#44; but that<lb/> matter for private ends would be subject to charge. However if I do<lb/> see fit sometimes to depart form this rule of the profession&#44; the <placeName>Albany</placeName><lb/> affair was not one to induce me. But this week I shall do so&#44; and<lb/> shall publish gratuitously a series of resolutions laudatory of yourself<lb/> and concerning the Occident. And I do this with the feelings<lb/> that invariably actuate me&#8212;to wit&#8212;a perfect contempt for personal<lb/> <add>&#63;</add>&#44; and a desire to forward everything having a tendency<lb/> to elevate the intellect and humanise the affections of my<lb/> fellow men.</p>
          <p rend="indent(1)">As I am particularly desirous that this matter should<lb/> be entirely cleared up before your next issue of the Occident<lb/> I must press upon you for an early reply stating the course<lb/> you purport taking</p>
          <p rend="indent(8)">I am Dear Sir</p>
          <p rend="indent(9)">yours Respectfully</p>
          <p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">Rob Lyon</persName></p>
          
          <div>
            <p><ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_8_5.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume 8 No. 5 pages 255 through 257. Click here to view.</ref></p>
            <p><ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_8_6.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume 8 No. 6 pages 306 through 312. Click here to view.</ref></p>
          </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>