<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Levin, N.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx9FF14_1</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Levin, N.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1842-06" source="" attested="yes">12 June 1842</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0001_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0001_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0001_2r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0001_2v.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Charleston</placeName> <date>12th June 1842</date></p>
				<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Your esteemed favor of the <date>6th</date> inst came<lb/> duly to hand and I am much grieved to learn that you had been<lb/> seriously indisposed I trust that you are again restored to health<lb/> and sincerely hope that our Heavenly Father will bless your future<lb/> days with uninterrupted health and happiness.  You <hi rend="underline">are</hi> correct in<lb/> your estimate of the organ innovation&#44; and the motives which<lb/> inspired the invocation of the muses&#59; but I think you are wrong<lb/> in the sentiment that &#8220;the gentiles must be anxious for us to yield<lb/> as idle our expectation of a messiah &#38;c&#8222;.  If the doctrine were to be promul<lb/>gated that the Jewish prophecies did not justify the <sic>beleif</sic> in the advent<lb/> of a Personage would it not be a direct attack upon their fundamental<lb/> <sic>beleif</sic>&#63;  For they take the prophecies &#38; find them fulfilled in the persons<lb/> of their Messiah notwithstanding the palpable contradictions that instead<lb/> of the &#8220;Prince of peace&#8222; He has been the demon of strife war &#38; bloodshed<lb/> with all their train of sorrows and crime.&#61;If this idea prevailed<lb/> I think it would be a direct blow at the very foundation of<lb/> their Religion.  Do you concern with me now&#63;  The <hi rend="underline">new</hi> creed I herewith<lb/> transcribe for your edification&#44; it was concocted by <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> &#38; <persName>Mr<lb/> Joshua Lazarus</persName> before the dedication of the synagogue &#38; placed upon<lb/> a Tablet in gilt letter on the right of the <hi rend="underline">achol</hi> on the left is placed<lb/> the 10 Commandments.  Before this excitement I presume no one read them<lb/> at least very few.  I myself never did read them while then feeling<lb/> confident that <persName>Mr P.</persName> had given us the Creed handed down to us by<lb/> <persName>Maimonides</persName>.  Inform me <hi rend="underline">if you can</hi>&#44; where he got his authority for<lb/> this version&#44; &#38; if it would be recognized by Jews&#63;  Here it is&#8212;</p>
				<p>I We believe in the existence of a Supreme Being who created governs &#38; sustains the Universe.</p>
				<p>II We believe that this Being is the only true &#38; living God&#44; the only Divine Being&#44; only<lb/> one in Unity&#44; and without plurality in any sense whatever.</p>
				<p>III We believe that God is incorporeal &#38; incomprehensible that he has never put on the figure<lb/> or body of any thing in Creation &#38; that there is nothing like him in the Universe.&#8212;</p>
				<p>IV We believe that God is without beginning &#38; without end &#38; that He is the only Eternal Being</p>
				<p>V We believe that God reigns alone over the Universe&#59; that there exists no mediator between<lb/> man &#38; his maker &#38; that it is proper to pray to Him only&#44; &#38; not through the merits of any<lb/> other being</p>
				<p>VI We believe that the Prophets were the only persons inspired by God&#44; &#38; that all their words are true</p>
				<p>VII We believe that <del>the</del> <persName>Moses</persName> was the greatest of the Prophets &#38; that none has appeared like unto him</p>
				<p>VIII We believe that the divine Law in our <sic>posession</sic> is that which was delivered to our<lb/> Fathers by <persName>Moses</persName>&#44; &#38; that all divine communication ceased with <persName>Malachi</persName> the last of<lb/> the Prophets</p>
				<p>IX We believe that the divine Law delivered by <persName>Moses</persName>&#44; will never be changed&#44; nor altered</p>
				<p>X We believe that God knows all our thoughts and actions.&#8212;</p>
				<p>XI We believe that God rewards all who observes his commands &#38; punishes those who transgress them</p>
				<p>XII We believe that the Messiah announced by the Prophets is <hi rend="underline">not</hi> come&#8212;<lb/> the Prophecies in relation to his coming <hi rend="underline">not being fulfilled</hi></p>
				<p>XIII We believe that the soul is <hi rend="underline">Immortal</hi>&#44; and that we shall be<lb/> accountable for our actions in the life to come.&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">This creed was also printed some time since &#38; used in the school for the instruction<lb/> of Jewish youth &#38; strange to say it passed the critical ordeal of all of us.  There<lb/> is much subtle wording in it &#38; several passages are blows dealt at the gentiles<lb/> and have no existence in the Text.  Let me have your views upon it.  How can<lb/> you advise the continuance of <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> as Hazan when he laughs at the idea<lb/> of observing the second day of our Holidays.  We know his sentiments and can we<lb/> <sic>beleive</sic> in the <sic>effiacy</sic> or truth of prayer from the lips of him who does not<lb/> <sic>beleive</sic> in the occasion which calls us together to offer up that prayer.  You<lb/> might with the same propriety assert that there would be efficacy in the<lb/> prayers of an atheist.  You cannot have read our reply carefully&#59; read over<lb/> his second letter to the Trustees &#38; you will there find that he will preach<lb/> errors &#38; abuses until the people tell him through the Board of Trustees<lb/> to preach truths.  You must know that in addition to these circumstances <persName>Mr<lb/> Poznanski</persName> in conversation with several Christian Ministers of our<lb/> city asserted&#44; &#8220;That the Messiah had not come&#44; nor</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>did the Prophecies justify the belief that he was to come as a Personage&#44;<lb/> it was figurative&#44; an ideality&#44; &#38; meant a happy &#38; peaceful <del>stake</del> state<lb/> of things&#44; enlightenment peace &#38;c this was our messiah&#8222; alluding to<lb/> <placeName>Carolina</placeName> or the <placeName>U. states</placeName>.  In his dedicatory sermons he spoke<lb/> of the &#8220;<placeName>U. S.</placeName> as our <placeName>Palestine</placeName>&#59; <placeName>Charleston</placeName> our <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> &#38; this &#40;alluding to the<lb/> synagogue&#41; our Temple.  I was induced by the solicitation of one of his<lb/> friends to ask him if this were true.  This <sic>occured</sic> a few days since<lb/> His reply was&#44; That the most amicable form of telling the question was<lb/> to submit it to the courts of the country although he regretted it much &#38;<lb/> declined to answer the question&#44; until he testified on the witness stand.<lb/>  This is what Lawyers would call a <hi rend="underline">negative pregnants</hi> or a denial<lb/> confirming the fact.  Why not deny it at once if untrue&#63; and I should<lb/> have been happy to have contradicted it&#8212;Take these facts in connection<lb/> with the <hi rend="underline">new creed</hi> &#38; let me have your opinion.  He told me moreover<lb/> that when the case came on for trial he would prove things countenanced<lb/> and enjoined upon us by the Rabbins which would tend to injure us in<lb/> the eyes of the christian community.  Not being versed in Talmudical lore<lb/> I am at a loss to know what grave charges he can bring before a<lb/> christian Tribunal to injure us.  The cause he espouses must be very<lb/> bad if it requires such disclosures to uphold it&#44; &#38; like <persName>Samson</persName> he<lb/> will have to be commingled in the ruin he would hurl upon us.<lb/>  He said he would also prove that the keeping of the second days of<lb/> the Holidays was not even <hi rend="underline">enjoined</hi> by the Rabbins and therefore an<lb/> abuse&#44; that we had now obtained the precise time &#38; it was folly to<lb/> keep more than one day.  Have the Rabbins advocated doctrines<lb/> subsequent to our ideas of charity &#38; good will&#63;  Rumor says that<lb/> he intends to prove that if a Gentile falls into the water &#38; a jew could<lb/> save him the Rabbis say let him drown&#8222;&#8212;&#38; may such barbarous<lb/> doctrines at which humanity shudders</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I think it becomes your impervious duty to notice in<lb/> the Occident as early as possible the Rationale&#44; bearing and tenor of the<lb/> Pamphlet sent to you&#44; in a <hi rend="underline">direct manner</hi>&#44; come out boldly &#38;<lb/> manfully&#44; give us <hi rend="underline">orthodox views</hi> instead of the <hi rend="underline">neologistic</hi> reasoning<lb/> of <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> &#38; his party&#44; but let them be tempered with charity<lb/> and brotherly love.  Your friends here expect this from you<lb/> and Judaism <hi rend="underline">demands</hi> this of you.  You cannot waver or falter<lb/> now&#44; you who have for 12 years been battling for what we<lb/> are now honestly &#38; zealously contending for&#44; must not<lb/> let us wage the war unassisted by your talents and experience.<lb/>  Our Jewish <sic>Bretheren</sic> throughout the world should know the<lb/> cause of the breach in our congregation through the medium of your<lb/> Periodical&#44; from the pen of one who is conversant with the<lb/> facts &#38; who has labored &#38; struggled to advance and establish<lb/> the moral &#38; Religious welfare of his people.  Nothing will afford<lb/> more pleasure to <sic>may</sic> of your <sic>Bretheren</sic> here &#38; elsewhere &#38; I<lb/> am confident you will p<add>&#63;</add> this crime.  In relation to<lb/> a conciliation&#8212;it is out of the question&#44; and as for inducing those<lb/> you named in your letter to join our ranks &#40;in public or private&#41;<lb/> it is worse than folly to think of it&#8212;each one &#40;excepting <persName>Hyam Cohen</persName>&#41;<lb/> is an ultra Reformer &#38; will support <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> in all his<lb/> views.  <persName>Hayam Cohen</persName> is his staunch supporter <del>of him</del>.  The courts of<lb/> the Country will reconcile every thing I hope satisfactorily.</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>You have not answered that portion of my letter relating to<lb/> your coming on here if your presence is necessary which<lb/> I am confident will be the case.  I know that every<lb/> advantage will be taken from the circumstance of our not<lb/> having any Hebrew scholars here who can disprove any authority<lb/> he <persName>Mr P.</persName> may adduce.  The party have already <sic>comenced</sic> collating<lb/> facts&#44; authorities&#44; &#38;c for the trial which will positively take place<lb/> in <date>October</date> I have no doubt the Congregation of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> would grant you leave of absence for 8 or 10 days&#44; especially when<lb/> they reflect that an interest is involved effecting them as well<lb/> as us&#44; for we are endeavouring to uphold the faith of <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> transmitted to us by our Fathers &#38; preserved intact for<lb/> upwards of 5000 years.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I thank you for your flattering <add>&#63;</add>&#8212;upon<lb/> my humble effort&#44; and value it highly as I feel assured you<lb/> are not the person to say what you do not believe&#44; I shall<lb/> endeavour to contribute to the Occident but I am not at<lb/> all acquainted with Religious subjects and am endeavoring<lb/> by every possible means to make myself familiar with<lb/> them.  I have commenced studying our holy language<lb/> grammatically and as I before informed you am a<lb/> strict conformist&#44; <hi rend="underline">without losing the spirit of the Religion</hi><lb/> and in every sense of the term I am a better man.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Allow me to thank you for the promptness with which<lb/> you replied to my favors &#38; to desire from you an interchange<lb/> of sentiment which must both instruct and edify me&#44;<lb/> and commending you to the brightest blessings of health Happiness<lb/> &#38; prosperity I remain</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">Your sincere Friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">N. Levin</persName></p>
				<p><persName>Mrs Levin</persName> &#38; Mr &#38; <persName>Mrs Moses</persName> desire their remembrances</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">to you.</p>
				<p>Please present my respects to <persName>Mr Hockenboy</persName> &#38; <persName>Mr Hart</persName> &#38; family Inquire of<lb/> <persName>Mr H</persName> whether he procured the Nos of the voice of <add>&#63;</add> for me.<lb/>  When I have more <sic>liesure</sic> I will send on you a&#47;c&#8212;</p>
				<p>P. S.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">If you conclude to come on &#40;which of course you will &#38; I beg<lb/> you will keep this fact <hi rend="underline">entirely confidential</hi> I mean you coming on&#41;<lb/> your expenses will all be defrayed.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Let me hear from you as early as possible</p>
			<p rend="indent(6)"><persName role="author"><hi rend="underline">N. L.</hi></persName></p>
				<p>I have only recd <hi rend="underline">2</hi> nos of the Occident<lb/> please send the others by <hi rend="underline">mail</hi></p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><placeName>Pa</placeName></p>
				<p>1 dear</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Uncle</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
