<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Buttenwieser, L.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF8_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Buttenwieser,
                            L.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Cincinnati, OH</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1861-10">20 October 1861</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f8_0012_3v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>
                <date>October 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1861</date>.</p>
            <p>Reverend Sir,</p>
            <p>As I see by the last number of the Occident you received<lb/> the copy of the
                Israelite, sent to you by me and contain-<lb/>ing my refutation of <persName>Mr de
                    Solla's</persName> pamphlet For you<lb/> devoted the full space of 9 words or
                the most of a Line<lb/> and a half to the <sic>critick</sic> of my article.</p>
            <p>If I apply the rule of our Sages: <add>מכלל הן אתה שומע לאו</add> to your
                article<lb/> headed „Incestuous Marriages”, and I cannot see any reason<lb/> why I
                should not apply it, my refutation has not found<lb/> grace before your editorial
                eyes.</p>
            <p>You say: „But this far the more complete and therefore<lb/> the more desirable
                response has appeared in the pub<lb/>lication” I have not seen <persName>Mr
                    Nathan's</persName> or any one's else<lb/> reply beside mine and am therefore of
                course not able to<lb/> judge, how complete <persName>Mr N's</persName> reply is.
                Your critic on <persName>Mr<lb/> N's</persName> pamphlet, although covering full 2
                pages of your<lb/> journal can guide me by no means, since your critic can<lb/> not
                claim any higher merit but to be a friend's eulogy on<lb/> the work of his friend
                and it is only fit to show that<lb/> you are on very good terms with and an admirer
                or intimate<lb/> friend of <persName>Mr N.</persName> Anything like an evidence of
                an impar<lb/>tial, <hi rend="underline">objective</hi>
                <sic>critick</sic> by quotations from the criticized<lb/> work the reader seeks in
                vain in your article.</p>
            <p>I have therefore to wait till I shall receive <persName>Mr N's</persName>
                pam<lb/>phlet, in order to find out myself, if your opinion on the completeness</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>if the said pamphlet is correct or not.</p>
            <p>But I think myself justified in not only <hi rend="underline">inviting you very</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">politely</hi>, but in <hi rend="underline">requesting you most
                    urgently and positively</hi>,<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">to point out to me the incompleteness of my refutation</hi>, viz<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">to show</hi> that <hi rend="underline">I have either not
                    refuted all arguments of</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline"><persName>Mr de Solla</persName> or that I have done so in an
                    unsatisfactory way</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If you are not <sic>abe</sic> to do so, you must acknowledge<lb/>
                the error or wrong of your indirect assertion.</p>
            <p>I hardly think it necessary to remind you that if all<lb/> pretended proofs of
                    <persName>de Solla</persName> are satisfactorily refuted by<lb/> my article,
                this my article has the same claim on complete<lb/>ness as a refutation filing a
                whole volume.</p>
            <p>If it were not for so many people who have no<lb/>
                <sic>judgement</sic> of their own, who always inquire in a refutation,<lb/> if every
                passage of the refuted work is mentioned and opposed<lb/> to and with whom no
                article filling only one column has<lb/> any weight at all, since they measure the
                weight of an<lb/> article by the inch of the foot,—I say, if it were not for<lb/>
                those, a single column of the Israelite, containing only<lb/> the 2 proofs of
                    <add>פצוע דכא</add> and <add>ישב ממזר באשדוד</add> would have been<lb/> fully
                sufficient to cause the 2 pillars of <persName>de Sollas</persName> struc<lb/>ture
                to fall to the ground. Every competent judge would<lb/> still have declared my
                refutation satisfactory and complete.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yea, I dare say, truly qualified judges would prefer<lb/> such a
                refutation, since it would be more in correspon<lb/>dence with the words of our
                Sages <add>בלשון קצרה</add><lb/>
                <add>כל היכא דנפילין מילי משתערי</add></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>As you assuredly acknowledge the validity of this rule, you<lb/> must have found
                other defects in my article, than its brevity and<lb/> I therefore repeat my <hi
                    rend="underline">urgent request, to name those defects to me</hi>.</p>
            <p>I have not the pleasure of knowing <persName>Mr Nathan</persName> nor have<lb/> I
                ever seen his newly published work or any other work of his.<lb/> I can therefore
                not <del>judge</del> yet able to judge how „fully” he is „armed for the<lb/> contest
                in behalf of Jewish purity.”</p>
            <p>But if you have an <sic>infavorable</sic> opinion of my armature, as<lb/> this can be
                easily inferred from you article, this your opinion can<lb/> only have been produced
                by weak points, found out in my recently<lb/> published article. For you never had
                any other chance to judge<lb/> of my knowledge of our theology. We met each other
                only twice in our life once in <placeName>Boston</placeName> and the second time
                here. <del>But</del><lb/> But neither time we discussed one topic or even one Iota
                of any <add>הלכה</add><lb/> or <add>שמעתא</add></p>
            <p>I therefore feel myself induced to <hi rend="underline">ask you again, to point
                    me</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">out the errors of my refutation</hi>.</p>
            <p>The great merit of <persName>Mr N's</persName> pamphlet in coming out in the<lb/>
                country; where his antagonist resides I fully acknowledge.<lb/> But I could not help
                well my refutation lacking this ex<lb/>cellent quality, since, of course, I cannot
                be expected to<lb/> go especially from here to <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> in
                order to publish my<lb/> refutation there.</p>
            <p>And, after all, allow me, Rev. Sir, to remark you in all sub<lb/>missive reverence
                that you are here again in contradiction with<lb/> the words of our Sages, a fact
                which is, of course, most surprising<lb/> in the champion and defender of our
                Orthodox cause.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In corroboration of this my remark I refer you to the Mishna <add>גרדים בשער הפשכה
                    ישגו ולוג וכו</add><lb/>
                <add>והעידו שני'</add> and the annotation of the Gemara to this Mishna:<lb/>
                <add>אין לך אומנות פחותה וכו'</add>.</p>
            <p>As I have now mentioned often enough, I cannot judge of the val<lb/>idity of your
                indirect reproofs of my refutation, until you please to<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">enumerate me all its faults in plain language</hi>.</p>
            <p>But I come lastly to another indirect reproof which I am fully justi<lb/>fied to
                contradict <hi rend="underline">flatly</hi> and <hi rend="underline"
                    >emphatically</hi> already now.</p>
            <p>You are pleased to say: In doing this, moreover, we discover nothing<lb/> like
                personality and bitterness against the aggressor, as the whole<lb/> „force of proofs
                is directed against the matter not the man.”<lb/> Now, do tell me, Mr Editor, where
                have you found one word of per<lb/>sonalities or bitterness in my article? Have I
                not treated the author<lb/> in the most polite manner and have only cared for the
                subject<lb/> not for the man who brought it forward? Have I not also pointed<lb/>
                this out in my refutation itself?</p>
            <p>Perhaps you feel inclined to deny all intentional slight treatment<lb/> of my
                refutation, by referring me to the final passage of your ar<lb/>ticle from: „Our
                limited space” to the end. But I hardly think it<lb/> possible that you believe me
                green enough, as not to know that<lb/> the whole alluded conclusion of your article
                consists in mere words with<lb/>out having any serious meaning at all. Or should
                you, after having<lb/> waited on your readers with such a critic and such arguments
                as yours<lb/> are, still have such a favorable opinion of your readers, as to think
                them<lb/> capable to judge of the various publications for themselves? They
                would<lb/> then make a splendid exception of the majority of American and
                Eu<lb/>ropean Jews. While in our days <add>יודעי התורה</add> are very scarce every
                where, the<lb/> majority of your readers, if not all, would be <add>חכמים ויודעי
                    התורה</add>.<lb/> You say, your <hi rend="underline">limited space compelled you
                    to treat the subject</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">briefly</hi>, and every one who casts only a glance at the last
                number<lb/> of the Occident must acknowledge the correctness of your statement,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For, had you not to benefit the Jewish community of
                    <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> and abroad by devoting almost 5 pages to a
                minute description of the<lb/> „Presentation of a Sepher in <placeName>San
                    Francisco</placeName>” and by devoting another<lb/> page and 1/3 to a report on
                the <sic>extremly</sic>
                <del>scarce</del> rare and therefore highly<lb/> surprising occurrence of a <add>בר
                    מצוה</add> in <placeName>Norfolk Str.</placeName> Synagogue</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>just think what our Orthodox cause would have lost, if those 2<lb/> matters had not
                become known! Of course have they the preference<lb/> to a full treatment of the
                    Mamzer<add>?</add> question and a proper critic on the<lb/> different articles,
                speaking on this subject!!!</p>
            <p>In order to show you that in writing all, I have written in this letter<lb/> I am not
                guided by partiality for my own slight work, I shall ex<lb/>tract some passages of a
                letter, I have received from a truly Orthodox<lb/> scholar.</p>
            <p>I am not at liberty to mention you the name of the writer, since<lb/> perhaps he does
                not want me to do so. Suffice it, to say, that the alluded<lb/> Gentleman ranks high
                in our Orthodox camp and I doubt not that you<lb/> and I wish many others consider
                him an authority.</p>
            <p>He wrote to me:</p>
            <p>The papers you have sent me have come to hand, I congratulate<lb/> you on the <hi
                    rend="underline">tone</hi> of your article. The <persName>Rev. Mr
                    Nathan's</persName> preface—his<lb/> work itself I have not seen—is too
                personal, whereas you are free<lb/> of sarcasm and bitterness.”</p>
            <p>At the end of the letter he wrote to me:</p>
            <p>I again repeat, of the replies I have hitherto seen yours is by<lb/> far the best so
                that <persName>Mr de Solla</persName> will have to acknowledge, that of<lb/> his
                opponents you are the most gentlemanly.”</p>
            <p>In fine I ask you politely, to <hi rend="underline">send me a copy of <persName>Mr
                        Nathan's</persName></hi></p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p><hi rend="underline">pamphlet</hi> and to let me know the price thereof and in
                what<lb/> way I can remit the money to you. If you have an agent<lb/> here, please
                mention me his name and I shall pay him the<lb/> amount or send me the pamphlet
                through his agency.</p>
            <p>Asking you again to <hi rend="underline">point me out the defects of my re</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">futation</hi> either in a private letter or publicly in
                your<lb/> Journal.</p>
            <p>I am, Rev. Sir, your obedient</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <persName role="author">L Buttenwieser</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <placeName>228 Fifth street</placeName>
            </p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_19_8.pdf">The above text refers to Occident
                        Volume 19 No. 8 pages 373 through 376. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
