<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF11_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="">5 October</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0005_3v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p>Wax seal</p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>Augusta</placeName>
                <date>October 5th</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I was anxious to reply to yours of <date>16th</date><lb/>
                immediately on its receit<add>?</add> &amp; to thank you for putting me in
                conceit<lb/> with myself but a variety of domestic arrangements &amp; some family
                letters<lb/> of importance compell'd me to delay replying to your very flattering
                favor.<lb/> Tis very pleasant when out of humor with the world &amp; yourself to
                break<lb/> the seal of a letter (from a kind of friend in a quiet corner of the
                world)<lb/> which excites yourself love &amp; throws a little rose colour on the
                dark<lb/> tints of life. In a constant intercourse with the world I have had<lb/>
                much to mortify &amp; distress me but as yet my sincerity in friendship has<lb/>
                never been doubted &amp; you do me only justice my kind friend, in<lb/> judging that
                I am as <hi rend="underline">jealous</hi>, in your cause, as you have found<lb/> me
                in that of newer friends. Think not you are alone in receiving<lb/> censure where
                you expected approbation. Although not a public<lb/> character, my motives are often
                misconstrued &amp; wrong interpre<lb/>tations given to them even by some very dear
                to me, I regret<lb/> it but sorrow not, as one without hope; for I know ere a
                little<lb/> while, all that appears dark, in my actions, will be illumed<lb/> by the
                light of truth! The task is a painful one to extract<lb/> the sweet from the bitter
                which the hand of malevolence is too apt<lb/> to surround us with, but I should feel
                prouder of you, my respected<lb/> friend, if there was less of the human &amp; more
                of the <hi rend="underline">humane</hi> feeling<lb/> in your expression of
                discontent towards the fair dames of <placeName>Charleston</placeName><lb/> remember
                “To these who suffer much, much shall be given”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For patience wears the brightest wealth in Heaven.”<lb/> God has
                endowed you with so much deeper knowledge than your</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>fellow, has gifted you with perception so far superior to ours; has inspired<lb/> you
                with power to illumine the path of your benighted people, has<lb/> blessed you with
                the power of elevating the Jewish character so as<lb/> to place it (if not superior)
                on a level with the religionists of other<lb/> faith that we marvel when we
                    find<del>ing</del> you entering into the<lb/> sarcasms of those inferior to you
                in mental blessings — methin<lb/>ks I hear you exclaim “But does <persName>Mrs
                    Moise</persName> think, because I am<lb/> more endowed with intellectual
                resources, more deeply versed in<lb/> a knowledge of God &amp; his perfectibility
                than those around me I am<lb/> exempt from human passions &amp; human weaknesses
                &amp; by no<lb/> means my dear Sir, but that you have the ability to root out<lb/>
                with a stronger hand, the tares that spring up among your wheat<lb/> &amp; when we
                find you wanting where are we to look for examples<lb/> to pattern by. Our letters
                of late have all contained, something<lb/> relative to <persName>Mr. P</persName>,
                let us by mutual consent, banish him, for<lb/> I wish at this distance, to see none
                of the dark shades thrown<lb/> around your portrait &amp; I fear he can never be
                introduced<lb/> without producing frowns, where I desire smiles, I have read
                the<lb/> poems of the <persName>Misses Moise</persName> some years ago &amp; was
                much pleased<lb/> with them, as they gave much promise of a rich poetic fancy
                accompani-<lb/>ed by the freshness of youth, you are happy in having such
                contributors<lb/> to your labors &amp; I should be most happy to enlist as a
                subaltern<lb/> even in your company, had I the time to devote to literary
                pursuits<lb/> In bygone days I had leisure &amp; would have repaid your
                patronage<lb/> by a promise of future usefulness but alas now I must check<lb/> all
                ambitious aspirations &amp; plodd on in the every day walks of life<lb/> satisfied,
                if I can as an accountable being, act my part in my path in life<lb/> amidst its
                trials &amp; its duties &amp; reconcile myself with the reflect-<lb/>ion that the
                soul is invigorated by the difficulties, &amp; purified</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>by the trials it meets &amp; overcomes in the journey of life — I have<lb/> 3 or 4
                unfinished communications which have been commen<lb/>ced since your Occident but I
                have not the time nor desire<lb/> to appear before the public under your
                scrutinizing eye.<lb/> I have had much lately to distract my mind from gleaning<lb/>
                any of the honors you are ready to bestow on humble aspir<lb/>ants in the cause of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. A beloved brother who I always<lb/> viewed as a
                pattern of piety who I was proud of for his beauty, his<lb/> talents &amp; filial
                piety has doomed me to despair &amp; his parents<lb/> to sorrow by marrying gentile
                woman; had he in youth<lb/> allowed his fancy to get the better of all those lessons
                inculcated<lb/> with a mothers watchfulness I would have pitied &amp; forgiven
                but<lb/> when at the age of 40 when the passions are cooled by reason<lb/> when
                reflection must awaken the decree issued against<lb/> all who marry with the
                heathens how can I excuse him!<lb/> He was my favorite brother my pride &amp; glory
                &amp; how has he<lb/> disappointed my fondest hopes; yet if God will forgive him
                    <add>?</add><lb/><add>?</add> surely ought &amp; yet I feel it hard to write the
                word<lb/> my son too my first born is about to leave the home of his<lb/> fathers
                &amp; seek his future in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> he will not go<lb/>
                without my consent &amp; I have given it because I know that<lb/> when our influence
                fails opposition will avail naught.<lb/> his object is to render his mother's &amp;
                orphan sisters &amp; broth<lb/>ers life more affluent, but I am selfish &amp; would
                rather<lb/> have a scanty pittance surrounded by my children &amp; bring<lb/>ing the
                sunshine of their love than the wealth of <placeName>indies</placeName><lb/> I fear
                that absence may do its work of forgetfulness<lb/> &amp; what would life be to me
                without the certainty of<lb/> being beloved &amp; having something to love on
                earth</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>you say I am impulsive therefore you must not scrutinize<lb/> my letters, for as my
                thoughts pious so do I pen them &amp; you<lb/> must be thankful that my pen cannot
                fly as swiftly as they<lb/> do or what a heterogeneous mass you would be taxed to
                read<lb/> But I have some correspondents, that I have to compose<lb/> my letters
                for, &amp; they are anything but agreeable ones; but to<lb/> those whose friendship
                I can depend on, I throw them<lb/> on paper, as they rush to my mind without any
                regard to<lb/> style penmanship or order. I have read several numbers of<lb/> the
                women of <placeName>Israel</placeName> &amp; am much pleased with them
                    <persName>Miss<lb/> A</persName> with a happy talent imparts interest &amp;
                character to many<lb/> which in the sacred book are only remarkable as the wives
                of<lb/> good &amp; great men &amp; as being mothers of the Jewish family. We<lb/>
                have bought it for our Library thereby enabling those scholars<lb/> who can
                appreciate them to read them, as well as children of a<lb/> larger <add>?</add> I
                often sigh, that my means, will not<lb/> sanction, my indulgence in possessing,
                every book that<lb/> comes out, relative to our people. I am a great admirer of<lb/>
                <persName>Charlotte Elizabeth</persName>, but have just finished a little work<lb/>
                (sent to <persName>Rosalie</persName> by a gentile friend) that savors quite
                too<lb/> much of the Saviour to suit my taste — I shall not allow<lb/> her to read
                it, as I cannot expunge, what is objectionable<lb/> which I often do, in works sent
                to her, there being such as connec<lb/>tion as to render it quite unintelligible by
                so doing — Aprospos<lb/> do you know what her real name is? Have you heard that<lb/>
                <persName>Miss Henry Myers</persName> is married to <persName>Tuckerman</persName>
                the <add>?</add> And<lb/>
                <persName>Charlotte</persName> to <persName>Griswold</persName> the authors
                Intermarriages are bad<lb/> enough when the young &amp; thoughtless enter into them,
                but</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>when women who are in the <add>paper ripped</add> &amp; yellow leaf of time
                enter<lb/> into such engagements what can they hope for.<lb/> The report of
                    <persName>Miss H's</persName> marriage has only reached me but <persName>Mrs
                    H</persName><lb/> has received a letter from <persName>Charlotte</persName>
                informing her, of her marriage<lb/> I have a pretty piece of poetry, called the
                “Dying Hebrew” if you<lb/> will receive it, without the authors name I will forward
                it<lb/> our weather is cool &amp; delightful, the autumnal leaves have not yet<lb/>
                begun to fall &amp; remind us, of our departure from this beautiful<lb/> world; and
                we will have no depressing heat to render our appro-<lb/>aching fast, uncomfortable,
                may you be written<lb/> in the book of a happy &amp; prosperous life, is my fervent
                prayers<lb/> and at the intercession of the good, for their fallen &amp; sinful<lb/>
                sisters, avails much I hope you will not be unmindful<lb/> of one, who stands much
                in need of forgiveness for positive<lb/> as well as negative sins — My daughter
                &amp; son both desire their<lb/> regards, they have a pleasant circle &amp; enjoy
                all the benefits<lb/> of the best society, although I often ask myself, if my
                precepts are<lb/> sufficiently impressed to prevent their marrying with the
                stranger<lb/> God must watch over them; cut off from their own people<lb/> I cannot
                deprive them of the charms of society — I found my<lb/>-self on the 5th side without
                being aware with this mom<lb/>ent how I am taxing your time &amp; patience. Let me
                soon<lb/> hear from you &amp; do inform me if there is more union among<lb/> your
                congregation than in <date>1840</date> — Remember me to my Cousins<lb/> good fortune
                seems to <del>some</del> to follow them through life; few<lb/> are more deserving,
                but if we judge only by the prosperity of our<lb/> friends of their goodness, what a
                sorry chance some of us will<lb/> have — I cry you mercy &amp; will subscribe my
                self</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">your friend</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">
                <persName role="author">R C Moise</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p rend="indent(4)">Mail</p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd I. Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <placeName>Pa</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="The following is written upside down at the top of the page.">The books are
                recd — will write<lb/> in relation to them when the money<lb/> is collected. Yours
                &amp;c <persName>Thos S Moise</persName><lb/> Many thanks in for the
                    <date>Saturday</date> post<lb/> it afforded amusement to many<lb/> of us &amp;
                    <persName>S A</persName> says her scrap books<lb/> has <sic>benefitted</sic>
                materially by it.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
