<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Jacobs, Henry S.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx3FF1_38</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Jacobs, Henry
                            S.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1866-07">5 July 1866</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0038_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0038_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0038_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b3f1_0038_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                <date>5th July 5626</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Rev Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Dear Sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">Your letter on your return home duly reached<lb/> me. I regret very
                sincerely to learn of your impaired health, of which<lb/> my
                    <placeName>Richmond</placeName> correspondents had before informed me; but most
                earnest-<lb/>ly do I pray that further tidings may be of a happier character.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The lukewarmness and indifference that<lb/> you noticed in your
                recent Southern trip, in religious matters, had<lb/> long ago been perceptible to
                me, and occasioned serious and painful<lb/> thought. This degeneracy has been
                creeping along for some time and<lb/> I see fearful signs of its continuous
                progress. The battle between<lb/> Principle and Gain almost invariably terminates in
                favor of the<lb/> latter; hence those leaders who will smooth away the
                “difficulties”<lb/> which beset the path of conformity with recognized duties,
                and<lb/> not insist on the uncompromising fidelity required of us, are<lb/> certain
                of being popular and influential. My “<sic>dilenda</sic> est<lb/> Carthago” is the
                onslaught in and out of the Pulpit on the<lb/> modern manufacture of a “Religion of
                Convenience.” I have<lb/> confidence in the innate piety and good sense of the
                people<lb/> who often, tho offenders against the the Law, do not palliate<lb/> or
                argue away the wrong, and may be wrought on for their</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>good <add>ושובו מדרכיהם הרעים</add>; but when Teachers rise up, and by<lb/> precept
                and example inculcate as unimportant, useless, and<lb/> contrary to the spirit of
                the age — all or much of what they had<lb/> been trained up to observe — what is to
                be expected? The awakened<lb/> religious feelings become enlisted in favor of what
                requires so little<lb/> effort; only build a magnificent place of worship,
                modernize,<lb/> hope<add>?</add> &amp; render agreeable its services, preserve
                decorum, &amp; have an<lb/> external varnish of piety, and the <add>ר"ה</add> is
                attained. I place<lb/> a great deal of the blame for this wretched state of
                affairs<lb/> on the shoulders of our so-called Orthodox chiefs, who are idle
                &amp;<lb/> selfish, and contribute nothing to the <hi rend="underline">general</hi>
                good of <placeName>Israel</placeName>. All<lb/> their efforts seem concentrated on
                little aims which began in their<lb/> own Synagogues and end there. And then there
                is no unity of<lb/> action. Look for assistance at the several large congregations
                at<lb/> the <placeName>North</placeName>. At the <placeName>19th St.</placeName>
                Synagogue, everything seems to have been<lb/> attained in <persName>Mr
                        Lyn's<add>?</add></persName> cadences &amp; his choir's artistic
                performances.<lb/> The pulpit is silent, and does not seem to be needed. Our<lb/>
                worthy brethren there are apparently contented with the order of<lb/> things as they
                are, and are either so pious as not to require<lb/> explanations or so wicked as to
                fear denunciation. At <persName>Dr. Raphall's</persName><lb/> &amp; <persName>Mr.
                    Isaacs's</persName>, I hear trumpet-tongued praises of the <hi rend="underline"
                    >choir</hi>, in<lb/> the former, it is said, led by a Xian! Do you not remember
                my<lb/> fickle and unsuccessful effort in <add>?</add> at the first Sephim of<lb/>
                the Board of Delegates to have its scope of a character which</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>might meet our wants;- a College — preparatory Schools — a<lb/> supervising Board to
                examine into the qualifications &amp; personal<lb/> worth of those coming to this
                country for office&amp;c? But no: it<lb/> seemed that the assembly of Delegates from
                various parts of the<lb/> Union looked only to the aggrandizement of <placeName>New
                    York</placeName>, and we<lb/> Dummies had only to listen with rapt attention to
                the to the Delphic<lb/> oracles &amp; play the meek parts of “make weights.” I
                hope<lb/> better things are in progress for I notice at last, some wakefullness<lb/>
                on the great needs of one day. But perhaps my expectations<lb/> are premature, and
                another <persName>Rip Van Winkle</persName> nap will follow.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your article in the <date>June</date> No. is sound &amp;<lb/>
                telling, and I trust to see it followed up by some tangible plan<lb/> for training
                up an American ministry. It is singular that<lb/> our wealthy Congrns. have not been
                influenced even by common<lb/> policy to do something even of a selfish nature for
                their own<lb/> future advantage; and I throw out the hint which you might<lb/> use,
                that lacking any general or organized effort, that each<lb/> might devote a portion
                of its funds annually set apart to edu<lb/>cate in <placeName>Europe</placeName> —
                after the usual Collegiate Course here — a<lb/> respectable &amp; pious-minded young
                man, in whose services it<lb/> would have the first claim. My little boy I
                    <sic>purpose</sic>, God<lb/> willing, bringing up to the sacred profession, and
                if nothing better, or<lb/> as good offer here at the proper age to send him to
                    <placeName>Breslau</placeName>; and<lb/> all my strivings peculiarly are devoted
                towards this attainment,</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>not depending on any Congregational action. I wish a few others<lb/> would attempt
                the same procedure. I can but <hi rend="underline">hope</hi> it.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Aletrino</persName> has shown some diligence<lb/> in
                the matter of the Agency, and has handed me the following bit of<lb/> additional
                subscribers, to whom please mail the Occident,—if possible<lb/> from the
                    <date>Nissan</date> No. when the present Vol. began. If you cannot do this<lb/>
                to all, endeavor to do so for the <persName>Messrs. De
                    Meza</persName>.—<persName>Joshua D Henriques</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>E. de Pina</persName>, <persName>Morris Woolf</persName>, <persName>A de
                    Sola</persName>, <persName>J. O. DeCastro</persName>, <persName>S J de
                    Meza</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>A H de Meza</persName>, &amp; <persName>Henry Aaron</persName>.
                    <persName>Mr B Y Benyamin</persName> is still uncertain<lb/> as to subscribing.
                Send a list of amts due you by previous Sub.<lb/> for collection. Send the follg
                Books p Express—addressed to <persName>Mr<lb/> M Alentino</persName>, <placeName>80
                    Prytania St. - N.O.</placeName></p>
            <table cols="2" rows="4">
                <row>
                    <cell>1 Set P Books — Sheep</cell>
                    <cell>@ $25.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1 “ “ fancy</cell>
                    <cell>@ $30.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1 Pentateuch Sheep mention the price</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1 Bible Ea 3.50 &amp; 5.00</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>As soon as he collects for these and subsns. I will see that the amt.<lb/> be
                promptly remitted you.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I hinted to <persName>Mr. Gutheim</persName> of his long
                silence;<lb/> and I understood him to say he would soon write you. Perhaps he<lb/>
                has already done so. The <placeName>Rampart St.</placeName> synagogue is to be torn
                down &amp;<lb/> made more spacious, the adjoining lot having been purchased. The
                Polish<lb/> on Colonial <add>?</add> to be finished for <add>פסח</add>, that on
                    <placeName>Jackson St</placeName> for <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mrs. Jacobs</persName> joins me in kind regards.</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">Yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">
                <persName role="author">Henry S. Jacobs</persName>
            </p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_24_3.pdf">The above text refers to Occident
                        Volume 24 No. 3 pages 97 through 106. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
