<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">A Southern Jew</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx9FF14_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">A Southern
                            Jew</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Savannah, GA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1843-07">16 July 1843</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0002_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0002_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0002_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b9f14_0002_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">8</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">
                <hi rend="underline">Jews in <placeName>Savannah</placeName></hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Savannah Georgia</placeName>
                <date>16 July 1843</date>.</p>
            <p>To the <addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee>,</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">My dear sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">The establishment<lb/> of public journals, and periodicals by the
                Jews in <placeName>Europe</placeName> and<lb/> this country, must be productive of
                much good, not only in<lb/> advocating, and <sic>illucidating</sic> our holy faith,
                but in collecting<lb/> and disseminating information on “the dispersed of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>.”<lb/> Under this impression I have been induced
                to prepare, and forward<lb/> for publication in your valuable journal, (what I
                regret to say<lb/> is but) an imperfect historical sketch of the Jews, and Hebrew
                Congregation in<lb/> this city. The Colony of <placeName>Georgia</placeName> was
                settled in <date>1732</date> under the auspices<lb/> of <persName>General
                    Oglethorpe</persName>, whose “strong benevolence of soul” was<lb/> sung by
                    <persName>Pope</persName>, and commented upon by all the good, and great
                men<lb/> of his day. The end, and aim of those who settled
                    <placeName>Georgia</placeName> was charity,<lb/> in its widest, and most
                extended sense, and the motto on the<lb/> seal of the Trustees, spoke but the
                language of truth. <hi rend="underline">Now sibi</hi>,<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">sed aliis</hi>. Not for ourselves, but for others. A Colony
                springing into<lb/> existence under such auspices, with a fertile soil, and a
                genial<lb/> climate, soon became an Asylum for the oppressed of every<lb/> land, and
                every faith. The door was open wide to all—land was<lb/> granted to each emigrant,
                and toleration raising its broad, and<lb/> ample, banner, proclaimed to all, entire
                freedom of conscience.<lb/> Under these circumstances it was to be expected that the
                Jew<lb/> with no country, “<hi rend="underline">but the grave</hi>,” would speedily
                seek that land<lb/> where “under his own vine, and his own fig tree,” he might<lb/>
                worship the God of his Fathers, “with none to molest, or make him<lb/> afraid.”
                Accordingly we find that as early as <date>1733</date>, about forty<lb/> Jews sailed
                from <placeName>London</placeName>, or in the language of the original<lb/>
                memorandum (kept in hebrew, and still preserved in this<lb/> city) “voluntarily
                embarked from <placeName>London</placeName>, and paid their passages”<lb/> “thence
                to this country, and arrived in <placeName>Savannah</placeName> in the state”<lb/>
                “of <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, on the <date>eleventh day of July 1733</date>.”
                The following are</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>the names of those Jews, who, thus early found a home in<lb/> the new colony of
                    <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, <hi rend="underline">towit</hi>,
                    <persName>Benjamin Sheftall</persName><lb/> and wife, <persName>Dr.
                    Nunes</persName>, and his mother, <persName>Moses Nunes</persName>,
                    <persName>Daniel<lb/> Nunes</persName> and <persName>Shem Nunes</persName>,
                their servant <persName>Isaac Nunes Henriques</persName><lb/> and wife and son.
                    <persName>Raphael Bernal</persName> and wife—<persName>David Olivera</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Jacob Olivera</persName>, and wife, and three children. <persName>Aaron
                    Depevia</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Benjamin Gideon</persName>, <persName>Jacob Crosta</persName>,
                    <persName>David L. Depass</persName> and wife,<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Veneral</persName>, <persName>W. Molera</persName>, <persName>David
                    Miranda</persName>, <persName>Jacob Miranda</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>David Cohen</persName>, and wife, son, and three daughters,
                    <persName>Abram<lb/> Minis</persName> and wife, and two daughters,
                    <persName>Simeon Minis</persName>, <persName>Jacob<lb/> Gowell</persName>, and
                    <persName>Abram D'Lyon</persName>. Of these emigrants, the<lb/>
                <persName>Sheftalls</persName>, <persName>Minis'</persName> and
                    <persName>D'Lyons</persName> remained in <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, and
                then<lb/> numerous descendants are still inhabitants of our city,<lb/> many of whom
                have and still do occupy offices of<lb/> honor, profit and trust. I have no means of
                ascertain=<lb/>ing what has become of the others. We have every reason to<lb/> know
                that even in this land of strangers <placeName>Israel's</placeName> God was<lb/> not
                forgotten, but that here amidst savage Indians, and<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Georgia's</placeName> dark forests the great <hi rend="underline">J
                    Am</hi> was worshiped<lb/> and in the same language in which
                    <persName>Abram</persName> and <persName>Isaac</persName>, and<lb/>
                <persName>Jacob</persName> prayed, which was heard on <placeName>Sinai</placeName>,
                and in the gorgeous<lb/> temple of <persName>Solomon</persName>, and in which the
                inspired men of<lb/> God poured forth their prophecies. We have however no<lb/>
                earlier <hi rend="underline">record</hi> than the <date>29 of August 1790</date>, on
                which day we<lb/> find a resolution, “that application be made to his
                Excel”=<lb/>=“lency the Governor to incorporate this congregation as a”<lb/> “Body
                politic by the name of Mickva Israel,” and accor=<lb/>=dingly a charter of
                Incorporation was granted on the<lb/>
                <date>30 November 1790</date>. The Jews however, as a congregation,<lb/> had prior
                to their incorporation assembled regularly in<lb/> a private house, on the
                    <date>Sabbaths</date>, and holy days and there<lb/> worshiped God according to
                the forms, and faith of their<lb/> ancestors, and subsequently a room was rented
                for<lb/> that purpose. But on the <date>19th day of April 1820</date> the<lb/>
                corner stone of a place for public worship was laid<lb/> with appropriate ceremonies
                on a lot which had been<lb/> previously granted to the Jewish Congregation by
                the<lb/> corporation of the city. This building was completed</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and consecrated and used for public worship according<lb/> to the forms of the
                Portuguese Jews, until <date><sic>december</sic> 1827</date> when<lb/> it was
                consumed by fire. This calamity left the Jews with=<lb/>out a place of worship, and
                they had recourse again to a<lb/> rented room. In <date>1837</date> they opened a
                subscription among their<lb/> fellow citizens by which they raised the sum of
                eleven<lb/> Hundred Dollars, which with the money received from the<lb/> insurance
                on the Synagogue destroyed by fire, and private<lb/> contributions, they were
                enabled in <date>1838</date> to erect the neat brick<lb/> temple, which you
                consecrated to the service of Almighty<lb/> God on the <date>24th of February
                    1841</date>. The Jews in this city have<lb/> never had the means of <hi
                    rend="underline">employing</hi> a regular Hazan, or rather<lb/> such an one as
                would suit them, and whenever service<lb/> has been performed, it has always been
                done <hi rend="underline">gratuitously</hi> by<lb/> some member of the Congregation.
                But they are not unmind<lb/>ful of the all-important subject, and with
                commenda=<lb/>ble zeal are now taking steps to ensure (at no distant<lb/> day) to
                themselves, and their posterity, the blessing, and the<lb/> comfort of a spiritual
                teacher. Foremost in this work of<lb/> love, and faith, have been
                    <placeName>Israel's</placeName> daughters, upon whose<lb/> efforts, the
                blessings of a beneficent God have rested.<lb/> To aid in this object of obtaining a
                permanent fund from<lb/> which the Hazan may be supported, the Jewish ladies<lb/>
                determined on giving a Fair, and in <date>March</date> last put<lb/> their plan in
                execution. They were nobly sustained by<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">every Christian sect</hi> in this city, and realized more
                than<lb/> sixteen Hundred Dollars, which has already been profitably<lb/> and safely
                invested. That spirit of charity which pre=<lb/>sided at the birth of our colony
                still reigns and sheds<lb/> its benign influence over the hearts of our
                Christian<lb/> friends, and on this occasion, charity was seen in all<lb/> its
                loveliness, and felt in all its heavenly force—pre=<lb/>=judice, and sectarian
                    <sic>intollerance</sic> stood rebuked and<lb/> abashed, and the heart of the Jew
                was gladdened by the<lb/> tender sympathy, and open handed charity of the<lb/>
                Christian. Although not strictly within the scope of this<lb/> communication, yet I
                can not suffer the occasion<lb/> to pass by without acknowledging with heart
                felt</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>gratitude, the kindness and liberality of our Jewish Brethren<lb/> abroad. We
                received contributions from <placeName>Canada</placeName>, <placeName>New
                    York</placeName>,<lb/>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Richmond</placeName>, <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, and
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>. Nor<lb/> must we fail to remember that we
                were also aided by<lb/> some of our people in <placeName>Bordeaux (in
                    France)</placeName>, and in <placeName>Liver=<lb/>pool</placeName>, and
                    <placeName>Hackney</placeName> in <placeName>England</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Such, sir, is, (as I have already said) an imperfect sketch of the<lb/> history of
                the Jews in this city, and I may add with pride<lb/> and thankfulness to God that
                they have always been a<lb/> respected and useful body of citizens. They defended
                their<lb/> country, and its liberties in the war of the Revolution, and<lb/> their
                names may be seen among the founders of<lb/> every charitable, and literary society
                in this city, and<lb/> in return they have received the most unasked<lb/> and
                undeviating kindness and liberality from their<lb/> fellow citizens. At this very
                time the city Judge,<lb/> and Sheriff are Jews—the collector of the Post is a<lb/>
                Jew, and a Jew occupies a seat in the Legislature of<lb/> the State from this city,
                and is a member of the Board<lb/> of Aldermen, besides other offices of minor
                im=<lb/>portance which are filled by Jews.<lb/> In conclusion, I would invoke the
                blessings of<lb/> Heaven on that city whose <del>house loved God</del>
                characteristic virtues are<lb/> charity and Liberality.</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)"><persName role="author">A Southern Jew</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
