<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Wise, Isaac M.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx9FF17_1</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Wise, Isaac M.</author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_1r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_1v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_2r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_2v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_3r.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_3v.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b9f17_0001_4r.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>7 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false">Fragile</condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>Small Pin No 4.<lb/>4&#47;</p>
				<p>Principles of Judaism<lb/> No 12</p>
				<p>Occident copy<lb/> <date>July</date></p>
				<p>1.</p>
				<p rend="align(right)">To the Editor of the Occident.</p>
				<p>Dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The object of this letter is to<lb/> continue my objections against the dogma<lb/> of the <sic>resurection</sic> of the body&#44; and to<lb/> vindicate the doctrine of the immortality<lb/> of the soul&#59; wherefore you will excuse me&#44;<lb/> that I at once commence without <del>all fashionable</del> any farther<lb/> preface<del>s</del>.  The process of life is a continual<lb/> struggle of the principle of life with <del>the</del><lb/> organic matter&#59; that principle of life puts in this manner<lb/> the organic machine <del>thus</del> in such a rapid and<lb/> uninterrupted motion&#44; that the latter is<lb/> so much impaired and enfeebled&#44; that the<lb/> former <del>might</del> would make its escape&#44; if the mate&#61;<lb/>rial machine <del>be</del> were not strengthened by rest&#44;<lb/> and nutritious food.  So we see the<lb/> principle of life always active <add>struggling</add> to escape from<lb/> its organic prison&#44; which calls to our mind<lb/> the words of an ancient sage <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#8220;thou livest against thy will.&#8221;  Still we <del>feel sorry</del> experience regret<lb/> when the hour of departure comes&#59; the<lb/> principle of life has <del>thus</del> been so long accustomed <del>itself</del><lb/> to its organic companion&#44; that the hour<lb/> of separation is an hour of agony and pain&#59; wherefore said the ancient sage<lb/> &#8220;thou diest against thy null&#8221; <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> <del>said the ancient sage.</del>  There is no man who is as<lb/> pious and <del>so</del> righteous&#44; so virtuous and good<lb/> as he could be&#59; none has ever done as much good as<lb/> he <del>could</del> might have done&#59; none <sic>developes</sic> his mental faculties<lb/> capacities to <del>that</del> the highest degree which they are<lb/> capable of attaining&#59; consequently every man<lb/> has his faults&#44; his infirmities&#44; his sins&#44;<lb/> which he <del>like so very much</del> is exceedingly anxious to cover with<lb/> the veil of obscurity and forgetfulness.</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>But notwithstanding all this&#44; <del>Still</del> we know that above us is the eye&#44; which<lb/> sees every thing&#59; an Ear which hears every thing<lb/> and all our transactions are recorded in the<lb/> book<del>s</del> of everlasting memorial&#59; we still <del>we</del><lb/> must give account before a Judge who knows<lb/> the thoughts of the heart&#44; although we wish<lb/> to have our transactions covered and forgotten<lb/> <del>&#8222;thou sh wilt</del><lb/> <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>  Thou will have to give an account &#8222;of thy deeds against they will.&#8221;<lb/>  Life in general is a chain of <del>antiteses</del> opposites<add>&#63;</add>&#44; of<lb/> struggles&#44; of sacrifices&#44; of self&#45;denial&#44; of temp&#61;<lb/>tations&#59; such is the life of the virtuous&#44; while<lb/> that of the vicious is a series of miseries&#44; of<lb/> calamities and self&#45;contempt&#44; wherefore an&#45;<lb/>other ancient sage said <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#8220;It <del>is</del> would have been better for man not to <del>be born</del> have been created than to <del>be born</del> have been.&#8221;<lb/>  After I have now lived against my will&#44; and<lb/> sacrificed my joys and pleasures&#44; born the<lb/> persecutions&#44; the <del>wounding</del> scoff&#44; the ironic<lb/> satire&#44; the <del>hellish</del> malignity of men&#59; after<lb/> I <del>went</del> have gone f<del>r</del>orth triumphantly from all tempta&#61;<lb/>tions and <del>irritations</del> excitement&#59; after I have died and have<lb/> given account of my acts&#59; after the truth has become<lb/> mine&#44; and I am permitted to live in the<lb/> company of <del>adequate</del> congenial spirits&#44; ravished and<lb/> satisfied with the glory <del>of the Glory</del> of the<lb/> Most High&#44; <del>I</del> shall I be forced to live again<lb/> on this earth&#63;  No&#44; that is impossible&#44;<lb/> I think too much of the goodness of God&#44;<lb/> that <del>I could think</del> the should inflict <del>such a</del> so horrible a wrong<lb/> <del>done by God himself</del> on his creatures.</p>
				<p>Hence we must <del>consider</del> keep in mind that God said<lb/> to <persName>Adam</persName>&#44; &#8220;In the sweat of thy face shalt thou<lb/> eat bread&#44; till thou return unto the ground&#44; for<lb/> out of it wast thou taken&#59; for dust thou art</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>and unto dust shalt thou return.&#8221; &#40;Genesis 3. 19.&#41;<lb/>  <persName>Abigail</persName> said to <persName>David</persName>&#44; &#8220;But the soul of my<lb/> lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with<lb/> the Lord thy God&#8221; &#40;I <persName>Samuel</persName> 25. 29&#41;.  <persName>David</persName><lb/> said&#44; &#8220;For thou wilt not <del>cead</del> gild my soul to the<lb/> grave&#44; thou wilt not suffer thy pious one to see<lb/> <sic>distruction</sic>&#59; thou <sic>wist</sic> make known unto me<lb/> the path of life&#44; the <sic>fulness</sic> of joy &#40;which is&#41;<lb/> with thy presence&#44; &#40;and&#41; the pleasures &#40;which are&#41;<lb/> at thy right hand for evermore&#8221; &#40;Psalm 16. 10&#44;11.&#41;<lb/>  We do not see&#44; how any one can torture these passages to <add>&#63;</add><lb/> into a resurrection of the body.</p>
				<p>If a general resurrection of the body will take place&#44; the question<lb/> <del>it is to be asked&#44;</del> arises will <del>the arisen ones</del> the revived die again<lb/> or not&#63; in case they die again&#44; another general<lb/> resurrection must take place&#44; and then an&#45;<lb/>other one&#44; and another one and so forth <del>into</del> to an<lb/> infinity of resurrections&#59; but in case they die not&#44;<lb/> then it will be a new creation&#44; but not these<lb/> very same bodies which have died&#59; for they are so<lb/> composed&#44; that they continually change their state<lb/> and particles&#44; dimensions&#44; form and colour&#44;<lb/> consequently they must die.  Hence&#44; what use is<lb/> in the resurrection of the body&#63;  If our opponents<lb/> say&#44; the soul cannot perfectly exist&#44; enjoy the purest<lb/> pleasures &#38; live in the happiest manner before<lb/> God in the <del>chorus</del> assembly of Angels and <del>adequate</del> congenial<lb/> spirits then they must first deny the doctrines<lb/> of Judaism&#44; which <del>makes</del> teaches God to be a<lb/> pure&#44; and absolute spirit&#44; and as God exists<lb/> without the aid of a body&#44; just as well the<lb/> disembodied human spirit which is the <sic>immage</sic> of God&#44; <del>can</del> exist with<lb/> all <del>his</del> its excellencies and <del>all his</del> faculties&#58;<lb/> And if they admit this <del>thesis</del> portion&#44; <del>then</del> they must<lb/> confess&#44; that the soul not only derives no</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>advantage from a <sic>resurection</sic> of <del>his</del> the body&#44; but<lb/> he is again forced into a piece of clay <del>of clay</del>&#44;<lb/> which enfeebles <del>his</del> its faculties&#44; and deprives <del>him</del><lb/> it of the highest joy&#44; to be with God&#44; to<lb/> know the truth.  I <sic>recieved</sic> lately a book&#44; of<lb/> which a very few copies exist&#44; viz&#58; The book<lb/> of <add>Hebrew</add> <persName>Tobias</persName> the Physician the grandson of the author of<lb/> &#8220;Beginning of Wisdom&#8221; <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; in which a great deal of Kabbalah and<lb/> physical matters are mingled in the same<lb/> manner that his grandfather has <del>intermixed</del> mixed up<lb/> <del>the</del> Kabbalah with the most sublime moral<lb/> philosophy.  One passage of this book is<lb/> remarkable and has a strong bearing upon<lb/> our subject&#44; wherefore I shall give you an<lb/> epitome of it&#59; bear in mind&#44; the author was<lb/> a Kabbalist of the dark ages&#58; &#8220;The principle of<lb/> <persName>Rabbi Jacob Yakof</persName> &#40;Kiddushin Vol 39&#41; <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#8220;the reward to virtue is not in this world&#8221; &#40;but<lb/> in a world to come&#41; has met with decided<lb/> opposition among the Rabbis and among<lb/> the doctors of our age&#59; they supposed&#44; the<lb/> soul <del>is</del> in a pure state is unfit to <sic>recieve</sic><lb/> either reward or punishment&#44; wherefore<lb/> they said a resurrection of the body must<lb/> take place&#59; and since so many Jews died<lb/> for their faith&#44; or pined away in oppression<lb/> and distress because of their Religion&#44; they<lb/> say&#44; the resurrection must take place shortly after<lb/> the coming of the messiah&#44; that those pious<lb/> martyrs may be rewarded and enabled to rejoice in the<lb/> final triumph of Judaism&#59; but as to those<lb/> who adhere to the principle of <persName>Rabbi Jacob Yakof</persName><lb/> the doctrine of a resurrection of the body is<lb/> altogether superfluous.&#8221;  I hope my opponents<lb/> will not excommunicate this old <del>author</del> writer.</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">fol. 3.</p>
				<p><del>wherefor they painted the</del> would called by them <add>Hebrew</add> or also<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add> with such splendid colours&#59; but<lb/> others made <del>the</del> a mistake <del>to take</del> in assuming this <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> for the future state of life of the same human<lb/> beings&#44; which produced the <sic>phantastic</sic> doctrine<lb/> of the resurrection of the body.  And even if<lb/> we take for granted&#44; that this world will be<lb/> destroyed and re&#45;created&#44; still the resurrection<lb/> is an impossibility.  In the crust of the earth we<lb/> see&#44; that the former destructions of organic life<lb/> <del>was</del> were effected by water&#44; as the remains of marine<lb/> animals in all parts of the globe plainly show&#59;<lb/> the water stood very long over the whole globe&#44;<lb/> which the thick strata having settled down from<lb/> standing water plainly indicate&#59; the organic<lb/> beings were buried under the mud&#44; which the<lb/> water was mixed with&#44; and after the <sic>seperation</sic><lb/> of land and water&#44; volcanic eruptions threw<lb/> the organic matter upon the surface of the earth&#44;<lb/> as some volcanoes do even in our times&#44; and<lb/> of which the surface of the earth bears evidence&#59; after which<lb/> <del>then</del> a new creation of organic being commen&#44;<lb/>ced.  No seed&#44; no egg&#44; no being of former<lb/> kingdoms of life could escape the general<lb/> destruction&#44; nor remain uncorrupted for so<lb/> long a period of time in the dissolving water<lb/> of the sea&#59; consequently each successive <del>creation</del> change<lb/> was an independent <del>one</del>&#44; entirely new&#44; a creation.<lb/>  It cannot be called a gradual transition&#59; for<lb/> each successive creation represents a greater variety<lb/> of kinds&#44; more <del>accomplished</del> complicated and more artful<lb/> organizations&#44; so that only the inorganic matter<lb/> was improved by the previous creations&#44; but the<lb/> animate beings themselves were always created<lb/> anew and independent of these former existing.</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>This destructive and re&#45;creative process we meet<lb/> with six times in the crust of the earth &#40;remember<lb/> the six days of creation&#41; consequently we are bound to<lb/> say &#8220;these are the laws of nature established by the will of<lb/> God for such revolutions.&#8221;  If now the world<lb/> should be destroyed and re&#45;created once more&#44;<lb/> it must certainly be in the same way as formerly&#59;<lb/> all bodies must be dissolved&#44; the organic matter improved&#44;<lb/> which will be thrown up by <del>thrown</del> volcanic eruptions<lb/> of the earth&#39;s surface&#44; and a new and independent<lb/> creation be commenced.  Now it would <del>it</del> be possible<lb/> enough&#44; that the same souls with their devel&#45;<lb/>oped capacities&#44; acquired abilities&#44; increased ener<lb/>gies and pure&#44; consciousness of their former<lb/> state be re&#45;clothed in an improved organic<lb/> body&#44; and live again a human life though<lb/> of a higher order&#59; still this very body in which<lb/> we are clothed now cannot resurrect to be<lb/> once more our garment as the old doctrine<lb/> of resurrection asserts&#59; then it must therefore be a new<lb/> creation and no such thing as a resurrection.<lb/>  I hope you will confess&#44; that I seriously<lb/> reflected on my subject&#44; and that I can in<lb/> some measure account for that fatal &#8220;no&#44;&#8221;<lb/> which I uttered in <placeName>Charleston</placeName>&#59; I must tell<lb/> you if my opponents can give as much<lb/> ground for their &#8220;yes&#8221; I am perfectly<lb/> satisfied&#59; But still if you can prove<lb/> by the bible&#44; that I am bound to believe<lb/> a literal resurrection of the body&#44; I shall<lb/> calmly lay aside all these insurmountable<lb/> difficulties&#44; and&#8212;believe.  I am now<lb/> about writing an Essay on immortality&#44; which<lb/> I trust&#44; since it is a reading matter to every<lb/> man and not merely to the Jew&#44; will be</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p>published next summer&#44; and I hope&#44; it will<lb/> diffuse better views on that important sub<lb/>ject&#44; than those entertained now.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Assuring you of my best friendship</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">and esteem I am always</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">truly yours</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">Isaac M. Wise</persName> DD</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
