<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
						<collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning</collection>
						<idno>LSDCBx3FF11_1</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Moise, R. C.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, I, Rev.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes">25 February</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0001_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0001_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0001_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="ilcajs_b3f11_0001_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p><addressee>Rev I Leeser</addressee></p>
				<p rend="align(right)"><date>Feb 25th</date></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Dear Friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">It  was with deep re&#45;<lb/>gret that I heard through our friend <persName>Rebecca</persName> that<lb/> you had been sick &#38; that you were still feeble<lb/> although recovered. I ardently hope you may<lb/> be perfectly well ere this <sic>receit</sic> of this. I fear<lb/> you exert your physical strength that it may<lb/> keep pace with the vigor of your mental power<lb/> now that I must ask you not to do for the<lb/> activity of your mind tends to weaken a constitu<lb/>tion not naturally robust.  If you would keep<lb/> your mind in repose I am satisfied your<lb/> health would improve I must beg you to be<lb/> more watchful of it &#38; remember you belong<lb/> to your people who cannot afford that you<lb/> exercise your strength to its inquiry. You are too<lb/> important to our spiritual health for us to allow<lb/> you without a caution to neglect yourself.<lb/> My son begs to be kindly remembered I know not<lb/> whether my commendation or your own kind attentions<lb/> have impressed him so favorably but certain it is<lb/> that he awards you all the merit you do readily<lb/> deserve.  <persName>S A</persName> has just come home from a long<lb/> visit to <placeName>Johns island</placeName>.  She is much improved in health<lb/> &#38; looks from the change&#59; pure country air &#38; the repose</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>which roaming in the woods &#38; communing with nature in<lb/> her unsophisticated state is well calculated to improve<lb/> the health &#38; the heart. The young people have had it quite<lb/> gay this winter there have been several private balls &#38;<lb/> sociables &#38; the arrival of strangers in the winter season<lb/> keeps those who desire society constantly in it. I have<lb/> been in such close mourning for the 2 past years<lb/> that I have been nowhere but where misfortune &#38; ill health<lb/> preside.  I however am determined if God protects us from any<lb/> ill I will for my Childrens sake visit &#38; have company at home<lb/> &#38; then I dare say catch a portion of their gaiety Even though<lb/> you were industrious in your efforts that my son should<lb/> captivate some of the fair assembly at the <add>&#63;</add> Malgr&#233;<lb/> toute cela he has returned unscathed not but that I<lb/> should be delighted for him to marry for there only is true<lb/> happiness to be enjoyed <add>&#63;</add> the marriage is of<lb/> two of congenial feelings &#38; habits.  The new minister<lb/> is expected in <date>May</date> I do not anticipate so beneficial a<lb/> change as many.  I am of a strange turn when content<lb/> with present state of things I prefer no change even<lb/> though it may be a beneficial one I always fear to<lb/> require too much both from Creator &#38; fellow<lb/> Mortals it is more a superstitious fear than an<lb/> amiable trait For I have found that to rest our<lb/> hopes too <add>&#63;</add> on any one desire often ends in<lb/> disappointment And the trials I have had to encounter<lb/> have checked all aspiring desires. I am on the <add>&#63;</add><lb/><add>&#63;</add> to receive my daguerres I presume you know<lb/> <persName>Rebecca</persName> is going to send me her &#38; her dear pets it is</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>so very kind of her to gratify me by such an attention.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">What a delightful discovery is that of <persName>Daguerres</persName><lb/> lot certainly should be much better than the<lb/> ancients for see the advantages we possess <persName>Daguerres</persName><lb/> that give us the positive though inanimate presence<lb/> of those we love. Rail roads that swift as Eagles<lb/> wings bring them to us &#38; most extraordinarily the Telegra<lb/>phic wires&#44; which with a velocity incredible bring us in<lb/>formation &#40;of those separated from us&#41; of sorrow or hap&#45;<lb/>piness&#33;  Yet man is no better his passions still<lb/> unchecked his propensities still leading him to evil<lb/> temptation lives with her smiles in spite of all the<lb/> advantages which this age of improvement &#38; discovery<lb/> affords us. <persName>Mrs. Henry</persName> is better&#44;  Rumor with her poisoned<lb/> tongue has said that a change had come over here relig<lb/>ious feelings &#38; that she did not find that consolation in her<lb/> own faith that she required. This I could not bring my<lb/> heart to believe &#38; contradicted the report although it<lb/> came from authority hard to doubt. I could believe<lb/> that with the body in torture &#38; the mind enfeebled<lb/> that she might be vacillating &#40;because my friend wants<lb/> division of character&#41; &#38; beg the prayers of any good<lb/> man But as I had acted with her had seen how com<lb/>pletely she was satisfied with her own faith&#44; I rejected<lb/> the idea and believed that as she regained her health<lb/> she would regain confidence in her own faith&#33;<lb/>  <persName>C&#39;ol. Myers</persName> has written to beg that all reports<lb/> injurious to him should be refuted for there was<lb/> no truth in it. <persName>Mrs. Bryan</persName> is with her &#38; it<lb/> is said that <persName>Mrs. Henry</persName> will never allow</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>to leave her again she is expected to visit <placeName>Charleston</placeName><lb/> as soon as she is able to travel &#38; then I will<lb/> give you a  more correct statement &#8212; Remember<lb/> me kindly to my friends the <persName>Levys</persName> &#38; all who<lb/> remember me.  I am now writing without being<lb/> able to see&#44; but I have had so many interruptions<lb/> that I am determined to finish in the dark<lb/> That you may soon be restored to health<lb/> is the sincere wish of your friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName role="author">R C Moise</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
