<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M., Dr.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS Isaac Leeser Collection</repository>
                        <collection>The Library of the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate
                            Learning</collection>
                        <idno>LSDCBx2FF6_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Mayer, M.,
                            Dr.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac,
                            Rev.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1859-03">29 March 1859</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1859-03">29 March 5619</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f6_0006_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f6_0006_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f6_0006_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="ilcajs_b2f6_0006_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Charleston, S. C.</placeName>
                <date>March 29 5619/1859</date>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Rev. Mr. I. Leeser</addressee>, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My dear Sir—</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">! <add>שמע בן אחיכם</add> Although I am<lb/> fully confident that
                the friendship and regard which, notwithstanding<lb/> our difference of religious
                views, you have at various times manifested<lb/> towards me, would be satisfied with
                the above open and sincere<lb/> confession on my part, in reply to your message
                conveyed to me, last<lb/> night, by <persName>Mr. Hart</persName>, yet, to show you
                that I reciprocate those<lb/> feelings, I deem it incumbent upon me to give you a
                full explanati-<lb/>on of my <hi rend="underline">long</hi> silence and <hi
                    rend="underline">seeming</hi> neglect.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is certainly unnecessary to assure you that neither ill
                feeling<lb/> nor <sic>wilful</sic> disregard caused that silence; my friendship and
                respect<lb/> for you have not in the least diminished; I could refer to many<lb/> of
                your acquaintances in this place, that I do not allow any<lb/> opportunity to pass,
                without expressing my highest appreciation<lb/> for you; nay! I would even defend
                you against all insinuations<lb/> of your <hi rend="underline">friends</hi>, who
                deem it proper to sound the praise of their<lb/> favorites at your expense; and
                    <persName>Rev. Mr. H. P. Jacobs</persName> can tell you<lb/> that, when you
                announced the discontinuance of the translation of<lb/> the Cozri by <persName>Dr
                    Fiskel</persName> (why this course?) I contemplated to<lb/> substitute the
                deficiency by my own translation. Circumstances<lb/> which led to my silence have
                prevented me to carry out that con-<lb/>templated work. So much upon this point.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And now, in the full expectation that you will make no farther<lb/>
                use of what I shall have to say, I will fully explain those cir-<lb/>cumstances. For
                the last two years, I have made the sad experience</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>that the path of a minister, especially of a Jewish one, is not strewn<lb/> with
                roses. I will not enter into details, but merely beg of you not<lb/> to base any
                conclusion or <sic>judgement</sic> upon what you might have<lb/> heard, or should
                still hear, as long as you have not heard also<lb/> the other party, my humble self
                    <add>דברים, לב, ט"ו !וישמן ישורון ויבעט</add> Thank God! not-<lb/>withstanding
                all the harassing annoyances and persecutions which<lb/> I have had to endure both
                on the part of those that are “with me,”<lb/> and those that are “against me,” my
                character stands forth<lb/> unstained and unscathed, and I have the consolation
                that<lb/> my course was one of the most uncompromising honesty and<lb/>
                straightforwardness. Yet, I must confess that all these experiences<lb/> have in so
                far discouraged me, that I do my duty to its fullest<lb/> extent, but abstain from
                all further cooperation and interference<lb/> in the religious affairs of our
                people, unless something <hi rend="underline">national</hi><lb/> appeals to my
                Jewish heart, in such cases I rush to the<lb/> post of duty with all zeal and
                enthusiasm. Have you read, for the last 18 months,<lb/> one line of controversy
                published by me in any of our Papers,<lb/> here or in <placeName>Europe</placeName>?
                I can assure you that I have received many<lb/> letters even blaming me for my
                inactivity; yet I still continue<lb/> to be silent; nay! if I had not still the hope
                for better things<lb/> to come, I should have retired from public life
                altogether.<lb/> Under such circumstances it is but natural, that even my<lb/>
                private correspondence must suffer; it so happens that you are<lb/> among the rest.
                I have yet a letter of <persName>Dr Holdheim</persName>, dated<lb/>
                <date>March 1. 1858</date>—to answer; I tried it often, but could not suc-<lb/>ceed.
                    <persName>Dr Philippson</persName> has not had a line from me since last
                    <date>August</date>,<lb/> and then I <hi rend="underline">merely</hi> complained
                of the irregularity with which I<lb/> receive the publications of “the Institute”.
                    <persName>Stein</persName> in <placeName>Frankfort</placeName><lb/> has been
                expecting a letter from me, ever since last <date>Juli.</date> Coming</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>nearer home, <persName>Einhorn</persName> whom I <hi rend="underline">must</hi>
                regard as one of my best friends<lb/> living, has to write two letters to my one,
                and others do not fare<lb/> better. I trust, as I do not wish to continue in this
                strain, that this<lb/> exposition will be accepted by you as a satisfactory apology
                for<lb/> my seeming neglect. In future, I shall endeavor to do better.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have received the first number of the weekly “Occident.”<lb/> I
                must congratulate you upon its appearance; it is <hi rend="underline">by far</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">the</hi><lb/> handsomest Jewish sheet of all I know; it really
                deserves to prosper.<lb/> I say this from the depth of my heart, altho' I cannot
                always<lb/> agree with the contents &amp; tendency of your publications. Should<lb/>
                you wish my literary co-operation, I am ready to serve you; but,<lb/> as you must
                perceive from the above, I cannot promise any <hi rend="underline"
                >original</hi><lb/> matter; and even translations of mine must not bear my name.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Here I am reminded to explain a fact which must seem to<lb/> you to
                be in contradiction with my exposition above: I allude<lb/> to the publication of
                “Hects Biblical History for Israelitish<lb/> Schools.” The work was ordered and
                undertaken by the School Com-<lb/>mittee of <persName>Dr Adler's</persName>
                Congregation, who appointed and requested me to make the translation. But I can show
                you from my cor-<lb/>respondence with <persName>Dr A.</persName> upon the subject,
                that I did not even respond<lb/> officially to that committee, but corresponded only
                privately with<lb/> the Doctor, and yielded only to <hi rend="underline">his
                    personal</hi>, earnest and re-<lb/>peated solicitations. All I received for my
                labor, are <hi rend="underline">two</hi> copies<lb/> of the work, one from
                    <persName>Dr A.</persName>, and another from the publishers.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You undoubtedly have known that I suffered intensely last<lb/>
                summer, that I was confined to my bed,—with very short inter-<lb/>vals—for 15 weeks;
                9 here and 6 in <placeName>New York</placeName>. But what<lb/> do you say to this:
                with the sole exceptoin of <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> (and<lb/> of course
                    <persName>Dr Adler</persName>) not one of the Reverend (?) gentlemen ever</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>came to see me; <persName>Dr Fishel</persName>, <persName>Mr. Lyons</persName> &amp;
                    <persName>Isaacs</persName> would not even speak to me,<lb/> when we met.
                Indeed! I do not care about it; men who can thus<lb/> forget their position, thus
                violate the very first law of religion, and<lb/> manifest such a stupid fanaticism,
                are better “left severely alone”<lb/> in their glory and “<add>?</add>.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I must let you also into the secret of <hi rend="underline">an</hi>
                <persName>Mortara</persName> movement<lb/> here. Having been opposed by the
                    <persName>Moise</persName> clique and others, the<lb/> meeting was a pitiful
                one; hardly 2 dozen Jews were present.<lb/> The Jews <del>only</del>, I am
                convinced, are united by their national<lb/> feeling only when there is something
                    “to—'<hi rend="underline">fress</hi>'”. A comparison<lb/> between the Swiss
                treaty affair and the <persName>Morara</persName> case, on one hand, and the<lb/>
                last Anniversary Dinner of our H. B. S. on the other, prove this fact beyond<lb/>
                all earthly doubt. I must confess, the more I see and hear of our<lb/> people in
                this country, the more I am convinced that <persName>Moses</persName>, were<lb/> he
                now to come amongst us, would again exclaim: !<add>Hebrew</add><lb/> While they
                would allow no opportunity to pass, whenever it is in their<lb/> power, to oppress
                &amp; persecute their own people and make them<lb/> feel their superiority—however
                questionable and counterfeited it<lb/> may be, they crouch and cringe before those
                of another creed, and<lb/> prove <sic>contemtible</sic> cowards whenever they are
                called upon to stand<lb/> up to their rights or defend their own Jewish-national
                affairs.<lb/> And in no city <del>at</del> is this more glaringly evident than in
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>.<lb/> There they could exercise some
                influence, but they neglect it, to<lb/> please &amp; flatter their Christian
                fellow-citizens; the defeat of <persName>Mr.<lb/> Mordecai</persName>, last fall, is
                exclusively attributable to the treachery of<lb/> his correligionists, especially,
                    <hi rend="underline">not exclusively</hi>, in the orthodox congregation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But I must conclude; accept <persName>Mrs. M.'s</persName> &amp; my
                own best regard<lb/> &amp; wishes, and write soon to</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">Yours, most friendly</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">Dr M Mayer</persName>
            </p>
            <p>By the bye,: How do you stand with</p>
            <p><persName>Dr Deutsch</persName>? Please send me the controversy</p>
            <p>between the unknown Jew, yourself &amp; <persName>Mr. Morais</persName>. I have heard
                of it, a few days</p>
            <p>ago, but never seen it. You know what controversy I am alluding to.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
