<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-01">January 9, 1863</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-01">5623</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_11.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >miscellany</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold">Board of Delegates of American Israel-<lb/>ites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">At a special meeting of the Executive Committee of<lb/> the Board of
                Delegates of American Israelites, held at<lb/> the city of
                    <placeName>New-York</placeName>, on <date>Thursday evening, January<lb/> 8th,
                    1863</date>, <persName>Henry I. Hart, Esq.</persName>, President in the
                chair:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The president laid before the committee a copy of<lb/> General Order
                No. 11, issued by <persName>General U. S. Grant</persName>,<lb/> commanding
                Department of the <placeName>Tennessee</placeName>, <date>December<lb/> 17th,
                    1862</date>, and also communications received by him<lb/> from
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, with reference to the revocation of<lb/> the
                same. Whereupon the following preamble and<lb/> resolutions were proposed, seconded
                and unanimously<lb/> adopted:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Whereas</emph>, The attention of this committee
                has been<lb/> called by the chairman to the following "General Or-<lb/>der No.
                11":</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">HEADQUARTERS THIRTEENTH ARMY CORPS,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">DEPARTMENT OF THE <placeName>TENNESSEE</placeName>,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>OXFORD, MISS.</placeName>, <date>DEC. 17,
                1862</date>.</p>
            <p>General Order No. 11.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Jews, as a class, violating every regulation of<lb/> trade
                established by the Treasury Department, also<lb/> department orders, are hereby
                expelled from the de-<lb/>partment within twenty-four hours from the receipt<lb/> of
                this order by post commanders.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">They will see that all this class of people are fur-<lb/>nished with
                passes and required to leave; and any<lb/> one returning after such notification
                will be arrested<lb/> and held in confinement until an opportunity occurs of<lb/>
                sending them out as prisoners, unless furnished with<lb/> permits from these
                headquarters.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">No passes will be given these people to visit head-<lb/>quarters for
                the purpose of making personal applica-<lb/>tion for trade permits.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">By order of <persName>MAJOR-GENERAL GRANT</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>John A. Rawlins</persName>, A. A. G.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Be it therefore</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That we have heard with
                surprise and<lb/> indignation the intelligence that in the present century<lb/> and
                in this land of freedom and equality, an officer of<lb/> the <placeName>United
                    States</placeName> should have promulgated an order<lb/> worthy of despotic
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName> in the dark ages of the<lb/> world's history.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That in behalf of the
                Israelites of the<lb/>
                <placeName>United States</placeName>, we enter our firm and determined pro-<lb/>test
                against this illegal, unjust and tyrannical man-<lb/>date, depriving American
                citizens of the Jewish<lb/> faith, of their precious rights, driving them,
                because<lb/> of their religious profession, from their business and<lb/> homes by
                the military authority and in pursuance of<lb/> an inequitable proscription.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That the Israelites of the
                    <placeName>United States</placeName><lb/> expect no more and will be content
                with no less than<lb/> equal privileges with their fellow citizens, in the
                en-<lb/>joyment of "life, liberty, and the pursuit of happi-<lb/>ness," as
                guaranteed by the Constitution of this<lb/> republic.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That it is peculiarly painful
                for the Israel-<lb/>ites of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who have
                freely tendered<lb/> their blood and treasure in defense of the Union they<lb/>
                love, to observe this uncalled for and inequitable<lb/> discrimination against them.
                Claiming to be second<lb/> to no class of citizens in support of the
                constitutional<lb/> government, they regard with sadness and indignation<lb/> this
                contumely upon the Jewish name, this insult to<lb/> them as a community, on the
                ostensible ground that<lb/> individuals supposed to be "Jews" have violated
                re-<lb/>gulations of trade, established by the Treasury De-<lb/>partment "and
                department orders."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>. That it is in the highest
                degree obnoxious<lb/> to them, as it must be to all fair-minded American
                cit-<lb/>izens, for the general body to be made accountable<lb/> for acts of
                particular persons <emph rend="italics">supposed</emph> to belong to<lb/> their
                denomination, but, as has been frequently de-<lb/>monstrated, in many cases really
                professing other<lb/> creeds. That if an individual be guilty of an infrac-<lb/>tion
                of discipline or offense against military law or<lb/> treasury regulations,
                punishment should be visited<lb/> upon him alone, and the religious community
                to<lb/> which he is presumed to be attached should not be<lb/> subjected to insult,
                obloquy, or disregard of its rights<lb/> as a penalty for individual offenses.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That the thanks of this
                committee and of<lb/> the Israelites of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, be
                and they are<lb/> hereby tendered to <persName>Major-General H. W.
                    Halleck</persName>,<lb/> General-in-Chief <placeName>U. S. A.</placeName>, for
                the promptitude with<lb/> which he revoked <persName>General Grant's</persName>
                unjust and out-<lb/>rageous order, as soon as it was brought to his
                atten-<lb/>tion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Resolved</emph>, That a copy of these
                resolutions, duly<lb/> attested, be transmitted to the President of the
                    <placeName>United<lb/> States</placeName>, the Secretary of War,
                    <persName>Major-General Halleck</persName>,<lb/> and <persName>Major-General
                    Grant</persName>, and that the same be com-<lb/>municated to the press for
                publication.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">[From the minutes.]</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)"><persName>MYER S. ISAACS</persName>, Secretary.</p>
            <p><placeName>New-York</placeName>, <date>January 9, 5623, 1863</date>.</p>
            <p/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold"><persName>GRANT'S</persName> ORDER EXPELLING THE</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold">JEWS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold">Why It was Issued—The History of a Cot-<lb/>-ton Speculation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><emph rend="italics">From the
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> Notional Democrat</emph>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We have already published <persName>General Grant's</persName>
                in-<lb/>famous order expelling the Jews from his mili-<lb/>tary department. We now
                give the published<lb/> record of the <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName> Superior
                Court in re-<lb/>ference to the suit brought by <persName>Jesse Grant</persName>,
                father<lb/> of <persName>General Grant</persName>, to recover his share of the<lb/>
                profits of the cotton speculation in which he<lb/> was engaged with the
                    <persName>Mack Brothers</persName>, his Hebrew<lb/> partners.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">SUPERIOR COURT.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"General Term-<persName>Jesse R. Grant</persName> vs.
                    <persName>Mack<lb/> Brothers</persName>. <persName>Judge Hoadly</persName>
                delivered the opinion.<lb/> The case was reserved from special term on<lb/> demurer
                to the petition. The action was insti-<lb/>tuted for the settlement of a partnership
                ac-<lb/>count.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The plaintiff avers that in <date>December, 1862</date>, he<lb/>
                entered into partnership with defendants, for the<lb/> purchase of cotton in the
                Military Department<lb/> of <persName>U. S. Grant</persName>; the condition of the
                agreement<lb/> that defendants were to furnish the capital and<lb/> the men to
                purchase and ship the cotton, and<lb/> the plaintiff to procure at the headquarters of<lb/>
                <persName>General Grant</persName> a permit to purchase it, secure the<lb/>
                transportation, and such other facilities as might<lb/> be consistent with the
                usages and interests of<lb/> the army. The plaintiff was to receive one-fourth<lb/>
                share of the net profits of sales after deducting<lb/> fro mgross proceeds the
                necessary expenses.<lb/> The petition further states that there was a real-<lb/>ized
                profit in the defendants' favor of not less<lb/> than $40,000, and that they refuse
                to render an<lb/> account, or pay the plaintiff his proportion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The defendants claim that the plaintiff con-<lb/>tributed by his
                own showing neither capital nor<lb/> lawful service to the copartnership, and
                that<lb/> their agreement to pay him a share of the<lb/> profits is, therefore,
                without sufficient consider-<lb/>ation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The Court cannot presume that the plaintiff<lb/> intended to allege
                that he undertook that which<lb/> was prohibited by law. His acts and promises<lb/>
                may have been illegal, and the partnership one<lb/> for a forbidden enterprise; but
                in the absence of<lb/> an answer so averring the Court cannot assume<lb/> it, unless
                the averments are inconsistent with<lb/> any other theory.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The purchase of cotton in the military de-<lb/>partment commanded
                by <persName>General Grant</persName> was il-<lb/>legal, unless carried on by
                permission of the<lb/> President, obtained through the Treasury
                De-<lb/>partment.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The plaintiff avers that he was to go to the<lb/> headquarters of
                    <persName>General Grant</persName> and procure a<lb/> permit to purchase cotton.
                Whether this was<lb/> expected to be obtained from the General<lb/> himself, from
                some member of his staff, or a<lb/> Treasury agent at headquarters, is not
                stated.<lb/> Whether the plaintiff was to procure it as a per-<lb/>sonal favor, or
                by the use of personal influence,<lb/> or in the ordinary mode of business, is
                not<lb/> shown. The Court could not presume he was to<lb/> get his permit from an
                officer not authorized by<lb/> law to give it, or that he was to procure it as
                the<lb/> reward of personal, political or other illegiti-<lb/>mate influence. They
                must rather infer that he<lb/> proposed to solicit and procure a permit in the<lb/>
                ordinary and proper way, from a Treasury agent<lb/> having authority to issue
                it.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"Again. It is averred that plaintiff was to and<lb/> did secure
                transportation. This may have been<lb/> done by procuring from some quartermaster,
                or<lb/> other officer controlling it, the improper and ille-<lb/>gal use of
                Government horses and wagons, or<lb/> steamboats; or he may have hired horses
                and<lb/> wagons from the people of the country, and se-<lb/>cured steamboat
                transportation in the usual<lb/> way. The mere fact that he was to procure<lb/>
                transportation at the headquarters of <persName>General<lb/> Grant</persName> is not
                decisive.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"The other item of service, the 'procuring of<lb/> such other
                facilities as might be consistent with<lb/> the usages and interests of the army,'
                is open to<lb/> the same double reading. The facilities, what-<lb/>ever they were,
                may <emph rend="italics">have been procured by honest<lb/> or dishonest
                    influences</emph>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"For these reasons, the <sic>defence</sic> suggested must<lb/> be
                presented by answer. The theory that the em-<lb/>ployment of the plaintiff was to
                procure the ille-<lb/>gal co operation of the military in a private en-<lb/>terprise
                must be alleged by sworn answer. If<lb/> true, it was equally disgraceful to the
                defendants<lb/> and the plaintiff, and, if proven, would insure<lb/> the dismissal
                of the petition with reprobation to<lb/> the two parties, upon the principle, among
                oth-<lb/>ers, <emph rend="italics">in pari delicto, potior est condito
                    defendentis</emph>.<lb/> Demurrer overruled and leave to answer."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Judge Storer</persName> agreed with the other members
                of<lb/> the Court on the question of the pleadings, "and<lb/> felt constrained to
                say that the whole of the<lb/> trade, as disclosed in this proceeding, was not<lb/>
                only disgraceful, but tends directly to disgrace<lb/> the country. It is the price
                of blood."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The following comments from the <placeName>New York</placeName><lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">World</emph> will show the enormity of the infamy of<lb/> this
                cotton speculation, and the reason why <persName>Gen-<lb/>eral Grant</persName>
                expelled the Jews:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"Even if it should turn out that <persName>Jesse
                Grant</persName><lb/> had a Treasury permit for this particular specula-<lb/>tion,
                that fact would not relieve the reputation<lb/> of <persName>General
                    Grant</persName>. If <persName>Jesse Grant</persName> had such a<lb/> permit, he
                must have got it through his son's in-<lb/>fluence. By his own showing, he obtained
                it at<lb/> his son's headquarters. Except for his relation-<lb/>ship to the
                Commanding General, any other citi-<lb/>zen could have procured it as easily as he.
                What<lb/> he made a matter of bargain and sale was his in-<lb/>fluence with
                    <persName>General Grant</persName>; what he stipulated<lb/> to receive for it
                was one-fourth of the net profits,<lb/> although he put in no capital and ran no
                risk.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">"There is still a darker shade to this transac-<lb/>tion, but it is
                not yet so well authenticated. A<lb/> correspondent writes to us upon
                information<lb/> which he received of one of <persName>Jesse Grant's</persName>
                neigh-<lb/>bors, that when <persName>Grant</persName> the father told
                    <persName>Grant</persName> the<lb/> son that the <persName>Macks</persName>
                refused to settle with him,<lb/> the General sent them word that unless they<lb/>
                promptly did so he would expel all the Jews<lb/> from his department, a threat which
                he soon<lb/> after made good by his well-known order for the<lb/> expulsion of the
                Jews. This is the first explana-<lb/>tion we have ever seen of the motive of that
                un-<lb/>accountable and discreditable order, and if <persName>Mack<lb/>
                    Brothers</persName> are really Jews, the explanation is not<lb/> incredible,
                considering that the main fact of the<lb/> cotton speculation is fully
                established."</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
