<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Solomon, D.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0006</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Solomon, D.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Mobile, AL</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1846-01" source="" attested="yes">January 4 1846</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0006_1R.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0006_1V.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0006_2R.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0006_2V.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Mobile</placeName><add>&#63;</add> <date>January 4 1846</date>.</p>
				<p><addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">My dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">Your favor <date>25st</date> ulto came duly to<lb/> hand this day and I had become somewhat fearful that my<lb/> letter had miscarried in consequence of not hearing from you<lb/> at an earlier day but I suppose and know that like myself<lb/> your moments are so engrossed that you have barely time to<lb/> attend to the more pressing duties which claim your attention</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">When I left <placeName>Mobile</placeName> last summer I had firmly intended to<lb/> call upon you and have a long conference with you in several<lb/> subjects of <del>gr</del> considerable importance to the cause of our<lb/> religion but being detained at <placeName>N arlington</placeName> on my way<lb/> I was obliged to omit my intended stay at <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> whilst journeying northward.  Contemplating to return to<lb/> your city for a few days during my stay at the<lb/> <placeName>north</placeName>.  Engagements of various character so far<lb/> interfered with my views as to render it impracticable<lb/> and <del>nt</del> I had so timed myself on my return trip<lb/> home reference to the Holidays. that I could not<lb/> delay a moment in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.  I regret exceedingly<lb/> that I did not have the pleasure of meeting you</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>but in the event of my again traveling northward in the<lb/> ensuing summer I shall certainly make arrangements to be<lb/> with you for a day or two under any circumstances or<lb/> &#38;  In relation to your subscribers in this place please<lb/> mention the amounts due by each for I have no copy of<lb/> the letter in which I forwarded the remittance and do not<lb/> remember how the amounts were paid.  Please specify the<lb/> sum due by each to the end of the <hi rend="underline">third volume</hi>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I will see <persName>Goldsmith</persName> and he will I feel satisfied<lb/> continue his subscription.  he was probably absent from<lb/> the city when his number was left remaining in the<lb/> Post office.</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">Consecration for Synagogue in <placeName>Mobile</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We afford one peculiar qualification to announce<lb/> to you the success which has attended our efforts in this<lb/> city in the establishment of a congregation and place<lb/> of worship.  On <date>Friday evening 27th Kislev</date>&#44;<lb/> corresponding with <date>26 Dec.</date> we opened for the first time<lb/> the new <del>place of</del> building which <del>we have&#63;</del> had latterly<add>&#63;</add> been<lb/> preparing for <del>the</del> our use.  It was originally used by<lb/> the Episcopalians from whom it passed into the<lb/> hands of the Unitarians and upon the disorganization<lb/> of that society in our city the Universalists <del>obtained</del> leased<lb/> it and <del>not</del> used by them during the preceding year.<lb/>  That Sect having <del>obtained</del> purchased another building<lb/> the congregation concluded to leave this one and<lb/> have taken it for a term of years.  We have <del>filled</del><lb/> fitted it up&#44; in a style of simplicity and neatness which</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>will accord it a place amongst the most costly of our synagogues<lb/> in this country.  The design we have had in view was<lb/> beauty and taste without any ostentatious or gaudy display<lb/> of architecture.  The work therefore is plain yet so<lb/> exceedingly neat and all the appointments being so<lb/> complete even to the covering of the entire floor that the<lb/> <hi rend="underline">coup d&#39;oeuil</hi> strikes every beholder with admiration and<lb/> satisfaction.  The opening services were under the direction<lb/> of <persName>W. Da Silva</persName> <sic>formely</sic> of <placeName>New York</placeName> who has been appointed<lb/> as <del>h</del> reader to the congregation.  In the absence of a choir<lb/> and from the fact that many and in fact a majority of<lb/> our members are unacquainted with the Portuguese<lb/> mode of reading&#44; the <del>services</del> ceremonies were<lb/> very simple and included <del><add>&#63;</add></del> little more<lb/> than the ordinary service <del>of</del> for the Eve of the<lb/> <date>Sabbath</date> with the addition of a discourse delivered by<lb/> <persName role="author">Col. D. Solomon</persName>.  It will suffice perhaps to express to you<lb/> the universal satisfaction <del>which</del> with which his remarks were<lb/> received.  There has been a general feeling of<lb/> favour and interest manifested in our undertaking by all<lb/> our coreligionists in the city and I trust I will not<lb/> be considerd as neglecting others if I particularly name<lb/> the zeal with which the President of the Congregation<lb/> &#40;<persName>Mail I Jones Eq</persName>&#41; has conducted the enterprise until its<lb/> happy consummation.  We are now fairly embarked under<lb/> the most auspicious circumstance and feel every confidence in progressing rapidly and satisfactorily.&#8221;</p>
				<p><placeName>Mobile</placeName> <date>January 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date>.</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>Relative to the matter of the Jewish Publication Society and also<lb/> in regard to your edition of the Pentateuch I will lay them<lb/> before the Board of <add>&#63;</add> and the congregation and hope<lb/> that we shall be able to do something for you.  <del>one dem</del> The<lb/> demands which we have lately made upon the liberality of<lb/> our friends in the completion of our undertaking here makes<lb/> me somewhat fearful that <del>th</del> all the success I could wish<lb/> for may not perhaps attend my presentation of the projects.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Please let me know whether you have any <del>edit</del> separate<lb/> numbers of the &#8220;<hi rend="underline">Daily Prayer Book</hi>&#8221; and what would be<lb/> the price for 10 or 15 of them.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In regard to my next number of &#8220;Short Sermons&#8221; I<lb/> have not commenced it because I did not know<lb/> whether you <del>might</del> would deem them worthy of publication<lb/> and was awaiting your reply.  Keep a place for me<lb/> however in your paper until the <date>20th</date> of the month<lb/> when I will endeavour to have another number in<lb/> your hands so that it can be published in <date>February</date><add>&#63;</add> number.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It would meet the views of your friends here<lb/> and might <del>perpa</del> perhaps serve some what the course of<lb/> our religion by publishing that portion of their letter<lb/> which I have marked relative to the opening of<lb/> our new place of worship.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You may expect to hear from me again in<lb/> something less than ten days.</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Very truly yr friend.</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">D Solomon</persName></p>
				<p>Excuse the wretched writing</p>
				<p>but I send this in haste</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
