<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Boston, MA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1848-01">January 11, 1848</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_8_1.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_8_2.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >miscellany</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>shown themselves as capable of discharging their<lb/> duty as any of their
                competitors; and that in various<lb/> other capacities, as well as in the pursuit of
                science<lb/> and art, they have shown themselves competent, by<lb/> their
                intelligence, to undertake the duties of any po-<lb/>sition to which an Englishman
                may aspire. (Cheers.)<lb/> I will not urge these circumstances, because, by
                do-<lb/>ing so I might seem to make this a matter of favor<lb/> and indulgence. No!
                I ask the Legislature to re-<lb/>move the disabilities under which the Jews
                labor,<lb/> not on account of any peculiar merits belonging to<lb/> Her Majesty's
                Jewish subjects, but because, being<lb/> subject to the burdens of the state, being
                born in this<lb/> country, being compelled to <sic>fulfil</sic> all those
                duties<lb/> which the state imposes on them, I maintain that they<lb/> have a just
                claim to be admitted to its honors and re-<lb/>wards. (Cheers.) I come, then,
                without press-<lb/>ing any peculiar merits appertaining to the Jews,<lb/> to
                consider the objections which are urged in<lb/> bar of the recognition of the rights
                which I claim<lb/> for them. In the front of those objections this is<lb/> put—that
                it is proposed to un-Christianize the coun-<lb/>try—that it is proposed to take away
                the Christian<lb/> character of the country by admitting not only Jews,<lb/> but
                every kind of infidel into Parliament and the of-<lb/>fices of State. (Hear, hear.)
                The hon. member<lb/> by that cheer seems to admit that I am correctly<lb/> stating
                the objections which are urged to the meas-<lb/>ure I am advocating. I will not say
                in answer to<lb/> such objections that the religion of man is a thing<lb/> apart
                from the business of man. (Hear, hear.) I<lb/> certainly will not say otherwise than
                that I think<lb/> that in our private concerns—in our daily occupa-<lb/>tions—in all
                those trades and professions which men<lb/> exercise, religion should have influence
                and control.<lb/> (Hear, hear.) Still more, therefore, when I am<lb/> speaking of
                the Legislature which has to dispose of<lb/> all the various interests of the
                country, should I be<lb/> disposed to say that religion ought to influence and<lb/>
                control its decisions. (Hear, hear.) I do not,<lb/> therefore, argue this question
                on the ground that<lb/> civil offices and seats in Parliament are totally
                sep-<lb/>arate and apart from religion; but what I do con-<lb/>tend for is, that it
                is entirely a mistake to suppose<lb/> that by the words of an act of Parliament, by
                the<lb/> postscript of an oath or the fag-end of a declaration,<lb/> you can insure
                religious motives and religious obliga-<lb/>tions. (Cheers.) I believe, and I think
                I can<lb/> prove, that by those declarations you do not obtain<lb/> the security
                which you pretend to obtain—that you<lb/> do by these means shut out men who are
                conscien-<lb/>tious and deserving—men who would execute the<lb/> duties of civil
                offices, and exercise the functions of<lb/> legislators with due regard to religious
                obligations—<lb/> and that you do not shut out those whom you profess<lb/>
                yourselves afraid of admitting, I mean, that class of<lb/> persons who, having
                thrown off altogether the obli-<lb/>gations of religion, do not conceive themselves
                bound<lb/> to <sic>fulfil</sic> any of its duties. (Cheers.) I say that it<lb/> must
                depend upon the general opinion of the country<lb/>—it must depend on the state of
                things therein ex-<lb/>isting—it must depend on the state of education—it<lb/> must
                depend on the religion existing in the country,<lb/> whether or not you have a
                Christian Parliament.<lb/> Let me, for the sake of illustration, refer to two
                very<lb/> different times. In the reign of <persName>James I.</persName> and
                    <persName>Charles<lb/> I.</persName> strong religious feeling existed in this
                country.<lb/> Men were divided into different sects, but nothing was<lb/> more
                remarkable than the deep religious fervor which<lb/> prevailed, sometimes burning
                more fiercely in one sect,<lb/> sometimes in another; but all believed
                themselves<lb/> bound by Christian obligations. Imagine that you<lb/> have before
                you the assembly in which <persName>Falkland</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>Hollis</persName>, and <persName>Vane</persName> met—men differing from
                each<lb/> other in religious views, but all sincerely religious,<lb/> and professing
                the doctrine of Christianity;—would<lb/> the Christian faith have been better
                secured in that<lb/> Parliament if no man had been permitted to enter it<lb/>
                without binding his conduct by a declaration "on<lb/> the true faith of a
                Christian?" (Cheers.) Would<lb/> it have added in the slightest degree to the
                security<lb/> of Parliament, and would you have believed more<lb/> strongly than you
                do now that those men were<lb/> Christians, because they had stated the fact at
                the<lb/> end of a declaration? Let us take another period<lb/> and another country.
                Let us imagine a Parliament<lb/> assembled in <placeName>France</placeName> towards
                the end of the last<lb/> century, at a time when many among the aristocra-<lb/>cy
                were the disciples of <persName>Voltaire</persName>, and among the<lb/> democracy of
                    <persName>Rousseau</persName>—let us suppose <persName>Mirabeau</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>Condorcet</persName>, <persName>Robespierre</persName>, and other men of
                that de-<lb/>scription, returned to that assembly; can you believe<lb/> that any
                security would have been obtained by com-<lb/>pelling every one of them to pledge
                himself to ob-<lb/>serve the oath which he took "on the true faith of a<lb/>
                Christian?" (Cheers.) I will refer to another<lb/> illustration, which our own
                country furnishes me<lb/> with. The complaint against the Jews is that they<lb/> are
                revilers of Christianity—that they make a mock-<lb/>ery of the Christian
                religion—that they hold up<lb/>
                <persName>Christ</persName> as an impostor, yet was there ever a man<lb/> who more
                sneered at Christianity—was there any<lb/> Jew of the last century who used such
                language with<lb/> the view of depreciating the doctrines of Christiani-<lb/>ty and
                destroying the belief in it in the minds of the<lb/> people, as
                    <persName>Gibbon</persName>? (Cheers.) Yet <persName>Gibbon</persName> took<lb/>
                your declaration. (Loud cheers.) He came to the<lb/> table and swore "on the true
                faith of a Christian."<lb/> (Cheers and laughter.) He held office under
                    <persName>George<lb/> III.</persName>—he sat on the Treasury bench, under a
                Govern-<lb/>ment which was more of a high church government<lb/> which was more
                disposed to raise the cry of "Church<lb/> and King," than perhaps any government
                which<lb/> ever existed during the reign of that monarch.<lb/> (Loud cheers.) Take
                the case of <persName>Mr. Hume</persName>.<lb/> (Hear, hear.) He did not, it is
                true, have a seat in<lb/> Parliament; but he held an office under Govern-<lb/>ment,
                and I believe that he held office for a short<lb/> time at the Court of
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>. The right hon. gen-<lb/>tleman the member for the
                University of <placeName>Oxford</placeName><lb/> must well know that there was no
                man in the last<lb/> century who wrote essays so much calculated to<lb/> undermine
                religion as <persName>Mr. Hume</persName>; and yet, if he had<lb/> been returned to
                Parliament, and had to make the<lb/> declaration "on the true faith of a Christian,"
                he<lb/> would have taken the oath with a smile or a sigh,<lb/> as the case might be,
                but he would have taken it,<lb/> and the cobweb would have been swept away. I<lb/>
                hold that it is not by a declaration of this kind that<lb/> you can obtain security.
                You say that the Legis-<lb/>lature ought to be a Christian Legislature; that<lb/>
                the Parliament ought to be a Christian Parlia-<lb/>ment; but do you not say that the
                nation is a<lb/> Christian nation, and that the British people are<lb/> a Christian
                people? Why, in the same sense in<lb/> which you say that the nation is a Christian
                nation,<lb/> though there may be 30,000 Jews among them, you<lb/> might say that the
                Parliament was a Christian Par-<lb/>liament, although among the 656 members of
                the<lb/> House of Commons there might be six persons pro-<lb/>fessing the Jewish
                religion. I therefore wish that<lb/> this ground of argument were not taken by
                those<lb/> whose object it is to prevent the Jews entering into<lb/> Parliament,
                because the general character of the<lb/> Parliament must depend now, as in former
                times, on<lb/> the sentiments of the people at large, and on the<lb/> sentiments of
                those who represent them; and it is<lb/> not be inserting seven words in an act of
                Parliament<lb/>—it is not by a mechanical contrivance of this kind<lb/>—that you can
                secure religious obligation. But I<lb/> have heard it said that, although there
                might be<lb/> such instances as those of <persName>Mr.
                Gibbon</persName>,—instances<lb/> of persons sitting in this house and subjecting
                them-<lb/>selves to the required declaration,—yet, that this<lb/> Parliament has
                been from time immemorial a Chris-<lb/>tian Parliament, that Christianity is
                acknowledged<lb/> to be part and parcel of the law of the land, and<lb/> that it
                would be a portentous innovation if we were<lb/> to quit that safe and secure ground
                of obligation. It<lb/> appears to me that great mistakes are made by those<lb/> who
                thus regard the history of this country. In the<lb/> early history of this country
                the Jews were perse-<lb/>cuted in every mode and by every contrivance which<lb/>
                cruelty could suggest. At one time they were forced<lb/> to surrender all their
                property, at another time they<lb/> were sent to prison, at another time they were
                tor-<lb/>tured, and at another time they were banished the</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>realm by a general act of the Legislature. (Hear,<lb/> hear.) Such was the treatment
                of the Jews. But,<lb/> with respect to the theory under which this law<lb/> was
                adopted, that theory was, not that the Le-<lb/>gislature should be open to all
                classes of Christians,<lb/> but that every member of it should belong to the<lb/>
                church which was then universal, the Roman Cath-<lb/>olic church. It is stated by
                    <persName>Bracton</persName>, that the statute<lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">De Haeretico Comburendo</emph> was supposed to be as<lb/>
                ancient as the common law itself. Every heretic<lb/> was committed to the flames at
                once; and I will<lb/> read to you the words of an ancient author
                    (<persName>Lvnde-<lb/>wode</persName>) to show what sort of a person a heretic
                was:<lb/> "Haereticus est qui dubitat de fide Catholica, et qui<lb/> negligit
                servare ea quae Romana ecclesia statuit se<lb/> servare decreverat." He thought that
                every man<lb/> was a heretic who did not adhere to the Roman<lb/> Catholic church,
                or who departed from it in any<lb/> particular. Such was the common law of this
                coun-<lb/>try, which was not framed in favor of Christianity,<lb/> but for the
                protection of what was then the estab-<lb/>lished church of the realm. But in the
                course of<lb/> time the Reformation came; various sects arose; the<lb/> Reformation
                was triumphant, and the church of<lb/>
                <placeName>England</placeName> became a Protestant church. But heretics<lb/> still
                continued to be punished, and in the reign of<lb/>
                <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, I believe, persons were sent to the flames<lb/> on
                account of heresy. But at another time there<lb/> arose a new distinction—a
                distinction founded, not<lb/> upon religious belief, but very much upon
                political<lb/> differences. The Roman Catholics of that day,<lb/> thinking that they
                had no chance of supremacy un-<lb/>der <persName>Elizabeth</persName> or
                    <persName>James I.</persName>, entered into repeated<lb/> conspiracies with a
                view to change the succession of<lb/> these realms. I am asking your attention on
                this<lb/> point, because it was at that time that the words<lb/> were introduced "on
                the true faith of a Christian."<lb/> In the time of <persName>Elizabeth</persName>
                it was necessary that the<lb/> oath of allegiance should be taken on the four
                evan-<lb/>gelists, which the Jews, a despised and neglected<lb/> race, could not
                take. But I will beg to read to you<lb/> the preamble of an act which is the first
                which I can<lb/> discover in which the words "on the true faith of a<lb/> Christian"
                were introduced, the act 3 <persName>James I.</persName>, c.<lb/> 4, entitled "An
                Act for the better Discovering and<lb/> Repressing of Popish Recusants."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">[We here omit sundry references to acts of Par-<lb/>liament.]</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When the ground of a political disqualification<lb/> was taken as a
                reason for exclusion from Parliament<lb/> or office, it was either on the score of
                the Roman<lb/> Catholics failing in their allegiance to the king, or<lb/> in the
                case of the Dissenters, that they were so<lb/> averse to the ecclesiastical
                constitution of these<lb/> realms, that the church could not be secure unless<lb/>
                they were excluded from office. But, whatever these<lb/> reasons might be, in the
                years <date>1828</date> and <date>1829</date> we<lb/> removed all those
                disabilities. Parliament declared,<lb/> in its wisdom, that the Roman Catholics
                should no<lb/> longer be subjected to the imputation to which they<lb/> had been
                exposed, that of infidelity to their Sove-<lb/>reign, and that they were as well
                qualified as any<lb/> other persons to hold office, with the exception of<lb/> some
                offices connected with the ecclesiastical consti-<lb/>tution of the kingdom. They
                declared, likewise,<lb/> that the Protestant Dissenters should not be subject<lb/>
                to the disqualification which excluded from corpora-<lb/>tions and from office—for
                they were before eligible<lb/> to Parliament—because disaffection to the church<lb/>
                establishment was no sufficient ground for depriving<lb/> them of the honors and
                rewards which were the<lb/> right of every subject to these realms. [Hear,<lb/>
                hear.] I submit, then to the house, that what is<lb/> called the Christian character
                of our constitution, if<lb/> it ever had any existence at all, has only existed<lb/>
                from the years <date>1828</date> to <date>1829</date>. Previous to the first<lb/> of
                those years your constitution excluded certain per-<lb/>sons from Parliament, but it
                was on the ground of<lb/> their political and civil disability to perform the
                du-<lb/>ties of good subjects and citizens. With respect to<lb/> the words in the
                oath of abjuration, I should say<lb/> that they were introduced, not for the purpose
                of ex-<lb/>clusion, but for the purpose of giving a superior<lb/> sanction to that
                declaration. If it had been intend-<lb/>ed to exclude the Jews from Parliament on
                the<lb/> ground that their erroneous faith ought to deprive<lb/> them of the
                character of British subjects, there would<lb/> have been introduced into that oath
                some declara-<lb/>tion like that against the doctrine of transubstantia-<lb/>tion,
                or a declaration of a belief in the New Tes-<lb/>tament, or some such declaration.
                You admit that<lb/> there are not direct words of exclusion, but you leave<lb/>
                exclusion to be inferred. It is said, again, that<lb/> Christianity is part and
                parcel of the law of the<lb/> land. I have always understood the meaning<lb/> of
                that statement to be, as I have heard it in-<lb/>terpreted by several learned
                persons, that any<lb/> writings reviling and blaspheming the Christian<lb/>
                religion, the Scriptures being part of the law<lb/> of the land, are illegal, and
                that those who so revile<lb/> and blaspheme may be punished. But I never<lb/>
                understood it to mean anything beyond that, and I<lb/> think it would be quite a new
                interpretation of that<lb/> doctrine to assert that, because Christianity is a
                part<lb/> of the law of the land, every person is required, on<lb/> taking the oath
                of office, to make that declaration<lb/> "on the true faith of a Christian." I think
                now,<lb/> therefore, I have established that the law was in-<lb/>tended and
                professed to exclude, not persons of the<lb/> Jewish persuasion, but persons whom it
                was deemed<lb/> advisable to keep out of Parliament on account of<lb/> political
                distinctions. I have shown to you that, as<lb/> the law is at present, there is no
                security whatever<lb/> for preventing an infidel from sitting in Parliament.<lb/>
                That declaration which the scruples of the Jew in-<lb/>duce him to refuse is taken
                at once by the man who<lb/> believes nothing. (Hear, hear.) If that be the<lb/>
                case, let us see further whether there is any reason,<lb/> not founded on our
                constitution, not founded on the<lb/> laws of the country, which should make you
                con-<lb/>tinue to exclude the Jews from Parliament and of-<lb/>fice. One ground
                which has been stated for their<lb/> exclusion is, that the Jews are a separate
                nation.<lb/> But the Jews themselves utterly deny this allegation.<lb/> They say
                that they are not attached to any foreign<lb/> state; and that, as the Jews in
                    <placeName>France</placeName> are French<lb/> subjects, those of
                    <placeName>England</placeName> are English subjects; and<lb/> that they are
                ready to do their duty as all good sub-<lb/>jects should do, either in time of war
                or otherwise.<lb/> Again, I say if they are aliens, to what country do<lb/> they
                belong? An alien is one who has another king<lb/> and another country, to whom his
                allegiance is ow-<lb/>ing, and therefore he cannot pay perfect obedience<lb/> to the
                laws of the state in which he lives, and is<lb/> subjected to some necessary
                disabilities. But those<lb/> Jews who have lived in this country for a century,<lb/>
                or a century and a half, who have their property in<lb/>
                <placeName>England</placeName>, their wives and their families, to what<lb/> other
                king or country can they resort in order to pay<lb/> their allegiance? To none
                whatever. It is obvious<lb/> to all the world that their attachment is to
                    <placeName>England</placeName>,<lb/> and to no other country. But then we are
                told,<lb/> though it is rather an insult than argument, that, as<lb/> the late
                    <persName>Mr. Cobbett</persName> used to say, we do <sic>no</sic> see the<lb/>
                Jews following the trades which other persons fol-<lb/>low. Is there not a
                sufficient reason for this in<lb/> your own laws? You disqualify them from
                holding<lb/> land, and in many cities from <sic>practising</sic> retail trades;<lb/>
                and what right have you to turn round and say to<lb/> the Jews—"You have no taste
                for the cultivation of<lb/> land, or for trades which other Englishmen follow!"<lb/>
                Is that justice? Is that argument? (Cheers.) I<lb/> believe that in
                    <placeName>France</placeName> the Jews enjoy all the honors<lb/> and emoluments
                which the state has to bestow; and<lb/>
                <persName>M. Dupin</persName>, and some other eminent persons who<lb/> have been
                elected to seats in the Legislature, are of<lb/> that persuasion. Do not, therefore,
                I beg of you,<lb/> rest their disqualification upon your former proscrip-<lb/>tion,
                and do not argue that, if you take it away, you<lb/> will not find the Jews
                fulfilling the obligations of cit-<lb/>izens like other men in similar
                circumstances. But<lb/> we have been told also, that there is a very solemn<lb/>
                denunciation in the prophecies, which would prevent<lb/> our granting to the Jews
                the rights which they claim.<lb/> It is obvious, that if such be the meaning of the
                pro-<lb/>phecies, it is not for us to decide what should be<lb/> done, but that
                Providence will accomplish by its</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
