<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Block, E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0116</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Block, E.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1849-09">September 5, 1849</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0116_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0116_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0116_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0116_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>N. York.</placeName>
                <date>Sep 5. 1849</date>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear <addressee>Isaac</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I owe you an apology for<lb/> my neglect in failing to inform you
                earlier<lb/> of my design to relinquish my school.<lb/> You know too well my
                friendship &amp; esteem for<lb/> you and how highly I estimate your good
                opinion<lb/> to believe for a moment that my silence could<lb/> be owing to any
                cause unpleasant or offensive<lb/> to you the fact is simply that altho I have<lb/>
                for a month past contemplated writing you a long<lb/> letter on the subject, various
                things have<lb/> occurred to cause me to defer it from day to day<lb/> the last was
                the fact of your absence in <placeName>Bali.<add>?</add></placeName></p>
            <p>I am grieved and mortified to have to state that<lb/> my endeavors to establish a
                classical school for<lb/> the Jews of <placeName>N York</placeName> have completely
                failed—<lb/> whether the cause of my want of capacity or moral<lb/> unfitness or
                simply from the want of proper<lb/> patronage &amp; support. That portion of the
                Jewish<lb/> public who feel any interest in the matter will judge<lb/> and of course
                for the greater part unfavorably to<lb/> me, the unfortunate are always in
                fault.<lb/> I have never as any time during the two years of my<lb/> probation had
                more than 14 pupils never during the<lb/> first six months more than 7 and those of
                all ages—from</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>the child of 7. sent to learn to spell &amp; read thro all the intermediate<lb/> ages
                to the boy of 12 who was somewhat prepared to<lb/> receive the kind of instruction I
                contemplated in my plan.<lb/> I of course had as many classes nearly as pupils, and
                apart<lb/> from Hebrew &amp; German had to undertake personally<lb/> all the various
                branches of instruction, to <sic>organise</sic><lb/> a school properly, under these
                circumstances, without<lb/> the aid of assistant teachers, was impracticable<lb/>
                <del>under such</del> the incapacity of some, the indolence<lb/> and obstinacy of
                others were serious obstacles, but I<lb/> bore up against all discouragement and
                during the last<lb/> year my school was supplied with capable teachers<lb/> in
                Hebrew in German in Music in <sic>latin</sic>. French<lb/> algebra and geometry and
                the English branches—<lb/> thus affording at least the groundwork of a system
                of<lb/> useful and practical education, well for the higher branches<lb/> I had
                three boys, of whom one alone applied himself<lb/> with tolerable
                    <sic>dilijince</sic>, and he is the only one of my<lb/> pupils to whom I can
                point with any pride to<lb/> illustrate the advantages of my tuition, altho' others
                have<lb/> in some branches made very satisfactory progress.<lb/> I have to add to
                the list of discouragements, the want<lb/> of punctuality in payment. There is yet
                due for tuition or<lb/> near $200. which I may never get. You thus see<lb/> that my
                failure is not the result of any want of perseverance<lb/> I held on as long as
                possible.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I regret that I must<lb/> necessarily remain your debtor for the
                bill you have<lb/> against me for <add>?</add>. I have on hand belonging</p>
            <p rend="The following is written at the bottom of the page in pencil.">
                <date>9-5-1849</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>to you the Tephiloth sent to <persName>A Dittenhoffer</persName> which he<lb/> did
                not take as his. Father tho't his old one would answer<lb/> and 3 spellers. I will
                either await an opportunity of<lb/> disposing of them for you, or hand them to your
                agt as you may<lb/> desire.—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have on consultation with <persName>Mr Jonas</persName> my Brother<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Judah</persName> &amp; other friends concluded to resume my former<lb/>
                avocation, and with strong promises of their support<lb/> I am now established in an
                office <placeName>No 120 Water St</placeName><lb/> where I am awaiting business as a
                commission merchant.<lb/> I do not flatter myself with hopes of immediate
                success,<lb/> and expect to encounter many difficulties. “mais <sic>boque</sic><lb/>
                la galère avec patience et courage on accomplit tout.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><del>My</del> I <add>?</add> remember that I have another apology to
                make in not<lb/> informing you directly of <persName>Sarah's</persName> engagement,
                but allowing<lb/> the information to reach you thro' general rumor.<lb/> You have
                seen the gentleman I believe, he stands very<lb/> high in
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName> as a rising member of his profession—and<lb/>
                is esteemed for his private worth as a good son, brother<lb/> and citizen. We are
                all much pleased with him.<lb/> My house at present is very full, besides
                    <persName>Rosalie's</persName> children<lb/> and <persName>Mrs.
                    Solomon</persName> &amp; Son, we have <persName>Zonny Labat</persName>
                during<lb/> his vacation from Yale, and <persName>Mrs. &amp; Miss Jacobs</persName>.
                The<lb/> cantatrice, it will not do to use plain english<lb/> little
                    schozu<add>?</add> one of my pupils is yet with us.<lb/>
                <persName>Rosalie</persName> will not leave us till late in
                <date>October</date>,<lb/> we have all continued to enjoy good health during
                the<lb/> season except myself. Mine has been bad, but</p>
            <p rend="The following is written at the bottom of the page.">
                <date>9-5-1849</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>is much improved since I have entered upon my new<lb/> business. All of us write in
                best regards to you.<lb/> Your <persName>Aunt Rehine</persName> is well
                    <persName>Ben</persName> recovered—you have<lb/> doubtless heard of
                    <persName>Rachel's</persName> loss of her youngest boy—<lb/> of congregational
                news this may interest you I know<lb/> nothing. I have been to two or three funerals
                recently<lb/> and have been struck by the narrow and confined<lb/> appearance of the
                burial place of one of the richest<lb/> and most numerous congregations of this
                great metropolis,<lb/> apart from the certainty of the necessity of removal<lb/> in
                a few years away from a continually encroaching<lb/> population, it seems like a
                desecration of the remains<lb/> of the dead to huddle them together in such a
                spot<lb/> surrounded as it is and overlooked by houses that<lb/> resemble barracks,
                teeming as they do with that<lb/> description of population that swarms upon
                the<lb/> outskirts of a large city—can you not in your<lb/> next Occident suggest
                the idea of a general<lb/> Jewish cemetery, located upon <placeName>Long
                    Island</placeName>, and guarded by state charter perpetually against<lb/>
                desecration by any possible charge of destination<lb/> to be provided with lots
                suitable for family burial<lb/> to be sold in f<add>?</add> only to those of Jewish
                ritual<lb/> and to be exempt from seizure or sale on execution.<lb/> Why cannot we
                as Jews <sic>avails</sic> ourselves of the<lb/> general improvements of the age in
                which we live?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">E. Block</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
