<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Wise, Isaac ?</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP20-807</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Wise, Isaac ?</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_807_001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_807_002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_807_003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_807_004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">Principles of Judaism</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="underline">No 111</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">To the Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p>Reverend Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Since you have been kind<lb/> enough to insert my letters in your
                magazine<lb/> I continue to write on my subject without any<lb/> farther
                    <del>introduction</del> preface or <del>excuse</del> apology; you may only<lb/>
                please to recollect, that <del>we</del> I have stated in my<lb/> last, that Judaism
                rests upon four strong and<lb/> immovable pillars, 1. God is God, 2. man is<lb/> His
                    <sic>immage</sic>, 3. man is accountable here and here˶<lb/>after to his Maker,
                and 4. <placeName>Israel</placeName> is His own<lb/> people. All the duties of a man
                and an Israelite in<lb/> all <del>positions</del> estimations of life are deducible
                from those<lb/> four <del>theses</del> positions, &amp; all the hopes in life and
                death, the<lb/> confidence, the fortitude, the moral strength, the joy<lb/>
                <del>happiness</del> of heart of an Israel<add>ite</add>
                <del>and his individuals</del><lb/> are based upon those doctrines. It would
                surprise<lb/> me if any one should <del>detect a human duty</del> be able to point
                out as high duty obligatory on man or any<lb/> moral excellency, <del>for</del>
                which one can not be accounted for<lb/>
                <del>by</del> upon one either or all of those <del>theses</del> principles. We have
                no difference of opinion<lb/>
                <del>dispute</del>, I believe, about the first <del>thesis</del> axiom; but
                with<lb/> the second and third <del>are</del> the differences commence;<lb/>
                <del>the</del> our opponents tell us, that <del>the body of</del> man, in his
                body,<lb/> will arise at some distant day, being then inhabited<lb/> by the same
                soul; &amp; that he will live nearly in the<lb/> same manner as we do now; In
                    <sic>connexion</sic> with<lb/> this resurrection of the body is the last
                judgment<lb/> and the everlasting <sic>demnation</sic> of those who deserve<lb/>
                such a deplorable lot; <del>and yet</del> besides other things of the<lb/> same
                kind. We suppose, that our opponents<lb/> take for granted, that if the soul of man
                be<lb/> perishable and die away, a resurrection of the body would<lb/> be
                impossible, wherefore they must <del>say</del> give with us in maintaining that<lb/>
                "The soul of man is immortal &amp; can exist and<lb/> exists without body; but that
                the body of man is</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>a subject to mortality &amp; cannot exist in <del>his</del><lb/> its proper functions
                without the soul;" thus we <del>are</del> have<lb/>
                <del>satisfied about</del> established the main point, the very basis of
                    <del>things</del> our discussion.<lb/> This dogma of ours is <del>a biblical
                    one</del> derived from the Bible, where man is<lb/> called an <sic>immage</sic>
                of God; but the dogma of an<lb/> immortal body appears to us to be of no biblical
                origin<lb/> as every impartial student of the Bible will admit, and<lb/> you,
                reverend sir, have <del>yet</del> not yet come out with your<lb/> biblical
                evidences. I shall first consider the matter<lb/> in a natural point of view; for it
                appears to me, that<lb/> the Rabbis expressed the most correct opinion on the<lb/>
                matter, when they said <add>כל הנביאים לא נתנבאו אלא לימות</add><lb/>
                <add>המשיח אבל עולם הבא עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך</add><lb/> "All <sic>The</sic>
                prophets prophesied only for the times of the<lb/> Messiah, but the future world no
                eye has ever seen<lb/> it but saw shine alone ˶O Lord<add>?</add>" (Berachoth 34) Hence<lb/>
                <add>דתניא כל יב' חודש גופו קיים ונשמתו עולה ויורדת לאחר יב' חודש</add><lb/> "It was
                taught (by the earlier Rabbis) that during the<lb/> months (after death) the body
                remains uncorrup-<lb/>ted; and <del>his</del> the soul ascends and descends
                (visiting the<lb/> spot where <del>his</del> its former <del>vehicle</del> tenement
                is <del>interred</del> buried); but after<lb/> two<add>?</add> months the body is
                dissolved and <del>his</del> the<lb/> soul ascends to return never again." Sabbath
                151)<lb/> Hence we read in Moreh Nebuchim of <persName>maimonides</persName><lb/>
                Part I. ch. 40 <add>הגוף בטל ונשמתו עולה ושוב אינה יורדת</add><lb/> "The noun <hi
                    rend="underline">Rusach</hi> is also the name of that<lb/> substance which
                    <del>is</del> remains of man after death<lb/> and which is not
                    <del>exposed</del> liable to dissolution," and<lb/> (<hi rend="underline"
                    >ibid</hi> 41 chapter xli) we read the same definition<lb/> of the term <add>רוח
                    וגו' והוא גם כן שם דבר הנשאר מן האדם אחר</add>. I shall say nothing about<lb/>
                the <add>המות אשר לא ישיגהו ההפסד</add> that the bodies of the dead<lb/> must roll
                themselves through <del>caves</del> subterranean channels to
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName><lb/> where they will be revived, nor about
                the</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>opinion <add>נפש</add> that the pious who have arisen<lb/> from death will be
                assembled in a tent made<lb/> of the skin of the Leviathan, and that they will<lb/>
                eat at a great feast the flesh of that <del>very</del><lb/> fabulous fish, which was
                killed and salted<lb/> by God for this purpose soon after the<lb/> creation; though
                these are substantial<lb/> portions of the resurrection-creed of those, which<lb/>
                you please to call orthodox, because they try<lb/> to explain those singular
                assertions to be of a<lb/> parabolic nature; but we have the same right to<lb/> say
                all statements about the revival of the body<lb/> are of the same nature. I shall
                confine myself<lb/> exclusively to the question of the resurrection of the<lb/>
                body. The surface of the earth contains one hundred and fifty six million, two
                hundred fifty thousand<lb/>
                <del>156 250 000</del> square miles of land including<lb/>
                <del>the</del> the vast regions of sandy deserts, stony<lb/> mountains, marshes and
                swamps, large<lb/> districts covered with perpetual snow and ice<lb/> and other
                uninhabitable portions. The present<lb/> population of our globe is
                    <sic>estemated</sic>
                <del>1200000000</del> twelve hundred millions;<lb/> if we suppose <del>that</del>
                one generation <del>take</del> to be<lb/> 30 years, and that since the creation
                of<lb/> man be <date>5611</date> years, there must have been then<lb/> our earth 187
                generations, which would give<del>s</del> the sum<lb/> of individuals <hi
                    rend="underline">1200,000,000x187</hi><lb/>2*=112200000000,<lb/> which would
                give a population of 72 to<lb/> a square mile, if the resurrection take place<lb/>
                in our age; none of our friends has ever<lb/> lost himself so far in mystical
                conjectures,<lb/> as to think it natural, that such a popu-<lb/>lation should exist
                on earth. Our old<lb/> brethren have two different methods to help<lb/> themselves
                out of this difficulty; they say <hi rend="underline">first</hi><lb/>
                <add>צער גלגול מחילות</add></p>
            <p rend="The following is a note in the right margin, near the bottom of the page.">*
                There is <add>?</add><lb/>ly an error in <persName>D W's</persName><lb/> formula
                here, we see<lb/> no reason for dividing<lb/> the product by two;<lb/> our calculation<lb/>
                <del>would</del> the population<lb/> after these dates<lb/> 1436 to a square<lb/>
                mile.</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>"<del>It be</del> know<del>n</del> that the world to come is<lb/> made for none but
                the righteous and the<lb/> Isralites" (Jebanoth 46.). But this is not in<lb/>
                <sic>accordence</sic> with the passage in <persName>Daniel</persName>, which<lb/>
                they suppose to be the expressive of the doctrine<lb/> of the <sic>resurection</sic>
                of the body. "And many of<lb/> those who sleep in the dust of the ground<lb/> he
                shall awake, some to an everlasting<lb/> life and some to shame and everlasting<lb/>
                reproach" (<persName>Daniel</persName> IIX 2) If our friends will<lb/> insist
                    <del>admit</del>, that <persName>Daniel</persName> speaks in this chapter
                only<lb/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, then they cannot help saying but
                that<lb/> only many of <placeName>Israel</placeName> will arise; some of these<lb/>
                who arise<del>n</del>
                <del>individuals</del> will be a shame and an<lb/> everlasting reproach,
                consequently they must ad-<lb/>mit, that among those what will arise will be<lb/>
                wicked people also; to <del>say</del> assert the wicked shall<lb/> arise and die
                again is incompatible with the<lb/> text, in which the <add>סעודה וסוכה של
                    לויתן</add> "everlasting" prohibits such<lb/> a construction. And if this contradiction<lb/>
                <del>should</del> is not to exist, our old friends cannot remove<lb/> the difficulty
                by the above quoted conjecture;<lb/> for it is <del>sure enough</del>
                unquestionable, that five children die to<lb/> one grown person, and what wrong can
                a<lb/> child have done? and among the rest of<lb/>
                <del>people</del> mankind they must reckon <add>הוי יודע שהעולם הבא אינו עשוי אלא
                    לצדיקים ולישראל</add><lb/> "one half innocent and one other half guilty",
                which<lb/> is a strict talmudical principle; consequently<lb/> the immense
                    <sic>numbre</sic> of 720 to a square<lb/> mile would be immaterially reduced.
                They<lb/> cannot remove this difficulty by conjecturing,<lb/> that them who has
                    <del>a</del>risen <del>people</del> will be of such a<lb/> spiritual nature,
                that they have no wants<lb/> whatever; for this would be no resurrection<lb/> of the
                same body, but a new creation;</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
