<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Jacobsohn, Joseph</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0230</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Jacobsohn,
                            Joseph</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865-06">June 28, 1865</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0230_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0230_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0230_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0230_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                <date>June 28 1865</date>
            </p>
            <p>To <addressee>Revd Isaac Lesser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Editor “Occident</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>Revd &amp; Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Though not your correspondent I still take the<lb/> liberty to
                gratify your desire and inform you of the reason of <persName>Dr<lb/>
                    Illowy's</persName> refusing a reelection after he had affected so much good
                in<lb/> the Congregation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the outset I beg leave to make you acquainted with<lb/> the new
                circumstances as they are now prevailing in our midst. Our<lb/> Cong. Schaarey
                Chased was originally founded <sic>a</sic> orthodox Cong.<lb/> still we had not more
                than the mere name in reality however we<lb/> were nothing <add>תפילין ציצית
                    ומזוזות</add> our fine Synagogue was empty on<lb/>
                <date>Sabbath</date> and Holydays and it was not seldom the case that<lb/> the
                reader had to stop and wait a considerable time before the<lb/> due number of
                    <sic>worshippers</sic> was complete. Over ten or eleven persons<lb/> never (the
                    <date>day of <sic>atonemet</sic></date> excepted) attended divine service
                    <add>שוחט</add><lb/> were useless and unknown articles; among several hundred
                children<lb/> there were not ten who could read a hebrew word and no religious<lb/>
                education was given to them; the never pronounced the glorious name<lb/> of God
                except when swearing or cursing; of the History of their<lb/> nation they knew no
                more than that they were jews, and this<lb/> they only learned from their christian
                schoolmates who called them<lb/> so. There was but one <add>עיר הנידחת</add> for the
                four Congs. whose members live<lb/> scattered all over this large city. The „ ladies
                Gallery “ was in such a<lb/> state that every decent <add>man</add> was bound to
                keep his eyes fixed to the ground<lb/> lest by an unintended glimpse on the gallery
                he should violate</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>the laws of decency and respect due to the sacred abode.</p>
            <p>Yes <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> was at time not much better than an
                    <add>שוחט</add><lb/> there was no religious <sic>superindendant</sic> and
                    <del>the</del>
                <add>שבת</add> and butcher<lb/> acted just according to their pleasure.</p>
            <p>From all these and a good many other evils <persName>Dr Illowy</persName> healed<lb/>
                the Cong. immediately at his arrival. The President <persName>S. Fried<lb/>ler
                    Esq</persName> supported him with all his<del>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del> might and influence and<lb/> in a very short time he succeeded in
                establishing <del>a</del>
                <date>Sabbath's</date><lb/> rest in the Cong; over eighty wholesale and retail
                    <add>merchants</add> closed at once<lb/> their places of business on
                    <add>שוחט</add>; the house of worship was crowdedly<lb/> every
                    <date>Sabbath</date>; the railing around the Ladies Gallery was draped<lb/> from
                inside<lb/> and assistant <add>תפילין ציצית מזוזות תפילות וחמשים</add> was engaged
                and peddler with<lb/>
                <add>שוחטים</add> commenced to make elegant business here.<lb/> The <add>שבת</add>
                had to subject to the rules of their <sic>Superintendant</sic><lb/> and the butchers
                who sell on <add>סוכות</add> had to have their meat sealed<lb/> with a seal procured
                by the Cong. for that purpose.</p>
            <p>The word of God was taught and expounded every <date>Sabbath</date> by<lb/>
                <persName>Revd Dr Illowy</persName> in a very able and eloquent manner and his<lb/>
                words fell upon many a <del>bless</del> fertile heart and yielded blissful<lb/>
                fruits. Besides a sunday <del>sunday</del> school, we have yet two large day<lb/>
                schools in which besides all the higher school branches taught<lb/> therein by
                competent and experienced teachers, the utmost care and<lb/>
                <sic>and</sic> attention are paid to the religious education of our children,
                as<lb/> instruction in hebrew reading, translating the bible and the prophets<lb/>
                the History of our Nation from the time of <persName>Abram</persName> to the<lb/>
                destruction of the second <add>temple</add>. The great change in our religious
                life<lb/> could best be seen last <add>והאספסוף התאוו תאבה</add> when there were
                    <sic>ove</sic> fifty tabernacles<lb/> in the city whilst when <persName>Dr
                    Illowy</persName> arrived here there was but one.</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>But while we were greatly rejoiced at our great success, our rapid<lb/> progress was
                suddenly checked by a party of young men the most<lb/> of them hailing from the
                    <placeName>North</placeName>, who came to this city a few years<lb/> ago and
                formed an association under the title of the “Deutche<lb/> Company.” This society
                increased <sic>rapidle</sic> during the last two years<lb/>
                <add>קדושה</add> and became numerous enough for the daring<lb/> enterprise to build
                a large and gorgeous reform Temple, which should<lb/> eclipse in magnificence that
                of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and in comparison to<lb/> which the great Temple
                of <placeName>New York</placeName> should be as the hut of the<lb/>
                    esquimaux<add>?</add>, to the royal palace of <persName>Napoleon</persName>, in
                the upper part<lb/> of this city. Meetings were held for that purpose officers
                elected<lb/> committees appointed and circulars sent around to all the Hebrews<lb/>
                in this city, and many reform friends and mal-contents joined the<lb/>
                Association</p>
            <p>Already every one young and old began to see gay visions of a<lb/> fashionable divine
                service. Family pews Ladies and Gentleman<lb/> together, beautiful choirs, operatic
                music, airs form “Robt Le Diable”<lb/> to the <add>אן כאלהנו</add> airs from the
                “Barber of <placeName>Seville</placeName>” adapted to the<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> and many other pleasant things too numerous to mention</p>
            <p>But when after all the exerted efforts they discovered secession to<lb/> be a
                failure, they gave up their first plan as <sic>empracticable</sic> &amp; a<lb/> new
                one and indeed a very ingenious one was formed. The most<lb/> of their members tried
                and succeeded to become members of the Cong<lb/> Schaarey Chased. the board of
                officers who accepted them, not<lb/> dreaming like <persName>Joshua</persName> when
                he made a treaty of peace<lb/> with the Gideonites, that any harm was meant by
                their<lb/> joining <del>into</del> the Cong., and but too late the found out<lb/>
                that they had run into a snare. The reform friends have no</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>need any more of building a new Temple, they will realize<lb/> all their fine visions
                without any expense, they have now a<lb/> majority in the Cong. and will use the
                fine edifice of the<lb/>
                <placeName>Rampart St</placeName> Synagogue for their purpose, and the old<lb/>
                members who will not agree <del>with the</del> to the new order of things<lb/> can
                build themselves another Synagogue. Now they went to work<lb/> the meanest and
                foulest tricks were set in operation for the purpose<lb/> of removing all the
                faithfull men from the administration, and<lb/> they succeeded. <persName>Mr
                    Friedlander</persName> who for 4 years worked indefatigab<lb/>ly for this Cong.
                was most ungratefully treated, provoked and<lb/> constantly vexed <sic>untill</sic>
                he left with disgust the chair and resigned.<lb/> This was <add>just</add> what they
                wanted. <persName>Mr Klopman</persName> and <persName>Mr Lehman</persName><lb/>
                followed his example, and the field being thus all at once evacuated<lb/> the
                invaders took possession of it elected as President the man of their<lb/> choice,
                fully fit to answer their purposes, and a certain individual<lb/> who since years
                past indulged in the habit of keeping his hand<lb/> in the pocket of the Cong.
                shouts and rejoices <add>now</add> at the great victory of<lb/> the liberals.</p>
            <p><persName>Dr Illowy</persName> seeing the approaching storm brooding over the<lb/>
                orthodox party of our Cong. did not desire to wait <sic>untill</sic> it would<lb/>
                discharge its destructive contents, for he foresaw that the people of the<lb/> would
                conquer and the old <del>and the old</del> Southerners be subjugated;<lb/> he
                resigned therefore at the <del>at</del> proper time with the best satisfaction in
                his heart<lb/> of having faithfully discharged all his duties and with a firm<lb/>
                adherence to his principles and the doctrines of our fathers</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">I remain dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Your most obedient Servt.</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">Joseph Jacobsohn</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Atty. At Law. <placeName>No 33 Exchange place</placeName>.</p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_23_3.pdf">The above text refers to Occident
                        Volume 23 No. 3 page 143. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
