<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Bomeisler, Evelyn</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0156</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Bomeisler,
                            Evelyn</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0156_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0156_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0156_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0156_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <add>?</add>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">The Eighth Anniversary Meeting of the Jewish Foster</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">Home Society of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">Report</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Another circle of months is perfected since our<lb/> last
                anniversary, and trusting to enlist your earnest<lb/> interest and reawaken your
                sympathies we present to<lb/> the friends and members of “The Jewish Foster Home
                Sy”, the<lb/> Eighth Annual record of its progress, condition and<lb/> requirements.
                To relieve distress, to rescue innocence<lb/> from temptation, to inculcate upon the
                minds of those<lb/> committed to our charge a knowledge of our holy<lb/> faith, and
                in so doing foster in their hearts a love and<lb/> veneration for its sacred
                teachings &amp; obligations and<lb/> prepare them for all moral and social
                responsibilities<lb/> that may await them, are the objects and aim of the<lb/>
                Institution,—considerations that appeal equally to our<lb/> pride and principles,
                and constitute the superstructure<lb/> that can be perfected only by the combined
                efforts<lb/> and influence of our people in giving aid, strength<lb/> and
                substantial permanency to its foundation—<lb/> as unity is the watch-word of our
                nation, so should<lb/> unanimity be the main spring of our associated<lb/>
                charities. A noble bridge spanning one of the<lb/> beautiful rivers of our own state
                becomes more secure<lb/> more stable in proportion to the pressure brought<lb/> to
                bear upon it—beautiful would be our record<lb/> if in our emergencies our friends
                would willingly so</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>exert their energies and capabilities that we might<lb/> feel the assurance of a
                firmer more enduring<lb/> establishment. The increased rates of provisions
                &amp;c<lb/> tell seriously &amp; ominously upon our means—the<lb/> detailed account
                of the Treasurer will give the financial<lb/> state of the Society—we have been
                obliged to dispose<lb/> of <add>?</add> stock, which was effected</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Our receipts inclusive of donations and subscriptions<lb/>
                <add>&amp; a balance of last year of 361.19</add> amount to
                $<del>2260.64</del>2499.45, the expenditures of the Society to #2460.64<lb/> balance
                245.29 Owing to the unfortunate state of our Country,<lb/> the subscription from our
                Southern friends is very limited—<lb/> To our Triennial Subscribers we return our
                cordial<lb/> thanks—, their obligations expire with this year,—<lb/> it has been
                suggested that in view of our present<lb/> need, many would be induced to continue
                their<lb/> subscriptions for a renewed limited period—we<lb/> respectfully present
                the matter for your consideration.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Since our last meeting children have been admitted<lb/> into the
                Home—three have been removed their parents being<lb/> enabled to maintain them, —one
                has been indentured to a<lb/> trade—Another has been called from our band under<lb/>
                sad circumstances—from the midst of the youthful<lb/> family of the 'Home', a bright
                little boy of nine years of<lb/> age was summoned to his Heavenly home—he died<lb/>
                suddenly from internal injuries received from a fall,<lb/> while on his way to
                school, and notwithstanding<lb/> the most careful attendance of the physician
                and</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>the motherly kindness of the matron, his case proved<lb/> beyond the reach of all
                human skill—His <add>The</add> funeral<lb/> arrangements were conducted by his
                relatives and members<lb/> of the <del>Board</del> Home,—the <persName>Rev. S.
                    Morais</persName> addressed the children<lb/> impressively on the occasion, when
                with the usual last<lb/> rites, his remains were interred in the <placeName>Federal
                    St</placeName><lb/> cemetery,—the lot was presented by the Congregation
                Mickve<lb/> Israel. Since our organization five boys have<lb/> attained their
                religious majority, which in each case<lb/> has been solemnized in synagogue and
                joyfully<lb/> celebrated at the Home—it has been the privilege of the<lb/> young
                Bar-mitzvah to invite all his seniors who may<lb/> have left the Institution to
                enter upon life's duties, to<lb/> celebrate the day with him at the Home—the
                affectionate<lb/> intimacy existing between those whose paths are now<lb/> cast in
                separate places, which these re-unions tend<lb/> to strengthen, will we hope be
                life-long and useful<lb/> in its consequences.* All accounts of the boys who<lb/>
                have been indentured are entirely satisfactory—the<lb/> eldest now in his 18th year,
                appropriates a regular<lb/> monthly allowance to his mother—his term of
                apprenticeship<lb/> expired some time since, but he still remains with<lb/> his
                employer from whom he receives the kindest<lb/> paternal care. Two boys yet remain
                in the Institution<lb/> who are of a suitable age to be placed to a trade, as<lb/>
                soon as an eligible situation can be secured for<lb/> them. We are happy here to
                express our warm</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>appreciation of the ability and fidelity of the matron<lb/> she exerts a most
                    <sic>happyfying</sic> influence upon the<lb/> children so intimately dependent
                upon her.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We regret having been obliged to dispense with the<lb/> useful
                services of <persName>Mrs. M. Dormitzer</persName> as a manager of the<lb/>
                Society—, the Board cordially unite in an expression<lb/> of kind wishes for her
                perfect restoration to health.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">A legacy of $50 has been bequested to the Society from<lb/> the
                benevolence of <persName>Mrs. B. Spanier</persName>, deceased. Twenty dollars<lb/>
                were realized by the disposal of a tasteful ornamental<lb/> sofa-cushion, presented
                by <persName>Mrs. J. L. Filerance</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">To <persName>Dr. A.C. Bournonville</persName> we would express our
                reserved<lb/> obligations—he is unwearying in his attention, and<lb/> unremitting in
                his kindness. From the German Ladies<lb/> Sewing Society we received a handsome
                donation of<lb/> clothing—we are extremely indebted for their contributions<lb/>
                during this and the preceding year. We would also<lb/> make acknowledgments to
                    <persName>Dr. D. Roberts</persName>, Dental Surgeon, to the<lb/> Hebrew
                Education Sy, and to all friends from whom we have<lb/> received gifts or services.
                To <persName>Mr Alfred A. Allen</persName>, Conveyances, we<lb/> are indebted for
                gratuitous services and disinterested<lb/> exertions<add>?</add> in behalf of the
                Home.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We earnestly ask the protection of the Most High<lb/> trusting that
                    <sic>that</sic> His kind Providence may shield<lb/> &amp; bless us now &amp;
                evermore.</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">—<persName role="author">Evelyn Bomeisler</persName></p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">Sec.</p>
            <p>* For instruction &amp; preparation of <add>two of</add> the boys<lb/> for the
                reading of their Bar Mitzvah portions, we<lb/> are deeply indebted to <persName>Miss
                    S. C. Peixotta</persName>, who kindly<lb/> and opportunely volunteered her
                efficient services.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
