<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Ezekiel, Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0217</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Ezekiel,
                            Jacob</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Richmond, VA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1866-08">Aug 27, 1866</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_3v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0217_4r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
                <date>Aug 27, 1866</date>
            </p>
            <p><addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee>,</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">My Valued Friend!</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">You must excuse<lb/> my remissness in not replying to<lb/> your kind
                favour received<lb/> some time since containing a<lb/> circular for the
                publication<lb/> of your works &amp;c now my<lb/> dear friend I am under the<lb/>
                opinion if you should propose<lb/> to publish <hi rend="underline">your own
                    productions</hi><lb/> separately, and issue a circu<lb/>lar for that specific
                purpose<lb/> you might succeed in obtaining<lb/> a large bit of subscribers, I<lb/>
                feel there are many persons<lb/> who would like to benefit you<lb/> in some becoming
                manner<lb/> and would subscribe <sic>liberaly</sic></p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>for copies of your own produc-<lb/>tions and lay accompanied<lb/> with a Sketch of
                your life and<lb/> your portrait to embellish the<lb/> first volume, and fix the
                work<lb/> at a definite price, so that<lb/> you might be well
                    renumerated<add>?</add>,<lb/> and the other works you propose<lb/> to publish
                issue a separate<lb/> circular for, I will try and<lb/> do the best I can for you.
                I<lb/> should suppose Four Octavo<lb/> volumes 500 pages each large<lb/> margins and
                stout paper<lb/> would be capable if contain-<lb/>ing all you desire, and print<lb/>
                a page or two on the prospectus<lb/> as a specimen of the work,<lb/> then put in the
                hands of one or<lb/> two persons in each city, I can<lb/> see no reason why a
                edition<lb/> of at least 1000 copies could<lb/> not be sold, I will do all I can</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>for it. I am under many obliga-<lb/>tions to you for the prompt and ef-<lb/>ficient
                manner you executed my<lb/> order with the bibles I ordered for<lb/>
                <persName>Sarah</persName> &amp; <persName>Leonora</persName>, they were
                high-<lb/>ly pleased with them, and considered<lb/> it a well timed present to
                each,<lb/> when you write, please let me<lb/> know the <add>?</add> I will
                re-<lb/>mit you the amount.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now for our congregation affairs,<lb/> I enclose you two circulars
                I<lb/> had struck off, I suppose you are<lb/> aware that <persName>Mr
                    Jacobs</persName> has receivd<lb/> an offer from the congregation<lb/> at
                    <placeName>Savannah</placeName> of $4200 to read<lb/> Lecture and Teach besides
                    per-<lb/><sic>quisites</sic> he does not desire to<lb/> leave here if we can
                raise a<lb/> reasonable amount for him, he<lb/> does not expect <del>any</del> near
                the<lb/> amount here, say if we can<lb/> raise about $2000 to $2500</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>we had a meeting on <date><sic>Teusday</sic><lb/> last 21h</date> rather thinly
                attended<lb/> there was about 1000 dollars<lb/> subscribed. <persName>Mr G. A.
                    Myer</persName> was pres-<lb/>ent and presided all worked very<lb/>
                harmoniously. I have not the<lb/> least doubt the congregation<lb/> of
                    <placeName>Richmond</placeName> will soon be con-<lb/>centrated into two, one
                Portu-<lb/>guese and the other German<lb/> as I contemplated in the circu-<lb/>lar,
                the Polish congregations are<lb/> “played out” and the new Ger-<lb/>man congregation
                will not be<lb/> able to sustain themselves I<lb/> understand, most of those
                two<lb/> elements will join us, and no<lb/> doubt those <sic>to</sic> wedded to
                the<lb/> German minhag will join <persName>Mr<lb/> Michelbachèl's</persName>
                congregation, I<lb/> do not now desire <hi rend="underline">only one</hi><lb/>
                congregation here I think <hi rend="underline">two</hi><lb/> will be better than
                there need</p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p>be no concenious<add>?</add> in regard<lb/> to minhag which might prove<lb/> very
                disastrous to us. I think<lb/> we will have a large meeting<lb/> tomorrow night,
                leading mem-<lb/>bers of the Polish cong. told me to<lb/>day that they will join us,
                I<lb/> understood that some desire to<lb/> join us if we will declare them<lb/>
                members instante with all the<lb/> rights and Privileges, they must<lb/> certainly
                think we are “Green”<lb/> as they out number us 3 to 1 or<lb/> more, and it would
                not take very<lb/> long ere they would oust us and<lb/> orange the whole system of
                loor-<lb/>ship, and we would be nowhere,<lb/>
                <sic>I</sic> they wish to join us they can<lb/> do so voluntarily and fall<lb/> into
                our lives <hi rend="underline">as we are</hi> and the<lb/> next year if we give them
                the<lb/> right of membership we can do<lb/> so. My idea is for to do away</p>
            <pb n="3V"/>
            <p>entirely with the <hi rend="underline">election</hi> for mem<lb/>bers and after they
                have been a<lb/> contributor for twelve months to<lb/> declare the members
                provided<lb/> they sign such conditions as we<lb/> think proper to prescribe to as
                to<lb/> guard against any difficulty<lb/> to have no congregation meeting<lb/>
                except for the Election of Hazan<lb/> for the contributing members to<lb/> elect on
                any given day <hi rend="underline">nine</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">trustees</hi>, a poll to be opened for<lb/> that purpose with
                proper inspec-<lb/>tors &amp; to be arranged in <add>?</add><lb/> to serve three
                years so that an<lb/> election would be <add>held</add> every <del>three</del><lb/>
                    year<del>s</del> for three trustees, the<lb/> trustees to arrange the whole
                af<lb/>fair of the congregation, to Elect<lb/> from among their number a<lb/>
                Parnass, <add>?</add> secretary also<lb/> to elect Hattanim &amp; Sharua<add>?</add>
                to<lb/> fix all salaries for the officers</p>
            <pb n="4R"/>
            <p>&amp;c &amp;c, I want to arrange not<lb/> to have any <hi rend="underline"
                    >congregational mee-</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">tings</hi> they always break
                up in<lb/> displeasure, from the fact, we<lb/> have no one here to manage<lb/> one
                properly, I want to arrange<lb/> if I can a system of liberality<lb/> and equality
                to all contributors<lb/> and have things to work har-<lb/>moniously if I can, I
                should<lb/> like a good looking plan of<lb/> your suggestions to carry out<lb/> my
                views, there was one feature<lb/> you spoke of when here, that was<lb/> a compact to
                be signed by all<lb/> who desired to be members, that<lb/> the minhag should not be
                altered<lb/> &amp;c &amp;c has been impressed in my<lb/> mind as a good article.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Hoping this may meet you in<lb/> the enjoyment of good health,<lb/>
                and may the almighty grant<lb/> you length of days in the fervent<lb/> wish of your
                    friend—<hi rend="underline"><persName role="author">Jacob
                    Ezekiel</persName></hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
