<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Cox, Samuel Hanson</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Cox, Samuel
                            Hanson</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Eardley, Culling E.,
                            Sir</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1857-08">August 10, 1857</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_9.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >miscellany</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The annexed letter from <persName role="author">Rev. Dr.
                    Cox</persName>, of the <placeName>United<lb/> States</placeName>, to
                    <persName>Sir Culling Eardley</persName>, of <placeName>England</placeName>,
                expresses<lb/> the unanimous sentiment of the people of this country<lb/> on the
                topic under consideration. Here we <emph rend="italics">have tried</emph><lb/> the
                experiment of granting political equality to Jews<lb/> in common with other
                denominations of religionists,<lb/> and have found it to work kindly and well. No
                evils<lb/> have resulted from it, but the contrary.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">Communicated for the Journal of Commerce.</p>
            <p>TO <addressee>SIR CULLING E. EARDLEY</addressee>, <placeName>BART.,
                    LONDON</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">From your late kind letter, the receipt of which I<lb/> gratefully
                acknowledge, my dear <persName>Sir Culling</persName>, you will<lb/> probably be
                leaving <placeName>London</placeName>, as I judge, for
                <placeName>Berlin</placeName>,<lb/> by the time this reaches you; to attend that
                meeting<lb/> of our Evangelical Alliance, which His Majesty, the<lb/>
                <persName>King</persName> of <placeName>Prussia</placeName>, has invited to his own
                capital, and<lb/> which, according to your kind urgency and that of<lb/> several
                others, I should be happy to attend, were this<lb/> compatible with relative duties
                here. As it is, you<lb/> will have some worthy representatives from
                    <placeName>America</placeName>,<lb/> beside <persName>Rev. Dr. Baird</persName>,
                    <persName>Rev. Dr. Kirk</persName>, <persName>Rev. Dr.
                Alex<lb/>ander</persName>, and a number of others, extensively and favor-<lb/>ably
                known in both hemispheres. As the grand<lb/> crowner of all, may the Great Head of
                the Church,<lb/> the King of <placeName>Sion</placeName>, our Lord and Saviour
                    <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, be<lb/> with you: illumining your way;
                prospering your de-<lb/>liberations and measures, to such results, as HIMSELF<lb/>
                may consistently perpetuate and bless, to the good of<lb/> nations, and ultimately
                to the conversion of the world<lb/> to the knowledge of the only living and true
                God.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">On another occasion, <persName>Sir Culling</persName>, I hope to
                enjoy<lb/> the luxury of your correspondence in a more extended<lb/> and private
                form; and also never to have it totally in-<lb/>termitted or relinquished, while we
                are both, by the<lb/> sovereign pleasure of God, continued in the present<lb/>
                world. But I seem to have a special reason for this<lb/> public letter; in reference
                to a topic of common and<lb/> ecumenical interest to Christian States and
                Christian<lb/> men; especially to the English world, both Anglican<lb/> and
                Anglo-American; as well as related to the legiti-<lb/>mate objects of the
                Evangelical Alliance, and the pro-<lb/>gress of Christianity, with its ascendant
                ju-<lb/>risdiction in the whole world. That topic<lb/> may vindicate the propriety,
                as well as il-<lb/>lustrate the design of this public
                    commu-<lb/><sic>munication</sic>. I allude distinctly to the recent action
                of<lb/> the House of Lords, in their rejection of the bill for<lb/> the removal of
                Jewish disabilities, in respect to the<lb/> oath required to be taken by the members
                of Parlia-<lb/>ment.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is not my plan to review the proceedings or the<lb/> speeches of
                their Lordships, though that of the <persName>Earl</persName> of<lb/>
                <placeName>Derby</placeName> especially, Lord Chancellor as he is, <persName>Sir
                    Cul-<lb/>ling</persName>, or your own venerated <emph rend="italics">Alma
                    Mater</emph>, the Univer-<lb/>sity of <placeName>Oxford</placeName>, I view as
                rather invitingly vulnerable;<lb/> especially in contrast with the nobler, and I
                must say,<lb/> the wiser views of the new <persName>Lord Bishop</persName> of
                    <placeName>London</placeName>. I<lb/> only design to take general regards of the
                matter, es-<lb/>pecially its results and its tendencies, as connected<lb/> with the
                duty of Christian men and the enlightened<lb/> policy of Christian nations; and
                these as seen by my<lb/> own countrymen, the most evangelical and intelligent<lb/>
                of them, and indeed by our whole country of the<lb/>
                <placeName>United States</placeName>; lamenting the position of their<lb/>
                Lordships, and censuring them for conduct, at<lb/> once, in their view, improper,
                unreasonable, inutile,<lb/> unprotestant, and derogatory to the just progress
                and<lb/> prospect of our age and their own great nation, as well<lb/> as savoring of
                the spirit of persecution toward so large,<lb/> and so opulent, and so respectable a
                portion of their<lb/> fellow-subjects. There is an animus in the action,<lb/> whose
                influence is easily detected, and must be dis-<lb/>approved by all the more elevated
                Christianity of<lb/> Christendom. Is ours the doctrine of the masters of<lb/> the
                Inquisitorial Commission? Is it our duty to <emph rend="italics">per-</emph><lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">secute</emph> any who may differ from us in religious
                views?<lb/> Is it the best way to benefit them, the way of wisdom<lb/> to convince
                them, or the proper way to conciliate to<lb/> our success the necessary benediction
                of our God?<lb/> Has he authorized it? What damage could accrue to<lb/> the State by
                honoring, in favor of the Israelite, at once,<lb/> his consistency and his scruples
                in the matter?<lb/> We are surprised, are grieved, at the conduct of<lb/> their
                Lordships. Its echoes are not excellent<lb/> or musical on this side of the
                    <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>.<lb/> We all think that they will not bear to
                be<lb/> reviewed in the strong light, either of honorable and<lb/> wise
                statesmanship, or of evangelical truth; and the<lb/> peers of
                    <placeName>England</placeName>, if they wish not to degrade their no-<lb/>bility
                in the eyes of all the world, as well as through-<lb/>out the immense majority of
                the Christian sentiment<lb/> of the British nation, ought to <emph rend="italics">go
                    and sin no more</emph>,<lb/> against the people who gave us the Holy
                Scriptures,<lb/> the nation from whom and of whom was our blessed<lb/> Saviour! and
                whom to persecute has been the shame,<lb/> the history, and the sin, of almost
                universal Christen-<lb/>dom.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is my definite object, my dear <persName>Sir Culling</persName>,
                to<lb/> commend THIS TOPIC to the solemn consideration of<lb/> the Evangelical
                Alliance, and also to their lucid and<lb/> deliberate action. It were well for them
                to act on it.<lb/> The learning and the piety and the dignity that are<lb/> there to
                convene, will make the metropolis of His<lb/> Majesty, <persName>Frederick
                    William</persName>, for the time, the lumi-<lb/>nous focal centre of
                Christendom. It seems to<lb/> court or claim the attention of mankind.<lb/> I am
                persuaded that in an assemblage so<lb/> august and so eminent, so truly
                philanthropic, so<lb/> sincerely Christian, and so signally <sic>patronised</sic> by
                one<lb/> of the noblest and most excellent sovereigns in the<lb/> world, their
                collective wisdom can be neither a discord<lb/> nor an ambiguity. Nor can it be
                unheeded. May we<lb/> not, then, hope for a worthy, out-spoken, and
                loud-<lb/>sounding deliverance, from their assembled and deli-<lb/>berative
                multitude? Shall such an occasion be lost to<lb/> the cause of universal liberty of
                conscience? We need<lb/> not remind them that the only legitimate monarch of<lb/>
                the conscience is the King of Kings and the Lord of<lb/> Lords.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It has struck me, too, my honored friend, that my<lb/> own dear
                country—with all its faults, I love it still—<lb/> may, with singular propriety, be
                the <emph rend="italics">censor morum</emph><lb/> of <placeName>Great
                    Britain</placeName>, on such a topic as this. If<lb/> you are the parent nation,
                the older and the<lb/> wiser, ought you not to set us, and the rest of<lb/> mankind,
                a wise and good example—and none other?<lb/> Whatever may be our delinquencies and
                sins, I must<lb/> urge that here the comparison is to us eminently hon-<lb/>orable!
                We have set you and the world in this, if not<lb/> in some other particulars, a
                noble and a good exam-<lb/>ple. We are the only great Christian nation known<lb/> to
                me, that has, either in popular sentiment or in our<lb/> civil enactments, NEVER
                AUTHORISED THE PRESECU-<lb/>TION OF THE JEWS. On the contrary, we have
                cher-<lb/>ished, respected and protected them. For this, pleased<lb/> and almost
                proud of it, I rejoice and bless the God of<lb/>
                <persName>Abraham</persName>. In our country, no law is framed for the<lb/>
                disfranchisement of one of them. The controversy<lb/> between the synagogue and the
                church is properly and<lb/> well maintained, on the basis of moral, historical,
                pro-<lb/>phetical and scriptural argumentation, and that alone.<lb/> Socially,
                commercially and vicinally, as well<lb/> as in all the general relations of life,
                our<lb/> intercourse is polite and kind, and our Christian<lb/> piety makes us
                respect them with sincere considera-<lb/>tion and benignity. Our first
                    <persName>President, WASHINGTON</persName>,<lb/> when first inaugurated in
                    <date>1789</date>, was approached and<lb/> addressed by their Rabbis and their
                Chiefs, from dif-<lb/>ferent cities, in terms of lauded propriety, and of
                law-<lb/>abiding fidelity to the established Government; and<lb/> that incomparable
                PATER PATRIAE, <emph rend="italics">patiens vocari</emph>, re-<lb/>plied to them in
                a style worthy of his official station,<lb/> worthy of his exalted character, worthy
                of the senti-<lb/>ments of a great though then comparatively youthful<lb/> nation.
                We have fully tried the unique experiment<lb/> ever since, and now report in their
                favor. They are<lb/> in the main characteristically good citizens; and we<lb/>
                should have no comparable hope that God would ever<lb/> use and honor us to make
                them good Christians, if,<lb/> misrepresenting the goodness of the Author of
                Chris-<lb/>tianity, we were to scorn, insult, abuse, or injure them<lb/>—as
                    <persName>WASHINGTON</persName>, to say nothing of any higher sanc-<lb/>tion,
                could never patronize, or willingly for one mo-<lb/>ment endure!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The reasons of their Lordships for retiring the bill<lb/> are
                immensely unsatisfactory. With all proper rever-<lb/>ence for their exalted
                position, as hereditary senators<lb/> of <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>, let
                it be something to them, that our<lb/> superior Christian civilization, as
                constructively<lb/> viewed in the contrast, redounds, in
                    <placeName>America</placeName> and in<lb/> all the world, only to our praise and
                to their own<lb/> manifold and manifest disparagement. The sins of<lb/> the Jews,
                their unbelief and alleged indocility, the<lb/> prophecies of retribution that
                regard them, however<lb/> clearly identified in their just interpretation and
                scope<lb/> as affecting them, afford no apology, or mitigation of<lb/> blame, to
                Christian nations, if any are found volun-<lb/>teering to punish them for it. It is
                that which<lb/> God has forbidden, not required at our hand. Be-<lb/>side, what harm
                can possibly accrue to church or<lb/> State, by conceding to them, as well as to
                Romanists<lb/> and Quakers, all their civil and political rights? Is<lb/> not a man
                fully qualified, so far as an oath goes or<lb/> ought to go, in civil relations,
                either Christian or Mo-<lb/>hommedan, or Jew or Heretic, when, on his
                responsi-<lb/>bility to God and man, he promises, in any court of<lb/> record or
                before competent witnesses, to do his duty<lb/> according to law? The proper
                jurisdiction of magis-<lb/>trates ought there to pause and be satisfied;—<emph
                    rend="italics">to God</emph><lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">the things that are God's</emph>! It is not theirs to
                interpose<lb/> between a man's conscience or creed, and that most<lb/> holy Judge
                eternal, to whom his and our account is so<lb/> soon to be rendered, with infallible
                equity and truth.<lb/> This is the doctrine of my country; and not on that
                ac-<lb/>count, but for higher reasons, it ought to be, in all con-<lb/>sistency and
                policy, the doctrine of every Christian<lb/> country on the globe. UBI LIBERTAS, IBI
                PATRIA.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Among the signs of the times, <persName>Sir Culling</persName>, it
                has not<lb/> escaped your own meditative sagacity as a christian,<lb/> that god is
                bringing that wonderful people to a<lb/> wonderful crisis in their destiny. They
                are<lb/> not relatively the people they were, to Christen-<lb/>dom, in the periods
                of mediaeval history. They have<lb/> risen, improved in social position, more
                intelligent,<lb/> eminently more potential, and now much more con-<lb/>siderable,
                even in the politics of <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">They hold the purse-strings of nations. They com-<lb/>mand the
                sinews of war, in the hostile moves of princes.<lb/> How much on bond and mortgage,
                with <placeName>England</placeName><lb/> and <placeName>France</placeName> to
                guarantee the payment, own they, of the<lb/> territories of the Sultan in
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, of the Pope in<lb/>
                <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and of many mighty monarchs in other places!<lb/> How
                prodigiously has their wealth accumulated! In<lb/> the <placeName>United
                    States</placeName>, within my own memory, their num-<lb/>bers, their synagogues,
                their intelligence, their opu-<lb/>lence, their respectability and influence, have
                steadily<lb/> altered, in one direction only. They love this country,<lb/> with
                reason. It is their occidental <placeName>Palestine</placeName>. They<lb/> have
                never done us harm—nor we them. I love to<lb/> think that God, who is said to govern
                nations in this<lb/> world, in which alone as nations they exist, according<lb/> to
                their secular and collective conduct in it, has mani-<lb/>festly blest us, for so
                hospitably, and so equally, and<lb/> so singularly entertaining them; and I feel no
                desire<lb/> that <placeName>America</placeName> should have the blessing in
                monopoly;<lb/> and not in communion with other Christian na-<lb/>tions, especially—I
                say it with liberal and gen-<lb/>uine filial piety—especially with <placeName>GREAT
                    BRIT-<lb/>AIN</placeName>! yes! there is an allied reason which I may not<lb/>
                omit to urge—the injuries they have suffered at the<lb/> hands of our fathers; in
                contrast with the benefits we<lb/> have derived, so vast and so incomparable, from
                that long<lb/> dismembered nation. Let us rather try to compensate<lb/> them for
                what they have had to feel and to bear—pri-<lb/>vations, ignominies, ostracisms,
                malignities, cruelties,<lb/> amercements, civil deaths, imprisonments, exiles,
                pro-<lb/>scriptions, and all manner of abuse! Are not justice<lb/> and generosity
                here to be co-operative in their favor;<lb/> practically one in all wise measures of
                reconciliation<lb/> and benevolence? How will the repeated and now too<lb/>
                systematic action of their Lordships look, when the<lb/> pen of truth shall portray
                it in full, on the page of his-<lb/>tory—especially if soon hereafter some Christian
                Israel-<lb/>ite, learned as <persName>Neander</persName>, shall move that pen? I
                blush<lb/> for the renowned posterity of the <persName>Earl</persName> of
                    <placeName>Derby</placeName>, if they<lb/> shall ever read, in the
                    <date>twentieth century</date> of the Chris-<lb/>tian era, the speeches in
                parliament of their august<lb/> ancestor; who seems now rather unconscious of
                such<lb/> an amphitheatre of interested yet impartial specta-<lb/>tors.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Those who have been studiously and pro-<lb/>fessedly conversant with
                the prophecies, are<lb/> mainly agreed, that, in the order of coming<lb/> events,
                the recovery of all the tribes of the long-<lb/>repudiated nation, to the knowledge
                of the only<lb/> true Messiah, to the hope of the Saviour of
                    <persName>Abraham</persName><lb/> and <persName>Isaac</persName> and
                    <persName>Jacob</persName>, CANNOT BE, IN THE FUTURE, DIS-<lb/>TANT FAR! <emph
                    rend="italics">And, so all <placeName>Israel</placeName> shall be saved; as it
                    is<lb/> written, there shall come out of <placeName>Sion</placeName> the
                    Deliverer, and shall<lb/> turn away ungodliness from <persName>Jacob</persName>;
                </emph>FOR THIS<emph rend="italics"> is my cove-<lb/>nant to them when I shall take
                    away their sins.</emph></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If the wheels of his chariot are to be delayed, I hope<lb/> the
                Lords Spiritual and the Lords Temporal of <placeName>England</placeName><lb/> are
                not to be in concert distinguished, as the fore-<lb/>doomed clogs of retardation, in
                the righteous judgment<lb/> of God; preventing for a season his destined and<lb/>
                triumphant progression through the world! But there<lb/> is a principle in the
                legislative intolerance of their<lb/> Lordships; there is a typical implication in
                it;<lb/> there is a sign of ominous and opaque aspect,<lb/> which makes me tremble
                for your fast-anchored<lb/> isle; rather than congratulate its government on<lb/>
                its adamantine fixity, or the certitude of its amicable<lb/> alliance with <emph
                    rend="italics">the reigning Lord God Omnipotent</emph>. The<lb/> Jews are yet
                    <emph rend="italics">beloved for the Fathers' sake</emph>. God is
                    un-<lb/>changeable—<emph rend="italics">the gifts and calling of God are without
                    re-<lb/>pentance</emph>; and I believe HE will punish those nations<lb/> that
                dare to injure them! I pray God to inspire the<lb/> illustrious brethren and fathers
                of your noble CONFER-<lb/>ENCE at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, now to meet in a
                few weeks, with<lb/> manly wisdom and godly truth, TO SPEAK FOR THE<lb/> RIGHT; so
                that their words may be like the echoes of<lb/> the artillery of heaven: to reach
                the spirits of men,<lb/> the intimacies of their moral consciousness, in the
                Old<lb/> World and the New World; warning them to <emph rend="italics">prepare<lb/>
                    the way of the LORD, </emph>and welcome his spiritual ad-<lb/>vances, as with
                the song of seraphs on the plains of<lb/>
                <placeName>Bethlehem of Judah</placeName>; saying, GLORY TO GOD IN THE<lb/> HIGHEST,
                PEACE ON EARTH, AND GOOD WILL TO MEN!<lb/> Our Saviour has told us—SALVATION IS OF
                THE JEWS!<lb/> OUR BLESSED SAVIOUR, our Redeemer and Lord <persName>Jesus<lb/>
                    Christ</persName>, was himself—A JEW.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We are all plainly bound to show them kindness,<lb/> and accord to
                them all the franchises and privileges of<lb/> religious freedom. I cannot help
                recording it, <persName>Sir Cul-<lb/>ling</persName>, to the honor of the Commons of
                    <placeName>England</placeName>, that so<lb/> strong a vote carried the plainly
                necessary reform in<lb/> the House! Let their Lordships not be too lofty to<lb/>
                consider it—in time. I am glad too that the consti-<lb/>tuency are so calmly and
                justly willing to repeat the<lb/> election of their candidate and representative.
                    <emph rend="italics">No<lb/> effort for the right, </emph>said your and our
                    <persName>Milton</persName>, <emph rend="italics">was ever<lb/> wholly
                    lost</emph>. The HUZZAS of <placeName>America</placeName> cheer them across<lb/>
                the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>—while the ALLELUIAS of Christians ascend<lb/> to
                God on both sides of it, when they pray—for the<lb/> salvation of all men!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">On this particular topic, my dear <persName>Sir Culling</persName>,
                I ac-<lb/>quit you before the world of all responsibility. I know<lb/> not indeed,
                as to details, what are your own politi-<lb/>cal estimates of the matter; how it may
                or may<lb/> not compromise or facilitate your influence; and I<lb/> have written
                this from my heart's fulness, in humble<lb/> hope of doing some good to the
                "magnificent and<lb/> awful cause" of RELIGIOUS LIBERTY; in which I<lb/> glory to
                say that my own is—<emph rend="italics">posthabita Samo,</emph>
                <placeName>Eng-<lb/>land</placeName>—the model country of the globe! <emph
                    rend="italics">Esto perpetua!</emph></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Thanking you, my good and honored brother in<lb/>
                <persName>Christ</persName>, for all your public-spirited enterprizes of
                bene-<lb/>ficence, for all your noble bearing toward <placeName>America</placeName>
                and<lb/> Americans, and for all your devoted and busy attach-<lb/>ment to the cause
                of the propagated truth of Christi-<lb/>anity, <emph rend="italics">in all the world
                    and to every creature</emph>, and thank-<lb/>ing you for your uniform kindness
                to myself, I remain,<lb/> with high respect, fraternally, yours in the ties
                un-<lb/>earthly of our common and glorious Christianity.</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><persName role="author">SAMUEL HANSON COX</persName>.</p>
            <p><placeName>NEW YORK</placeName>, <date>August 10, 1857</date>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
