<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0028</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.N.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865">1865</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865">5625</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0028_1R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0028_1V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0028_2R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0028_2V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0028_3R.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <add>ערב פסח</add>
            </p>
            <p>
                <date>5625</date>
                <add>
                    <date>1865</date>
                </add>
            </p>
            <p>My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">Your letter of <date>March 7th</date> is<lb/> received but I have no
                time to send a<lb/> lengthened reply. The cause of my silence is<lb/> not sickness,
                I am, thank God, in good health;<lb/> Every moment of the day is however so
                occupied<lb/> with Synagogue and School that I have no<lb/> leisure to write. I have
                a sacred duty to perform;<lb/> to lay by what may serve to keep my poor<lb/> wife in
                case of my death, <add>ממתנות בשר ודם</add>. She is<lb/> a hopeless invalid, and I
                want to screen her, while<lb/> I have the power to work, from the cold charity<lb/>
                of the world. Otherwise I would not labor 11<lb/> hours a day at school-keeping in
                this Enervating<lb/> climate. Often do I reproach myself with<lb/> neglecting my old
                friends, but Even when disposed<lb/> to take up the pew, I am physically unable.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am not disposed to find fault with you<lb/> for your unasked
                opinion on the subject of the<lb/> calling to the Sepher of the <add>בר מצוה</add>
                <add>“Bar Mitzvah” JE transcription</add>. I regret you<lb/> have been appealed to,
                and hope you have not</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in the right bottom corner of the page.">two
                sheets<lb/>20-613</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>given a decided opinion on the subject. When<lb/> I was first here, no boy was ever
                called up<lb/> before being confirmed, and the plan was so far<lb/> beneficial that
                every boy who came to Sepher was<lb/> acquainted <del>by</del> with the leading
                principles of his faith.<lb/> Things changed for the worse during my absence,<lb/>
                and I have had enough to do, to bring matters with<lb/> a proper train. Your
                interference, well meant<lb/> as I am sure it is, will only weaken my hands.<lb/> I
                do not care a straw for confirmation, except<lb/> as a means of Enabling me to
                impart, months before the ceremony takes place, religious instruction,<lb/> at least
                its chief Elements. The Sunday School<lb/> is very good in its way, but it is not
                sufficient<lb/> for the purpose. The child you allude to, was<lb/> brought up in
                    <placeName>N/O</placeName>, and did not know anything.<lb/> The <sic>Bar
                    Mitzva</sic>, under such circumstances is<lb/> a sin and a mockery. But what is
                the Bar<lb/> Mitzvah? If <placeName>Israel</placeName> was <add>יום טוב</add>, why
                was<lb/> the Bar Mitzvah instituted? It is clearly a<lb/> Rabbinical mode of
                Confirmation, prefaced as it<lb/> has always been by sound religious
                instruction.</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>Unless this be erroneous, and I shall be very<lb/> glad if you will set me right, in
                case I am<lb/> wrong in this view, confirmation stands on<lb/> the same footing as
                the old method of<lb/> instruction, and as the ancient mode of giving<lb/> the boy a
                    fulness<add>?</add> of knowledge before his 13th year<lb/> is no longer
                possible, I, and others, situated<lb/> as I am, must do our best to substitute
                something<lb/> Else before calling up to Sepher, in order that<lb/> the Bar Mitzvah,
                as in many Congregations,<lb/> may not dwindle away with a meaningless<lb/>
                ceremony, only connected with new clothes,<lb/> a gold watch, and a good breakfast,
                    d<add>?</add>,<lb/> or dance. The child in question is nevertheless<lb/> so
                hopelessly stupid, that, since the receipt of your<lb/> last, I have resolved on
                calling him to Sepher without<lb/> preparatory confirmation. My nephew
                    <persName>David</persName>,<lb/> whose Bar Mitzvah is at hand, I intend to
                confirm.<lb/> And then, I am sure, people here will be as anxious<lb/> for its
                reintroduction, as they were favorable to it<lb/> in former times. The Reform party
                here is<lb/> bestirring itself, and it will need all my prudence</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>savoir dire and savoir faire to prevent and outbreak<lb/> similar to what has
                occurred in <placeName>Curacao</placeName>. The party<lb/> wishes to go to extreme
                lengths, an organ, <persName>Marks's</persName><lb/> prayer Book and other ultras
                are spoken of.<lb/> Another party <hi rend="underline">who want no minister</hi>,
                but simply<lb/> a reader to marry and bury them is on the watch<lb/> to create
                disturbances, and bring about a separation.<lb/> The Congregation cannot support two
                Synagogues.<lb/> The By Laws are also against such a step. There<lb/> is much talk
                about petitioning the government<lb/> to repeal these By Laws. Should that be
                done,<lb/> “<persName>Othello's</persName> occupation's gone.” For neither party
                could<lb/> give me my present salary, which is barely able<lb/> to support me in
                this extravagantly dear place.<lb/> I want no organ, <del>and</del> nor do I want
                    <persName>Marks's</persName> Prayer<lb/> Book. It would be laughable, were the
                affair not<lb/> so serious, to hear the crude notions of the young and<lb/> the old
                on this topic, Reform. Some of the hitherto<lb/> hyper-orthodox, among the rest, the
                party who<lb/> addressed you on the case of the Bar Mitzvah,<lb/> advocate the most
                incongruous measures. I keep<lb/> silence and have given no opinion except the<lb/>
                organ and Prayer Book. At the proper time it<lb/> must, by Law, be referred to me.
                But unless there be<lb/> something like unanimity, and no <del>pr</del> likelihood
                of<lb/> discussion, I will not give my adhesion to any<lb/> proposals for changing
                our present system of<lb/> worship which is working admirably. You are<lb/> happily
                ignorant of the perfidy and treachery of<lb/> Curacaoleans. Do not heed what they
                write you, they<lb/> are not to be trusted. They are injudicious friend, and<lb/>
                are terable<add>?</add> enemies<lb/> and the turn of a straw changes</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in pencil at the top right corner of the page.">
                <date>1865</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p>them from one to the other. You can now<lb/> comprehend the position I am placed in.
                The<lb/> question was put to you out of pique against me, not from any religious
                motive. I guessed<lb/> it would be done and was therefore not surprised at<lb/> nor
                angry with, the contents of your letter.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am about sending you some money for<lb/> the dozen Bibles and the
                few Prayer Books had<lb/> last year. But I have no memorandum of the<lb/> cards of
                Creeds &amp;c sent me at same time. I<lb/> wrote you of having received the
                missing<lb/> Books p “Responsible,” but as I have no<lb/> place to keep them in, I
                intend handing them<lb/> to my <persName>David Piza</persName> to dispose of in
                your<lb/> accot<add>?</add>. They have been damaged by sea-water<lb/> and must be
                sold considerably under the usual<lb/> price.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I must now conclude with wishing you <add>שמחת</add><lb/>
                <add>פסח</add>, in which <persName>Mrs. N.</persName>—her mother, and
                    <persName>David</persName><lb/> join, with remembrances to old friends with
                whom<lb/> we spent <add>Hebrew</add> a quarter of a century ago.</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">I am</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">MNNathan</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
