<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_12_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Cincinnati, OH</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1868-11">November 27, 1868</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_12_1.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_12_2.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >miscellany</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="align(center)">THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">ISRAELITE.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName>BLOCH &amp; CO.</persName>, Publishers.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>CINCINNATI,
                    OHIO</placeName>,....................<date>NOVEMBER 27, 1868</date>.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName>GRANT</persName> AND THE JEWS.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We cheerfully give place to the following<lb/> distinguished
                correspondence which will,<lb/> beyond all doubt, be read with pleasure by<lb/> all
                of our readers who, like ourselves, de-<lb/>sire to see justice done to
                    <persName>General Grant</persName>,<lb/> now the incoming Executive head of
                the<lb/> Government:</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">(Letter from Hon. <persName>I. N. Morris</persName>, of
                    <placeName>Ill.</placeName>)</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>QUINCY, ILL.</placeName>, <date>Nov. 15,
                1868</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="italics"><persName>Dr. Isaac M. Wise</persName>, Editor of the
                    Israelite:</emph>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I send you enclosed a copy of a letter in<lb/> my possession from
                    <persName>General Grant</persName>, together<lb/> with one from <persName>Mr.
                    Moses</persName> written to <persName>General<lb/> Grant</persName>, and to
                which this is a reply. Few men<lb/> have the moral greatness of character to<lb/>
                write such a letter. Its publication during<lb/> the pendency of the election would
                have cast<lb/> suspicion on the motive which prompted it,<lb/> no such suspicion can
                arise now.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am aware that you and many of you<lb/> have conceived that
                    <persName>General Grant</persName> did you<lb/> great injustice in promulgating
                Order No.<lb/> 11. His frank denial of any such intention<lb/> proves not only the
                magnanimity of his<lb/> character, but that he is incapable of enter-<lb/>taining
                against the Jews, or any other peo-<lb/>ple, as a sect or race, an unkind feeling.
                He<lb/> is too great and good for that. Will you,<lb/> therefore, do the General the
                justice to pub-<lb/>lish his letter in your widely extended<lb/> paper. I assume the
                liberty of sending it<lb/> to you for that purpose. I remain, sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yours, respectfully,</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)"><persName>I. N. MORRIS</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">(Letter from <persName>Adolph Moses, Esq.</persName>, to
                    <persName>General Grant</persName>.)</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>QUINCY, ILL.</placeName>, <date>Sept. 3,
                1868</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="italics"><persName>Gen. U. S. Grant</persName>, <placeName>Washington,
                        D. C.</placeName></emph>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">SIR—I address you at the earnest solicita-<lb/>tion of your friend,
                Hon. <persName>I. N. Morris</persName>, in<lb/> relation to the matter now generally
                known<lb/> as Order No. 11. It will hardly surprise you<lb/> that we, as a people,
                already over-sensitive<lb/> through former oppression and contumely<lb/> should
                lament the issuance of that order,<lb/> whatever the immediate causes might<lb/>
                have dictated. I am assured by high author-<lb/>ity, some of which I might call
                Jewish, that<lb/> no idea of special dislike to the Jews<lb/> prompted you, on the
                contrary, that you<lb/> regret the sweeping effect of the order.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">However generous this avowal may be on<lb/> your part, yet you are
                well aware that a<lb/> word spoken or a sentence written ceases<lb/> to be the
                property of the speaker or writer<lb/> and passes into the domain of history,
                par-<lb/>ticularly when spoken or written by a man<lb/> of super-eminent position
                and worth. I<lb/> regret that our people, who love to enjoy the<lb/> quiet retreat
                of private life, should be so<lb/> prominently paraded in this campaign, but<lb/>
                the instinct of self-defense presses utter-<lb/>ance, however unwelcome the task.
                Our<lb/> demands are simply to be judged like other<lb/> people and not to have the
                vices and short-<lb/>coming of our bad men illuminated at the<lb/> expense of the
                many virtues and excellent<lb/> qualities of our good men.</p>
            <p> rend="indent(1)"Whatever the issue of this campaign may<lb/> be, <persName>Mr.
                    M.</persName>, assures me that you bear no ill-<lb/>will to the Jewish people,
                and if they feel<lb/> the severe compulsion to cast their <sic>suffrages</sic><lb/>
                against you in this campaign, they do so—<lb/>in many instances—<emph rend="italics"
                    >under protest</emph>, for with<lb/> them their long-assailed reputation
                de-<lb/>mands the greatest sacrifices, even at the<lb/> risk of being misunderstood
                by the judg-<lb/>ment of the hour. Excuse the liberty of<lb/> addressing you—I have
                the encouragement<lb/> of one of your friends.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Very, respectfully.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)"><persName>ADOLPH MOSES</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">(Letter from <persName>General Grant</persName> to hon. <persName>I.
                    N. Morris</persName>.)</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>GALENA, ILL.</placeName>, <date>Sept. 14,
                1868</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <emph rend="italics">Hon. <persName>I. N. Morris</persName>:</emph>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">DEAR SIR—I am in receipt of a letter of<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. A. Moses</persName> of the <date>3rd</date> inst., enclosing one<lb/>
                from you, bearing same date. My first in-<lb/>clination was to answer <persName>Mr.
                    Moses</persName>, because<lb/> you desired it; then I thought it would be<lb/>
                better to adhere to the rule of silence as to<lb/> all letters. Were I once to
                commence an-<lb/>swering all political questions asked of me,<lb/> there would not
                be time between now and<lb/> the <date>3rd of November</date> to get through.
                    <persName>Mr.<lb/> Moses</persName>, I think, will readily understand this.<lb/>
                In regard to Order No. 11, hundreds of let-<lb/>ters have been written to me about
                it by<lb/> persons of the faith affected by it. I do or<lb/> did not answer any of
                the writers, but per-<lb/>mitted a statement of the facts concerning<lb/> the origin
                of the order to be made out and<lb/> given to some one of them for publication.<lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">I do not pretend to sustain the order</emph>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">At the time of its publication, I was in-<lb/>censed by a reprimand
                received from <placeName>Wash-<lb/>ington</placeName> for permitting acts which
                Jews<lb/> within my lines were engaged in. There<lb/> were many other persons within
                my lines<lb/> equally bad with the worst of them, but the<lb/> difference was that
                the Jews could pass<lb/> with impunity from one army to the other,<lb/> and gold, in
                violation of orders, was being<lb/> smuggled through the lines, at least so it<lb/>
                was reported. The order was issued and<lb/> sent without any reflection and
                without<lb/> thinking of the Jews as a sect or race to<lb/> themselves, but simply
                as persons who had<lb/> successfully (I say successfully, instead of<lb/>
                persistently, because there were plenty of<lb/> others within my lines who envied
                their<lb/> success) violated an order, which greatly<lb/> inured to the help of the
                rebels.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><emph rend="italics">Give <persName>Mr. Moses</persName> assurance
                    that I have no<lb/> prejudice against sect or race, but want each<lb/>
                    individual to be judged by his own merit</emph>. Or-<lb/>der No. 11 does not
                sustain this statement,<lb/> I admit, but then <emph rend="italics">I do not sustain
                    that order</emph>.<lb/> It never would have been issued, if it had<lb/> not been
                telegraphed the moment it was<lb/> penned, and without reflection.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yours, truly,</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)"><persName>U. S. GRANT</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We shall have something to say in our<lb/> next issue in view of the
                above correspond-<lb/>ence, as also in further definition of the<lb/> course taken
                by us respecting <persName>General<lb/> Grant</persName> and Order No. 11, prior to
                his nom-<lb/>ination by the <placeName>Chicago</placeName> Convention; not<lb/> that
                the disinterestedness or rectitude of<lb/> THE ISRAELITE in those premises need
                any<lb/> re-affirmation, but that the history of Order<lb/> No. 11 and of the
                commotion produced by<lb/> it would be less complete without that final<lb/> word of
                ours.—ED. IS.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
