<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Halevi, Joseph</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_NC-30</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Halevi,
                            Joseph</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Cleveland, OH</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url=""/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">no beginning <add>?</add>
                <persName role="author">Joseph Ha Levi</persName><lb/>
                <placeName>Clevela</placeName><lb/>
                <date>ca. 1852</date><lb/> "<persName>Leeser</persName>"</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="underline">
                    <add>Hebrew</add>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p>from things prohibited and from forbidden sex relations. Every learned<lb/> man knows
                that thought about a misdeed is worse than the misdeed itself,<lb/> because the
                thought is the work of the <del>body</del> spirit whereas the misdeed is the<lb/>
                work of the body. Now if men and women, boys and girls, sit together,<lb/> can they
                be free of unworthy thought? Will you blind the eyes of man,<lb/> so that they
                should not see the beauty of the girls and the women?<lb/> Especially since there
                are lewd people, even though their number be small,<lb/> we have to turn our eye
                even upon this minority. Or if there are seated<lb/> mischievous boys, and they see
                at their side an old woman with wrinkled<lb/> face, she will be for them a matter of
                playfulness and fun. Such are<lb/> the evil thought which will destroy the ways of
                modesty; these are the<lb/> ways of the shadow of death and disorder.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Please understand, my friends and brothers, that the aim of all
                man-<lb/>kind is to improve its actions, and the aim of every holy community is<lb/>
                to perfect its ways, and is this the road for the perfection of our souls?<lb/>
                Shall we attain to purity and holiness by means of this change? No, my<lb/>
                brothers. Do not do evil. Do not change good customs established upon<lb/> pillars
                of modesty and righteousness which increase eternal life, for new<lb/> ways, resting
                upon acts that bring no profit and of little good intention,<lb/> which increase
                disorder and confusion, whose way is hell and perdition.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Look at your brothers, <persName>Montefiore</persName> and
                    <persName>Rothschild</persName>, and the other prin-<lb/>ces and wealthy men of
                    <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, <placeName>Prague</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Frankfort</placeName>, and the other European<lb/> communities. Their
                houses are filled with gold and silver. They lack<lb/> nothing that is good,
                nevertheless, they are not ashamed of the customs<lb/> of their ancestors, as they
                received them from ancient days, and they<lb/> glorify the Holy One of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. Ask about the corners of the earth, the<lb/> holy
                communities of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africa</placeName>. Did
                they ever do a thing like this?<lb/> Why then should you pride yourself in
                    <placeName>America</placeName> with strange doings, and<lb/> show off with
                novelties that bring no good.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And if you ask, "Do not all the nations among whom we dwell, the
                same.<lb/> Do they not go to pray in their houses of prayer, a mixed company, and
                are<lb/> not afraid of immoral thoughts, then why should we differ from them?"<lb/>
                To this I shall answer you briefly. Who among you will give surety for<lb/> the
                purity of their thoughts? Frequently I heard their young men say,<lb/> ""Let us go
                to that church, for pretty girls gather there". And now, if<lb/> you desire, wager
                with me, and I shall give my entire wealth that if we ask<lb/> the wise men of the
                gentiles and their priests which the road is, to<lb/> guide toward purity of heart
                and holiness, they will admit and frankly<lb/> say that our way is the holy one, for
                men and women to sit separately.<lb/> This is the straight path for coming near to
                God; it has the greater power<lb/> and great strength, just as light is superior to
                darkness.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Last but not least, the last argument is very dear to me, in
                our<lb/> Torah it is written, "And ye shall be for me a kingdom of priests and
                a<lb/> holy nation", also the majority of the prophets prophesied in this vein,<lb/>
                "And <del>the</del> many nations shall go according to thy light", therefore, it is
                in-<lb/>cumbent upon us all the more to guard ourselves from every stumbling<lb/>
                block and sin, and to remove from our synagogues, the least thing that<lb/> might
                bring a thought of wickedness. Thus will the light of our Torah<lb/> shine upon the
                face of the whole world and bring about the proper spirit<lb/> in the heart of all
                its inhabitants.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Beloved brothers, pay attention to my words and do not disdain
                my<lb/> reproof. Receive the advice of your brother who seeks the peace of his<lb/>
                people and desires its honor and glory forever.</p>
            <p><persName role="author">Joseph Halevi</persName>, merchant<lb/> in the city of
                    <placeName>Cleveland</placeName><lb/> and member of the congregation<lb/> Ansche
                Chessed Yisrael</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
