<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Block, E.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0116</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Block, E.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1849-09" source="" attested="yes">September 5, 1849</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0116_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0116_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0116_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0116_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>2 pages on 1 sheet
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>N. York.</placeName> <date>Sep 5. 1849</date></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Dear <addressee>Isaac</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">I owe you an apology for<lb/> my neglect in failing to inform you earlier<lb/> of my design to relinquish my school.<lb/>  You know too well my friendship &#38; esteem for<lb/> you and how highly I estimate your good opinion<lb/> to believe for a moment that my silence could<lb/> be owing to any cause unpleasant or offensive<lb/> to you the fact is simply that altho I have<lb/> for a month past contemplated writing you a long<lb/> letter on the subject&#44; various things have<lb/> occurred to cause me to defer it from day to day<lb/> the last was the fact of your absence in <placeName>Bali.<add>&#63;</add></placeName></p>
				<p>I am grieved and mortified to have to state that<lb/> my endeavors to establish a classical school for<lb/> the Jews of <placeName>N York</placeName> have completely failed&#8212;<lb/> whether the cause of my want of capacity or moral<lb/> unfitness or simply from the want of proper<lb/> patronage &#38; support.  That portion of the Jewish<lb/> public who feel any interest in the matter will judge<lb/> and of course for the greater part unfavorably to<lb/> me&#44; the unfortunate are always in fault.<lb/>  I have never as any time during the two years of my<lb/> probation had more than 14 pupils never during the<lb/> first six months more than 7 and those of all ages&#8212;from</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>the child of 7. sent to learn to spell &#38; read thro all the intermediate<lb/> ages to the boy of 12 who was somewhat prepared to<lb/> receive the kind of instruction I contemplated in my plan.<lb/>  I of course had as many classes nearly as pupils&#44; and apart<lb/> from Hebrew &#38; German had to undertake personally<lb/> all the various branches of instruction&#44; to <sic>organise</sic><lb/> a school properly&#44; under these circumstances&#44; without<lb/> the aid of assistant teachers&#44; was impracticable<lb/> <del>under such</del> the incapacity of some&#44; the indolence<lb/> and obstinacy of others were serious obstacles&#44; but I<lb/> bore up against all discouragement and during the last<lb/> year my school was supplied with capable teachers<lb/> in Hebrew in German in Music in <sic>latin</sic>.  French<lb/> algebra and geometry and the English branches&#8212;<lb/> thus affording at least the groundwork of a system of<lb/> useful and practical education&#44; well for the higher branches<lb/> I had three boys&#44; of whom one alone applied himself<lb/> with tolerable <sic>dilijince</sic>&#44; and he is the only one of my<lb/> pupils to whom I can point with any pride to<lb/> illustrate the advantages of my tuition&#44; altho&#39; others have<lb/> in some branches made very satisfactory progress.<lb/>  I have to add to the list of discouragements&#44; the want<lb/> of punctuality in payment.  There is yet due for tuition or<lb/> near &#36;200. which I may never  get.  You thus see<lb/> that my failure is not the result of any want of perseverance<lb/> I held on as long as possible.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I regret that I must<lb/> necessarily remain your debtor for the bill you have<lb/> against me for <add>&#63;</add>.  I have on hand belonging</p>
				<p rend="The following is written at the bottom of the page in pencil."><date>9&#45;5&#45;1849</date></p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>to you the Tephiloth sent to <persName>A Dittenhoffer</persName> which he<lb/> did not take as his.  Father tho&#39;t his old one would answer<lb/> and 3 spellers.  I will either await an opportunity of<lb/> disposing of them for you&#44; or hand them to your agt as you may<lb/> desire.&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I have on consultation with <persName>Mr Jonas</persName> my Brother<lb/> <persName>Mr Judah</persName> &#38; other friends concluded to resume my former<lb/> avocation&#44; and with strong promises of their support<lb/> I am now established in an office <placeName>No 120 Water St</placeName><lb/> where I am awaiting business as a commission merchant.<lb/>  I do not flatter myself with hopes of immediate success&#44;<lb/> and expect to encounter many difficulties.  &#8220;mais <sic>boque</sic><lb/> la gal&#232;re avec patience et courage on accomplit tout.&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><del>My</del> I <add>&#63;</add> remember that I have another apology to make in not<lb/> informing you directly of <persName>Sarah&#39;s</persName> engagement&#44; but allowing<lb/> the information to reach you thro&#39; general rumor.<lb/>  You have seen the gentleman I believe&#44; he stands very<lb/> high in <placeName>Charleston</placeName> as a rising member of his profession&#8212;and<lb/> is esteemed for his private worth as a good son&#44; brother<lb/> and citizen.  We are all much pleased with him.<lb/>  My house at present is very full&#44; besides <persName>Rosalie&#39;s</persName> children<lb/> and <persName>Mrs. Solomon</persName> &#38; Son&#44; we have <persName>Zonny Labat</persName> during<lb/> his vacation from Yale&#44; and <persName>Mrs. &#38; Miss Jacobs</persName>.  The<lb/> cantatrice&#44; it will not do to use plain english<lb/> little schozu<add>&#63;</add> one of my pupils is yet with us.<lb/>  <persName>Rosalie</persName> will not leave us till late in <date>October</date>&#44;<lb/> we have all continued to enjoy good health during the<lb/> season except myself.  Mine has been bad&#44; but</p>
				<p rend="The following is written at the bottom of the page."><date>9&#45;5&#45;1849</date></p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>is much improved since I have entered upon my new<lb/> business.  All of us write in best regards to you.<lb/>  Your <persName>Aunt Rehine</persName> is well <persName>Ben</persName> recovered&#8212;you have<lb/> doubtless heard of <persName>Rachel&#39;s</persName> loss of her youngest boy&#8212;<lb/> of congregational news this may interest you I know<lb/> nothing.  I have been to two or three funerals recently<lb/> and have been struck by the narrow and confined<lb/> appearance of the burial place of one of the richest<lb/> and most numerous congregations of this great metropolis&#44;<lb/> apart from the certainty of the necessity of removal<lb/> in a few years away from a continually encroaching<lb/> population&#44; it seems like a desecration of the remains<lb/> of the dead to huddle them together in such a spot<lb/> surrounded as it is and overlooked by houses that<lb/> resemble barracks&#44; teeming as they do with that<lb/> description of population that swarms upon the<lb/> outskirts of a large city&#8212;can you not in your<lb/> next Occident suggest the idea of a general<lb/> Jewish cemetery&#44; located upon <placeName>Long Island</placeName>&#44; and guarded by state charter perpetually against<lb/> desecration by any possible charge of destination<lb/> to be provided with lots suitable for family burial<lb/> to be sold in f<add>&#63;</add> only to those of Jewish ritual<lb/> and to be exempt from seizure or sale on execution.<lb/>  Why cannot we as Jews <sic>avails</sic> ourselves of the<lb/> general improvements of the age in which we live&#63;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Yours</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)"><persName role="author">E. Block</persName>.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
