<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Englander, A.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0010</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Englander, A.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>San Francisco, CA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1860-10">October 20. 1860</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0010_1R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0010_1V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0010_2R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0010_2V.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p>
                <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>
                <date>October 20. 1860</date>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <addressee>Rev. Isaac Leeser</addressee>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Rev. Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">A few weeks after we were delighted<lb/> with <persName>Dr.
                    Cohns</persName>
                <hi rend="underline">maiden sermon</hi>, he gave us his <hi rend="underline">woman
                    Sermon</hi>, taken<lb/> as his text from <add>דברים לא י"ב הקהל את העם הַקְהֵל
                    אֶת הָעָם</add> and proving therefrom, that.<lb/> man woman, girls &amp;c &amp;c
                are not only <del>bound</del> allowed to unite and hear the word<lb/> of God, yet
                they are bound according this text, to do so. He <sic>complaint</sic><lb/> of our
                religion as having for such a length of time <sic>excludet</sic> woman from<lb/> so
                many privileges, to which they are <sic>rightously</sic> entitled, but that the
                time<lb/> has come when we remedy such an evil, in short he <sic>exaltet</sic> the
                ladies<lb/> to such a degree, he spoke so much of their greatness, that the
                congrega<lb/>tion did not think themselves to be in a Synagogue, but in the heaven amongst<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">angels</hi>, even the ladies were taken by surprise, as they
                never were aware<lb/> before of their being so very great. The <add>ימים ה"נ</add>
                had set in fairly, Ladies &amp;<lb/> gentlemen <sic>appeart</sic>
                <hi rend="underline">together</hi> like in a theater, yet it works well as the
                peop<lb/>le here, are enlightened enough to know, how to behave in the house of<lb/>
                God, even before <persName>Dr. Kohn</persName> was here. The Dr. preached a
                    <sic>splendit</sic> sermon<lb/> on the first day of <add>רה"ש</add> in German,
                reminding the Cong. for the sake of<lb/> our holy religion, to keep the
                        <date><sic>Sabath</sic></date>—which had till the present day<lb/> no
                effect—, than he implored the blessings of heaven for all and every<lb/> one, here
                and anywhere else, the orthodox even not excepted. He did not<lb/> forget the death,
                and every one was moved to tears, as the Dr. has got a<lb/> great talent to press
                them out, of the most stony heart—the second<lb/> day he preached in
                    <del>German</del> english, also, first rate. The <add>פיוטים</add><lb/> were all
                read—the <add>שחרית</add> of the first day was read by the Dr.)—bit in<lb/>
                <add>שחרית</add> the <add>מוסף</add> were omitted and the Cong. Were taken by
                sur<lb/>prise, as they could not pray the <add>מלכויות זכרונות</add>, as the
                    <add>מוסף שמיני בלחש</add> com<lb/>menced <add>חזן</add> and right off Shemona
                esra bekol—. The synagogue<lb/> was <sic>crowdet</sic>, and the service a splendid
                one, the Haphthora<lb/> on the first day was read by the Dr. in German, on the
                second day<lb/> by some person else in hebrew. <date>Yom Kipur</date> we were
                delighted with<lb/> 3 sermons all listened at with great awe, the service was
                conducted<lb/> like heretofore, and the day passed away <sic>delightfult</sic>, and
                to the<lb/> satisfaction of all. Luckas<add>?</add> passed away very pleasantly, the
                Dr</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>preached on the first day, explaining the <sic>comandment</sic> of the feast and<lb/>
                of the <add>קדיש</add>, although there is but one <add>ארבע מיניםארבע מינים</add> in
                the Congregation,<lb/> &amp; <hi rend="underline">one <add>אתרוג v לולב</add></hi>
                in the Yard of the Synagogue, that'll do for all—on<lb/>
                <add>סוכה</add>, also <hi rend="underline"><add>ערב רה"ש וי"כ</add></hi>, there was
                even no <add>הושענה רבה</add> in the Synagogue Ema<lb/>nuel, as the Dr. Rabbi did
                not attend even himself, but in the former<lb/> years, there were these days well
                    <sic>attented</sic> service, however now, as<lb/> the Rabbi does not attend his
                followers will do the same.—On <date>Sun<lb/>day</date> the <add>מנין</add> inst.
                The yearly meeting of the Cong. Em. took place, also<lb/> the election of officers
                as much as I understand, it passed of very<lb/> quiet, <persName>Mr H
                    Seligman</persName> was reelected President, and indeed he de<lb/>serves
                reelection, as he is a perfect Gentleman, doing Justice to all pastors,<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Sachs</persName> vicpres. Reelected, the other officers I do not know,
                who was<lb/> elected. A Resolution, <hi rend="underline"><sic>extenting</sic></hi>
                the Term of Office as Rabbi of the Cong from 3 to 5 years, passed unanimously, as
                such was provided<lb/> to the Dr. prior to his arrival here. A communication from
                the <persName>Dr<lb/> K.</persName> changing the reading of the Thora from one year
                to three years was<lb/> read, a warm debate ensued, and after the same was adopted
                by the<lb/> majority of <hi rend="underline">one</hi>, it was further agreed upon
                that a <sic>Comittee</sic> of 5<lb/> be appointed, to converse with the Dr. whether
                it was not a great wrong<lb/> to adopt such a change, and if the Rabbi succeeds in
                considering the<lb/> same, to the contrary, in the 3 years Cyclus<add>?</add> can
                    <add>שבת בראשית</add>. One of<lb/> the Com. <sic>refered</sic> the Rabbi to the
                    <add>שולחן ערוך</add>, which the latter rejects as<lb/> being in <del>any</del>
                no way his authority, he does not <sic>aknowledge</sic> the <add>ש"ע</add>
                con<lb/>sequently the Dr showed that some 700 years ago, it was customary<lb/> to
                read the Thora <hi rend="underline">through</hi> once in three years, and so it is,
                or will<lb/> be established to the notion of the Dr <add>שמיני עצרת</add> he spoke
                in his sermon<lb/> about the matter, but could not satisfy those who are opposed to
                it, he<lb/> urged also the speedy adoption of the new <add>תפילה</add>
                    (<persName>Herzbachers</persName>) <del>but</del> not<lb/>withstanding, there
                are only <hi rend="underline">two</hi> of them here and none to be had in
                    <placeName>N. Y.</placeName><lb/> is that not strange, that of so great an
                    <sic>artikel</sic>, only <del>li</del> a limited amount<lb/> was printed.—Well I
                suppose the Cong. Em. Did not dream that there<lb/> ever another Cong. will be
                foolish enough to adopt the same—and see<lb/> Cong. Em. in the next—. The Dr. spoke
                also in his service again of the<lb/> necessity, of abolishing <add>מוסף</add>, we
                do not intend to go to <add>ירושלים</add> to bring<lb/>
                <add>קרבנות</add> said he, for us there is no <add>משיח</add>, we live happy here,
                and enjoy<lb/> all privileges we wish to enjoy, we wish not to bend for a jewish
                King.<lb/> I think the Dr is right, because in <add>ירושלים</add>, he could not get
                $3000 a year</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in pencil at the bottom of the page."
                    ><date>10-20-1860</date> Y</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>nor would he get a house furnished so fine and gratis like here, besides<lb/> a
                couple a hundred Dollars, <add>רה"ש</add> gift.—<add>ירושלים</add> and
                    <add>משיח</add> are two ob<lb/>jects which are despised in the heart of the Dr.
                he would not say <add>ותחזני</add><lb/> in <add>יעלה ויבוא</add>, <add>זכרון משיח בן
                    דוד</add> not <add>ובכן תן כבוד</add>__but Sir there<lb/> are thank God, a good
                many in the Cong. Em. Who think quite otherwise<lb/> and although in the minority,
                yet they will live and die for their religious<lb/> principle, as already steps have
                been taken, to establish a new <add>ועריכת נר לבן ישי משיחנו</add>, which<lb/> will
                and must be done ere long, and beyond doubt with success—<lb/> One thing is strange,
                the Dr says there are no more <add>קהל</add> in the present<lb/> time as he goes
                into <add>כהנים</add>, yet he performed a sample<add>?</add> of week,<lb/> ago the
                ceremony of <add>בית הקברות</add> what inconsistency!—One thing is to<lb/> be
                regretted, that is, the Cong. Em. Has since its existence some 8 or 9 years<lb/>
                lived in most astonishing peace and <sic>harmonie</sic>, which fact is shown by<lb/>
                its prosperity, they have <sic>expendet</sic> for a Synagogue over 35000 Doll, for
                a<lb/> new grave yard on 20000 Doll. <del>and</del> she is out of debts and has on
                230<lb/> members, and now one man has by his actions, created
                <sic>disharmonie</sic>, <sic>quarells</sic><lb/> and private difficulties, between
                its members, between former friends, men<lb/> of long standing intimacy, are now
                enemies, because they think now diffe<lb/>rently on religious question <add>פדיון
                    הבן</add>. One more fact worth of notice<lb/> is, that when the Board of
                Officers on the new burial ground met, to make<lb/> laws for the government of the
                same, the question rose, who is entitled to be<lb/> buried in a jewish graveyard,
                whether children of jewish parents not cir<lb/>cumcised, are <add>איכה א', טז' על
                    אלה אני בוכיה עיני עיני</add>, the Dr. was consulted, and he said, that children
                of je<lb/>wish parents even if not circumcised are <add>יהודים</add>—<add>אוי
                    לרשע</add>—<lb/> However, there are but two such instances known in this city,
                where parent do<lb/> not circumcise. There were besides the next regular synagogue
                    <add>יהודים</add><lb/> on the <add>שארית ישראל</add> some four more meetings of
                worship well <sic>attende</sic>, the <add>ימים ה"נ</add><lb/>
                <add>מנהג פולין</add> was <sic>crowdet</sic> and well conducted, and it made me feel
                well to<lb/> hear the prayers chanting in the old established usage and see the
                greatest or<lb/>der and devotion prevail; their minister <persName>Dr.
                    Henry</persName>, a pious and learned Ger<lb/>man, preached a most impressive
                sermon on the first day of <add>שארית ישראל</add>. The Congre<lb/>gation is in a
                flourishing condition, counts some 80 members, and they have purchased a piece of
                ground to erect a <add>רה"ש</add> for themselves for<lb/> which purpose more than
                1500 Doll. Were donated on <add>בית הקברות</add>. Their the <add>י"כ</add><lb/>
                <add>בית המדרש</add>, some 30 members their service was recording their rite, it was well<lb/>
                <sic>attented</sic>, so were the balance, all of which I paid a flying
                    visit<add>?</add>. <persName>Dr. Eck<lb/>man</persName> had a service for the
                children only, which he called <add>חפצי בה</add>, it was<lb/> well adapted for his
                purpose, and the children showed much improvement<lb/> in hebrew reading and
                prayers—The Israelites are <sic>rapitly</sic> increasing<lb/> all over the state,
                every where is the feeling for our cause alive, in
                    <placeName>Sacra<lb/>mento</placeName>, <placeName>Stockton</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Marysville</placeName>, <placeName>Nevada</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Grass Valley</placeName> &amp;c &amp; every where they kept</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in pencil at the bottom of the page."
                    ><date>10-20-1850</date> Y</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>divine service on the <add>י"ה</add>, without being affected by reform—On the
                first<lb/> day of <add>רה"ש</add> and on <add>י"כ</add> I counted but three jewish
                Stores open, that is well<lb/> worth mentioning, and shows that Judaism is not
                declining in spite of<lb/> a few reformers,—such matters have happened before
                    <add>והמצילנו מידם בכל דור ודור</add><lb/>
                <add>ובכל זאת על מי אנו תחשעו על אבינו שבשמים</add> The Cong. Emanuel think of
                selling their present Sy<lb/>nagogue and building a great Temple, when final action
                should take<lb/> place in this matter I let you know.—The tenth anniversary
                Ball<lb/> of the Eureka benevolent Soc. took place on the <date>9th</date> inst. I
                spend a half<lb/> an hour there, it was a <sic>splendit</sic> affair, leaving the
                    Socit<add>?</add> some 1200 Doll<lb/> profit, I think that the Eureka is the
                most flourishing benev. Society<lb/> in the State, has got nearly 300 members,
                    <del>one</del> a Capital of 18000 Doll, and they<lb/> doing great great
                charity.—There are also two Bner<add>?</add> Beris <sic>Societys</sic><lb/> here,
                one works in english in existence a couple of years, and another one<lb/> works in
                german, established but 3 months and promises to be a very<lb/> important one, as it
                counts already some 280 members, both lodges are in<lb/>deed a great honor to
                    <del>h</del> our nation—There are two Gentlemen in our<lb/> city worth of
                notice, one, <persName>Senator Benjamin</persName> of
                    <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>
                <sic>attenting</sic> the ce<lb/>lebrated New Alexander case, and the other
                    <persName>Benjamin II</persName> the <sic>travelor</sic><lb/> the latter is here
                a few months, awaiting some assistance from our co<lb/>religionist, to proceed to
                    <placeName>China</placeName>, to hunt for our last brothers—but until<lb/> news,
                he has not met with any success, neither do I think that he will,<lb/> people here
                think, they can do better with their charity—</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">True<add>?</add> Israelite.</p>
            <p>Rev Sir! I have given to you in this communication a true statement<lb/> of every
                thing concerning our coreligionists at this place and else<lb/>where, you may <del>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del> take from it all that suits you, and I'll keep<lb/> you posted of every thing
                of importance, assuring you, that the true<lb/> faith of our ancestors, finds a
                great many supporters here, and were<lb/> it not for <persName>Dr. Kohn</persName>,
                    <hi rend="underline">reform</hi> |: destruction of our ancient faith, so dead
                it/<lb/> would never have rooted here, but <add>Hebrew</add>.—What was<lb/> the
                doings of the <persName>Dr. K.</persName> in <placeName>Brandenburg</placeName>?—of
                which you referred some times<lb/> ago in your paper? <sic>Asuring</sic> you my
                sincere friendship, I remain<lb/> Sir yours with high esteem</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">
                <persName role="author">A. Englander</persName>
            </p>
            <p>P.P. I knew <persName>Dr. Wise</persName>? I mean <persName>Isaac
                Wise</persName>—<lb/> some twenty years ago, when he was Schoolteacher<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Tachau in Böhmen</placeName>, then he did not dream, of being a Dr
                Divinity in <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> or writing a Jewish History, or to
                become once a <sic>traveller</sic> for the cause of the<lb/> destruction of our
                ancient faith—.</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in pencil at the bottom of the page."
                    ><date>10-20-1860</date> Y 20-316 </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
