<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0182</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Rehine, Zalma</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1837-12" source="" attested="yes">December 24, 1837</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1837-12" source="" attested="yes">Kislev 24th 5598</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0182_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0182_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0182_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0182_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> <date>December 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Kislev 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 5598</date></p>
				<p>Dear Uncle.</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">It is with a good deal of mortification that I write to you<lb/> about a new difficulty that has occurred between me and the congregation.<lb/>  You know that at the last meeting I was elected for three years at a<lb/> salary of eight hundred Dollars.  I at once objected to the salary&#44; and so<lb/> stated to the committee&#59; and was perfectly satisfied to have the<lb/> matter rest for a year at least.  Now however&#44; as you will see<lb/> by the constitution which I send&#44; there is a law 27&#44; page 23<add>&#63;</add>&#44; which<lb/> demands a bond for the faithful performance of the duty of office.<lb/>  When the thing was first mentioned I at once refused signing<lb/> a bond for three years&#59; and asked it as a great favour to let the<lb/> matter rest.  But the Parnass was urged by some persons&#44; and on<lb/> <date>Thursday</date> two weeks ago he put a paper in my hand which contains<lb/> as one stipulation that I should stay of three years&#44; and that<lb/> the congregation should pay eight hundred Dollars in full&#44; at the<lb/> regular quarter day&#44; each under a penalty of &#36;500.  He wanted an<lb/> answer at once by <date>Friday</date> to lay it before the board on <date>Sunday</date>&#59; of course<lb/> the time was too short to consult with you&#44; and I accordingly upon<lb/> my own thoughts of what <add>is</add> correct and proper refused to sign for<lb/> more than one year&#44; till I were sure that the congregation would not<lb/> consent to give my usual salary&#44; upon which by the by no vote was<lb/> taken&#44; as the question only occurred on &#36;800&#44; the confusion being so great<lb/> that every thing went on rather curiously.  At the meeting of the<lb/> Board this day two weeks&#44; <persName>Mr. Hackenburg</persName> proposed to let the<lb/> matter rest for one year&#44; but <persName>Mrssrs Allen</persName>&#44; <persName>J. A. Phillips</persName> &#38; <persName>A. Hart</persName><lb/> refused&#44; and it was determined to call a meeting on this day two weeks.<lb/>  Since then <persName>Mr. Gratz</persName>&#44; <persName>Mr. Israel</persName>&#44; <persName>Mr. Allen</persName>&#44; <persName>Mr. Hart</persName> and<lb/> <persName>Mrs Gratz</persName> have been urging me to sign the bond&#44; and all acknowledge<lb/> that it is unjust to reduce the salary.  There are those in the congrega&#95;</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>tion who would move to let the election aside&#44; in case it were understood I refused accept&#95;<lb/>ing the terms.  There is a great objection in the minds of my friends to have<lb/> <persName>Lyons</persName> elected&#44; and they say&#44; that it is nevertheless probable that he would<lb/> succeed.  They appeal to me&#44; whether I would consent to see him unworthy<lb/> as him in office&#44; and whether my character would not be subject to<lb/> an inadversion<add>&#63;</add> if for the sake of maintaining my own opinion or<lb/> even positive declaration&#44; I should refuse acceding to the wishes of my<lb/> friends.  Further <persName>Mr. Gratz</persName> just now said that he would bring the<lb/> business again before the congregation at their next meeting.<lb/>  These are all the principal features of the case.  My own opinion<lb/> is decidedly opposed to my pledging myself to stay with the congregation&#44;<lb/> as they have done so much to mortify me&#59; secondly&#59; tis almost<lb/> yielding my entire independence&#59; thirdly it is an act of injustice&#44;<lb/> and it is certainly not reasonable to exact my <add>&#63;</add> thereto.<lb/>  However the whole subject has caused me a great deal of painful<lb/> excitement and care and thought.  As I said my own opinion is unchanged<lb/> which I expressed to <persName>Simha</persName> the last time we went up to St<add>&#63;</add> <persName>Emanuels</persName><lb/> of which she can tell you.  Yet I now defer to you&#44; and refer the whole<lb/> to your judgment&#44; and as you command&#44; so I shall obey.  If you think my<lb/> opinion right&#44; and that I ought not to yield&#44; I shall refuse&#59; but if you<lb/> desire my stay&#44; I shall then sign the paper and send it to <persName>Mr<lb/> Allen</persName> without any further remark.&#95;&#95;Answer this therefore<lb/> at once as soon as you get it&#44; and put the letter in the post office before<lb/> it closes.  However think well&#44; and reflect that upon your advice<lb/> the happiness or unhappiness of my future life may depend.  According<lb/> my view of the question I can lose nothing by leaving <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#44;<lb/> for the congregation who cannot treat me properly after an acquaintance<lb/> of 8 years deserve not to have me.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The fourth volume of the Prayer Book is done.  The fifth has progressed</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>as far as the book of <persName>Ruth</persName>&#44; and I hope we shall see the end of it this<lb/> week.  I am almost resolved to go and see you&#44; and speak with you<lb/> face to face<lb/> but it being <date><sic>Hanukah</sic></date> I do not well know how to leave.<lb/>  But if you wish to see me&#44; I will come on this day week&#44; and return<lb/> again on <date>Monday</date> or <date>Tuesday</date>&#8212;I acknowledge the receipt of 120 by <persName>Mr.<lb/> Levy</persName>.  People from <placeName>Richd.</placeName> have not yet paid one cent&#44; thought five<lb/> books are now as good as done.  Is not this supporting a useful<lb/> <sic>enterprize</sic>&#63;  My health is better <sic>that</sic> it has been&#44; altho&#39; at<lb/> nights I sleep very disturbed.&#95; Old <persName>Lemon</persName> &#40;<add>&#63;</add>&#41;some<lb/> time since told me to remember him to you&#44; I forgot to mention it.<lb/> <persName>Rachel Seixas</persName> gave me an embroidered bag aunt I also forgot<lb/> to mention this and have had no opportunity for sending.  Very likely<lb/> it will come with the books.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">On <date>Friday</date> and <date>Rosh Hodesh Tibeth</date><add>&#63;</add> I shall be 31 years<lb/> old.  She would judge it to be time that now I should be treated<lb/> more like a man than a child&#59; but the people I live <add>&#63;</add><lb/> are unable to avoid higgling and taking the cheapest<lb/> goods&#44; altho&#39; of inferior quality.  Cheap stores are fashiona&#95;<lb/>ble&#44; and cheap minsters of course are better than dear ones&#8212;<lb/>  However that is not the question now&#59; and would to mercy that<lb/> nothing like the present had occurred to give me such<lb/> a mean opinion of the majority of the congregation I now<lb/> have.</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">My love for all the folks and</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)">believe me</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">your obt. neph.</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)"><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
				<p rend="Note&#58;">Paper torn on right side near center&#44; obscuring some words.</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>If you think proper write by express.</p>
				<p><addressee>Mr. Zalma Rehine</addressee></p>
				<p><placeName>No 25 Camden St.</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Baltimore</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Md</placeName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
