<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Pleasants, T. S.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0220</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Pleasants, T.
                            S.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Beaver Dam, VA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1829-06">June 20, 1829</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0220_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0220_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0220_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0220_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="indent(7)">
                <placeName>Beaver dam</placeName>
                <date>June 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1829</date>
            </p>
            <p>My dear friend,</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I intended to write in the course of a few days, tut the<lb/> note
                which I recd yesterday, induces me to write immediately, and to offer<lb/> some
                apology for my not calling on thee while in <placeName>Richmond</placeName> last
                week. I left<lb/> home at a time that ill suited my convenience—though I full
                promised<lb/> myself the pleasure of an interview with thee. After doing my
                little<lb/> business, I was so tired &amp; exhausted, and had so little time left,
                that<lb/> I concluded, very reluctantly, to satisfy myself with a call on
                    <persName>B. H.<lb/> Judah</persName> at the museum, and to leave with him a
                message for thee,<lb/> stating my disappointment &amp; regret at being deprived of
                the pleasure of<lb/> seeing thee. Had I received the least intimation while there,
                that thou<lb/> wouldst be down, I would have remained. But I did not know that<lb/>
                he sent thee word, neither do I yet; but I presume so, from the fact of<lb/> thy
                hearing I was there. I hope therefore, my friend, thou will ascribe my not<lb/>
                calling on thee to the right cause; for I assure thee it would have given me
                the<lb/> highest gratification to see thee, if I could have found time to have an
                hour or<lb/> two of conversation with thee. I should have <sic>staid</sic> longer at
                the museum with<lb/> our friend <persName>B. H. Judah</persName>, with whose
                urbanity I was highly pleased; but we<lb/> were interrupted by visitors, &amp; as I
                expected his duty required he should<lb/> wait on them, I withdrew. He appears to be
                a man well versed in Hebrew<lb/> learning, &amp; of much intelligence; but above all
                he possesses I think in a<lb/> great degree, the virtue of charity; the brightest
                gem which can adorn the<lb/> profession of religion. It is truly gratifying to meet
                with a man of such<lb/> enlarged views; &amp; the last <sic>enquiry</sic> I would
                make concerning him, would be,<lb/> to what particular profession he belonged? for
                where we see virtue &amp; charity &amp;<lb/> humility abound, we should never
                    avil<add>?</add> about particular modes of belief.<lb/> Those amiable feelings,
                are in all, the legitimate offspring of the divine perfection,<lb/> the influences
                of which are universal, in proportion to the reciprocal action<lb/> on the part of
                the creature. Such being the impressions I feel towards him, I was<lb/> sorry to be
                interrupted, especially as I wished to gain some information from</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>an authentic source of the present state of the Jews, their manners &amp;c. While
                in<lb/> conversation he offered me a controversial work, the letters of <persName>D.
                    Levi</persName> to <persName>Dr.<lb/> Priestly</persName> on the merits &amp;
                evidences of their respective religions. I did not intend<lb/> to write to thee
                until I had done reading it, but having finished the first series<lb/> &amp; made
                some progress in the second, I can form some judgment of its execution.<lb/> He is a
                writer of very considerable talent, and great ingenuity. His exposition of<lb/> the
                prophecy of <persName>David</persName> was new to me: as well as some of his
                translations of<lb/> Hebrew terms; of which however I am no judge. The common mass
                of mankind<lb/> has to depend very much on the learned for a correct interpretation
                of many<lb/> passages of scripture, and when they differ among themselves, what are
                the ignorant<lb/> to do? “Who shall decide where doctors disagree”? As long as this
                is the case,<lb/> controversy must be endless, in respect to particular doctrines;
                and we must<lb/> therefore be left to do that which we know to be right, by
                cultivating every<lb/> virtue, doing injury to none, and <sic>practising</sic> all
                the good we can. This is the<lb/> end, doubtless, of the law &amp; the prophets.
                Indeed, my friend, I delight to contemplate,<lb/> the <hi rend="underline"
                    >practical</hi> exhibition of those sublime principles which ought to regulate
                our<lb/> lives, for more than the mere profession of them. To return to
                    <persName>Levi's</persName> work,<lb/> I think many of his arguments against the
                new testament might be<lb/> readily answered. Sagacious critics may no doubt be able
                to make<lb/> many things appear absurd, which are founded on truth. For a
                controversial<lb/> writer though, he is very exempt from bitterness, and I am
                reading his book<lb/> with a good deal of interest; for I am always pleased to see
                both sides.<lb/> Many of his strictures are very just on the Christians,
                particularly when he<lb/> speaks of the animosity between different sects—a fact
                which I confess gives<lb/> a powerful advantage to our opponents, and which has
                sometimes almost<lb/> disgusted me with the name of Christian. This has been the
                rock on which many<lb/> have split in their search after truth, when they judged of
                the Christian religion<lb/> by the acts of its professors; thereby denying such a
                principle as vital, redeeming<lb/> religion to exist in any people. But as
                    <persName>D. Levi</persName> himself candidly &amp; zealously<lb/> admits, the
                new testament does not <sic>authorise</sic> such <sic>abberation</sic> from the
                law<lb/> of moral rectitude.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I should have answered thy last valued letter, received some
                weeks<lb/> since, but that I flattered myself I should have had the pleasure to
                acknowledge<lb/> it in person. I can only account for our friend <persName>J. P.
                    Staker's</persName> not writing from</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>the circumstance that he received an important appointment immediately on<lb/> his
                return home in the <placeName>Baltimore</placeName> rail Road Company, which
                together with the<lb/> arrangements previous to entering upon its duties occupied
                nearly all his time.<lb/> Indeed I have only received a very few lines, at a time,
                from him since he left<lb/> me, though when he is at leisure I get a letter from him
                almost every week.<lb/> I am sorry now he did not leave his letter with me, to copy
                (as he wrote it in<lb/> a hurry &amp; it required a few corrections), but I thought
                he could do it himself much<lb/> better. I have written to him about it, but have
                received no answer yet.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I assure thee my dear friend, I feel very much gratified that my
                correspondence<lb/> should, on account of the spirit of moderation which I sincerely
                felt, have recd.<lb/> such a compliment from a Jew as it did from thy friend
                    <persName>Jacob Mordecai</persName>. It<lb/> is a very desirable thing to gain
                the respect of our opponents, so seldom the<lb/> fruit of religious controversy.
                Hard names are never productive of any benefit. I<lb/> think I have informed thee
                before, of the pleasure which the perusal of thy letter<lb/> by one or two of my
                friends afforded them, one of whom congratulated me on the<lb/> agreeable result of
                gaining a friend instead of making an enemy by religious<lb/> disputation. When I
                quoted the passage from Deuteronomy in my last letter<lb/> I was not fully aware
                that it was so literally complied with by the Jews.<lb/> I thought however, &amp; I
                still think, that <hi rend="underline">literally</hi>, the words “when thou
                liest<lb/> down &amp; when thou risest up &amp; when tho walkest by the way &amp;c”
                might embrace<lb/> almost ever division of time. I did not intend to convey the idea
                that it<lb/> was impracticable to love God above all things: by no means. I hope
                &amp; believe<lb/> it is attainable both by Jew &amp; Gentile. If I recollect right,
                there were certain<lb/> parts which I underscored, some of which I thought it would
                be difficult to<lb/> comply with, particularly that which requires the commandment
                to be placed as front<lb/>lets between the eyes.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I learned from <persName>B. H. Judah</persName> the probability that
                thou mightest take charge<lb/> of the Jewish Congregation in
                    <placeName>Philada</placeName>. If this be so, and it should compel<lb/> thee to
                leave <placeName>Richmond</placeName> before I go down again, it will produce a
                lasting regret<lb/> on my mind that I did not see thee when I was down. If the offer
                should<lb/> be accepted I yet cherish the hope that I may have the pleasure of
                seeing<lb/> thee before they departure. I shall be glad to know they decision on the
                subject.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I recd. The whig thou sent me some weeks since, but did not get
                the<lb/> letter which accompanied it. Please to give my respects to <persName>B. H.
                    Judah</persName><lb/> and believe me to be very sincerely thy friend</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">T S Pleasants</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p rend="indent(5)"><addressee>Mr. Isaac Leeser</addressee>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
