<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Illowy, Dr.</author>
				<editor/>
				<sponsor/>
				<funder/>
				<principal/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
				item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note/>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution/>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
							Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP_NC-4</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head/>
					<letHeading>
						<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Illowy, Dr.</author>
						<addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Leeser,
							Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865-01">January 19, 1865</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author/>
							<editor/>
							<respStmt>
								<resp/>
								<name/>
							</respStmt>
							<title/>
							<decoNote/>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl/>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation/>
							<textLang/>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_1.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_2.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_3.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_4.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_5.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_6.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_4_7.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
										>letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 6 sheets <dimensions/>
								</extent>
								<foliation/>
								<collation/>
								<condition fragment="false"/>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout/>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote/>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote/>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions/>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote/>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p/>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat/>
						<envDesc occ="false"/>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin/>
						<provenance/>
						<acquisition/>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source/>
								<change/>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent/>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates/>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl/>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p/>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p/>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p/>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p/>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p/>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p/>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p/>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p/>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition/>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc/>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc/>
					<label/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation/>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item/>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""/>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)">Ant. <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, <date>January 19,
					1865</date>.</p>
			<p>Editor of the "Occident", <placeName><sic>Philadelphai</sic></placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">DEAR SIR: There is, perhaps, no country in the world<lb/> where the
				Hebrew communities are so frequently increased by<lb/> numbers of proselytes, as in
				this country; and our trans-<lb/><sic>antlantic</sic> breth<del>e</del>ren must
				surely, when they learn from the<lb/> different American Jewish periodicals these
				happy tidings,<lb/> greatly rejoice, and think the time of the advent of the<lb/>
				Messiah is nigh, truth commences to dawn over the Gentiles,<lb/> and break the long
				night of ignorance and superstition, and<lb/> fill their hearts, as prophesied, with
				the fear of God, and<lb/> the true knowledge of His unity, whilst we here are, to
				our<lb/> deepest regret, convinced that it is not God, but the "altar<lb/> of God,"
				to which these proselytes are coming. To find or<lb/> please a husband whom they
				love, the daughters of the Gentiles<lb/> join our nation, but by no means our
				religion; and we must not<lb/> deceive ourselves, since we are convinced in our
				heart that<lb/> it is not the power of truth but the sharp arrows of Cupid to<lb/>
				which this rapid increase of our nation, by the sons and daugh-<lb/>ters of
					<placeName>Edom</placeName>, is to be attributed; for, as heedlessly as
				they<lb/> often run away from the fatherhouse, following the man of their<lb/>
				choice, without the consent and blessing of their parents, so<lb/> they abandon, yet
				with much less scruple, their church, kneel-<lb/>ing down at the altar of the
				Synagogue, where the heedless<lb/> maiden expects to be united to the subject of her
				love.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Reverend sir, by writing this, I do not intend to blame<lb/> either
				the proselytes or those who admitted them into the<lb/> covenant of
					<persName>Abraham</persName>. תושחלתע it is now a time, when to be<lb/> silent
				is the best and wise<del>e</del>st policy; we must see and hear</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">-2-</p>
			<p>much and be silent, we see them every day converting Jews<lb/> into Gentiles, our
				hearts break <add>. תושחלתע it is now a time, when to be</add>, but our lips<lb/>
				are mute and we are silent; why should we not be silent when<lb/> Gentiles are
				converted into Jews? I merely intend to con-<lb/>quer the erroneous idea of our
				people in general, who believe<lb/> that the making of proselytes is one of the most
				God-pleas-<lb/>ing actions that can be performed, though, in fact, even if<lb/>
				everything is done in full accordance with the law, it cannot<lb/> be regarded as a
					<add>Hebrew</add>. We are permitted by law to admit<lb/> Gentiles into the
				covenant of <persName>Abraham</persName>, under certain con-<lb/>ditions; this,
				however, is only a permission <add>Hebrew</add> but not a<lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Let me, therefore, exhibit before your readers several<lb/>
				passages, by which I may show them what the Talmud thinks<lb/> of proselytes in
				general:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">1. Yebamot<del>h</del>, 109. Says <persName>Rabbi
						Yi<del>t</del>z<del>c</del>hak</persName>, <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add> Misfortune after misfortune shall befall<lb/> those who admit
				Gentiles into the covenant of <persName>Abraham</persName>; to<lb/> which Tossephoth
				remarks, though it seems to be a <add>Hebrew</add> to<lb/> make <add>Hebrew</add>,
				for, if otherwise, <persName>Jehoshua</persName> would not have con-<lb/>verted
					<persName>Rahab</persName>, and <persName>Hillel</persName> would not have
				complied with the<lb/> desire of the two heathens to be converted, still these
				are<lb/> but exceptional cases. <persName>Jehoshua</persName> knew from the
				character of<lb/>
				<persName>Rahab</persName>, and so knew <persName>Hillel</persName>, that they would
				one day be strict<lb/> and faithful Jews, <add>Hebrew</add>:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">2. Kiddushim, 70. Says <persName>Rabbi
				<del>Ch</del>Helbo</persName>: Leprosy is not<lb/> so hurtful to the body as
				proselytes are to the cause of<lb/> Judaism, <add>Hebrew</add>,
					<persName>Rashi</persName> gives the reason—<lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">3. Niddah, 11. The proselytes in <placeName>Israel</placeName>
				prevent the coming</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">-3-</p>
			<p>of the Messiah, <add>Hebrew</add>:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">4. Abodah Zarah, 3. In the days of <persName>David</persName> and
					<persName>Solomon</persName> pro-<lb/>selytes were not accepted; no admission
				into the covenant<lb/> was then granted to Gentiles. Though we find that in the<lb/>
				days of <persName>Solomon</persName>, over 150,000 heathens embraced the Jewish<lb/>
				religion, these, however, says <persName>Rabb<del>o</del>i
					Yo<del>c</del>hanan</persName>, Yebamo<del>t</del>h 79,<lb/> were but
					<add>Hebrew</add>, which means, as <persName>Rashi</persName> explains,
				they<lb/> made themselves Jews, embraced our religion, but were never<lb/> accepted
				or acknowledged as such by our nation, <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>: A similar case is found in <persName>Esther</persName>,
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add> the word <add>Hebrew</add> in the <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> says
				distinctly they made themselves Jews, but were not<lb/> accepted or acknowledged as
				such by the nation.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">5. Sanhedrin, 99. Says <persName>Rabbi Azzay</persName>:
					<persName>Timnah</persName> was a<lb/> princess, the daughter of a king,
				desirous to become a Jew-<lb/>ess, she went for that purpose to
					<persName>Abraham</persName>, <persName>Isaac</persName>, and
					<persName>Jacob</persName>,<lb/> who all refused (not to convert her but) to
				admit her into<lb/> the covenant, and <sic>recognise</sic> her as a member of their
				family;<lb/> she then went and became <add>Hebrew</add>, and said:<lb/> I prefer to
				be a servant-maid in that nation, than to be a<lb/> princess of any other,
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">From all these different quo<del>a</del>tations, we can
					suffic<del>e</del>ient-<lb/>ly see that our sages were never in favor of making
				prosel-<lb/>ytes, and when <persName>Rabbi Eliezer</persName>, Pessachim 78, says
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>, he does not mean to say that<lb/>
				<placeName>Israel</placeName> shall make proselytes; for if so, he had better say
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add> or <add>Hebrew</add>, but the word <add>Hebrew</add> refers to
				the<lb/> preceding word, <add>Hebrew</add>, and the whole idea is but this;
					<placeName>Israel</placeName></p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">-4-</p>
			<p>was driven from their country to live with the many different<lb/> nations of the
				earth, only for the great purpose to spread<lb/> the name and unity of God all over
				the earth, to light the<lb/> light of God wherever there is darkness, and, through
				us,<lb/> all the nations of the earth shall know that there is but<lb/> one God.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">There is, to my knowledge, but one passage which<lb/> speaks more
				favorably of the admission of <add>Hebrew</add> to Judaism,<lb/> and this is the
					<add>Hebrew</add> Section <add>Hebrew</add>, where we read as<lb/> follows,
					<add>Hebrew</add>:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">What opinion had our sages of proselytes?</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">A very unfavorable one!</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">6. Pessachim, 112, we read—<persName>Rabbi <del>Yehudah</del> Judah
						Han<del>n</del>as<del>s</del>i</persName><lb/> enjoined upon his children,
				before he died, that none of his<lb/> family should intermarry with proselytes,
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add> *<add>Hebrew</add> In Midrash Yalkut <add>Hebrew</add>, we read:
					<persName>Rabbi <del>Ch</del>Hiyah</persName> said<lb/> "Do not trust
				proselytes, have no confidence in their piety,<lb/> neither in that of their
				children, <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>. This unfavorable opinion<lb/> we find justified in
					<date>Sabbath</date>, 33, by <add>Hebrew</add>, the<lb/> son of proselytes, (his
				father and mother were proselytes—<lb/><persName><hi rend="underline"
							>Rash<del>y</del>i</hi></persName>,) who denounced <persName>Rabbi Simon
					ben Yo<del>c</del>ha<del>y</del>i</persName> before the king,<lb/> in
				consequence of which the latter was compelled to save his<lb/> life by a hasty
				flight to a cavern, wherein he remained hidden<lb/> twelve years; and when, after
				the death of the king, he left<lb/> the cavern and met the denunciator
					<add>Hebrew</add>, he said—<lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<p>* When <persName>Rabby J.</persName> died, his four sons were already married,<lb/>
				therefore we translate <add>Hebrew</add> his family.</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">-5-</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Here I beg leave to remark, that, when we meet the very<lb/> same
					<add>Hebrew</add> again in the Moed Kat<del>o</del>an, 9, as the name<lb/> of a
				great man to whom <persName>Rabbi Sim<del>e</del>on ben
					Yo<del>c</del>ha<del>y</del>i </persName>sends his<lb/> son to request his
				blessing, it is merely a misprint, and<lb/> instead of <add>Hebrew</add>, it ought
				to be <add>Hebrew</add>,<lb/> mentioned in Talmud Jerusalem Taanith, sect. 2d:
					<add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add> (see Mateh Mosheth,<lb/> who also assumes as most probable that
				this <add>Hebrew</add> is<lb/> the same <add>Hebrew</add> of Moed Kat<del>o</del>an
				to whom <persName>Rabbi Sim<del>e</del>on ben<lb/>
					Yo<del>c</del>ha<del>y</del>i</persName> sent his son to be blessed).</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">From different other places in the Talmud, we learn that<lb/> it was
				always regarded as an insult to be called "Son of a<lb/> Proselyte," see Yoma, 71,
					<add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The rank of proselyte was inferior to that of a
				<add>Hebrew</add><lb/> or <add>Hebrew</add>, he was next to a freed slave. — See
				Mishnah Horayth<lb/> 13, <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We find that when <persName>Ezra</persName> found out that many
				Israelites<lb/> who came up with him from <placeName>Babylon</placeName> to
					<placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> lived with<lb/>
				<add>Hebrew</add>, he ordered them to be sent away with their<lb/> children, and so
				they did. Why did he give them such a<lb/> cruel command, could they not, as many in
				similar cases are<lb/> doing now, make their wives Jewesses, or at least let
				the<lb/> children be circumcised and stay with their fathers? Surely<lb/> for no
				other reason than this that <persName>Ezra</persName> did not want to dis-<lb/>grace
				the nation by making such proselytes and sport with the<lb/> holy Word of God, and
				make by-ways and side-doors to the<lb/> sacred edifice of our holy religion, that
				every one may<lb/> smuggle himself in and our whatever he pleases, and thus
				suit<lb/> every one's way of thinking, as <persName>Iben Ezra</persName> to
					<persName>Ezra</persName> vi. explains,</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">-6-</p>
			<p><add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Hoping that this may cause our people to change their<lb/> opinion
				concerning proselytes, I remain, dear sir,<lb/> Most respectfully yours,</p>
			<p><persName role="author">DR. ILLOWY</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<hi rend="underline">(THE OCCIDENT, Vol. XXIII No. 1 (<date>April 1865</date>), p.
					30-33)</hi>
			</p>
			<div>
				<p>
					<ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_23_1.pdf">The above text refers to Occident
						Volume 23 No. 1 pages 30 through 33. Click here to view.</ref>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
