<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Illowy, Dr.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Illowy, Dr.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865-02">February 3, 1865</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1865-02">Shevat 7, 5625</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_1.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >miscellany</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="align(center)">THE JEWISH MESSENGER.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>NEW YORK</placeName>, <date>SHEVAT 7, 5625, FEBRUARY
                    3, 1865</date></p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Louisiana</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>NEW ORLEANS</placeName>.—We have heretofore called
                attention to<lb/> the controversy agitating our co-religionists at
                    <placeName>New<lb/> Orleans</placeName> on the subject of the <emph
                    rend="italics">Mohel</emph> who had been sus-<lb/>pended from duty by <persName
                    role="author">Dr. Illowy</persName>, the Rabbi of the con-<lb/>gregation. It
                appears that the Doctor had been called<lb/> upon to retract his position, and a
                communication had<lb/> been made to him by the officers of the congregation<lb/>
                with which <persName>Mr. Goldenberg</persName> was identified, demanding a<lb/>
                withdrawal of his censure. <persName role="author">Dr. Illowy</persName> requests us
                to<lb/> publish the following reply, which he transmitted to this<lb/> request. It
                is proper to say that his aciton is fully<lb/> endorsed by <persName>Rabbi
                    Hirsch</persName>, of <placeName>Frankfort</placeName>, and other<lb/> high
                authorities. We have already stated our convictions<lb/> that the Doctor's course
                was dictated by an earnest pur-<lb/>pose of serving <placeName>Israel</placeName>,
                and perpetuating the purity of<lb/> the rite of circumcision, and was in accordance
                with<lb/> correct precedent:</p>
            <p>To the Gentlemen of the Committee from the Congregation<lb/> "Shaaray Tefila," in
                    <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">GENTLEMEN:—I hereby most respectfully acknowledge<lb/> the receipt
                of your favor dated the <date>28th of December</date>,<lb/> in which you request me,
                by order of your congregation,<lb/> to recall what I have publicly pronounced
                against <persName>Mr.<lb/> Goldenberg</persName>, a member of your congregation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Believe me, gentlemen, and the Almighty who seeth<lb/> into man's
                heart, He alone knows it, that I never felt<lb/> the least animosity against the
                person of <persName>Mr. G.</persName>, and<lb/> would my conscience tell me that I
                have done him<lb/> wrong, I would not hesitate a moment to ask his
                for-<lb/>giveness, and revoke my declaration, but since I am per-<lb/>fectly
                convinced that I have acted fully in accordance<lb/> with our sacred code, I regret
                not being able to comply<lb/> with your desire.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I further beg leave, gentlemen, to state before you<lb/> the case in
                its true shape, that you be better able to<lb/> judge whether that what I have done
                was in consistency<lb/> with duty, law and justice, or not.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is very true, as every one who is but slightly<lb/> acquainted
                with the Hebrew language, without being a<lb/> theological scholar can read in
                    <add>Hebrew</add>, that the male<lb/> child of a non-Israelitish mother can be
                admitted into<lb/> Judaism, and brought into the covenant of
                    <persName>Abraham</persName>;<lb/> and there is no need to hear first the
                opinion of Euro-<lb/>pean Rabbis about it; every layman will know how<lb/> to decide
                this question. It is, however, not to be over-<lb/>looked that the admission of a
                child into Judaism is<lb/> subject, like that of an adult to the condition that the<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> must first be at least apparently convinced that there<lb/> is no
                other motive that impels the proselyte to embrace<lb/> Judaism than true and sincere
                conversion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have further to remark that, though the law per-<lb/>mits the
                proper authority to admit a non-Israelite into<lb/> Judaism, it is still not more
                than a permission granted<lb/> by the law; by no means, however, can it be
                regarded<lb/> a <add>Hebrew</add>, a religious duty enjoined upon us; because
                ex<lb/>perience has shown that in all ages proselytes have done<lb/> Judaism more
                harm than good; as <persName>Rabbi Chelbo</persName> says, Yebamoth
                    <add>Hebrew</add>, "Leprosy is<lb/> not so hurtful to the body, as proselytes
                are to Juda-<lb/>ism." <persName>Rashy</persName> Nidah , p. 11, explains this
                passage with<lb/> the following words: <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">On another place we read—<add>Hebrew</add>, "The<lb/> proselytes
                prevent the coming of the Messiah." Niddah<lb/> p. 11.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Rabby Yitzchak</persName> said, "Misfortune after
                misfortune<lb/> shall befall those who admit non-Israelites into Judaism."<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> to which Tossephoth Yebamoth remarks: "Though it<lb/> seems
                to be a <add>Hebrew</add> to make proselytes, for, if otherwise<lb/>
                <persName>Yehoshua</persName> would not have made <persName>Rahab</persName> a
                Jewess, and<lb/> likewise would <persName>Hillel</persName> not have complied with
                the desire<lb/> of two heathens, to be made by him Israelites; still,<lb/> these are
                quite different cases. <persName>Yehoshua</persName> knew from<lb/> the character of
                    <persName>Rahab</persName>, and so knew <persName>Hillel</persName> from
                the<lb/> character of the two heathens, that they will one day be-<lb/>come strict
                and faithful Jews"—<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">After these remarks, allow me yet to add, that we are,<lb/> to our
                deepest regret, sufficiently convinced that of all<lb/> these non-Israelitish
                mothers in this city, who consented<lb/> that their children be entered into the
                covenant of cir-<lb/>cumcision, there is not one that has done so from the<lb/> pure
                motive, to see her child worship one day the One<lb/> only God of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>,—a religion which she herself denies<lb/> in word
                and deed: but they did so to please the Jewish<lb/> grandparents or their Jewish
                husbands, (who themselves<lb/> have no other motive than that the children be
                entitled,<lb/> in case of death, to a piece of ground on the Jewish bu<lb/>rial
                place). They would, however, not allow the <add>Hebrew</add> to<lb/> be applied to
                them; though I explained to some of them<lb/> plainly that without the
                    <add>Hebrew</add>, a child of a non-Israelitish<lb/> mother, can by law never be
                regarded as a Jew, though it<lb/> be circumcised; it was nevertheless, refused,
                because they<lb/> do not want to have their children <sic>baptised</sic> as Jews.
                They<lb/> consent sooner to have them circumcised than to be <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <sic>baptised</sic> as Jews, for in their religion, the baptism is the<lb/>
                principal and most important act.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now let us see what are the consequences of the cir-<lb/>cumcision
                of these children, (of whom there are about<lb/> twelve in our city of different
                ages, from five months up<lb/> to twelve years, to whom <add>Hebrew</add> was never
                applied). They<lb/> will pass as Jews, because they are circumcised, and<lb/> marry
                daughters of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, though circumcision never<lb/> made them
                Israelites. But, more than this, what must<lb/> be foreseen is, that the children of
                these marriages will<lb/> be regarded by law as <add>Hebrew</add>, of whom God says—<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> Using the expression <add>Hebrew</add>, which may sound badly
                in<lb/> your ears, I must refer to Talmud Yebamoth, p. 46,<lb/> where we read as
                follows: "<persName>Rabby Chiya</persName> came to the<lb/> city of
                    <placeName>Gabla</placeName>, there he saw several daughters of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> married to proselytes, who were circumcised,
                but had<lb/> no <add>Hebrew</add>, and when <persName>Rabby Yochanan</persName>
                heard of it, he said<lb/> to him (to <persName>Rabby Chiya</persName>), go and call
                out in the syna-<lb/>gogue that the children of these people are <add>Hebrew</add>,
                who<lb/> are forbidden to come into the congregation of the<lb/> Lord."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And now allow me, gents, to ask you another ques-<lb/>tion—what
                shall one day become of such children, even<lb/> if they would have both
                    <add>Hebrew</add> and <add>Hebrew</add>? Educated by a<lb/> Christian mother and
                an irreligious father, who publicly<lb/> violates <date>sabbaths</date> and
                festivals, and whose table is dese-<lb/>crated by all kinds of forbidden food, as it
                is the case<lb/> here, which cannot be denied; the mother goes to church<lb/> and
                the father has neither church nor synagogue; in the<lb/> parental house, the child
                can not perceive even a slight<lb/> tint of our religion, no other
                    <date>sabbath</date> than this of his<lb/> mother—the <date>Sunday</date>—for
                the father has no day of rest<lb/> at all, neither on <date>Sabbath</date> nor on
                    <date>Sunday</date>. Be sincere,<lb/> and say would it not be much better for
                those poor child-<lb/>ren to let them be what their mothers are, Christians,<lb/>
                than convert them for appearance sake into Jews, which<lb/> they will never be, and
                enjoin upon them heavy duties,<lb/> which, as you yourselves know, they will never
                fulfill?—<lb/>Can there yet be anything more detrimental to the cause<lb/> of
                Judaism than to make such Jews?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. G.</persName> propounded simply the question before
                the dif-<lb/>ferent <sic>rabbies</sic>, whether the son of a non-Israelitish
                mo-<lb/>ther can be admitted to the covenant? Of course they<lb/> must answer in the
                affirmative. But had <persName>Mr. G.</persName> stated<lb/> all the above mentioned
                circumstances, then, I am sure,<lb/> that there is no such a man in this world, who
                has only<lb/> a spark of justice and religious feeling in his heart, that<lb/> can
                approve the admission of such children into Judaism,<lb/> for we would only educate
                them as enemies to our reli-<lb/>gion, which last is far more respected by true
                Christians<lb/> than by irreligious Jews. In vain would we inflict bodi-<lb/>ly pain
                upon the poor creature, and commit a grave of<lb/>fence against our holy religion,
                morality, justice, and<lb/> humanity.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">These, gents, are, in short, the reasons wherefore I<lb/> ordered
                the <add>Hebrew</add> not to circumcise in future children<lb/> of non-Israelitish
                mothers, but <persName>Mr. G.</persName>, on account of his<lb/> circumcision fees,
                (for were it religious scruple, he would<lb/> surely not go on <add>Hebrew</add> to
                auctions, and would not arrange<lb/> a ball as he did on the eve of last
                    <add>Hebrew</add>), was not<lb/> satisfied, and declared in a most insulting
                manner that<lb/> he has done so before, and will in future, in spite of rea-<lb/>son
                and religion, continue to do so; and it is, therefore,<lb/> that I publicly declared
                him unfit for the holy office of<lb/> a <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">That I had the right to do so, gentlemen, I refer you<lb/> to
                    <add>Hebrew</add>, which reads as follows:<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Hoping that this letter will convince you that I acted<lb/> in
                obedience to my duties,<lb/> I remain, gentlemen,<lb/> Most respectfully yours,</p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">Dr. ILLOWY</persName>
            </p>
            <p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, <date>Dec. 29th, 5625</date>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
