<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Eckman, Julius</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0202</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Eckman, Julius</author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1851-05" source="" attested="yes">May 13. 1851</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1851-05" source="" attested="yes">5611</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0202_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0202_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0202_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0202_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">Beth Elohim Congregation of <placeName>Charleston</placeName></p>
			<p rend="align(right)indent(-1)"><hi rend="The following line is circled">send proof on galley</hi></p>
				<p><add>&#63;</add> &#47; To the Editor of the Occident</p> 
				<p>My dear Sir&#33;</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Fain charged by you in your last Occi&#8222;<lb/>dent with inconsistency.</p>
				<p>For myself&#44; I am regardless of <del>the said</del> such an accusation&#44; being<lb/> full satisfied&#44; <del>being</del> with the Purity and Rectitude of my<lb/> Intentions&#44; and <del>as</del> my position at present&#44; with the Congre&#8222;<lb/>gation Beth Elohim of <placeName>Charleston</placeName> <del>in which</del> among whom I have the honor to teach&#44;<lb/> would render it <hi rend="underline">improper</hi> and <hi rend="underline">undignified</hi> to enter into a full<lb/> exposition of my principles&#44; so long after my election.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I must <add>therefore</add> respectfully request&#44; that you will suspend<lb/> your Opinion in relation to my Course&#44; until the period<lb/> shall arrive&#44; when it may become necessary&#44; that I should<lb/> appear before my <sic>Brethern</sic> under my own name in<lb/> <sic>defence</sic> of Truth&#44; Justice&#44; and the Holy Word of God.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Sincerity and Candor&#44; are certainly Virtues which we great&#8222;<lb/>ly admire&#59; but we should be careful&#44; how we pass sentence&#44;<lb/> before we are full possessed of facts and circumstances con&#8222;<lb/>nected with the subject upon which we are about to decide.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">For your satisfaction&#44; however&#44; I would state&#44; that my<lb/> views were <hi rend="underline">fully</hi> and <hi rend="underline">plainly</hi> expressed to those members<lb/> of the Congregation who presented themselves for that purpose&#44;<lb/> <add>previous to my election</add> and&#44; nevertheless&#44; I was elected <hi rend="underline">contrary</hi> to my expectations&#44;<lb/> by an almost unanimous Vote&#8212;I believe only one In&#8222;<lb/>dividual having voted <del>against me</del> in the negative&#44; <del>who</del> has<lb/> since become one of my warmest friends and supporters</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>While I regard my humble acquiescence to the requi&#8222;<lb/>sitions of the Circular&#44; of the Congregation Beth Elohim<lb/> of <placeName>Charleston</placeName>&#44; as admissible according to the letter of<lb/> strict Judaism&#44; I have never hesitated on all occasions&#44; after the<lb/> <del>I have</del> earliest period of my arrival &#8222;to oppose<lb/> any thing that encroached upon the principles<lb/> of ancient Judaism&#44; as that might have the ten&#8222;<lb/>dency to wound the feelings of the pious and con&#8222;<lb/>scientious Israelite&#44; whose sincere attachments and<lb/> affections claim our highest Respect and Attention.</p>
				<p>That the Almighty God blessed be He&#44; may enable His<lb/> humble servant&#44; and the most trying circumstances<lb/> to effect some little good among his people&#44;<lb/> in his <del>is the</del> most fervent and ardent Prayer.</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)">Yours respectfully</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)"><persName role="author">Julius Eckman</persName></p>
				<p><placeName>Charleston</placeName> <date>May 13. 5611</date></p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">L Prim</hi></p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Note by the Editor</hi> It is indeed painful in the extreme for one like<lb/> us to be called upon to insert communications as in the last number<lb/> of our magazine wherein the merits of opposite opinions are<lb/> discussed&#44; and upon which we are in a measure called upon<lb/> to pass our opinion&#44; for to say nothing when grave measures<lb/> of principle are at stake would at once show that we are unworthy to occupy the editorial supervision of a Jewish periodical the <add>&#63;</add></p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>of which it is to speak out boldly on all matters affecting Judaisia.  We<lb/> were called upon to print a piece <sic>depracatory</sic> of some remarks about<lb/> <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> which he had inserted&#44; and which <add>had</add> appeared solely because<lb/> <persName>Mr P.</persName> stood as the representative of certain ideas against which we have<lb/> always protested and against which we have preached &#38; written for a<lb/> number of years.  We had <sic>therefor</sic> no injustice to that gentleman to let<lb/> an intelligent correspondent who is himself a liberal altho&#39; <add>&#63;</add> writer<lb/> disturb <persName>Mr P.</persName> in his retirement&#44; especially since we are assured that<lb/> he has still a strong party devoted to him and his principles.  At the<lb/> same time another friend forwarded to us <del>the</del> a commendation of the<lb/> course of <persName>Mr P.&#39;s</persName> successor in office&#44; a gentleman highly praised for his<lb/> learning and zeal&#44; and the powerful and <sic>disintersted</sic> efforts he is making<lb/> to bring his flock back to a proper mode of thinking on religious matters.<lb/>  We are perfectly willing to let the Occident speak on behalf of such<lb/> laudable efforts&#44; and we wish with all our heart that they may be<lb/> successful to the fullest extent.  But can any one assert that we<lb/> should not at the same time protest against the propriety of any<lb/> gentleman&#39;s taking office where he is brought forward as the defender<lb/> of opinions which we must condemn&#63;  Can it be asked of us that<lb/> we should by our silence endorse a course of proceeding which<lb/> we would never have adopted&#63;  We leave it to <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> himself<lb/> and our valued friends who find fault with our notice of last month&#44;<lb/> whether we could have acted otherwise.  We know full well that<lb/> <persName>Dr. E&#39;s</persName> position is a faithful one in the extreme&#59; to stand as the<lb/> mediator between two opinions and endeavour honestly to execute<add>&#63;</add><lb/> there&#44; is a task which the greatest minds may fail under&#59; we<lb/> admire his courage to defy so powerful an opponent as <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName><lb/> who both from his <sic>connexions</sic> &#38; talents is an opponent of no one <add>&#63;</add>&#59;</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>but all this does not reach our first objection&#44; which is that the <persName>Dr.<lb/> Eckman</persName> should have hesitated before he assured <add>&#63;</add> in full<lb/> of danger &#38; difficulties.  We should deeply regret that our remarks<lb/> should have thrown in his way the least obstacle&#44; as have the<lb/> best to diminish his usefulness.  But if so it was entirely una<lb/>voidable&#59; we belong to no school of of reformers&#44; we know of no one here<lb/> living in <placeName>Europe</placeName> whose footsteps we could safely follow&#59; and let our<lb/> teachers in this country place themselves on the platform of<lb/> Scripture &#38; tradition&#44; and they may depend on our support little<lb/> as this is just now&#44; and nothing that we can affect shall be left<lb/> undone to assist them in their labours.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We are perfectly aware that <persName>Dr. E.</persName> cannot of his own accord<lb/> revive<add>&#63;</add> the organ or restore religion in <placeName>Charleston</placeName>&#59; and that all he<lb/> can do in his present position is to bring matters in train<add>&#63;</add> for a future<lb/> restoration to the ancient standard.  But we only ask of him that<lb/> he should declare against <hi rend="underline">all</hi> that has been done&#44; openly<lb/> and unequivocally&#59; let there be no reservation of mind&#44; nothing<lb/> be left for any doubt&#44; and then can we speak as approvingly on our<lb/> personal friends so now of the Reverend Doctor.  Let us again repeat<lb/> that we attack no man&#39;s motives&#59; but surely we have an undoubted<lb/> right to say that these men of <placeName>Israel</placeName> who feel a deep interest in<lb/> the maintenance of a uniformity in religion have a claim on<lb/> all who profess to teach to speak without disguise and to<lb/> labour without fear&#44; without regarding whom their word may<lb/> indite<add>&#63;</add>.  Let us beware of that most <sic>dangeris</sic> enemy to truth<lb/> <hi rend="underline">flattery</hi>&#59; let our teachers also guard against <hi rend="underline">self&#45;deception</hi>&#44; and<lb/> let the people see that they support these most who show the worst <hi rend="underline">consistency</hi>&#59; and all will be well.  We have for our fault no wrongs<lb/> to revenge against any of our public men in the country&#44; and<lb/> what we say of them is the simple expression<add>&#63;</add> of our honest contribution<lb/>  We know well enough that this does not bring us many friends&#59; but it<lb/> at least proves that we speak what we believe the truth.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Now as respects <persName>Dr. E.</persName> we are pleased to record that his views were known<lb/> before his election&#59; and let us therefore hope that all who now differ from him<lb/> may speedily be <sic>come</sic> his sincere friends&#44; and give him their aid and countenance in</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
