<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckman, Julius</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0202</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckman,
                            Julius</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-05">May 13. 1851</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-05">5611</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0202_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0202_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0202_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0202_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">Beth Elohim Congregation of <placeName>Charleston</placeName></p>
            <p rend="align(right)indent(-1)">
                <hi rend="The following line is circled">send proof on galley</hi>
            </p>
            <p><add>?</add> / To the Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p>My dear Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Fain charged by you in your last Occi„<lb/>dent with
                inconsistency.</p>
            <p>For myself, I am regardless of <del>the said</del> such an accusation, being<lb/>
                full satisfied, <del>being</del> with the Purity and Rectitude of my<lb/>
                Intentions, and <del>as</del> my position at present, with the Congre„<lb/>gation
                Beth Elohim of <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <del>in which</del> among whom I have the honor to teach,<lb/> would render it <hi
                    rend="underline">improper</hi> and <hi rend="underline">undignified</hi> to
                enter into a full<lb/> exposition of my principles, so long after my election.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I must <add>therefore</add> respectfully request, that you will
                suspend<lb/> your Opinion in relation to my Course, until the period<lb/> shall
                arrive, when it may become necessary, that I should<lb/> appear before my
                    <sic>Brethern</sic> under my own name in<lb/>
                <sic>defence</sic> of Truth, Justice, and the Holy Word of God.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Sincerity and Candor, are certainly Virtues which we great„<lb/>ly
                admire; but we should be careful, how we pass sentence,<lb/> before we are full
                possessed of facts and circumstances con„<lb/>nected with the subject upon which we
                are about to decide.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For your satisfaction, however, I would state, that my<lb/> views
                were <hi rend="underline">fully</hi> and <hi rend="underline">plainly</hi> expressed
                to those members<lb/> of the Congregation who presented themselves for that purpose,<lb/>
                <add>previous to my election</add> and, nevertheless, I was elected <hi
                    rend="underline">contrary</hi> to my expectations,<lb/> by an almost unanimous
                Vote—I believe only one In„<lb/>dividual having voted <del>against me</del> in the
                negative, <del>who</del> has<lb/> since become one of my warmest friends and
                supporters</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>While I regard my humble acquiescence to the requi„<lb/>sitions of the Circular, of
                the Congregation Beth Elohim<lb/> of <placeName>Charleston</placeName>, as
                admissible according to the letter of<lb/> strict Judaism, I have never hesitated on
                all occasions, after the<lb/>
                <del>I have</del> earliest period of my arrival „to oppose<lb/> any thing that
                encroached upon the principles<lb/> of ancient Judaism, as that might have the
                ten„<lb/>dency to wound the feelings of the pious and con„<lb/>scientious Israelite,
                whose sincere attachments and<lb/> affections claim our highest Respect and
                Attention.</p>
            <p>That the Almighty God blessed be He, may enable His<lb/> humble servant, and the most
                trying circumstances<lb/> to effect some little good among his people,<lb/> in his
                    <del>is the</del> most fervent and ardent Prayer.</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours respectfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">Julius Eckman</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <date>May 13. 5611</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="underline">L Prim</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Note by the Editor</hi> It is indeed painful in the extreme for
                one like<lb/> us to be called upon to insert communications as in the last
                number<lb/> of our magazine wherein the merits of opposite opinions are<lb/>
                discussed, and upon which we are in a measure called upon<lb/> to pass our opinion,
                for to say nothing when grave measures<lb/> of principle are at stake would at once
                show that we are unworthy to occupy the editorial supervision of a Jewish periodical
                the <add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>of which it is to speak out boldly on all matters affecting Judaisia. We<lb/> were
                called upon to print a piece <sic>depracatory</sic> of some remarks about<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> which he had inserted, and which <add>had</add>
                appeared solely because<lb/>
                <persName>Mr P.</persName> stood as the representative of certain ideas against
                which we have<lb/> always protested and against which we have preached &amp; written
                for a<lb/> number of years. We had <sic>therefor</sic> no injustice to that
                gentleman to let<lb/> an intelligent correspondent who is himself a liberal altho'
                    <add>?</add> writer<lb/> disturb <persName>Mr P.</persName> in his retirement,
                especially since we are assured that<lb/> he has still a strong party devoted to him
                and his principles. At the<lb/> same time another friend forwarded to us
                    <del>the</del> a commendation of the<lb/> course of <persName>Mr P.'s</persName>
                successor in office, a gentleman highly praised for his<lb/> learning and zeal, and
                the powerful and <sic>disintersted</sic> efforts he is making<lb/> to bring his
                flock back to a proper mode of thinking on religious matters.<lb/> We are perfectly
                willing to let the Occident speak on behalf of such<lb/> laudable efforts, and we
                wish with all our heart that they may be<lb/> successful to the fullest extent. But
                can any one assert that we<lb/> should not at the same time protest against the
                propriety of any<lb/> gentleman's taking office where he is brought forward as the
                defender<lb/> of opinions which we must condemn? Can it be asked of us that<lb/> we
                should by our silence endorse a course of proceeding which<lb/> we would never have
                adopted? We leave it to <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> himself<lb/> and our valued
                friends who find fault with our notice of last month,<lb/> whether we could have
                acted otherwise. We know full well that<lb/>
                <persName>Dr. E's</persName> position is a faithful one in the extreme; to stand as
                the<lb/> mediator between two opinions and endeavour honestly to
                execute<add>?</add><lb/> there, is a task which the greatest minds may fail under;
                we<lb/> admire his courage to defy so powerful an opponent as <persName>Mr
                    Poznanski</persName><lb/> who both from his <sic>connexions</sic> &amp; talents
                is an opponent of no one <add>?</add>;</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>but all this does not reach our first objection, which is that the <persName>Dr.<lb/>
                    Eckman</persName> should have hesitated before he assured <add>?</add> in
                full<lb/> of danger &amp; difficulties. We should deeply regret that our
                remarks<lb/> should have thrown in his way the least obstacle, as have the<lb/> best
                to diminish his usefulness. But if so it was entirely una<lb/>voidable; we belong to
                no school of of reformers, we know of no one here<lb/> living in
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName> whose footsteps we could safely follow; and let
                our<lb/> teachers in this country place themselves on the platform of<lb/> Scripture
                &amp; tradition, and they may depend on our support little<lb/> as this is just now,
                and nothing that we can affect shall be left<lb/> undone to assist them in their
                labours.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We are perfectly aware that <persName>Dr. E.</persName> cannot of
                his own accord<lb/> revive<add>?</add> the organ or restore religion in
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>; and that all he<lb/> can do in his present
                position is to bring matters in train<add>?</add> for a future<lb/> restoration to
                the ancient standard. But we only ask of him that<lb/> he should declare against <hi
                    rend="underline">all</hi> that has been done, openly<lb/> and unequivocally; let
                there be no reservation of mind, nothing<lb/> be left for any doubt, and then can we
                speak as approvingly on our<lb/> personal friends so now of the Reverend Doctor. Let
                us again repeat<lb/> that we attack no man's motives; but surely we have an
                undoubted<lb/> right to say that these men of <placeName>Israel</placeName> who feel
                a deep interest in<lb/> the maintenance of a uniformity in religion have a claim
                on<lb/> all who profess to teach to speak without disguise and to<lb/> labour
                without fear, without regarding whom their word may<lb/> indite<add>?</add>. Let us
                beware of that most <sic>dangeris</sic> enemy to truth<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">flattery</hi>; let our teachers also guard against <hi
                    rend="underline">self-deception</hi>, and<lb/> let the people see that they
                support these most who show the worst <hi rend="underline">consistency</hi>; and all
                will be well. We have for our fault no wrongs<lb/> to revenge against any of our
                public men in the country, and<lb/> what we say of them is the simple
                    expression<add>?</add> of our honest contribution<lb/> We know well enough that
                this does not bring us many friends; but it<lb/> at least proves that we speak what
                we believe the truth.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now as respects <persName>Dr. E.</persName> we are pleased to record
                that his views were known<lb/> before his election; and let us therefore hope that
                all who now differ from him<lb/> may speedily be <sic>come</sic> his sincere
                friends, and give him their aid and countenance in</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
