<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP20-754</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_754_001.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p><persName>Mr J L Moss</persName> having stated that <persName>Mr D. Samuel</persName>
                had requested him<lb/> to say that <persName>Mr Samuel</persName> had written a note
                to the Polish congregation re-<lb/>questing them to perform the subsequent funeral
                services at the<lb/> house during the seven days, wherefore the Board adopted
                the<lb/> following Preamble &amp; resolutions</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Parnass having stated to the Board that <persName>Frederick<lb/>
                    Samuel</persName> a member of another congregation and not a seat-<lb/>holder of
                this had died and that it was the wish of his family<lb/> that he should be buried
                in our burial ground,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">On motion of <persName>J. A. Phillips</persName></p>
            <p>Resolved <sic>That</sic> the Parnass be authorized to permit such<lb/> interment on
                payment of one hundred Dollars and on the express<lb/> condition that the funeral
                rites and morning &amp; evening service for<lb/> the seven days be performed by the
                    <persName role="author">Rev. Mr. Leeser</persName> according to our<lb/> customs
                &amp; not otherwise, &amp; that a copy of this preamble &amp; reso<lb/>lution be
                sent to the family of the deceased.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">Lately Published</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">a new version of the Holy Scriptures from the original Hebrew in
                English</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">under the following Title</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">The Twenty-four Books</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">of the</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">Holy Scriptures</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">carefully translated</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">according to the Massoretic text, on the basis of the</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">English Version</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">and supplied with</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">short explanatory notes</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">by</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName> (of
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>)</p>
            <p>This work forms an elegant quarto volume of 1011 pages printed in double
                columns,<lb/> with large and clear types and on fine paper or as befitting
                comparison<lb/> as regards its exterior appearances with my English publication. It
                will be<lb/> sold at the following prices: In sheets or paper wrappers at $6.00; in
                plain<lb/> sheep at $7.00; in sheep, gilt backs at $8.00; in plain morocco at $9; in half<lb/>
                <add>?</add> morocco at 10; in plain finished gilt edged morocco at 11; in<lb/>
                extra finished gilt edged morocco at 12.</p>
            <p>The translator to be has had much experience in various literary labors<lb/> has had
                his attention direct for many years lost to the shortcomings of the<lb/> common
                English or <persName>King James</persName> Bible Version, in view of the many
                important<lb/> discourses on the meaning of words and phrases brought to light by
                the unremitting<lb/> studies of both Jewish &amp; critics <sic>critics</sic> for the
                last two hundred centuries.<lb/> These labors have of late years been embodied in
                several new versions of the<lb/> Old Testament Scriptures (so called) the only ones
                existing in the Hebrew language<lb/> by many learned men in
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <placeName>France</placeName>,
                    <placeName>England</placeName>, &amp; <placeName>Holland</placeName>; and from
                the well known deep<lb/> scholarship of German Theologians it will be apparent that
                these especially must</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>have labored faithfully and profitably in this important field. The translator<lb/>
                flattering himself that his general acquaintance with Hebrew, German &amp;<lb/>
                English reaches him at least not more unfitted than any other person in this<lb/>
                country from succeeding in this difficult field, has accordingly ventured to<lb/>
                preface a new English version founded on the same general principles<lb/> of
                interpretation elaborated elsewhere, without at the dame time having<lb/> altogether
                the basis of the common translation in use in <placeName>America</placeName> &amp;<lb/>
                <placeName>England</placeName>. He has however not copied any authorities, but
                has<lb/> himself endeavored to judge for himself, and has carefully weighed
                differ-<lb/>ent opinions as far as his ability to do so extends. He will not assert
                that<lb/> he has escaped error, but he can assure with truth that he has<lb/>
                endeavored to do his full duty in the process<add>?</add>.</p>
            <p>The following kind critique of the book is contained in the <date>July</date>
                number<lb/> of the Princeton Review, added by the <persName>Rev. Charles
                    Hodge</persName> D. D. of the <sic>presbyterian</sic><lb/> church, the only
                journalist to whom a presentation copy was furnished.</p>
            <p><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                <date>Sep. 20. 1854</date>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>My address is <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
                <placeName>Philadelphia Pennsylvania</placeName>.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                <date>May 2nd 5598</date>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Uncle.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Hays</persName> I understand is going down to
                    <placeName>Baltimore</placeName><lb/> tomorrow; I take therefore the opportunity
                to write you, as I have done<lb/> so for several weeks past. On <date>Sunday</date>
                of last week I sent you a<lb/> paper containing a notice of my books, which I
                presume you obtained<lb/> through the post office. On <date>Monday</date> at six
                    <sic>oclock</sic> I started for<lb/>
                <placeName>New York</placeName>, and met <persName>Dr. Cohen</persName> the next day
                at <add>?</add>
                <persName>Noah's</persName><lb/> office, he doubtfully told you that he had seen me.
                I remained<lb/> in <placeName>New York</placeName> till <date>Thursday</date>
                evening five o'clock when I returned<lb/> hither and arrived not <sic>untill</sic>
                near four o'clock, owing to some accident<lb/> to the tender in consequence of which
                another engine had to be sent for<lb/> from <placeName>Amboy</placeName>, which
                detained us till near eleven before we got fairly<lb/> under <sic>weigh</sic>,
                whereas we ought to have been near <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> at that
                time. I collected about four hundred Dollars in <placeName>N. York</placeName>,<lb/>
                and I have accordingly to return in a few weeks when I hope<lb/> to get the
                remainder. People are not yet ready to settle, altho<add>ugh</add><lb/> I have given
                them so long credit. But I must consider that times<lb/> have been uncommonly hard
                and people find it difficult to meet<lb/> their ordinary engagements;—<persName>Mr.
                        <add>?</add>as</persName> appears well, and looks<lb/> quite stout and
                hearty. I was at <persName>Mr. Kursheedt's</persName> and <persName>Mr
                    <add>?</add><lb/> B. Hart</persName> desired to be particularly remembered to
                you. They seemed<lb/> quite well. <persName>David Seiner</persName> has returned
                from <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>, he has <add>?</add><lb/> very thin, though is
                otherwise well. I met <persName>Elkalah</persName> for the first<lb/> time since she
                left <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, she certainly is greatly altered in her<lb/>
                looks and this not for the better.—I spoke to but few in relation<lb/>
                <add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p><add>?</add><lb/> I should like to ask your opinion upon many other points from time
                to<lb/> time, if you would permit me, to address you occasionally what I trust<lb/>
                you will grant me, and I assure you, that you shall never need blame<lb/> yourself
                for the favour granted.—If you can conveniently do it,<lb/> please to make your
                reply in English, that it may be extensively<lb/> circulated.—Answer this if you can
                by the earliest packet, since<lb/> not I alone but many other persons are anxious
                for your opinion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have seen with pleasure that <persName>Mr De Sola</persName> has
                undertaken<lb/> a new edition of the Portuguese service, since the books formerly
                found<lb/> by <persName>David Levy</persName>
                <sic>is</sic> are not now to be had any more though often inquired<lb/> after. Two
                years ago I wanted to undertake the same labour myself,<lb/> but a <sic>sever</sic>
                illness, the small-pox, kept me confined for several months,<lb/> and my health has
                ever since continued too bad to permit me to<lb/> undertake so heavy a task. Having
                been thus myself prevented by<lb/> the hand of God from accomplishing my design, I
                am glad to see it under-<lb/>taken by one who I hope is fully capable to do justice
                to the work. If it is<lb/> well done, I shall rejoice that it has been accomplished,
                and shall on<lb/> my endeavours, feeble as they are, to forward the author's design.
                If you<lb/> think proper you may communicate this to him, altho' I have never<lb/>
                had the pleasure of hearing any thing about him, till I heard of his<lb/> prospectus
                some weeks since from a bookseller of eminence, who belongs<lb/> to our
                congregation, and not till this morning was the prospectus itself<lb/> placed in my
                hands.—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am afraid I have detained you too long, particularly by
                matters<lb/> not relevant to my inquiries, if so I beg you to excuse me; and to<lb/>
                forgive the errors if a stranger, who speaks to a father and teacher<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>; whom he would gladly personally see &amp; know.
                May our<lb/> God preserve you many years in health and prosperity, and may
                there<lb/> never be wanting one in your family to sit on the seat of judgment in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
