<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M N</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0064</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M N</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1853-01">Jany. 9, 1853</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1853-01">5613</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0064_1R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0064_1V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0064_2R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0064_2V.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, <date>Jany. 9<hi rend="sup"
                        >Th</hi> 5613 (1853)</date>.</p>
            <p>My dear <addressee>Leeser</addressee>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">At the end of this month, I shall be, like you, an<lb/> ungowned
                parson, and therefore, I devote myself, before that time<lb/> to the pleasing duty
                of writing you a few lines, while I can still,<lb/> without opposition, claim the
                title of Revd. You are, no doubt, aware<lb/> that applications have, until very
                recently, been made to me by parties<lb/> in <placeName>Savannah</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Mobile</placeName>, which were declined. <persName>Mr.
                    Eckmann</persName> did<lb/> not please the folks here; indeed I don't know who
                can. The are very<lb/> willing to employ the best minister possible, but the truth
                is, they don't<lb/> want to pay. They would like <persName>Mr. Touro</persName> to
                do that duty. It is quite<lb/> honor sufficient that they have accepted his gift,
                and having secured<lb/> that effectually, their obligations are ended. They have
                been playing<lb/> a farce with me during the last fortnight. It ended as I
                foresaw,<lb/> with a positive rejection of their overtures. When they made
                their<lb/> proposals, they were, and are still, indebted to me for several
                months<lb/> services; which there is no likelihood of getting paid, unless out<lb/>
                of the old gentleman's pocket. He is heartily tired of these continued<lb/> draws on
                his purse, and I will no longer submit to be <del>the</del> a pensioner<lb/> on his
                bounty, when those who are able to satisfy my claims, lack<lb/> the will and
                inclination. Since my engagement in <date>Feby 50</date>, he<lb/> has paid nearly
                two thirds of my salary. Last <date>May</date> a great effort<lb/> was made, and a
                list was subscribed by several, by which offerings were to be abolished tacitly, and
                a contribution, to cover and include<lb/> seat rents and monthly dues, substituted.
                Many of the subscribers, in<lb/> good circumstances too, have broken faith; and
                those who have kept it,<lb/> now decline to keep to their engagement, because, they
                justly allege,</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>that the <sic>burthen</sic> of maintaining the synagogue ought not to<lb/> devolve on
                them alone. What the upshot is to be, time only will<lb/> reveal. But I can assure
                you, that however ardent my zeal to<lb/> devote myself to
                    <placeName>Israel's</placeName> cause, I should be a fool to remain<lb/> here
                with the prospect of hard labor and no bread to eat. It is<lb/> certainly harsh to
                characterize the greater part of the congregation<lb/> as devoid of honor,
                principle, religion, and gratitude but it is<lb/> nevertheless perfectly true. I can
                prove it to be so to you and any<lb/> one's satisfaction. <persName>Mr.
                    Touro</persName> has expressed himself satisfied<lb/> with my action and
                conduct; not so with those of the congregation.<lb/> Neither the decency and decorum
                of public worship, nor the advocacy<lb/> and exposition of our faith, have suffered
                thro' me in this city.<lb/> The synagogue has not lost a jot of its prestige from
                the night<lb/> of the consecration until this moment. This my congregation are<lb/>
                forced to admit, and, from the documents I send you, which you<lb/> are at liberty
                to publish in the Occident, if you think fit, they<lb/> are not willing to part with
                me. My object in forwarding them, is<lb/> to prove, if necessary, to the Jewish
                public, under what circumstances<lb/> I have taken leave of the ministry, and with
                what feelings. That<lb/> you may understand the whole proceedings, I must confide to you,<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">under the seal of secrecy, particulars, which you are not at
                    liberty<lb/> to divulge, except with my consent</hi>. In <date>February
                    51</date>, finding that<lb/> there was no desire on the part of the Congregation
                to pay me my<lb/> salary, them 3 months in arrear, and <persName>Mr.
                    Touro</persName> having until then<lb/> discharged the greater portion, I wrote
                to him, stating my painful<lb/> position, urging him either to endow the ministry,
                or to guarantee<lb/> the future payment of my stipend. The former he positively<lb/>
                declined, the latter he consented to, for 2 years, but no longer.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This guarantee expires with this month, and he will not renew</p>
            <p rend="The following number is written at the bottom of the page in pencil.">
                <date>1-9-1853</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>it. The congregation knows nothing of this arrangement, but I com-<lb/>municate it to
                you, under the solemn request, <hi rend="underline">that you will not<lb/> name it
                    to any one</hi>, for the purpose of explaining my real motives<lb/> of retiring.
                Duty does not call on me to starve; and the congregation<lb/> with their magnificent
                offer of $2000 a year, can, but will never<lb/> pay me. I have no wish to be
                prejudiced by my people, nor yet<lb/> of exposing my constituents; yet, unless I
                admit you behind the<lb/> scenes, you will, I am certain, make some comments to
                my<lb/> disadvantage. Having revealed the above, you will acquit me<lb/> of any
                impropriety in sending in my letter of resignation in<lb/>
                <date>July</date> last. It was unconditional, because I could not maintain<lb/>
                myself here on less salary, and <add>it</add> enabled the congregation to
                engage<lb/> another person at a lower figure. They saw this at a glance, and<lb/>
                were glad that I <sic>cancelled</sic> a contract which tied me to them for<lb/>
                life. Hence they made no effort to induce me to <sic>recal</sic> my<lb/>
                resignation, but proceeded to act on it at once. Application was<lb/> made to you,
                and on your declining, to <persName>Mr. Echman</persName>. On his<lb/> accepting the
                situation at <placeName>Mobile</placeName>, <hi rend="underline">Resolution No1</hi>
                was passed <add>at a General meeting</add>.<lb/> I received the committee most
                kindly, but declined to reengage<lb/> myself until I was assured by a requisition,
                signed by a large<lb/> majority of the congregation, that they were favourable to
                my<lb/> reappointment. The committee admitted the justice of my<lb/> resolve,
                reported it at the next General Meeting, but when one of<lb/> them moved the
                appointment of a new committee to wait upon each<lb/> individual member of the
                congregation, and ascertain the general<lb/> feeling towards me, the motion was
                voted down by a large majority<lb/> out of 20 members present, and the <hi
                    rend="underline">Resolution No 2</hi> in the second<lb/> committees letter
                    <add>was</add> substituted. Do not lose sight of the fact, that<lb/> when they
                passed this Resolution, they owed me over 4 months salary;</p>
            <p rend="The following number is written at the bottom of the page in pencil.">
                <date>1-9-1853</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>which is not yet liquidated, altho' there is a large amount<lb/> of arrearages due by
                persons in prosperous circumstances. My<lb/> letter in reply is <hi rend="underline"
                    >No 3</hi>; and you must concede that it is a most<lb/> temperate and dignified
                one, considering the manner <del>in</del> with which<lb/> they treated my proposal.
                I stated to <persName>Mr. Touro</persName>, that if <hi rend="underline"
                >he</hi><lb/> desired to retain me and engage my services I would remain; but that
                experience of 3 years had shown me that no dependence<lb/> was to be placed in the
                good faith and honor of the congregation;<lb/> and now, no circumstances, not even a
                requisition signed by<lb/> every one of them, will induce me to forego my
                determination<lb/> of leaving. I return to <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> in end
                this month, thence to <placeName>Europe</placeName><lb/> where I propose taking up
                my abode in future.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And now, my dear <persName>Leeser</persName>, as we may possibly
                not<lb/> see each other again on earth, accept my most friendly and heartfelt<lb/>
                wishes for your happiness and success. In whatever part of the world my future lot
                    <del>will</del> may be cast, I shall be delighted to hear from you<lb/> and
                rejoice to learn that you are more happy in the decline of life<lb/> than you have
                been in the meridian. Your name will be esteemed<lb/> and honored, and your worth
                acknowledged long after the grass has<lb/> grown over your grave, whilst your
                detractors will be forgotten as<lb/> tho' they had never been. My dear wife as usual
                sends her love,<lb/> and we both request you to tender our regards to our old<lb/>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> friends. That this may meet you in health and
                good spirits is the farewell greeting of</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">Your old friend &amp; wellwisher</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">
                <persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName>
            </p>
            <p>P.S. I will hand to <persName>G. Kursheedt</persName> before my<lb/> departure $9 for
                3 yr subscription to the<lb/> Occident up to <date>May 1853</date>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
