<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP20-754</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_20_754_001.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>1 page on 1 sheet
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p><persName>Mr J L Moss</persName> having stated that <persName>Mr D. Samuel</persName> had requested him<lb/> to say that <persName>Mr Samuel</persName> had written a note to the Polish congregation re&#45;<lb/>questing them to perform the subsequent funeral services at the<lb/> house during the seven days&#44; wherefore the Board adopted the<lb/> following Preamble &#38; resolutions</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Parnass having stated to the Board that <persName>Frederick<lb/> Samuel</persName> a member of another congregation and not a seat&#45;<lb/>holder of this had died and that it was the wish of his family<lb/> that he should be buried in our burial ground&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">On motion of <persName>J. A. Phillips</persName></p>
				<p>Resolved <sic>That</sic> the Parnass be authorized to permit such<lb/> interment on payment of one hundred Dollars and on the express<lb/> condition that the funeral rites and morning &#38; evening service for<lb/> the seven days be performed by the <persName role="author">Rev. Mr. Leeser</persName> according to our<lb/> customs &#38; not otherwise&#44; &#38; that a copy of this preamble &#38; reso<lb/>lution be sent to the family of the deceased.</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">Lately Published</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">a new version of the Holy Scriptures from the original Hebrew in English</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">under the following Title</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">The Twenty&#45;four Books</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">of the</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">Holy Scriptures</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">carefully translated</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">according to the Massoretic text&#44; on the basis of the</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">English Version</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">and supplied with</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">short explanatory notes</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">by</p>
				<p rend="align(center)"><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName> &#40;of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#41;</p>
				<p>This work forms an elegant quarto volume of 1011 pages printed in double columns&#44;<lb/> with large and clear types and on fine paper or as befitting comparison<lb/> as regards its exterior appearances with my English publication.  It will be<lb/> sold at the following prices&#58; In sheets or paper wrappers at &#36;6.00&#59; in plain<lb/> sheep at &#36;7.00&#59; in sheep&#44; gilt backs at &#36;8.00&#59; in plain morocco at &#36;9&#59; in half<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> morocco at 10&#59; in plain finished gilt edged morocco at 11&#59; in<lb/> extra finished gilt edged morocco at 12.</p>
				<p>The translator to be has had much experience in various literary labors<lb/> has had his attention direct for many years lost to the shortcomings of the<lb/> common English or <persName>King James</persName> Bible Version&#44; in view of the many important<lb/> discourses on the meaning of words and phrases brought to light by the unremitting<lb/> studies of both Jewish &#38; critics <sic>critics</sic> for the last two hundred centuries.<lb/>  These labors have of late years been embodied in several new versions of the<lb/> Old Testament Scriptures &#40;so called&#41; the only ones existing in the Hebrew language<lb/> by many learned men in <placeName>Germany</placeName>&#44; <placeName>France</placeName>&#44; <placeName>England</placeName>&#44; &#38; <placeName>Holland</placeName>&#59; and from the well known deep<lb/> scholarship of German Theologians it will be apparent that these especially must</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>have labored faithfully and profitably in this important field.  The translator<lb/> flattering himself that his general acquaintance with Hebrew&#44; German &#38;<lb/> English reaches him at least not more unfitted than any other person in this<lb/> country from succeeding in this difficult field&#44; has accordingly ventured to<lb/> preface a new English version founded on the same general principles<lb/> of interpretation elaborated elsewhere&#44; without at the dame time having<lb/> altogether the basis of the common translation in use in <placeName>America</placeName> &#38;<lb/> <placeName>England</placeName>.  He has however not copied any authorities&#44; but has<lb/> himself endeavored to judge for himself&#44; and has carefully weighed differ&#45;<lb/>ent opinions as far as his ability to do so extends.  He will not assert that<lb/> he has escaped error&#44; but he can assure with truth that he has<lb/> endeavored to do his full duty in the process<add>&#63;</add>.</p>
				<p>The following kind critique of the book is contained in the <date>July</date> number<lb/> of the Princeton Review&#44; added by the <persName>Rev. Charles Hodge</persName> D. D. of the <sic>presbyterian</sic><lb/> church&#44; the only journalist to whom a presentation copy was furnished.</p>
				<p><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> <date>Sep. 20. 1854</date>.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>My address is <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName> <placeName>Philadelphia Pennsylvania</placeName>.</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> <date>May 2nd 5598</date></p>
				<p>Dear Uncle.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Hays</persName> I understand is going down to <placeName>Baltimore</placeName><lb/> tomorrow&#59; I take therefore the opportunity to write you&#44; as I have done<lb/> so for several weeks past.  On <date>Sunday</date> of last week I sent you a<lb/> paper containing a notice of my books&#44; which I presume you obtained<lb/> through the post office.  On <date>Monday</date> at six <sic>oclock</sic> I started for<lb/> <placeName>New York</placeName>&#44; and met <persName>Dr. Cohen</persName> the next day at <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Noah&#39;s</persName><lb/> office&#44; he doubtfully told you that he had seen me.  I remained<lb/> in <placeName>New York</placeName> till <date>Thursday</date> evening five o&#39;clock when I returned<lb/> hither and arrived not <sic>untill</sic> near four o&#39;clock&#44; owing to some accident<lb/> to the tender in consequence of which another engine had to be sent for<lb/> from <placeName>Amboy</placeName>&#44; which detained us till near eleven before we got fairly<lb/> under <sic>weigh</sic>&#44; whereas we ought to have been near <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> at that time.  I collected about four hundred Dollars in <placeName>N. York</placeName>&#44;<lb/> and I have accordingly to return in a few weeks when I hope<lb/> to get the remainder.  People are not yet ready to settle&#44; altho<add>ugh</add><lb/> I have given them so long credit.  But I must consider that times<lb/> have been uncommonly hard and people find it difficult to meet<lb/> their ordinary engagements&#59;&#8212;<persName>Mr. <add>&#63;</add>as</persName> appears well&#44; and looks<lb/> quite stout and hearty.  I was at <persName>Mr. Kursheedt&#39;s</persName> and <persName>Mr <add>&#63;</add><lb/> B. Hart</persName> desired to be particularly remembered to you.  They seemed<lb/> quite well.  <persName>David Seiner</persName> has returned from <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>&#44; he has <add>&#63;</add><lb/> very thin&#44; though is otherwise well.  I met <persName>Elkalah</persName> for the first<lb/> time since she left <placeName>Virginia</placeName>&#44; she certainly is greatly altered in her<lb/> looks and this not for the better.&#8212;I spoke to but few in relation<lb/> <add>&#63;</add></p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p><add>&#63;</add><lb/>  I should like to ask your opinion upon many other points from time to<lb/> time&#44; if you would permit me&#44; to address you occasionally what I trust<lb/> you will grant me&#44; and I assure you&#44; that you shall never need blame<lb/> yourself for the favour granted.&#8212;If you can conveniently do it&#44;<lb/> please to make your reply in English&#44; that it may be extensively<lb/> circulated.&#8212;Answer this if you can by the earliest packet&#44; since<lb/> not I alone but many other persons are anxious for your opinion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I have seen with pleasure that <persName>Mr De Sola</persName> has undertaken<lb/> a new edition of the Portuguese service&#44; since the books formerly found<lb/> by <persName>David Levy</persName> <sic>is</sic> are not now to be had any more though often inquired<lb/> after.  Two years ago I wanted to undertake the same labour myself&#44;<lb/> but a <sic>sever</sic> illness&#44; the small&#45;pox&#44; kept me confined for several months&#44;<lb/> and my health has ever since continued too bad to permit me to<lb/> undertake so heavy a task.  Having been thus myself prevented by<lb/> the hand of God from accomplishing my design&#44; I am glad to see it under&#45;<lb/>taken by one who I hope is fully capable to do justice to the work.  If it is<lb/> well done&#44; I shall rejoice that it has been accomplished&#44; and shall on<lb/> my endeavours&#44; feeble as they are&#44; to forward the author&#39;s design.  If you<lb/> think proper you may communicate this to him&#44; altho&#39; I have never<lb/> had the pleasure of hearing any thing about him&#44; till I heard of his<lb/> prospectus some weeks since from a  bookseller of eminence&#44; who belongs<lb/> to our congregation&#44; and not till this morning was the prospectus itself<lb/> placed in my hands.&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am afraid I have detained you too long&#44; particularly by matters<lb/> not relevant to my inquiries&#44; if so I beg you to excuse me&#59; and to<lb/> forgive the errors if a stranger&#44; who speaks to a father and teacher<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#59; whom he would gladly personally see &#38; know.  May our<lb/> God preserve you many years in health and prosperity&#44; and may there<lb/> never be wanting one in your family to sit on the seat of judgment in <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> <add>Hebrew</add></p>
				<p><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
