<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">S. J.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0120</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">S. J.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1858-02">February 1858</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1858-02">Adar 5618</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0120_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0120_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0120_3r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0120_4r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="underline">The Hazan</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A<add>?</add> Editor</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">In your last number there appeared a<lb/> communication signed by
                the high sounding and bombastic<lb/> title of “<hi rend="underline">A Reader and
                    Preacher indeed</hi>”, <del>who</del> the writer of which after asking<lb/> your
                pardon for <sic>recomending</sic> to <persName>S. A.</persName> certain Optical
                Instruments,<lb/> proceeds most learnedly (as <hi rend="underline">he</hi> supposes)
                to <sic>reccomend</sic> him (<persName>S. A.</persName>)<lb/> a few more (pairs I
                suppose he meant.) Spectacles to find out in a<lb/> certain Book, Chapter and Verse
                    <add>given,</add> that which he the man of “deeds”<lb/> must have known, if he
                knew any thing about the matter, was<lb/> not there to be found, for he says, “we
                shall recommend him to look<lb/> “through the first Spectacles (did he mean pair?)
                and read the following words in<lb/> “Oracle Hayim Chap 53 Baer Hateb 16.” and then
                gives a hebrew quota=<lb/>tion, which he translates as follows, as being found in
                the place<lb/> so learnedly mentioned by him namely “A Sheliach Zibbur<add>?</add>
                has to pursua<lb/>”=ade, moralize, and to advise the Congregation in God's
                words”<lb/> Now in the Bear Hateb which <del>whic</del> was compiled by the <del>
                        b<add>?</add>
                </del><lb/> learned and pious <persName>Rabbi Judah Askanazi</persName> who was a
                    <add>דיין</add> in<lb/>
                <placeName>Lichen<add>?</add> in Poland</placeName> in the 16 paragraph on the 53
                Chapter <del>it says</del><lb/> instead of it saying any thing about his
                    <sic>pursuading</sic>-Moralizing<lb/> or <sic>adviseing</sic> them,
                    <del>it</del> says that the reader who endeavors to<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline"><sic>shew</sic> off</hi> too much, be it either with or without
                the consult of<lb/> the Congregation, will on <date>sabbaths</date> or Festivals
                renders himself<lb/>
                <sic>disgusing</sic> (<add>מגונה</add>)</p>
            <p>Now what induced your <sic>corrispondent</sic> to render himself<lb/> such an
                in-“glorious spectacle” as he is, but attempting</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>to palm off such a statement, must be but known to himself,<lb/> but it would very
                much puzzle any honest and straightforward<lb/> man to account why one rejoicing in
                such high sounding<lb/> titles as he claims for himself, and one who
                    <del>should</del> ought to know.<lb/>
                <del>why</del> should make <hi rend="underline">such</hi> statements when either
                silence or truth<lb/> would have answered as well!</p>
            <p>The <placeName>Quebec</placeName> man not as yet satisfied with his first<lb/>
                demonstration makes a second attack, and says,<lb/> “We recommend him
                    therefer<add>?</add> to put on his second Spectacles and read<lb/> “in the
                above-mentioned books Oracle Hayim Chap 53. 25.”<lb/> which he says reads as follows
                viz “The Sheliach Zibbux is called<lb/> “Hazan because he has to see how he shall
                read”</p>
            <p>Now, after with all due humility, having put on two <hi rend="underline"
                >pair</hi><lb/> of Spectacles, and <del>have examined</del> having examined no
                less<lb/> than eleven editions of the Book named by him, I have<lb/> been forced to
                the conclusion that all <del>that</del> he says <del>stands</del> about<lb/>
                <del>in</del> the 53 Chap 25 paragraph is nothing <add>else</add> but a tissue
                of<lb/> falsehoods, for in everyone of the eleven different editions of<lb/> the
                “Oracle Hayen Chap 53. 26” instead of saying any thing<lb/> about why the Hazan is
                called this, or that, or any thing of<lb/> the Kind; <add>it</add> simply says “that
                a Hazan should not be dismissed<lb/> “from his employment, unless some blemish is
                found in him.”<lb/> and nothing more.</p>
            <p>What has induced a “Reader and Preacher” thus voluntarily<lb/> to give false
                statements, must be a matter of some surprise,<lb/> but if all readers are as much
                given to such tricks as your<lb/> Provincial <sic>corrispondant</sic>, then sooner
                their services are</p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3</p>
            <p><sic>dispenced</sic> with, the better for the cause of truth of religion;<lb/> He
                then quotes a passage where according to <hi rend="underline">his</hi>
                translation<lb/> it says, “A Congregation when they wish to engage a Rabbi and”<lb/>
                “a Reader, and are unable to pay both, shall <sic>enguage</sic> the Rabbi if he
                has”<lb/> “great learning and experience, but if not they shall <sic>enguage</sic>
                the reader,”<lb/> after which in great joy at the discovery, he <add>
                    <del>then</del>
                </add> says<lb/> “Here we see that the reader has a dignity equal to that of the
                Rabbi.”<lb/> Now, here he appears to have already forgotten what he had wrote<lb/>
                but a few moments before <add>?</add> for there according to his<lb/> own shewing if
                a proper Rabbi can be obtained for the Congrega=<lb/>=tion he shall be employed, but
                in case such a one cannot<lb/> be obtained, there only—and not till then, “shall
                they choose a reader.”<lb/> Thus according to his own <del>shewing</del> theory the
                reader is <hi rend="underline">only</hi> to be<lb/> hired <hi rend="underline"
                    >because</hi> a proper Rabbi cannot be obtained, making<lb/> the necessity of
                the <add>reader</add> depend on a mere chance, instead<lb/> of his “having a dignity
                equal to that of the Rabbi.”</p>
            <p><sic>Apearantly</sic> not as yet fully satisfied with the immense<lb/> amount of
                valuable information, that he had supplied<lb/> your numerous readers with, he says
                “I quote another”<lb/> and then <hi rend="underline">pretends</hi> to give a
                translation of the 581 Chap<lb/> 1st paragraph of the Oracle Hayam, which he states
                says<lb/> “He (the reader) shall be so pious that he can acquit or discharge every
                one<lb/> with his prayers.”</p>
            <p>Now this is exactly like his former attempts to palm off that<lb/> which he
                    <del>knew</del> must have known to be untrue, for instead<lb/> of that Book
                saying “He (the reader) shall be so pious” it<lb/> merely states that there is a
                custom of arising early, from<lb/>
                <date>Rosh Hodesh Elul</date>. lite<add>?</add> the day of Atonement to say</p>
            <pb n="4R"/>
            <p>certain prayers (there M<add>?</add>) and nothing more. Following this<lb/> short
                paragraph of only 13 words, there is a commentary by <persName>Rabbi Myer<lb/>
                    Israels</persName>, who lays down a great many rules about readers during<lb/>
                <add>ימים נוראים</add>, such as that they should be over thirty years of age,<lb/>
                that they should be married mere <add>Hebrew</add> but even including the<lb/>
                Comment. No such words as “He (the reader) should be so pious”<lb/>
                <add>ever</add> occurs, and is only to be found in the <add>fertile</add>
                imagination of your<lb/>
                <sic>corrispondent</sic> from <placeName>Quebec</placeName>.</p>
            <p>What has induced this “<hi rend="underline">Reader and Preacher indeed</hi>,”
                thus<lb/> to attempt to impose on the readers of the Occident,<lb/> is a matter of
                conjecture only, but that the Editor<lb/> should allow such statements to appear in
                his journal,<lb/> where the <sic>slighest</sic> glance over them, would <add>at
                    once</add> have exhibited<lb/> their falsity, is truly a matter of
                astonishment.</p>
            <p>Arguments to be convincing should have proberty for<lb/> their basis, for it matters
                but little how pleasant<lb/> a theory may appear, once known that falsehood and<lb/>
                not veracity is the means used, the whole whoever<lb/> comely to the eye must fall,
                and thus, any one<lb/> under the garb of religion using falsehood and deceit<lb/>
                renders himself an in-”glorious Spectacle” and finally<lb/>
                <sic>injurs</sic> that which he attempts to benefit.</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <persName role="author">S.J.</persName>
            </p>
            <p><placeName>New York</placeName>
                <date>Adax 5618</date>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
