<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0040</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Kingston, Jamaica</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-07">July 5, 1863</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_1R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_1V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_2R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_2V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_3R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0040_3V.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>Kingston, Jamaica</placeName>
                <date>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July 1863</date>
            </p>
            <p>My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your various letters received here between the <date>20th<lb/>
                    April</date> last and <date>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date> did not meet my
                sight until the latter date,<lb/> on my return from a voyage to <placeName>St.
                    Thomas</placeName>
                <placeName>Curaçao</placeName> during those<lb/> 6 weeks. My tour was ostensibly to
                see my brother off. We had not set<lb/> eyes on one another for 14<add>?</add>
                years, during which time he had got married,<lb/> but his wife, like mine, is
                    <add>עקרה</add>. Prior to my departure, the Congregational ruler<lb/> of
                    <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> had invited me to permit them to put forth my
                name as a candidate<lb/> fro the vacant situation of minister, which I prudently
                declined; as is the<lb/> event of the Congregation's refusal to elect me, my
                position here would have<lb/> been injured. On my arrival at <placeName>St.
                    Thomas</placeName>, the rulers invited me to meet<lb/> them, and, after that
                interview took action. <del>After</del> I sailed (3 days after) <add>the
                    interview</add> for<lb/>
                <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>. A meeting of the voting members was called <add>in
                    my absence</add> and two propositions<lb/> were submitted for their decision.
                The first, to raise the salary from $1200, the amount of stipend advertised, to
                $1800; which was carried, 10 only dissenting,<lb/> and they, only on the plea that
                the congregation could not afford the larger<lb/> sum. The second, to elect a
                minister. The President proposed me, adding<lb/> that he had not my permission, but
                hoping that the expression of the<lb/> member, in my favour, might induce me to
                accept. The proposition was<lb/> carried without a <hi rend="underline">dissenting
                    voice</hi>. The second day after my arrival, a<lb/> deputation waited upon me
                with a numerously and respectably signed<lb/> address, inviting me to stay a
                fortnight longer, before going to <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>. I was<lb/> obliged
                to decline, but, to soften the refusal, read and preached <del>for</del> in the<lb/>
                Synagogue on <date>Friday night the 1st May</date>. The next morning I embarked<lb/>
                on my return from <placeName>Curaçao</placeName> in the <date>20th May</date>, I
                stayed at <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName></p>
            <p rend="The following is written in the top right."> 20-666, 1 of 2</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>till the <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> June</date>; and on <add>מוסף</add> read
                    <add>שחרית</add> and preached again.<lb/> Each time the Synagogue was filled. My
                reception in both places was<lb/> gratifying in the extreme. Now about
                    <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>. <add>?</add><lb/> is a generous, charitable man,
                of large proportions and with a<lb/> larger heart. In five minutes we understood
                each other perfectly. We had<lb/> many discussions on various Jewish subjects,
                Scriptural, Rabbinical,<lb/> Synagogal, raised, I suppose, for the purpose of
                drawing me out.<lb/> Books were introduced, and many a hard passage in <add>משנה
                    דינים מפרשים</add><lb/> was submitted for my opinion. Whether I acquitted myself
                will or ill, I cannot<lb/> say; but I am sure you will be pleased to hear that the
                    Chactaeu<add>?</add>, when he<lb/> came to accompany me to the vessel, presented
                me with a <add>מדרשים</add> in<lb/> Hebrew &amp; English, conferring on me the rank
                and title of <add>תעודה</add> and,<lb/> calling upon all congregations to
                acknowledge and receive me as such.<lb/> I suppose you know his title is <hi
                    rend="underline">Opper Rattiner</hi><add>?</add>, or Chief Rabbi. He<lb/>
                teaches extemporaneously, much in the style of <persName>Plessner</persName>,
                illustrating his<lb/> discourse copiously from midrash. He asked me to give him a
                test one<lb/>
                <date>Sabbath</date> just before the sermon was to be delivered, and I selected
                Prov. XVIII.I.<lb/> on which he discoursed for about 30 minutes, in Dutch. I was
                told by good<lb/> judges it was an able exposition, but, tho' I understood parts
                here and there,<lb/> I cannot say anything about it. Sometimes he preaches in
                Portuguese. His<lb/> performance of the marriage ceremony, I also witnessed. It was
                very<lb/> impressive. He always addresses the young couple before the ceremony;
                and<lb/> besides, has interviews with both in <hi rend="underline">private
                    before</hi> the union, at which I<lb/> understand he talks very seriously to
                them about their duties as husband<lb/> and wife, and also to God and
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. His charities are disputed akin<lb/> to Jew &amp;
                Christian. During the epidemic of small pox last year, when the other<lb/> clergy
                fled for their lives, he was at the bedsides of white, Black colored, administering
                medicines, pecuniary relief (in which the government gave</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>him carte blanche to draw) spiritual consolation, offering up prayer at the<lb/>
                instance of Christian sufferers, and helping occasionally with his own hands,<lb/>
                to put the dear in their coffins. He is highly respected by the Dutch
                Government.<lb/> His stipend is paid by the state, not by the Synagogue. I did not
                preach at <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>,<lb/> for the following reason. A
                requisition, respectably signed was sent to the Mahamad,<lb/> that I should preach.
                The mahamad sent for the Chacham<add>?</add>, and asked him if he had<lb/> any
                objection to me. On his answering, none, they told him that his pulpit would be<lb/>
                occupied by me the following <date>Sabbath</date>. To this, he replies, he would not
                object,<lb/> provided the mahamad asked his permission to have the pulpit so
                occupied. This<lb/> they refused to do, but sent me an intimation by letter that
                they would be happy<lb/> if I would comply with the request of the Congregation.
                Having been informed<lb/> of what had taken place, I declined, in my reply, to give
                an affirmative answer,<lb/> as the letter from the mahamad did not state expressly
                that the Chacham's<add>?</add>,<lb/> permission to occupy his pulpit had been
                obtained; but on <add>receiving</add> their assurance<lb/> that he had sanctioned
                it, I would be happy to comply with their request.<lb/> This led to another
                communication implying that I wished to dictate to them,<lb/> and informing me that
                the matter was at an end. Tho this I answered, disclaiming<lb/> most solemnly any
                intention of dictating to them the line of conduct <hi rend="underline">they</hi>
                should<lb/> pursue, but adding that the line of conduct <hi rend="underline">I</hi>
                had to pursue, agreeably to the<lb/> rules of good breeding and social etiquette
                which <del>
                    <add>?</add> every</del> obtained wherever<lb/> civilization and refinement
                existed, was not to occupy any pulpit until<lb/> I received the permission of the
                party to whom it rightfully belonged. In<lb/> a postscript, I said that being a
                stranger they would pardon me for declining any<lb/> further correspondence on the
                subject. There is a board called the <hi rend="underline">Conseijo deo<lb/>
                    Anciannos</hi>, consisting of past Presidents, which acts as a court of Review
                    <add>of</add>,<lb/> or appeal from, the acts of the mahamad. To this board, the
                proceedings in the<lb/> matter were submitted a few days after, and out of 15
                members present, 14<lb/> decided that the pulpit could at no time be occupied
                without the previous</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>consent and permission of the chacham. The dissentient<add>?</add> was the
                brother<lb/> of the President. To the chacham's honor I must state that he
                waited<lb/> personally on 7 or 8 of the most influential and wealthy of these
                    A<add>?</add><lb/> and, knowing the resentment they felt at the indignity put
                upon him by the<lb/> mahamad, as well as apprehending violence in the debate,
                exacted from them<lb/> a solemn pledge that they would keep away from the sitting,
                otherwise their<lb/> number would have swelled the notes condemnatory of the
                mahamad. This<lb/> question had been long pending, but not opportunity was afforded
                for settling it<lb/> before. The chacham's assertion that the pulpit belonged to him
                and my<lb/> firm support of his rights have now set the matter at rest, and
                strengthened<lb/> his position against the attempted encroachment of the mahamad.
                During<lb/> the progress of the discussion, I kept at home convinced that, in the
                influenced<lb/> passions of the Congregation against the mahamad, the latter would
                have been<lb/> bodily ejected from their seats in Synagogue, if I had gone up and
                down<lb/> and proved the impropriety of their action. I send you these
                particulars<lb/> in the event of your hearing any thing <del>about it</del> from the
                other side. The <persName>Revd.<lb/> Mr. <hi rend="underline"
                    >Santcroos</hi></persName> is the first <add>מורינו הרב</add>, he is the
                son-in-law of the chacham, and gives<lb/> instruction in Hebrew &amp; Religion to
                the youth of the Congregation, in the <add>מדרש</add><lb/> a certain number of hours
                p day; morning and evening. He is a very able<lb/> man. In his and his
                father-in-law's society, I spent much of the 18 days I<lb/> was at
                    <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>. The wives of both are, I think, even more
                scrupulous than<lb/> the husbands. They are very <hi rend="underline">pious and</hi>
                charitable women, and their kindness<lb/> to orphan children most touching. No shop
                or store is open among <sic>our</sic> on <date>Sabbath</date> or Holy day; even the
                second days are strictly kept.<lb/> Their rejoicings, as weddings, circumcisions,
                consecration of <sic>deadlings</sic><add>?</add> are<lb/> indeed joyous, whilst
                their mournings are sad and melancholy. The abattons<lb/> or butcheries are out of
                the town, and they have, <add>if</add> I mistake not, two Shoctim<lb/> and two
                Shomeim over whom, as well as the butcher, the Chacham keeps a<lb/> most watchful
                eye. The Chazan, the <persName>Revd. Mr. Cardozo</persName>, altho' 73 years of
                age<lb/> shows in his decline what he must have been in his prime. He reads the<lb/>
                service and Parashah with fine musical intonation and accurately<lb/> grammatical
                pronunciation. The Synagogue is a fine old building,<lb/> but the centre is spoiled
                by the hugeness and massiveness of the pillars<lb/> which intercept the view and
                prevent the eye from taking in the <add>bold</add> proportions<lb/> of the interior
                at a glance. The ladies' galleries are latticed in true moorish<lb/> style. It is
                useless <sic>too</sic> look up, the eye of a lynx would fail to make out
                        <del><add>?</add></del><lb/> the features of any fair one seated there. The
                Reading Desk and pulpit are<lb/> fine, the Hechal out of all proportion with the
                height of the building, and<lb/> the exterior of the building is <del>hideous</del>
                ugly; the western front positively<lb/> hideous. Divine service is performed twice a
                day, morning and evening<lb/> the whole week through, with always plenty of minyan.
                In the <add>עומר</add></p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p>3 times; and in those weeks, the chacham lectures generally every<lb/> other evening,
                either from Scripture or from the mishna, always extemporaneously<lb/> without a
                note before him. <placeName>Curaçao</placeName>, in fine, so far as practical
                Judaism,<lb/> on old orthodox, rabbinical principles, is concerned, is very
                considerably<lb/> ahead of our sister Congregations in the other <placeName>W. I.
                    Islands</placeName>, and need<lb/> not fear <hi rend="underline">any</hi>
                comparison as regards adherence to the ancient landmarks of our revered
                religion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am waiting momently for the arrival of the steamer<lb/> from
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName>, to receive the yea or nay to my ultimatum,<lb/>
                from the <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> Congregation. My terms are, no
                specified<lb/> term of engagement, salary as fixed by the congregation, and<lb/> a
                pension, if after 10 years I am unable, or may be declared<lb/> incapable
                    <del>of</del>, mentally or physically, of performing my duties.<lb/> This
                pension, modestly fixed at $600 <add>?</add> is the pons<lb/> asinorum betwixt us.
                The good folks kick against it, whilst<lb/> ready to pension off their hitherto
                acting Chazan <persName>Maduro</persName><lb/> tomorrow at $400 <hi rend="underline"
                    >half</hi> his salary, (I only ask for a<lb/> third) and also admitting that no
                man will suit them<lb/> so well as I, combining as I do the capability of a<lb/>
                teacher, whom they require so much, with that of a chazan<lb/> and Preacher. The
                Government had told them plainly that<lb/> if they do not take <add>?</add> me one,
                it will send them <del>one</del><add>a minister</add> from
                    <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>,<lb/> with whom the <del>Congregation</del>
                Government will make a contract<lb/> whether its provisions be palatable or not. I
                have offered to<lb/> allow myself to be put on the same footing as other
                government<lb/> officers, at the instance of the governor. Today's mail</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in pencil at the bottom right.">20-666 2 of 2</p>
            <pb n="3V"/>
            <p>will decide the point in dispute. If against me, I will, at<lb/> once take up the
                letter from <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, which I have<lb/> answered today. It
                only arrived on the <date>30th May</date>, tho' written<lb/> in <date>April</date>,
                and I received it on the <date>5th June</date>, the day I returned<lb/> home, but
                too late for replying to <del>that</del> it by that months<lb/> mail. I will not, at
                present, correspond with you on<lb/> the subject in deference to your wishes, but I
                expect <persName>Mr.<lb/> A.</persName> will. I have, at all events, opened up the
                subject<lb/> to him, and communicated how I am at this moment<lb/> situated with the
                    <placeName>St. Thos.</placeName> Cong. It will be a trying<lb/> position for any
                man, with such opponents as silent that<lb/> and wise. Yet it is worth holding for
                that sake alone.<lb/> But what will principally deter me is the present<lb/>
                unsettled state of the country. Were I to take it, I<lb/> would not keep any school,
                as I would have enough to <add>do</add> with men of giant intellect, without being
                bothered<lb/> with teaching children. I am afraid, the mail will be closed<lb/>
                before the European steamer arrives, and I will have to<lb/> wait for the next
                monthly American steamer, as no <sic>dependance</sic>, can be placed on sailing
                vessels.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I deeply sympathize with you on the death<lb/> of your old aunt
                    <persName>Mrs. Rehine</persName>, <add>כבודו</add>. The <persName>Revd. Mr.
                    Myers</persName><lb/> is just at my elbow, and begs me to say he will take
                an<lb/> early opportunity of writing you, that he sent you some<lb/> newspapers, and
                desires his kinds regards. The same to<lb/>
                <persName>J.</persName>, <persName>Mrs. N.</persName> and <persName>Mrs.
                    S.</persName> and with apologies for not answering<lb/> your letters more fully,
                which I will do next time, and<lb/> also hoping that my long Meguillah may not</p>
            <p rend="The following is continued on the left side of the page.">tire your old eyes,
                which I suppose like those of all<lb/> old Patriarchs <add>Hebrew</add> and
                deserving you are old<lb/> inquiring friend <add>?</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">I am</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">Yours ever truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">M. Nathan</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
