<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP_New_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Morais,
                            Sabato</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1868-02">February 8 1868</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_13.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold">IN MEMORIAM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="bold">A Eulogy on the Late <persName>Rev. Isaac Leeser</persName>,
                    De-<lb/>livered at the Synagogue, <placeName>Seventh Street,<lb/> Above
                        Arch</placeName>, on <date>Saturday, February 8</date>, by the<lb/>
                    <persName role="author">Rev. S. Morais</persName>, Minister of the
                    Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">What the pillar of cloud was to our fathers by day<lb/> and the
                pillar of fire by night, are the wise and the<lb/> learned to us, O fellow
                Israelites! We walk at the<lb/> light which their bright intellects emit. Our
                progeni-<lb/>tors, wending their steps through trackless deserts,<lb/> cast a look
                around, and lo! a guide from heaven led<lb/> them forth. We, the travelers of a road
                rough and<lb/> rugged, see a beacon illumining our horizon. At its<lb/> radiance we
                can always discover a safe issue. Oh!<lb/> how lurid would be the mist created by
                its absence.<lb/> But <placeName>Israel</placeName> will never be enshrouded in
                darkness. I<lb/> read it in the chronicles of truth, "<emph rend="italics">He will
                    not take<lb/> away*</emph> the pillar of cloud by day nor the pillar of
                fire<lb/> by night from before the people."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The future will, like the past, be directed by God's<lb/> own
                agency. To the end of time the house of <persName>Jacob</persName><lb/> will produce
                men whose spiritual teaching shall mold<lb/> the minds of multitudes. Let us never
                fear that infi-<lb/>delity will dethrone piety; that the rule of wickedness<lb/>
                will supplant that of godliness. A <persName>Gideon</persName> arose and<lb/> the
                idols were scattered away.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Samuel</persName> became the judge when the children of
                a<lb/> high priest contaminated the altar. The same<lb/> day which beheld the
                instruments of Roman torture<lb/> tear the life of the great
                    <persName>Akibah</persName>, saw the birth of<lb/>
                <persName>Rabbi Judah</persName>, the prince of knowledge.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yet, though the history of all ages affords the con-<lb/>solatory
                assurance that the Lord will not leave the<lb/> flock of his pasture a prey to the
                devouring wolf, a<lb/> feeling of dismay seizes us when faithful shepherds<lb/>
                vanish from our presence. To us, whose vision is<lb/> narrow, it appears as if none
                could be found to fill up<lb/> the void. For those whose spirit was wafted to
                the<lb/> abode of eternity, we considered vigilant guardians,<lb/> trustworthy
                servants of their Master. We seek for<lb/> their equal, but meet the sluggard and
                the faithless.<lb/> Shall we then be condemned if the love we bear reli-<lb/>ions
                instruction incites us now to lament?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The pain we experienced at the loss which the lite-<lb/>rary world
                sustained by the death of a Jewish savant<lb/> in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, was
                scarcely abated when the melancholy<lb/> tidings arrived from
                    <placeName>France</placeName> that another among the<lb/> greatest had descended
                to the grave. <persName>Munk</persName> has not<lb/> long survived
                    <persName>Luzzatto</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Those two giants of intellect, who had very nigh<lb/> reached the
                highest point of human knowledge, were<lb/> cut off while yet vigorous. Those two
                mighty laborers<lb/> in the field of science ceased to dispense the delicious<lb/>
                fruits they had gathered. One was surprised by<lb/> death while diving into the
                depth of scriptural exe-<lb/>gesis and philology: the other while engaged (oh,<lb/>
                wondrous undertaking!) without sight, to collate<lb/> ancient manuscripts and set in
                order a library most<lb/> extensive and rare. For quenched was the light of<lb/>
                those eyes which had discovered treasures hidden in<lb/> obscurity. But how
                refulgent that mind, whose<lb/> working enriched the world with volumes
                historically<lb/> and philosophically profound! <persName>Munk</persName>, like
                    <persName>Luzzatto</persName>,<lb/> continued, without rest, to pour out new
                ideas, that<lb/> others might slake their thirst at the fountain of his<lb/> wisdom.
                But at the bidding of the Most High the<lb/> gushing stream dried, and we have not
                since beheld<lb/> another flow so copiously.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But the prediction of <persName>Ezekiel</persName> seems to have
                been al-<lb/>most literally verified in us for "a sad report follows<lb/> the other
                hastily," to tell us that "the law hath ceased<lb/> to be imparted by a priest."
                Yes, that descendant and<lb/> true disciple of <persName>Aaron</persName>, who
                ministered to one congre-<lb/>gation in <placeName>Northern Europe</placeName>, but
                taught ever son of<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> who loves the language, the literature, and the<lb/>
                religion of his people, has also recently departed from<lb/> earth. He has joined
                the two illustrious beings that<lb/> had but shortly preceded him to the dwelling of
                joy.<lb/> But we—what have we not lost on the day that
                    <persName>Rap-<lb/>paport</persName> was seated among the blessed? Him we
                could<lb/> ask, and his lips would impart sublime knowledge.<lb/> For "the law of
                truth was in his month;" "he walked<lb/> with God in equity and peace," "and did
                turn many<lb/> away from sin. Aye, an angel of the Lord of Hosts<lb/> was he."</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Rappaport</persName> was my ideal of a Rabbi.
                Exceedingly<lb/> learned, yet exceedingly meek. Rigidly attached to the<lb/>
                traditions of the fathers, but willing to concede when<lb/> by yielding nothing
                sacred was surrendered. And him<lb/> I would fain have consulted, if the ritual of
                the Syna-<lb/>gogue, so variously and erroneously represented in<lb/> this country,
                can ever be unalterably fixed by a syno-<lb/>dical convention. Alas! He also has
                gone hence,<lb/> and the noblest monument of his extraordinary talent<lb/> remains
                incomplete. His Encyclopaedia of the Tal-<lb/>mud, and of collateral works, forming
                in itself a<lb/> world of learning, may, perhaps be suffered to molder<lb/> away as
                a writing of no value.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For this we may reasonably lament, O, brethren<lb/> and friends! For
                the publication of that inestimable<lb/> work would clear many doubts, elucidate
                many ob-<lb/>scure questions, while adding another jewel to the<lb/> grown of the
                law.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But who would have believed that the hand which<lb/> two months ago
                recorded the demise of the sage at<lb/>
                <placeName>Prague</placeName>, would be also palsied in death?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Rest thy aching heart on the bosom of eternity,<lb/> thou so long
                racked by deep and earnest thoughts!<lb/> Thou didst thy work well, and thine alone
                is the<lb/> merit, for there was none to help or counsel.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is even so, my beloved hearers. When <persName>Isaac<lb/>
                    Leeser</persName> went forth, armed with firey zeal, to fight the<lb/> battles
                of the Lord, he stood alone. A host might have<lb/> then been arrayed against
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, but not one was<lb/> found in our camp able to
                cope with the foe. A youth<lb/> arose to the defense of his religion and his
                people.<lb/> Was the name of the Jew aspersed? His vigorous pen<lb/> wrote the words
                which put the offender to the blush.<lb/> Were the truths of
                    <placeName>Sinai</placeName> impugned? He strove to<lb/> confound the
                unbeliever. On the pulpit; in the press;<lb/> at social gatherings, he stood as the
                bright exponent<lb/> of principles which he never forsook, though he bore<lb/> for
                their sake the jeers of the scoffer and the con-<lb/>tumely of the skeptic.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Gifted with versatility of mind, endowed with<lb/> the powers of an
                endurance that few can equal;<lb/> formed by nature with faculties extraordinarily
                reten-<lb/>tive, he could accomplish, unaided, more than others<lb/> with efficient
                supports. For, despite his clerical<lb/> duties, necessarily various and onerous in
                a large con-<lb/>gregation, the works he produced have been multi-<lb/>farious, and
                extensive. Shall I enumerate them? My<lb/> friends, there is scarcely a religious
                book of note in<lb/> the <placeName>United States of America</placeName> that does
                not bear on its<lb/> title page the name of <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The prayers you offer to God, have, by his industry,<lb/> been
                translated into the vernacular, and elegantly<lb/> printed. The Bible you read, for
                instruction and<lb/> spiritual comfort, has, by his toil, been freed from<lb/>
                biased interpretations, and rendered more compre-<lb/>hensible. The volume in which
                your children learn<lb/> the rudiments of Hebrew knowledge; those which in-<lb/>form
                them of the character and dogmas of their reli-<lb/>gion, and others which unfold
                before their eyes the<lb/> wisdom of the ancients, are the fruits of his
                unwearied<lb/> perseverance; "for an education" was the motto in-<lb/>scribed on the
                banner he first unfolded in this new<lb/> world, and increasingly upheld. He had
                discovered<lb/> that that was the most efficacious means to awaken<lb/> his brethren
                to a sense of their religious duties, and<lb/> he resorted thereto, as evinced by
                his personal and<lb/> literary exertions.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Has he been successful? Most assuredly so. Not<lb/> to the extent of
                his desires, nor commensurately with<lb/> his labor; nevertheless to a high degree.
                I, myself,<lb/> though comparatively a new comer, can bear testi-<lb/>mony to the
                step in advance made in our midst by our<lb/> coreligionists. Will any one deny that
                our lamented<lb/> brother gave the first impetus? No. Others may have<lb/> done
                nobly, but <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName> was the pioneer that<lb/> cleared away
                all obstructions.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This fact, which ought to be incontestably admit-<lb/>ted, was lost
                sight of by men who are, or profess to<lb/> be, his superiors. Hence the bitter
                sarcasm which<lb/> assailed him, and aggravated his natural irascibility,<lb/>
                conscious of having worked indefatigably, he was<lb/> both pained and angered, when
                belittled by ungene-<lb/>rous minds. That he had not explored the depth of<lb/>
                Talmudical science; that his acquaintance with our<lb/> casuistical writers and the
                Hebrew literature of the<lb/> day was limited; ought to have been overlooked by<lb/>
                reason of the ardor with which he espoused the cause<lb/> of education, for that is
                the great debt which <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> owes <persName>Isaac
                    Leeser</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Contrasted with a <persName>Luzzatto</persName>, he might have
                been<lb/> merely a tyro. <persName>Munk</persName> exceeded him by fact and he<lb/>
                would, for certain, have profited by sitting at the feet<lb/> of the great
                    <persName>Rappaport</persName>. Yet, he labored even more<lb/> beneficially than
                those three universally renowned<lb/> scholars. For they sought to lead further the
                already<lb/> tutored; he sought to be a guide for the untutored.<lb/> They
                endeavored to enlarge and beautify the temple<lb/> of knowledge; he strove to lay
                its foundations, that it<lb/> might be set up. Few, very few are the
                individuals<lb/> who, in this country, can duly appreciate the masterly<lb/>
                productions of those European literati; but <persName>Leeser's</persName><lb/>
                writings can be read round every fireside advanta-<lb/>geously, both to the young
                and to the old. Therefore<lb/> ought his memory to be revered and eternized.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As to myself, I have performed only an act of jus-<lb/>tice. Called
                upon to officiate at the funeral of one<lb/> with whom I have been associated in the
                discharge<lb/> of educational and ministerial functions, I would have<lb/>
                pronounced on that mournful occasion, the eulogy he<lb/> well merited. But I was
                precluded by the expressed<lb/> wish of the deceased. Simplicity of manners had<lb/>
                been his characteristic through life, and he exempli-<lb/>fied it in the hour of
                death. He ordered that the ritual<lb/> service as recited at the burial of the
                humblest Is-<lb/>raelite should alone be heard when he was about to<lb/> be
                consigned to mother earth, and none dared con-<lb/>travene the injunction. But the
                Ecclesiastical Board,<lb/> of which I have the honor to be a member, resolved<lb/>
                that a public expression of sorrow at the demise of<lb/> our colleague, was highly
                due to his virtues and deeds;<lb/> and I full assented.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My friends! I utter what I profoundly feel when I<lb/> say that no
                man of <placeName>Israel</placeName> has yet found a grave in this<lb/> country of
                our adoption, who deserves to be enshrined</p>
            <p>* Literally the Hebrew verb stands in the future tense.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
