<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
				<editor/>
				<sponsor/>
				<funder/>
				<principal/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
				item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note/>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution/>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
							Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP_New_7</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head/>
					<letHeading>
						<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
						<addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
						<deliverer/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Boston, MA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1848-01">January 11, 1848</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author/>
							<editor/>
							<respStmt>
								<resp/>
								<name/>
							</respStmt>
							<title/>
							<decoNote/>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl/>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation/>
							<textLang/>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_7_1.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_7_2.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
										>miscellany</material>letter </support>
								<extent>2 pages on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
								</extent>
								<foliation/>
								<collation/>
								<condition fragment="false"/>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout/>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote/>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote/>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote/>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p/>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat/>
						<envDesc occ="false"/>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin/>
						<provenance/>
						<acquisition/>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source/>
								<change/>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent/>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates/>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl/>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p/>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p/>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p/>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p/>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p/>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p/>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p/>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p/>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition/>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc/>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc/>
					<label/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation/>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item/>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""/>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p>own means its own purposes. For I would ask<lb/> where it is that those who use this
				argument would<lb/> draw the line? I have told you that in
					<placeName>France</placeName> they<lb/> hold all offices to which Frenchmen are
				admitted,<lb/> and that more than one member of the Chambers<lb/> has been of the
				Jewish persuasion. Even in this<lb/> country we have much relaxed the rigor of our
				en-<lb/>actments respecting them. A Jew has been a ma-<lb/>gistrate, a Jew has been
				a sheriff. By a late statute,<lb/> which was introduced by the right hon. member for<lb/>
				<placeName>Tamworth</placeName>, Jews may hold offices in corporations,<lb/> and it
				was but the other day that a Jew was admit-<lb/>ted to the office of alderman in the
				corporation of the<lb/> city of <placeName>London</placeName>. (Hear, hear.) I ask
				you what<lb/> right or business have you to interpret a prophecy so<lb/> as to draw
				the line between an alderman and a com-<lb/>missioner of customs—between a justice
				of the peace<lb/> and a person having a right to sit in Parliament?<lb/> (Hear,
				hear.) What enabled you or authorized you<lb/> to say where the line intended by the
				prophecies<lb/> should be drawn, and how can you take upon your-<lb/>selves to draw
				the limits of the line the Almighty<lb/> intended to mark out? (Cheers.) It would
				be, in<lb/> respect to the Almighty being, to</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">
				<quote>"Strike from his hand the balance and the rod,</quote>
			</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">
				<quote>"Rejudge his justice—be the God of God."</quote>
			</p>
			<p>I trust that no such presumption will fail to our lot—<lb/> that we shall do that
				which we think our duty to our<lb/> fellow countrymen, and the best for the country
				ac-<lb/>cording to our imperfect reason, and rest in pious<lb/> but humble
				confidence that the Almighty will accom-<lb/>plish his purpose by means best known
				to his wis-<lb/>dom. (Cheers.) But, Sir, there is that which I can<lb/> hardly call
				an argument, but which operates more<lb/> against those whose cause I have
				undertaken perhaps<lb/> than any other thing. There is a popular prejudice<lb/>
				against the name of the Jew founded upon various<lb/> circumstances to which I need
				not allude—founded<lb/> upon what I think a mistaken view of Sacred Writ,<lb/> and
				the dislike and distrust there is on the part of<lb/> men of a different religion.
				But that popular preju-<lb/>dice which induced the Administration of
					<date>1753</date>, after<lb/> passing an act for the naturalization of the Jews,
				to<lb/> come down in a hurry, in the next year, for the pur-<lb/>pose of repealing
				it, has, I believe, very greatly died<lb/> away (hear, hear,)—that it has subsided
				in this me-<lb/>tropolis I have with my own eyes a proof, because a<lb/> gentleman
				in the city of <placeName>London</placeName>, well known in that<lb/> city by his
				extensive transactions, by his wealth, his<lb/> charity and liberality, was elected
				for that city by<lb/> nearly 7,000 votes at the last general election.<lb/> (Hear,
				hear.) I quote that as a proof that this<lb/> house would not be safe in
				saying—"Such is our<lb/> opinion; we are liberal; we intend well to our Jew-<lb/>ish
				fellow-subjects, but there is such a prejudice<lb/> amongst the people against them
				that it would not<lb/> be safe to legislate in their favor" (Hear, hear.)—<lb/> I
				warn hon. gentlemen not to rely upon that feeling,<lb/> I believe that the people
				are to the full as enlight-<lb/>ened as the members of this house. (Hear.) I
				be-<lb/>lieve that the general opinion, and the right and true<lb/> opinion, as I
				conceive it to be, is that religious opin-<lb/>ions ought not to bring with them any
				penalty or<lb/> punishment. (Hear, hear.) I believe that that is<lb/> the right and
				true opinion, overbearing any preju-<lb/>dice that may have existed against the
				Jews. (Hear,<lb/> hear.) I have now, sir, stated to you the reasons<lb/> why I think
				that the objections which have been<lb/> made against the admission of the Jews are
				futile<lb/> and unfounded. If I am asked what are the prevail-<lb/>ing reasons for
				the motion that I propose, I appeal in<lb/> the first place to the constitution of
				these realms; I<lb/> appeal to that constitution which is intended to give<lb/> to
				every man those rewards, that honor, that estima-<lb/>tion to which his character
				and talents may entitle<lb/> him. (Hear, hear.) I appeal to that constitution<lb/>
				which is the enemy of restriction or disqualification<lb/> (hear); to that
				constitution which by the abrogation<lb/> of the laws existing a few years ago has
				put an end<lb/> even to those cases of exception which our ancestors<lb/> thought,
				upon the ground of imminent danger to the<lb/> state and church, they were justified
				in imposing. I<lb/> ask you in the name of that constitution to take<lb/> away this
				last remnant of religious persecution,<lb/> to show that you are not influenced by
				the num-<lb/>bers or terrors that might make that which was an<lb/> act of political
				justice an act of political necessity.<lb/> (Cheers.) I ask you in the name of that
				constitution<lb/> to admit the Jews to all the privileges, to all the rights,<lb/>
				of which those who are not excluded from them are<lb/> so justly proud (cheers);
				and, let me tell you,<lb/> that you cannot judge of the feelings of those who<lb/>
				are excluded by the number of those who might wish<lb/> for seats in Parliament, or
				who might aspire to hold<lb/> office under the Crown. Many a man who would<lb/> not
				seek for either, would be content to pass his days<lb/> in obscurity, and would wish
				for no other advanta-<lb/>ges than those of private life; but he feels the
				galling<lb/> degradation, the brand that is imposed upon him, when<lb/> he is told
				that men of all other classes, men of the es-<lb/>tablished church, Protestant
				Dissenters and Roman<lb/> Catholics, may all enter within these walls, may all<lb/>
				enjoy those advantages, but that he belongs to a sect<lb/> which by the law and
				constitution is proscribed and<lb/> degraded. (Cheers.) But I would make a
				still<lb/> higher appeal. I would make an appeal to the prin-<lb/>ciples of that
				Christianity which has so long been<lb/> the law of the land. (Cheers.) I appeal to
				you,<lb/> then, in the name of that religion which is a religion<lb/> of charity and
				love, "to do unto others as you would<lb/> they should do unto you." (Cheers.) I ask
				you<lb/> why it is, that when we are taught by examples and<lb/> parables that we
				ought to love our neighbors, it is<lb/> not priests or Levites who are singled out
				as instan-<lb/>ces for our approbation and admiration; but it is one<lb/> of a
				proscribed sect—one who belonged to what was<lb/> then the refuge of all nations? I
				ask why it is that we<lb/> are taught that all men are brothers—that there is
				no<lb/> part of the human race, however divided from us by<lb/> feelings or color,
				that ought to be separated from us?<lb/> but that all belong to the family of man,
				and ought<lb/> to be loved as brothers. (Cheers.) I ask you,<lb/> therefore, in the
				name of that constitution which is<lb/> the constitution of freedom, of liberty, and
				of justice<lb/>—I ask you in the name of that religion which is<lb/> the religion of
				peace and good will towards men—to<lb/> agree to the motion which I have the honor
				to make.<lb/> The noble lord then moved "that the house should<lb/> resolve itself
				into a committee on the removal of the<lb/> civil and political disabilities
				affecting Her Majesty's<lb/> Jewish subjects," and resumed his seat amidst loud<lb/>
				and continued cheers.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">A debate ensued in which several members took<lb/> part, and it was
				adjourned over to the following day.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>SIR ROBERT INGLIS</persName>, in reply to <persName>Lord
					John<lb/> Russell</persName> said that the question was not one between<lb/>
				Christians and Jews, but between Christians and<lb/> non-Christians. Now,
					<placeName>England</placeName> for years past had<lb/> not only had a
				constitution, but also a Christian con-<lb/>stitution, and he defied <persName>Lord
					J. Russell</persName> to produce a<lb/> single instance in which the oath of
				office had not<lb/> always been taken upon some Christian symbol. It<lb/> might be
				true that <persName>David Hume</persName> and <persName>Edward
				Gibbon</persName><lb/> as infidels would not have scrupled to take at the<lb/> table
				the declaration now required by law; but was<lb/> that a sufficient argument for
				blotting out of our stat-<lb/>ute book a solemn declaration that our first duty
				as<lb/> legislators was to discharge our duties as Christian<lb/> men? A Jew could
				not listen to our form of pray-<lb/>er, in which we called upon
					<persName>Christ</persName> to have mercy<lb/> upon us, without either
				committing an awful blas-<lb/>phemy, or going through a deliberate mockery of<lb/>
				religion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">He would not withhold these concessions from the<lb/> Jews on
				account of the smallness of their numbers<lb/> if he could believe them just; but as
				he did not<lb/> think them so, he thought he had a right to ask<lb/> whether it was
				either right or expedient to make<lb/> them to 20,000 or 30,000 or 40,000 persons at
				the<lb/> risk of exasperating 3,000,000 or 4,000,000. He<lb/> had called the last
				bill introduced on this subject a<lb/> bill to enable <persName>Mr.
					Solamons</persName> to become an alderman<lb/> of <placeName>London</placeName>,
				and he called this bill a bill to enable the<lb/>
				<persName>Baron L. de Rothschild</persName> to become a member of Par-<lb/>liament.
				He then proceeded to show that the Jews<lb/> were a separate nation, with a separate
				creed, and<lb/> for that purpose read a letter from a Jewish rabbi,</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p>and an extract from the speech of <persName>John Duke</persName> of<lb/>
				<placeName>Bedford</placeName> against the Jew Bill of <date>1753</date>. He
				called<lb/> upon the House by every consideration of interest<lb/> and duty to pause
				before it changed the Christian<lb/> constitution of the Legislature, and before it
				haz-<lb/>arded the confidence of the people in the Christian<lb/> institutions of
				the empire.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Lord ASHLEY</persName> also opposed the motion. He
				con-<lb/>tended that religion had a great deal to do with poli-<lb/>tics—that the
				House knew that fact—and that it<lb/> proved it by every one of its daily actions.
					<persName>Mr.<lb/> Macaulay</persName> in an elaborate essay had declared
				that<lb/> Government by its <sic>essantial</sic> character was interdict-<lb/>ed
				from contemplating and accomplishing Christian<lb/> ends; but he well recollected
				that that distinguished<lb/> writer had in another speech declared that
				"every-<lb/>thing which lowered Christianity in <sic>pablic</sic> estima-<lb/>tion
				was high treason against the civilization of man-<lb/>kind." He then controverted
					<persName>Mr. Macaulay's</persName> doc-<lb/>trine, that to talk of Christian
				government was as<lb/> absurd as to talk of Christian cookery or of Christian<lb/>
				cobblery, and passed a heavy censure upon him for<lb/> having confounded for the
				sake of witticism the<lb/> lowest operations of the mind with the operation of<lb/>
				the highest influences of the soul. It was true that<lb/>
				<persName>Gibbon</persName> and <persName>Hume</persName> might as infidels have sat
				in that<lb/> House; but they could only have done so by pro-<lb/>fessing that in
				their opinion Christianity was part<lb/> and parcel of the law of the land.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The House was now called upon to break down<lb/> all the barriers
				which prevented the Jews from sit-<lb/>ting in Parliament. No advantage would be
				gained<lb/> by such an enactment—no compensation would be af-<lb/>forded for the
				great shock which it would occasion to<lb/> thousands of honest and conscientious Christians.<lb/>
				<persName>Lord John Russell</persName> rested his case upon justice.<lb/>
				<persName>Dr. Arnold</persName>—whose words he quoted—denied that<lb/> the Jews had
				any claim to emancipation on that<lb/> ground, and his Lordship had not ventured to
				say a<lb/> word in refutation of that denial. The present was<lb/> altogether a
				question of principle—it was a legisla-<lb/>tive declaration that for all the
				purposes of public<lb/> government, of making laws, and of administering<lb/> public
				affairs, Christianity was altogether needless.<lb/> To such a doctrine he could not
				assent even for a<lb/> single hour. If the Jews had been already in
				Parli-<lb/>ament, he would not have proposed to turn them out,<lb/> but it was a
				widely different question to propose to<lb/> bring them in and to repeal for their
				introduction an<lb/> oath which was a declaration of Christianity on the<lb/> part
				of the Legislature. In saying this, he disclaimed<lb/> any antipathy to the Jews,
				and gave a glowing des-<lb/>cription of the knowledge, intelligence,
				literature,<lb/> and perseverance of the Jews of the present age,<lb/> both in this
				country and other countries of <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
