<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.; Kursheedt,
                    Gershom</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0053</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.;
                            Kursheedt, Gershom</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1850-10">October 1, 1850</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1850-10">5611</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0053_1R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0053_1V.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0053_2R.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0053_2V.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">Abstract of contract between H.C. D. Judah</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">and <persName role="author">M. N. Nathan</persName></p>
            <p>The said Congn. engaged to pay <persName role="author">M. N. N.</persName> $2500 P
                annum during<lb/> the term of his ability to perform the services required of him so
                long<lb/> as his behaviour shall not be regarded and considered as unbecoming<lb/> a
                minister of the Jewish Congregation. Salary to be paid <add>in</add> monthly<lb/>
                <sic>instalments</sic> if desired.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In consideration of such salary <persName role="author">M. N.
                    N.</persName> shall perform<lb/> the regular services in the Synagogue as Hazan
                or Reader<lb/> according to the customs of the Spanish &amp; Portuguese Jews,
                commonly<lb/> called “Minhag Sephardim.” as well as those duties usually<lb/>
                performed out of Synagogue, and devolving customarily on Jewish<lb/> ministers; and
                it shall further be obligatory on <persName role="author">M. N. N.</persName><lb/>
                to deliver a sermon, discourse, or lecture in the English language<lb/> Every
                    <date>Sabbath</date>, and the first day of every Jewish Festival or<lb/> Holy
                day, as well as on all occasions of General rejoicing<lb/> or Humiliation prescribed
                by the civil authorities of the land.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is also agreed that the said <persName role="author">Mr. N.
                    N.</persName> shall<lb/> perform no religious service or religious ceremony out
                of the<lb/> Synagogue for any member of this above named Synagogue, or for<lb/> any
                other person without the written order of its presiding officer.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is further understood that this contract is entered<lb/> into
                under the present existing constitution Laws and Regulations<lb/> of the said Hebrew
                Congregation “Dispd. of Judah.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This contract, signed in Duplicate/shall<lb/>' commence from this
                first day of <date>Feby 1850. 5610</date>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">Signed <persName role="author">M. N. Nathan</persName></p>
            <p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">G. Kursheedt</persName> Preside.</p>
            <p>Memoradum</p>
            <p>This contract was entered into in accordance with resolution of Congregation<lb/> of
                    <date>Jany. 24Th 1850</date>. specifying “that <hi rend="underline">after</hi>
                <persName>Judah Louis Esq.</persName> Shall sign the act<lb/> of donation of the
                Synagogue, the Presidt. shall contract with <persName role="author">Revd. M. N.
                    N.</persName><lb/> “for his services as Hazan &amp; Preacher to their
                congregation during the term of his<lb/> “good behavior and ability (temporary
                sickness not to interfere) to perform<lb/> “the services generally conducted by
                persons occupying the like positions”<lb/> “the minister to be bound to give six
                months notice in writing of his intention<lb/> to resign his office.” And be it
                further enacted “That any member</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>of this Congn. making any charge or charges against the minister<lb/> shall do so in
                writing, and shall present the same to the board<lb/> of officers, who shall if they
                deem it necessary convene the body<lb/> at large stating the object of the meeting,
                and notify the minister<lb/> to attend to defend himself; a vote of <hi
                    rend="underline">three fourths</hi> of the justified<lb/> members present shall
                have power to suspend or remove him from<lb/> office <persName>Isaac
                    Soria</persName></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Secy.</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                <date>Octr. 1St 5611 <add>1850</add></date>
            </p>
            <p>My dear <addressee>Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Herewith you have copy of my contract with<lb/> the congregation.
                You know me too well to suppose that I would have<lb/> accepted any engagement under
                the the dictatorial order of “sign or<lb/> resign.” Nor would our mutual friend
                    <persName role="author">Gershom Kursheedt</persName> have<lb/> allowed himself
                to be the medium of such a communication.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">The provision relative to the preaching was my own act.<lb/> In the
                contract drawn up by <persName role="author">G. K.</persName> I was to preach
                whenever the Presidt.<lb/> called on me to do so. However safe I might have been
                with the article<lb/> so worded with <persName role="author">G. K.</persName> as
                Presidt., it might have been made a vehicle<lb/> of annoyance under a Presidt.
                    inimical<add>?</add> to me, and therefore rejected<lb/> it. The last resolution
                of the Congregation is fair and reasonable<lb/> and prevents the body from
                condemning me whereas; its silence on<lb/> the subject of fire<add>?</add> is also
                in my favor. I must either be acquitted<lb/> or removed; there is no middle course.
                Another point is also liable<lb/> to remarking—viz—that I must be a party consulted
                should any alterations<lb/> in the present existing Laws and Regulations be entered
                upon, affecting<lb/> me personally. I am protected under any emergency.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The universal feeling of indignation pervades the Jews,<lb/> in this
                city at the shameful treatment of your late congregation towards<lb/> you. My advice
                to you is do not embark in a weekly paper. It will<lb/> not pay. Go into business,
                if not at the <placeName>north</placeName>-at the <placeName>South</placeName>. Doff
                the gown<lb/> which you have honored for twenty years. It will reflect no disgrace on<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">you</hi> to engage in business. Either as Revd. or plain Mr.
                you can serve your people.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Our Holy days went off harmoniously, as tho' we had been
                established<lb/> for a quarter of a century.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">All your friends including <persName>Mrs. N.</persName> and myself
                wish you<lb/> success and prosperity, health and happiness in whatever you
                undertake</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">Your's affectionately</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">
                <persName role="author">M. N. Nathan</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                <date>Oct 1. 5611<add>1850</add></date>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My most worthy friend will excuse the lack of<lb/> my usual
                punctuality in replying to his last<lb/> recd. form, when I state that the frequent<lb/>
                <sic>occurence</sic> of Holidays have kept me very<lb/> much occupied during the
                remainder of the<lb/> time. I hope what is set forth on the<lb/> annexed page (all
                which I endorse) will<lb/> satisfy you and your friends that certain<lb/>
                expressions have been attributed to me which<lb/> I never uttered. The Constitution
                &amp; By Laws<lb/> of the Congregation are there I exhibited to you<lb/> when in
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, although they are<lb/> now about to be
                altered. You will recollect<lb/> that in our laws there is no mention made<lb/> of a
                Hazan, wherefore the resolution of the<lb/> congregation given on the
                    <sic>preceeding</sic> page<lb/> was necessary to enable me to enter into<lb/>
                contract with <persName role="author">Mr. Nathan</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The <sic>comse</sic> purused toward you by a<lb/> portion of your
                congregation meets with<lb/> the universal censure of our people here<lb/> and to my
                certain knowledge it is severely<lb/> commented upon in many parts of the<lb/>
                Union. Never mind friend <persName>Leeser</persName> your<lb/> good acts will
                outlive the memory of your<lb/> persecutors. It is the fate of the good to<lb/> have
                enemies. <persName>King David</persName> had many, none<lb/> but the insignificant
                move through the world<lb/> undisturbed. I hope always to have some<lb/> unfriendly
                acquaintances, they do us good.<lb/> There are men who delight in bringing
                their<lb/> superior down to their own level, but they<lb/> rarely succeed. I could
                write volumes on this subject<lb/> but it is not necessary, you know the sentiments
                of your friend</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <persName role="author">Gershom K.</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <addressee>Revd Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
