<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0040</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Kingston, Jamaica</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1863-07" source="" attested="yes">July 5, 1863</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_1R.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_1V.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_2R.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_2V.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_3R.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0040_3V.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 3 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Kingston&#44; Jamaica</placeName> <date>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July 1863</date></p>
				<p>My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Your various letters received here between the <date>20th<lb/> April</date> last and <date>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date> did not meet my sight until the latter date&#44;<lb/> on my return from a voyage to <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName> during those<lb/> 6 weeks.  My tour was ostensibly to see my brother off.  We had not set<lb/> eyes on one another  for 14<add>&#63;</add> years&#44; during which time he had got married&#44;<lb/> but his wife&#44; like mine&#44; is <add>Hebrew</add>.  Prior to my departure&#44; the Congregational ruler<lb/> of <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> had invited me to permit them to put forth my name as a candidate<lb/> fro the vacant situation of minister&#44; which I prudently declined&#59; as is the<lb/> event of the Congregation&#39;s refusal to elect me&#44; my position here would have<lb/> been injured.  On my arrival at <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>&#44; the rulers invited me to meet<lb/> them&#44; and&#44; after that interview took action.  <del>After</del> I sailed &#40;3 days after&#41; <add>the interview</add> for<lb/> <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>.  A meeting of the voting members was called <add>in my absence</add> and two propositions<lb/> were submitted for their decision.  The first&#44; to raise the salary from &#36;1200&#44; the amount of stipend advertised&#44; to &#36;1800&#59; which was carried&#44; 10 only dissenting&#44;<lb/> and they&#44; only on the plea that the congregation could not afford the larger<lb/> sum.  The second&#44; to elect a minister.  The President proposed me&#44; adding<lb/> that he had not my permission&#44; but hoping that the expression of the<lb/> member&#44; in my favour&#44; might induce me to accept.  The proposition was<lb/> carried without a <hi rend="underline">dissenting voice</hi>.  The second day after my arrival&#44; a<lb/> deputation waited upon me with a numerously and respectably signed<lb/> address&#44; inviting me to stay a fortnight longer&#44; before going to <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>.  I was<lb/> obliged to decline&#44; but&#44; to soften the refusal&#44; read and preached <del>for</del> in the<lb/> Synagogue on <date>Friday night the 1st May</date>.  The next morning I embarked<lb/> on my return from <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName> in the <date>20th May</date>&#44; I stayed at <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written in the top right."> 20&#45;666&#44; 1 of 2</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>till the <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> June</date>&#59; and on <add>Hebrew</add> read <add>Hebrew</add> and preached again.<lb/> Each time the Synagogue was filled.  My reception in both places was<lb/> gratifying in the extreme.  Now about <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>.  <add>&#63;</add><lb/> is a generous&#44; charitable man&#44; of  large proportions and with a<lb/> larger heart.  In five minutes we understood each other perfectly.  We had<lb/> many discussions on various Jewish subjects&#44; Scriptural&#44; Rabbinical&#44;<lb/> Synagogal&#44; raised&#44; I suppose&#44; for the purpose of drawing me out.<lb/> Books were introduced&#44; and many a hard passage in <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> was submitted for my opinion.  Whether I acquitted myself will or ill&#44; I cannot<lb/> say&#59; but I am sure you will be pleased to hear that the Chactaeu<add>&#63;</add>&#44; when he<lb/> came to accompany me to the vessel&#44; presented me with a <add>Hebrew</add> in<lb/> Hebrew &#38; English&#44; conferring on me the rank and title of <add>Hebrew</add> and&#44;<lb/> calling upon all congregations to acknowledge and receive me as such.<lb/>  I suppose you know his title is <hi rend="underline">Opper Rattiner</hi><add>&#63;</add>&#44; or Chief Rabbi.  He<lb/> teaches extemporaneously&#44; much in the style of <persName>Plessner</persName>&#44; illustrating his<lb/> discourse copiously from midrash.  He asked me to give him a test one<lb/> <date>Sabbath</date> just before the sermon was to be delivered&#44; and I selected Prov. XVIII.I.<lb/> on which he discoursed for about 30 minutes&#44; in Dutch.  I was told by good<lb/> judges it was an able exposition&#44; but&#44; tho&#39; I understood parts here and there&#44;<lb/> I cannot say anything about it.  Sometimes he preaches in Portuguese.  His<lb/> performance of the marriage ceremony&#44; I also witnessed.  It was very<lb/> impressive.  He always addresses the young couple before the ceremony&#59; and<lb/> besides&#44; has interviews with both in <hi rend="underline">private before</hi> the union&#44; at which I<lb/> understand he talks very seriously to them about their duties as husband<lb/> and wife&#44; and also to God and <placeName>Israel</placeName>.  His charities are disputed akin<lb/> to  Jew &#38; Christian.  During the epidemic of small pox last year&#44; when the other<lb/> clergy fled for their lives&#44; he was at the bedsides of white&#44; Black colored&#44; administering medicines&#44; pecuniary relief &#40;in which the government gave</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>him carte blanche to draw&#41; spiritual consolation&#44; offering up prayer at the<lb/> instance of Christian sufferers&#44; and helping occasionally with his own hands&#44;<lb/> to put the dear in their coffins.  He is highly respected by the Dutch Government.<lb/>  His stipend is paid by the state&#44; not by the Synagogue.  I did not preach at <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>&#44;<lb/> for the following reason.  A requisition&#44; respectably signed was sent to the Mahamad&#44;<lb/> that I should preach.  The mahamad sent for the Chacham<add>&#63;</add>&#44; and asked him if he had<lb/> any objection to me.  On his answering&#44; none&#44; they told him that his pulpit would be<lb/> occupied by me the following <date>Sabbath</date>.  To this&#44; he replies&#44; he would not object&#44;<lb/> provided the mahamad asked his permission to have the pulpit so occupied.  This<lb/> they refused to do&#44; but sent me an intimation by letter that they would be happy<lb/> if I would comply with the request of the Congregation.  Having been informed<lb/> of what had taken place&#44; I declined&#44; in my reply&#44; to give an affirmative answer&#44;<lb/> as the letter from the mahamad did not state expressly that the Chacham&#39;s<add>&#63;</add>&#44;<lb/> permission to occupy his pulpit had been obtained&#59; but on <add>receiving</add> their assurance<lb/> that he had sanctioned it&#44; I would be happy to comply with their request.<lb/>  This led to another communication implying that I wished to dictate to them&#44;<lb/> and informing me that the matter was at an end.  Tho this I answered&#44; disclaiming<lb/> most solemnly any intention of dictating to them the line of conduct <hi rend="underline">they</hi> should<lb/> pursue&#44; but adding that the line of conduct <hi rend="underline">I</hi> had to pursue&#44; agreeably to the<lb/> rules of good breeding and social etiquette which <del> <add>&#63;</add> every</del> obtained wherever<lb/> civilization and refinement existed&#44; was not to occupy any pulpit until<lb/> I received the permission of the party to whom it rightfully belonged.  In<lb/> a postscript&#44; I said that being a stranger they would pardon me for declining any<lb/> further correspondence on the subject.  There is a board called the <hi rend="underline">Conseijo deo<lb/> Anciannos</hi>&#44; consisting of past Presidents&#44; which acts as a court of Review <add>of</add>&#44;<lb/> or appeal from&#44; the acts of the mahamad.  To this board&#44; the proceedings in the<lb/> matter were submitted a few days after&#44; and out of 15 members present&#44; 14<lb/> decided that the pulpit could at no time be occupied without the previous</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>consent and permission of the chacham.  The dissentient<add>&#63;</add> was the brother<lb/> of the President.  To the chacham&#39;s honor I must state that he waited<lb/> personally on 7 or 8 of the most influential and wealthy of these A<add>&#63;</add><lb/> and&#44; knowing the resentment they felt at the indignity put upon him by the<lb/> mahamad&#44; as well as apprehending violence in the debate&#44; exacted from them<lb/> a solemn pledge that they would keep away from the sitting&#44; otherwise their<lb/> number would have swelled the notes condemnatory of the mahamad.  This<lb/> question had been long pending&#44; but not opportunity was afforded for settling it<lb/> before.  The chacham&#39;s assertion that the pulpit belonged to him and my<lb/> firm support of his rights have now set the matter at rest&#44; and strengthened<lb/> his position against the attempted encroachment of the mahamad.  During<lb/> the progress of the discussion&#44; I kept at home convinced that&#44; in the influenced<lb/> passions of the Congregation against the mahamad&#44; the latter would have been<lb/> bodily ejected from their seats in Synagogue&#44; if I had gone up and down<lb/> and proved the impropriety of their action.  I send you these particulars<lb/> in the event of your hearing any thing <del>about it</del> from the other side.  The <persName>Revd.<lb/> Mr. <hi rend="underline">Santcroos</hi></persName> is the first <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; he is the son&#45;in&#45;law of the chacham&#44; and gives<lb/> instruction in Hebrew &#38; Religion to the youth of the Congregation&#44; in the <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> a certain number of hours p day&#59; morning and evening.  He is a very able<lb/> man.  In his and his father&#45;in&#45;law&#39;s society&#44; I spent much of the 18 days I<lb/> was at <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>.  The wives of both are&#44; I think&#44; even more scrupulous than<lb/> the husbands.  They are very <hi rend="underline">pious and</hi> charitable women&#44; and their kindness<lb/> to orphan children most touching.  No shop or store is open among <sic>our</sic> on <date>Sabbath</date> or Holy day&#59; even the second days are strictly kept.<lb/> Their rejoicings&#44; as weddings&#44; circumcisions&#44; consecration of <sic>deadlings</sic><add>&#63;</add> are<lb/> indeed joyous&#44; whilst their mournings are sad and melancholy.  The abattons<lb/> or butcheries are out of the town&#44; and they have&#44; <add>if</add> I mistake not&#44; two Shoctim<lb/> and two Shomeim over whom&#44; as well as the butcher&#44; the Chacham keeps a<lb/> most watchful eye.  The Chazan&#44; the <persName>Revd. Mr. Cardozo</persName>&#44; altho&#39; 73 years of age<lb/> shows in his decline what he must have been in his prime.  He reads the<lb/> service and Parashah with fine musical intonation and accurately<lb/> grammatical pronunciation.  The Synagogue is a fine old building&#44;<lb/> but the centre is spoiled by the hugeness and massiveness of the pillars<lb/> which intercept the view and prevent the eye from taking in the <add>bold</add> proportions<lb/> of the interior at a glance.  The ladies&#39; galleries are latticed in true moorish<lb/> style.  It is useless <sic>too</sic> look up&#44; the eye of a lynx would fail to make out <del><add>&#63;</add></del><lb/> the features of any fair one seated there.  The Reading Desk and pulpit are<lb/> fine&#44; the Hechal out of all proportion with the height of the building&#44; and<lb/> the exterior of the building is <del>hideous</del> ugly&#59; the western front positively<lb/> hideous.  Divine service is performed twice a day&#44; morning and evening<lb/> the whole week through&#44; with always plenty of minyan.  In the <add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<pb n="3R"/>
				<p>3 times&#59; and in those weeks&#44; the chacham lectures generally every<lb/> other evening&#44; either from Scripture or from the mishna&#44; always extemporaneously<lb/> without a note before him.  <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName>&#44; in fine&#44; so far as practical Judaism&#44;<lb/> on old orthodox&#44; rabbinical principles&#44; is concerned&#44; is very considerably<lb/> ahead of our sister Congregations in the other <placeName>W. I. Islands</placeName>&#44; and need<lb/> not fear <hi rend="underline">any</hi> comparison as regards adherence to the ancient landmarks of our revered religion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am waiting momently for the arrival of the steamer<lb/> from <placeName>Europe</placeName>&#44; to receive the yea or nay to my ultimatum&#44;<lb/> from the <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> Congregation.  My terms are&#44; no specified<lb/> term of engagement&#44; salary as fixed by the congregation&#44; and<lb/> a pension&#44; if after 10 years I am unable&#44; or may be declared<lb/> incapable <del>of</del>&#44; mentally or physically&#44; of performing my duties.<lb/>  This pension&#44; modestly fixed at &#36;600 <add>&#63;</add> is the pons<lb/> asinorum betwixt us.  The good folks kick against it&#44; whilst<lb/> ready to pension off their hitherto acting Chazan <persName>Maduro</persName><lb/> tomorrow at &#36;400 <hi rend="underline">half</hi> his salary&#44; &#40;I only ask for a<lb/> third&#41; and also admitting that no man will suit them<lb/> so well as I&#44; combining as I do the capability of a<lb/> teacher&#44; whom they require so much&#44; with that of a chazan<lb/> and Preacher.  The Government had told them plainly that<lb/> if they do not take <add>&#63;</add> me one&#44; it will send them <del>one</del><add>a minister</add> from <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>&#44;<lb/> with whom the <del>Congregation</del> Government will make a contract<lb/> whether its provisions be palatable or not.  I have offered to<lb/> allow myself to be put on the same footing as other government<lb/> officers&#44; at the instance of the governor.  Today&#39;s mail</p>
				<p rend="The following is written in pencil at the bottom right.">20&#45;666 2 of 2</p>
			<pb n="3V"/>
				<p>will decide the point in dispute.  If against me&#44; I will&#44; at<lb/> once take up the letter from <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>&#44; which I have<lb/> answered today.  It only arrived on the <date>30th May</date>&#44; tho&#39; written<lb/> in <date>April</date>&#44; and I received it on the <date>5th June</date>&#44; the day I returned<lb/> home&#44; but too late for replying to <del>that</del> it by that months<lb/> mail.  I will not&#44; at present&#44; correspond with you on<lb/> the subject in deference to your wishes&#44; but I expect <persName>Mr.<lb/> A.</persName> will.  I have&#44; at all events&#44; opened up the subject<lb/> to him&#44; and communicated how I am at this moment<lb/> situated with the <placeName>St. Thos.</placeName> Cong.  It will be a trying<lb/> position for any man&#44; with such opponents as silent that<lb/> and wise.  Yet it is worth holding for that sake alone.<lb/> But what will principally deter me is the present<lb/> unsettled state of the country.  Were I to take it&#44; I<lb/> would not keep any school&#44; as I would have enough to <add>do</add> with men of giant intellect&#44; without being bothered<lb/> with teaching children.  I am afraid&#44; the mail will be closed<lb/> before the European steamer arrives&#44; and I will have to<lb/> wait for the next monthly American steamer&#44; as no <sic>dependance</sic>&#44; can be placed on sailing vessels.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I deeply sympathize with you on the death<lb/> of your old aunt <persName>Mrs. Rehine</persName>&#44; <add>Hebrew</add>.  The <persName>Revd. Mr. Myers</persName><lb/> is just at my elbow&#44; and begs me to say he will take an<lb/> early opportunity of writing you&#44; that he sent you some<lb/> newspapers&#44; and desires his kinds regards.  The same to<lb/> <persName>J.</persName>&#44; <persName>Mrs. N.</persName> and <persName>Mrs. S.</persName> and with apologies for not answering<lb/> your letters more fully&#44; which I will do next time&#44; and<lb/> also hoping that my long Meguillah may not</p>
				<p rend="The following is continued on the left side of the page.">tire your old eyes&#44; which I suppose like those of all<lb/> old Patriarchs <add>Hebrew</add> and deserving you are old<lb/> inquiring friend <add>&#63;</add></p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">I am</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)">Yours ever truly</p>
			<p rend="indent(11)"><persName role="author">M. Nathan</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
