<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP_New_13</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1868-02" source="" attested="yes">February 8 1868</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_13.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">print</material>
								</support>
								<extent>1 page on 1 sheet
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
				<p rend="align(center)"><hi rend="bold">IN MEMORIAM.</hi></p>
				<p rend="align(center)"><hi rend="bold">A Eulogy on the Late <persName>Rev. Isaac Leeser</persName>&#44; De&#45;<lb/>livered at the Synagogue&#44; <placeName>Seventh Street&#44;<lb/> Above Arch</placeName>&#44; on <date>Saturday&#44; February 8</date>&#44; by the<lb/> <persName role="author">Rev. S. Morais</persName>&#44; Minister of the Congregation.</hi></p>
				<p rend="indent(1)">What the pillar of cloud was to our fathers by day<lb/> and the pillar of fire by night&#44; are the wise and the<lb/> learned to us&#44; O fellow Israelites&#33;  We walk at the<lb/> light which their bright intellects emit.  Our progeni&#45;<lb/>tors&#44; wending their steps through trackless deserts&#44;<lb/> cast a look around&#44; and lo&#33; a guide from heaven led<lb/> them forth.  We&#44; the travelers of a road rough and<lb/> rugged&#44; see a beacon illumining our horizon.  At its<lb/> radiance we can always discover a safe issue.  Oh&#33;<lb/> how lurid would be the mist created by its absence.<lb/>  But <placeName>Israel</placeName> will never be enshrouded in darkness.  I<lb/> read it in the chronicles of truth&#44; &#34;<emph rend="italics">He will not take<lb/> away&#42;</emph> the pillar of cloud  by day nor the pillar of fire<lb/> by night from before the people.&#34;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The future will&#44; like the past&#44; be directed by God&#39;s<lb/> own agency.  To the end of time the house of <persName>Jacob</persName><lb/> will produce men whose spiritual teaching shall mold<lb/> the minds of multitudes.  Let us never fear that infi&#45;<lb/>delity will dethrone piety&#59; that the rule of wickedness<lb/> will supplant that of godliness.  A <persName>Gideon</persName> arose and<lb/> the idols were scattered away.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Samuel</persName> became the judge when the children of a<lb/> high priest contaminated the altar.  The same<lb/> day which beheld the instruments of Roman torture<lb/> tear the life of the great <persName>Akibah</persName>&#44; saw the birth of<lb/> <persName>Rabbi Judah</persName>&#44; the prince of knowledge.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Yet&#44; though the history of all ages affords the con&#45;<lb/>solatory assurance that the Lord will not leave the<lb/> flock of his pasture a prey to the devouring wolf&#44; a<lb/> feeling of dismay seizes us when faithful shepherds<lb/> vanish from our presence.  To us&#44; whose vision is<lb/> narrow&#44; it appears as if none could be found to fill up<lb/> the void.  For those whose spirit was wafted to the<lb/> abode of eternity&#44; we considered vigilant guardians&#44;<lb/> trustworthy servants of their Master.  We seek for<lb/> their equal&#44; but meet the sluggard and the faithless.<lb/>  Shall we then be condemned if the love we bear reli&#45;<lb/>ions instruction incites us now to lament&#63;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The pain we experienced at the loss which the lite&#45;<lb/>rary world  sustained by the death of a Jewish savant<lb/> in <placeName>Italy</placeName>&#44; was scarcely abated when the melancholy<lb/> tidings arrived from <placeName>France</placeName> that another among the<lb/> greatest had descended to the grave.  <persName>Munk</persName> has not<lb/> long survived <persName>Luzzatto</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Those two giants of intellect&#44; who had very nigh<lb/> reached the highest point of human knowledge&#44; were<lb/> cut off while yet vigorous.  Those two mighty laborers<lb/> in the field of science ceased to dispense the delicious<lb/> fruits they had gathered.  One was surprised by<lb/> death while diving into the depth of scriptural exe&#45;<lb/>gesis and philology&#58; the other while engaged &#40;oh&#44;<lb/> wondrous undertaking&#33;&#41; without sight&#44; to collate<lb/> ancient manuscripts and set in order a library most<lb/> extensive and rare.  For quenched was the light of<lb/> those eyes which had discovered treasures hidden in<lb/> obscurity.  But how refulgent that mind&#44; whose<lb/> working enriched the world with volumes historically<lb/> and philosophically profound&#33;  <persName>Munk</persName>&#44; like <persName>Luzzatto</persName>&#44;<lb/> continued&#44; without rest&#44; to pour out new ideas&#44; that<lb/> others might slake their thirst at the fountain of his<lb/> wisdom.  But at the bidding of the Most High the<lb/> gushing stream dried&#44; and we have not since beheld<lb/> another flow so copiously.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But the prediction of <persName>Ezekiel</persName> seems to have been al&#45;<lb/>most literally verified in us for &#34;a sad report follows<lb/> the other hastily&#44;&#34; to tell us that &#34;the law hath ceased<lb/> to be imparted by a priest.&#34;  Yes&#44; that descendant and<lb/> true disciple of <persName>Aaron</persName>&#44; who ministered to one congre&#45;<lb/>gation in <placeName>Northern Europe</placeName>&#44; but taught ever son of<lb/> <placeName>Israel</placeName> who loves the language&#44; the literature&#44; and the<lb/> religion of his people&#44; has also recently departed from<lb/> earth.  He has joined the two illustrious beings that<lb/> had but shortly preceded him to the dwelling of joy.<lb/>  But we&#8212;what have we not lost on the day that <persName>Rap&#45;<lb/>paport</persName> was seated among the blessed&#63;  Him we could<lb/> ask&#44; and his lips would impart sublime knowledge.<lb/>  For &#34;the law of truth was in his month&#59;&#34; &#34;he walked<lb/> with God in equity and peace&#44;&#34; &#34;and did turn many<lb/> away from sin.  Aye&#44; an angel of the Lord of Hosts<lb/> was he.&#34;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Rappaport</persName> was my ideal of a Rabbi.  Exceedingly<lb/> learned&#44; yet exceedingly meek.  Rigidly attached to the<lb/> traditions of the fathers&#44; but willing to concede when<lb/> by yielding nothing sacred was surrendered.  And him<lb/> I would fain have consulted&#44; if the ritual of the Syna&#45;<lb/>gogue&#44; so variously and erroneously represented in<lb/> this country&#44; can ever be unalterably fixed by a syno&#45;<lb/>dical convention.  Alas&#33;  He also has gone hence&#44;<lb/> and the noblest monument of his extraordinary talent<lb/> remains incomplete.  His Encyclopaedia of the Tal&#45;<lb/>mud&#44; and of collateral works&#44; forming in itself a<lb/> world of learning&#44; may&#44; perhaps be suffered to molder<lb/> away as a writing of no value.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">For this we may reasonably lament&#44; O&#44; brethren<lb/> and friends&#33;  For the publication of that inestimable<lb/> work would clear many doubts&#44; elucidate many ob&#45;<lb/>scure questions&#44; while adding another jewel to the<lb/> grown of the law.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But who would have believed that the hand which<lb/> two months ago recorded the demise of the sage at<lb/> <placeName>Prague</placeName>&#44; would be also palsied in death&#63;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Rest thy aching heart on the bosom of eternity&#44;<lb/> thou so long racked by deep and earnest thoughts&#33;<lb/>  Thou didst thy work well&#44; and thine alone is the<lb/> merit&#44; for there was none to help or counsel.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is even so&#44; my beloved hearers.  When <persName>Isaac<lb/> Leeser</persName> went forth&#44; armed with firey zeal&#44; to fight the<lb/> battles of the Lord&#44; he stood alone.  A host might have<lb/> then been arrayed against <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; but not one was<lb/> found in our camp able to cope with the foe.  A youth<lb/> arose to the defense of his religion and his people.<lb/>  Was the name of the Jew aspersed&#63;  His vigorous pen<lb/> wrote the words which put the offender to the blush.<lb/>  Were the truths of <placeName>Sinai</placeName> impugned&#63;  He strove to<lb/> confound the unbeliever.  On the pulpit&#59; in the press&#59;<lb/> at social gatherings&#44; he stood as the bright exponent<lb/> of principles which he never forsook&#44; though he bore<lb/> for their sake the jeers of the scoffer and the con&#45;<lb/>tumely of the skeptic.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Gifted with versatility of mind&#44; endowed with<lb/> the powers of an endurance that few can equal&#59;<lb/> formed by nature with faculties extraordinarily reten&#45;<lb/>tive&#44; he could accomplish&#44; unaided&#44; more than others<lb/> with efficient supports.  For&#44; despite his clerical<lb/> duties&#44; necessarily various and onerous in a large con&#45;<lb/>gregation&#44; the works he produced have been multi&#45;<lb/>farious&#44; and extensive.  Shall I enumerate them&#63;  My<lb/> friends&#44; there is scarcely a religious book of note in<lb/> the <placeName>United States of America</placeName> that does not bear on its<lb/> title page the name of <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The prayers you offer to God&#44; have&#44; by his industry&#44;<lb/> been translated into the vernacular&#44; and elegantly<lb/> printed.  The Bible you read&#44; for instruction and<lb/> spiritual comfort&#44; has&#44; by his toil&#44; been freed from<lb/> biased interpretations&#44; and rendered more compre&#45;<lb/>hensible.  The volume in which your children learn<lb/> the rudiments of Hebrew knowledge&#59; those which in&#45;<lb/>form them of the character and dogmas of their reli&#45;<lb/>gion&#44; and others which unfold before their eyes the<lb/> wisdom of the ancients&#44; are the fruits of his unwearied<lb/> perseverance&#59; &#34;for an education&#34; was the motto in&#45;<lb/>scribed on the banner he first unfolded in this new<lb/> world&#44; and increasingly upheld.  He had discovered<lb/> that that was the most efficacious means to awaken<lb/> his brethren to a sense of their religious duties&#44; and<lb/> he resorted thereto&#44; as evinced by his personal and<lb/> literary exertions.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Has he been successful&#63;  Most assuredly so.  Not<lb/> to the extent of his desires&#44; nor commensurately with<lb/> his labor&#59; nevertheless to a high degree.  I&#44; myself&#44;<lb/> though comparatively a new comer&#44; can bear testi&#45;<lb/>mony to the step in advance made in our midst by our<lb/> coreligionists.  Will any one deny that our lamented<lb/> brother gave the first impetus&#63;  No.  Others may have<lb/> done nobly&#44; but <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName> was the pioneer that<lb/> cleared away all obstructions.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">This fact&#44; which ought to be incontestably admit&#45;<lb/>ted&#44; was lost sight of by men who are&#44; or profess to<lb/> be&#44; his superiors.  Hence the bitter sarcasm which<lb/> assailed him&#44; and aggravated his natural irascibility&#44;<lb/> conscious of having worked indefatigably&#44; he was<lb/> both pained and angered&#44; when belittled by ungene&#45;<lb/>rous minds.  That he had not explored the depth of<lb/> Talmudical science&#59; that his acquaintance with our<lb/> casuistical writers and the Hebrew literature of the<lb/> day was limited&#59; ought to have been overlooked by<lb/> reason of the ardor with which he espoused the cause<lb/> of education&#44; for that is the great debt which <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> owes <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Contrasted with a <persName>Luzzatto</persName>&#44; he might have been<lb/> merely a tyro.  <persName>Munk</persName> exceeded him by fact and he<lb/> would&#44; for certain&#44; have profited by sitting at the feet<lb/> of the great <persName>Rappaport</persName>.  Yet&#44; he labored even more<lb/> beneficially than those three universally renowned<lb/> scholars.  For they sought to lead further the already<lb/> tutored&#59; he sought to be a guide for the untutored.<lb/>  They endeavored to enlarge and beautify the temple<lb/> of knowledge&#59; he strove to lay its foundations&#44; that it<lb/> might be set up.  Few&#44; very few are the individuals<lb/> who&#44; in this country&#44; can duly appreciate the masterly<lb/> productions of those European literati&#59; but <persName>Leeser&#39;s</persName><lb/> writings can be read round every fireside advanta&#45;<lb/>geously&#44; both to the young and to the old.  Therefore<lb/> ought his memory to be revered and eternized.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">As to myself&#44; I have performed only an act of jus&#45;<lb/>tice.  Called upon to officiate at the funeral of one<lb/> with whom I have been associated in the discharge<lb/> of educational and ministerial functions&#44; I would have<lb/> pronounced on that mournful occasion&#44; the eulogy he<lb/> well merited.  But I was precluded by the expressed<lb/> wish of the deceased.  Simplicity of manners had<lb/> been his characteristic through life&#44; and he exempli&#45;<lb/>fied it in the hour of death.  He ordered that the ritual<lb/> service as recited at the burial of the humblest Is&#45;<lb/>raelite should alone be heard when he was about to<lb/> be consigned to mother earth&#44; and none dared con&#45;<lb/>travene the injunction.  But the Ecclesiastical Board&#44;<lb/> of which I have the honor to be a member&#44; resolved<lb/> that a public expression of sorrow at the demise of<lb/> our colleague&#44; was highly due to his virtues and deeds&#59;<lb/> and I full assented.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">My friends&#33;  I utter what I profoundly feel when I<lb/> say that no man of <placeName>Israel</placeName> has yet found a grave in this<lb/> country of our adoption&#44; who deserves to be enshrined</p>
				<p>&#42; Literally the Hebrew verb stands in the future tense.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
