<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Schwarz, Joseph, Rabbi; Levy,
                    Jadok, Rabbi</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0295</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Schwarz, Joseph,
                            Rabbi; Levy, Jadok, Rabbi</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">“the Friends of the
                            Israelites of Palestine”</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1849-08">August 1849</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1849-08">13 Elul 5609</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p>make with this<lb/> and the certificates about<lb/> three pages, and print<lb/> 200
                copies, or 8 quires<lb/> on letter sheet<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">new</hi>
                <add>?</add>.</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">To the <addressee>Friends of the Israelites of
                    Palestine</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Knowing that the descendants of <placeName>Israel</placeName> have
                not relinquished<lb/> the ancient character of benevolence for which they have
                been<lb/> always distinguished the undersigned messengers from the
                    <placeName>Holy<lb/> Land</placeName>, beg <add>?</add> to lay before you the
                following statement,<lb/> in the full hope that it may incite you to aid the small
                rem<lb/>nant yet residing in the country over which once ruled chiefs<lb/> and
                princes governing in the spirit of our religion, and when<lb/> spoke the ports and
                prophets of our own race in a language<lb/> never to be forgotten. It was owing to
                our transgressions that<lb/> we as a nation were banished from that land, where formerly<lb/>
                <del>there</del> reigned plenty and elegance, but where now all in desolation<lb/>
                and ruin.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For several centuries after the destruction of the Temple<lb/> and
                the final expulsion of the people after the unsuccessful strug-<lb/>gle for freedom
                under the guidance of <persName>Bar Cochaba</persName> against the<lb/> legions led
                on by the captains of <persName>Aelian Hadrian</persName>, the Israelites<lb/> were
                not permitted to dwell in their own patrimony, the <add>?</add> of their<lb/>
                fathers was not permitted to be hidden by them, as though the<lb/> presence of the
                Hebrew would be signal for rebellion, and recall<lb/> the ancient freedom which was
                making into decay under the<lb/> despotism of the Roman Emperors <add>and only on
                    the payment of a ton were they permitted to repair singly to<lb/> the ruins of
                        <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> to weep there over the subversion of their
                    state and were<lb/> when compelled there to return again to their<lb/> exile
                    homes.</add> But with the over throw<lb/> of the Christian powers by the
                    <persName>Mohamed</persName> and many Jews gradually<lb/> sought the desolate
                fields of their own land, and established themselves<lb/> in its waste places amidst
                fear and trembling. This land pro-<lb/>tected though oppressed by the followers of
                the Koran. And when the<lb/> crusaders in their mad attempt to become what they
                    <add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>the burial place of the founder of their religion made war against<lb/> the Saracens,
                the Israelites were found stoutly defending the <placeName>Holy
                City</placeName><lb/> by the side of their <sic>Moslim</sic> protectors, and when
                    <del>the city</del> it was at length<lb/> taken, the blood of our brothers
                flowed like water in its streets;<lb/> and reeking with slaughter the Christian
                knights returned thanks<lb/> for the victory which they fancied would secure them
                the possession<lb/> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> &amp;
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName>. But their reign was brief, and the<lb/>
                <persName><sic>Soltan</sic></persName> of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
                    <persName>Saladdin</persName>, recovered what his predecessor had<lb/> lost, and
                ever since <placeName>Palestine</placeName> has remained the p<add>?</add>tion of
                the<lb/> followers of <persName><sic>Mahomed</sic></persName>. Although under them
                too an lot<lb/> has been exceedingly grievous, exposed as we are to the
                rapacity<lb/> of the Pachas and the <add>?</add> of the Arab plunderers who<lb/>
                have infested the land from time immemorial: still the land of<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> has been a place of refuge to us in many a
                trouble;<lb/> and when the inquisition of <placeName>Spain</placeName> induced the
                    <persName>king and queen</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Castillo</placeName>,
                    <persName>Ferdinand</persName> &amp; <persName>Isabella</persName> to expel the
                Jews from the<lb/>
                <placeName>Iberian Peninsula</placeName>, followers as they soon were by the
                    <persName>king</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Portugal</placeName>, thousands
                turned their steps to the st<add>?</add>
                <placeName>Pa-<lb/>lestine</placeName>, and became the founders of the Portuguese
                congrega-<lb/>tions still existing there, and the carried with them as to<lb/> other
                parts of <placeName>Turkey</placeName>, the language of <placeName>Spain</placeName>
                which still<lb/> continues their vernacular lingue. By de<add>?</add> other<lb/>
                emigrants from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, <placeName>Poland</placeName> &amp;
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName> joined them;<lb/> and all along with a holy
                devotion, amidst every <add>?</add><lb/>tion to the place of the sepulchre of their
                fathers, a land<lb/> endeared to every son of <placeName>Israel</placeName> by the
                great deeds which were<lb/> wrought there in their behalf.</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">A <persName>Don Joseph Caro</persName>, a <persName>Rabbi Isaac
                    Luria</persName> and the great names<lb/> have flourished from time to time in
                the genial clime of the<lb/> land of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, <add>?</add> the
                migrations of which we have just spoken;<lb/> but with all this the Israelites there
                are subject to great many<lb/> deprivations, and are necessarily dependent on the
                aid of others<lb/> for their support. It is not now as formerly, that the whole
                land<lb/> is covered with villages and farms, and every foot of ground
                ren-<lb/>dered productive by the industry of man; for the far larger number of
                towns<lb/> are totally destroyed, and the land is waste because there are<lb/> no
                inhabitants to cultivate it. The terraces on the hills which<lb/> produced food in
                abundance have been washed away by<lb/> the winter rains; since the industry of the
                husband man has<lb/> ceased to guard them against destruction; and what land<lb/> is
                still productive lies fallow because of the wandering<lb/>
                <sic>Beduin</sic>, who loves to reap when he has not sowed. Com-<lb/>merce is
                scarcely known; <del>?</del> navigation is not attended to;<lb/> the mechanic arts
                are not needed in a country when the inha-<lb/>bitants have so few wants as the
                roving Arabs who now dwell<lb/> there; <sic>wherfore</sic> with all their efforts it
                is almost impossible for<lb/> the few Israelites, who chiefly dwell at
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <placeName>Hebron</placeName>,<lb/>
                <placeName>Z<add>?</add></placeName>
                <placeName>Tiberia</placeName> to obtain a livelihood.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It has accordingly been the practice of European Jews to<lb/> aid
                their brothers in <placeName>Palestine</placeName> with annual donations, to
                collect<lb/> which messengers were sent out to bring the funds to the managers<lb/>
                in the chief cities just named. But the expenses attending this<lb/> mode are
                evidently very great, and to obviate this, the undersigned<lb/> accredited
                messengers from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> have been instructed to appeal<lb/>
                to all congregations in <placeName>America</placeName> to organize a permanent
                relief</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>fund, to consist of free will offerings, annual collections and stated<lb/>
                contributions, which are to be forwarded to such persons as the<lb/> Israelites of
                this country may themselves designate, and distri-<lb/>buted in good faith and
                impartially among all who stand in<lb/> need of assistance. The subjoined
                certificates will at once show that<lb/> a number of influential persons in this
                country have already offered<lb/> their services; and we hope that you will induce
                your congregation or<lb/> immediate friends to be active in the cause, and to send
                out through<lb/> a committee in your own neighborhood or the various gentlemen<lb/>
                here named in <placeName>New York</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> any fund you may collect.<lb/> The
                Portuguese congregation in <placeName>New York</placeName> have already appropriated
                $25<lb/> per annum; other bodies in that place have followed with similar
                donations<lb/> and all this independently of the Hebra <add>Hebrew</add> whose
                object it is to<lb/> aid the poor of the <placeName>Holy Land</placeName>. In case
                our appeal is responded to,<lb/> we can assure our brethren in
                    <placeName>America</placeName> that the congregations<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName> will not send out any more <del>any</del>
                special<lb/> messengers, wherefore <del>they</del> you will not hereafter be
                troubled by <del>any</del><lb/> personal applicants. Due notice will be given as
                soon as possible<lb/> of the distributing commission to be appointed in
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and we<lb/> can give the most positive
                assurance that the wishes of the donor shall<lb/> be faithfully carried into
                effect.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><add>?</add> the blessing of God on you all we sign ourselves</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">your brothers</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">
                <persName role="author">Rabbi Joseph Schwarz</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">
                <persName role="author">Rabbi Jadok Levy</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">messengers from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName></p>
            <p>
                <placeName>New York</placeName>
                <date>Elul 13th. 5609</date>
            </p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_7_7.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume
                        7 No. 7 pages 345 through 348. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
