<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP_New_6</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Boston, MA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1848-01" source="" attested="yes">January 11, 1848</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_kaplan_new_6.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">miscellany</material>
								</support>
								<extent>1 page on 1 sheet
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
				<p rend="align(center)">DAILY ADVERTISER.</p>
				<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>BOSTON</placeName>&#58;</p>
				<p rend="align(center)"><date>TUESDAY MORNING&#44; JAN. 11&#44; 1848</date>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">ADMISSION OF JEWS TO PARLIAMENT.&#8212;In<lb/> the House of Commons on the <date>15th</date> ult. <persName>Lord John<lb/> Russell</persName> introduced the anticipated motion for the re&#45;<lb/>moval of the civil and political disabilities of Jewish<lb/> subjects&#44; with a view to such an amendment of the<lb/> oath which is required to be taken by members of<lb/> the House&#44; that it may not exclude <persName>Mr. Rothschild</persName>&#44;<lb/> who was chosen at the late election as a member for<lb/> one of the districts of the city of <placeName>London</placeName>.  This su&#45;<lb/>ject has been earnestly discussed in some of the Brit&#45;<lb/>ish reviews&#44; and it is in various points of view one of<lb/> considerable interest.  We therefore copy the speech<lb/> of <persName>Lord John Russell</persName> on introducing his motion&#44; in<lb/> which he has treated the subject with great ability<lb/> and skill.  We copy the speech from the <placeName>London</placeName><lb/> Times&#58;&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">REMOVAL OF JEWISH DISABILITIES.&#8212;<persName>Lord<lb/> J. Russell</persName>.&#8212;As I understand that my honorable<lb/>friend the member for the University of <placeName>Oxford</placeName> means<lb/> to oppose the motion for the house resolving itself<lb/> into a committee of the whole house to consider the<lb/> disabilities at present affecting Her Majesty&#39;s Jewish<lb/> subjects&#44; I feel myself compelled&#44; before making that<lb/> motion&#44; to state to the house the general grounds on<lb/> which I intend to rest it.  I am&#44; at the same time&#44;<lb/> given to understand by my honorable friend&#44; that if<lb/> a majority of the house should agree to go into com&#45;<lb/>mittee on the subject&#44; he does not mean to carry his<lb/> opposition to the point of refusing to consent to the<lb/> committee adopting the resolution which is necessa&#45;<lb/>ry to the introduction of a bill.  That being the case&#44;<lb/> it will be as convenient to the house to take the dis&#45;<lb/>cussion at this stage as to reserve it&#44; as was done on<lb/> former occasions&#44; till the house had resolved itself<lb/> into committee.  In bringing forward this subject I<lb/> feel that I cannot avail myself of many of the topics<lb/> which those who formerly proposed the removal of<lb/> disabilities on account of religious tenets were able<lb/> to appeal to for the purpose of inducing this house to<lb/> comply with their propositions.  I cannot say&#8212;as I<lb/> did in proposing the repeal of the Test and Corpora&#45;<lb/>tion Acts&#8212;&#34;Here are some three millions of Her<lb/> Majesty&#39;s subjects&#44; engaged in all the pursuits of in&#45;<lb/>dustry in your cities and towns&#44; forming a most im&#45;<lb/>portant portion of the community&#44; and distinguished<lb/> for their loyalty to the house of <placeName>Hanover</placeName>&#44; undevia&#45;<lb/>tingly maintained ever since that illustrious family<lb/> was seated on the throne of these realms.&#34;  I can&#45;<lb/>not&#44; like the great orator who introduced the ques&#45;<lb/>tion of Catholic disabilities&#44; refer to the state of a<lb/> neighboring country as a potent motive to induce the<lb/> house to remove the cause of discontent and dissat&#45;<lb/>isfaction.  I cannot speak&#44; as he did&#44; of the indigna&#45;<lb/>tion felt by a whole people at the deprivation of their<lb/> rights&#59; nor can I point to the dangers which would<lb/> menace the peace and welfare of the country from<lb/> refusing the claim to relief.  I can employ none of<lb/> those arguments in favor of my proposition.  I feel<lb/> that this is a question which does not affect a very<lb/> large portion of the people of this country&#44; and does<lb/> not involve in its acceptance or rejection the momen&#45;<lb/>tous consequences which were justly apprehended on<lb/> former occasions.  I am prepared to argue this ques&#45;<lb/>tion as one of principle&#44; not of political expediency&#8212;<lb/> as a question involving&#44; indeed&#44; the political liberties<lb/> of the country&#44; but involving them only as they con&#45;<lb/>ern 30&#44;000 or 40&#44;000 people&#44; members of a commu&#45;<lb/>nity which is not disposed&#44; nor indeed able&#44; if it<lb/> were disposed&#44; to excite clamor and tumult&#44; to agi&#45;<lb/>tate the country by means of public meetings&#44; or to<lb/> produce a social convulsion&#44; if its demands should<lb/> not be conceded.  But&#44; although I am unable to ap&#45;<lb/>peal to the topics to which I have referred&#44; I must&#44;<lb/> nevertheless&#44; take the liberty of informing the house<lb/> that there may be danger&#44; not affecting the public<lb/> tranquility indeed&#44; but affecting the character and<lb/> dignity of the Legislature&#44; if the claims of our Jew&#45;<lb/>ish fellow subjects continue longer to be refused.  It<lb/> may then be said that the Legislature is unwilling to<lb/> concede the claim of religious liberty&#44; that Parlia&#45;<lb/>ment has never adopted those just principles of equal&#45;<lb/>ity which ought to be applied to all the subjects of<lb/> Her Majesty&#59; but that when the question regarded<lb/> vast bodies of men&#44; important from their numbers<lb/> and wealth&#44; or threatening from their dissatisfaction<lb/> and discontent&#44; the Legislature yielded a reluctant<lb/> assent to their claims for the sake of immediate<lb/> peace&#59; and that when an opportunity presented itself<lb/> of doing an act of justice without any danger&#44; and<lb/> without inconvenience to public interests&#44; the Par&#45;<lb/>liament acted on the principle of religious perse&#45;<lb/>cution&#44; and was determined to show the world<lb/> that it was not from any willingness to adopt en&#45;<lb/>larged and liberal principles as the rule of its<lb/> conduct that it had on former occasions yield&#45;<lb/>ed to the petitions of its fellow subjects.&#8212;<lb/> &#40;Cheers.&#41;  I venture to say&#44; that if such an opinion<lb/> as that should become prevalent&#44; it must have a<lb/> very injurious effect on the character of this<lb/> house.  There is&#44; as I have before said&#44; but little<lb/> risk of danger to the public peace involved in the re&#45;<lb/>jection or adoption of my proposition.  One danger<lb/> was pointed out as likely to arise from its adoption&#44;<lb/> many years ago&#44; by my hon. friend who intends to<lb/> oppose me on the present occasion&#44; but he is not in a<lb/> position to repeat his warning now.  In <date>1830</date> my<lb/> hon. friend took upon himself the character of a<lb/> prophet&#44; and said &#34;You may depend upon it that if<lb/> you admit the Jews to civil offices and seats in Par&#45;<lb/>liament&#44; it will follow that in less than seven years<lb/> you will have a reform of Parliament.&#34;  &#40;&#34;Hear&#44;&#34;<lb/> and laughter.&#41;  But&#44; without the admission of Jews<lb/> to Parliament&#44; as the precursor of the so much dread&#45;<lb/>ed event&#44; within two years of the time when my<lb/> hon. friend used those words I have referred to the<lb/> reform of Parliament was effected.  &#40;Hear&#44; hear.&#41;<lb/>  Therefore&#44; there is&#44; at least&#44; one danger which it<lb/> will be unnecessary to take into consideration in dis&#45;<lb/>cussing this question.  &#40;&#34;Hear&#44;&#34; and laughter.&#41;  I<lb/> place the question upon this simple&#44; but I think&#44;<lb/> solid ground&#8212;that every Englishman is entitled to<lb/> the honors and advantages which the British consti&#45;<lb/>tution gives him.  &#40;Cheers.&#41;  I state further&#44; that<lb/> religious opinion of itself ought to be no disqualifica&#45;<lb/>tion for the enjoyment of those rights.  &#40;Renewed<lb/> cheers.&#41;  I found myself on a declaration in one of<lb/> the statutes of the law of <placeName>England</placeName>&#8212;&#34;It is the birth&#45;<lb/>right of the people to enjoy the privileges common to<lb/> all.&#34;  I found myself on a declaration made in the<lb/> House of Lords during the discussions on the Con&#45;<lb/>formity Bill&#44;&#8212;&#34;The Lords think that an English&#45;<lb/>man cannot be reduced to a more unhappy condition<lb/> than to be put by law under an incapacity of serving<lb/> his prince and country&#59; and therefore nothing but a<lb/> crime of the most detestable nature ought to put him<lb/> under such a disability.&#34;  I say&#44; then&#44; that on this<lb/> ground&#44; unless something shall be proved to disqual&#45;<lb/>ify Jews&#44; they stand in the position of persons born<lb/> in this country&#44; bearing all the burdens which are<lb/> imposed on them&#44; and ready to serve their prince<lb/> and their country in any capacity in which they may<lb/> be called upon&#44; and that&#44; therefore&#44; they are entitled<lb/> to all the rights and privileges enjoyed by their fel&#45;<lb/>low&#45;subjects.  &#40;Cheers.&#41;  I state this with confi&#45;<lb/>dence&#44; and I will not attempt to ask your favor by<lb/> anything which I might urge in behalf of the merits<lb/> of the Jews.  I think this is not a matter of favor to&#45;<lb/>ward the Jews&#44; but that&#44; unless some strong ground<lb/> of disqualification be proved against them&#44; it is a<lb/> matter of right.  &#40;Cheers.&#41;  I&#44; therefore&#44; will not<lb/> urge that even those who have opposed the claims of<lb/> the Jews have admitted their peaceable conduct and<lb/> their moral character as subjects&#8212;that they are gov&#45;<lb/>erned by that moral law which is adopted by and is<lb/> binding on us&#8212;that there are among them many per&#45;<lb/>sons distinguished for eminent talents&#8212;that in the<lb/> offices of which they have been admitted they have</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
