<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0251</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Albany, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="[1850?]">[1850?]</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url=""/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="unk" paper_type="" size="Legal"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p>
                <placeName>
                    <hi rend="underline">Albany</hi>
                </placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <hi rend="underline">For the Occident</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="underline">American Liturgy</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <persName>Rev. Beth-Din</persName> in his first assembly<lb/> acknowledged
                the necess<del>ar</del>ity of a general Liturgy in<lb/>
                <placeName>America</placeName>, and made it so his <sic>probleme</sic> to
                establish<lb/> the <add>Hebrew</add> according to the <add>Hebrew</add> and vocation
                of the<lb/> modern time; the <sic>motiv</sic> of this problem was neither<lb/>
                desire of innovation nor lust of fame nor that giddy<lb/> disposition of reform, but
                only and simple</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 1. to bring unity among the members of every<lb/> congregation, as
                well as among all the American <sic>Sinagogues</sic></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 2. to <del>remain</del> maintain the word of the Living God<lb/> by
                    <persName>Moses</persName> his <sic>servent</sic> in the free land of
                        <placeName><sic>Amerika</sic></placeName>.<lb/> The <sic>amiercan</sic>
                Israelite came from different countries,<lb/> and brought <sic>divers</sic>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, and this is and must be a<lb/> source of confusion, quarrel and
                disagreeableness in<lb/> the Synagogue and congregation. Moreover, the whole<lb/>
                people of <placeName>Israel</placeName> serves one God, reads and believes one<lb/>
                Thora, is inspired by one hoping, all together walking<lb/> the same way, in the
                same manner, leaned upon the<lb/> same support, why should be strangers to one
                another<lb/> by our garment? Unity is a feature of Gods divine character,<lb/> unity
                and peace is his holy will, unity and peace is the<lb/> end that our godly doctrine
                will aim! Verily I feel<lb/> myself so <sic>strangly</sic> so separated when I enter
                a Synagoe<lb/> that has another <add>Hebrew</add>, so that I can hardly fancy
                the<lb/> worshiping people as my <sic>jewish</sic> brethren. These<lb/>
                <sic>divers</sic>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, yea, those differently coloured garments built<lb/> the partition
                wall among <sic>Portuguise</sic>, <sic>Germain</sic>, Polish<lb/> and Bohemian Jews,
                and they became strange to one<lb/> another, although we all are descendants of the
                same<lb/> ancestors, and observe the same <sic>religios</sic> law. But the<lb/>
                <sic>Amerikan</sic> Jew shall know and love his brethren, and<lb/> thus that
                partition wall may fall in suddenly.</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>Moreover, it is remarkable for every feeling Israelite,<lb/> that the symptoms of a
                very ritual <sic>periode</sic> for our Reli-<lb/>gion appear here and there, I speak
                of fails that lifted<lb/> up their <sic>distorying</sic> hand against the Synagogue.
                Behold,<lb/> In one place the <add>Hebrew</add> seemed them to be wrong,
                    <sic>unworthly</sic><lb/> to be said, and without question or scrupulousness,
                without<lb/> regarding the <add>Hebrew</add> nor having an auhtority to
                undertake<lb/> a <sic>religios</sic> alteration, they <sic>expeled</sic> the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> and all,<lb/> they are able to reply us, is, we did not like
                so many praye-<lb/>ers. In another place people understand not the
                <sic>hebrew</sic><lb/> language, therefore they want to pray in the
                    <sic>germain</sic> langu.<lb/> again without any authority. Thus the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> is neglected,<lb/> and is not the <sic>neglegance</sic> of the
                dogmas the ruin of<lb/> the whole religion? In other places is it no question<lb/>
                at all to talk about such a small matter as the Syn.<lb/> is, and
                    <sic>dislikness</sic> on the customs of the old, the ancient<lb/> songs, tans
                and ceremonies shut the door of the Synag. or<lb/> made the <sic>cosecrated</sic>
                hall of the Most High to a place of<lb/> tediousness, of profane consideration and
                reflection, instead<lb/> of the hall of elevation and sublimity to sanctify and
                adorn<lb/> our soul, we have a house for meeting. And the<lb/> consequence of those
                must be the ruin of the whole Religion.<lb/> Viewing those <sic>motivs</sic> for
                establishing a general liturgy,<lb/> I expect, that this labour would be “a
                felicitous mid”,<lb/> according to the doctrine of the <add>Hebrew</add> to unite
                all<lb/> the different parties and satisfying them. Be not terrified,<lb/> my
                orthodox brother, for that “filicitous mid”, it is evident,<lb/> that the
                    <persName>Rev. B. D.</persName> honoured our Rabbi with this
                <sic>probleme</sic>,<lb/> and <persName>Rabbi Wise</persName> is, though one of the
                first philosophical scholars,<lb/> an orthodox <sic>talmudist</sic>, not moving one
                step from the<lb/>
                <sic>talmudical</sic> basis, and it is doubtless, that our Rabbi is the
                grea-<lb/>test <add>Hebrew</add>, who entered <placeName>America</placeName>. To
                convince you <del>on</del> concerning<lb/> my words I give you the principles as the
                basis of the liturgy</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>in question <sic>wit</sic> all the <add>?</add> itations<add>?</add> out of the
                    <sic>talmud</sic><lb/> in the original tongue as I heard it by <persName>Rabbi
                    Wise</persName><lb/> when he took occasion in an evening <sic>discours</sic> to
                speak<lb/> about it, and you-yourselves may judge, but not, I pray<lb/> too hasty;
                for these words are spoken by a man, who<lb/> is true with God and honest with his
                law.</p>
            <p>
                <add>Hebrew</add>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 1. „To pray thrice <sic>dayly</sic> is a law of
                    <persName>Moses</persName> according to<lb/> „the opinion of the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> in his <add>Hebrew</add>. The Rabbi <sic>showd</sic><lb/>
                there that the <add>Hebrew</add> is against this opinion, but justified<lb/> this
                principle with that <sic>talmudical</sic> energy and sagacity<lb/> that only may be
                got by a long study of the <sic>talmud</sic>.<lb/> I suppose, this principle is
                doubtless, and write no demon„<lb/>stration at all, the <add>Hebrew</add> is
                    <sic>enogh</sic> authority for us.<lb/> This principle teaches sufficiently,
                that no alteration<lb/> in the service should be undertaken by men ignorant<lb/> in
                the <sic>scienses</sic> of our Religion, for <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 2. <add>Hebrew</add> are not generally obliging, but only local
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> There <sic>shew</sic> the Rabbi by many
                    <sic>talmudical</sic> citations, that<lb/> the <add>Hebrew</add> was not
                practiced in <add>Hebrew</add> nor that of <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> in
                    <add>Hebrew</add>. <sic>Concludingly</sic> he said: the <sic>divers</sic>
                <add>Hebrew</add> now existing<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>, which
                    <sic>descendent</sic> of a very ancient time, are the most<lb/> evident
                demonstration for this principle. We learn by<lb/> that, that the establishing of a
                    <add>Hebrew</add> to <placeName>America</placeName> independent<lb/> of all
                other <add>Hebrew</add> that “<sic>filicitous</sic> mid” is possible by those,<lb/>
                who know to distinguish between <add>Hebrew</add> and <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 3. “to pray is the most perfect service” (<add>Hebrew</add>)
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> (<add>Hebrew</add>) <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> Yet clearer
                words wrote the <add>Hebrew</add> in his commentary to<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> (<add>Hebrew</add>) <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>
                <add>Hebrew</add>
            </p>
            <p>The Rabbi said a multitude of <add>Hebrew</add> to justify the <add>Hebrew</add>,
                and<lb/> then he expressed his own view in that question:</p>
            <p>The matter is thus (read the Morate Nebuitim of <add>Hebrew</add> and the<lb/>
                ancient history by <persName>Rothek</persName>) In <placeName>Egypt</placeName> our
                ancestor learned<lb/> the offering service, yea, they saw even those beasts,
                God<lb/> commended to sacrifice him, <sic>worshipped</sic> as Deities. It was<lb/>
                afterwards impossible for them to search that sublime<lb/> and spiritual Dea, that
                God would forgive the sin of man<lb/> without offering him any satisfaction, he
                would hear the<lb/> supplication without <sic>recieving</sic> a present, nor that he
                should<lb/> please our thanksgiving without gratifying his kindness<lb/> by a
                corporal sign of our gratitude. Two ends were aimed<lb/> by the divine
                    <sic>docterine</sic> of the offerings: a. to build a bridge<lb/> between God and
                man, and b. to bring them away of the <sic>egyptian</sic><lb/> superstition. In the
                question, what will be the service after<lb/> rebuilding the sanctuary at
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> I ought to answer<lb/> with <add>Hebrew</add>
                for there is said by the Prophet <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p>But our Thora precepts us our God as the most perfect<lb/> spirit, and the spirit can
                only be adored by and in the spirit,<lb/> and thus is but the prayer.</p>
            <p>We learn by this princi., that we have no reason to<lb/> pray for restoring of the
                offering service, therefore all<lb/> such prayers shall not be taken up in our
                liturgy.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 4. „The reflective effect upon spirit and heart of the praying<lb/>
                „subject is the purpose of <del>prayer</del> the prayer, briefly, the<lb/>
                    „<del>refl</del> effect of it can only be subjective but never objective;<lb/>
                this is an evident truth both religious and philosophical.<lb/> That principle is
                taught by the ancient <add>Hebrew</add> in <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> when there is said
                    <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p>will it be of <add>Hebrew</add> like 6-9 <add>Hebrew</add> or <add>Hebrew</add> like
                18-11 <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> or according <add>Hebrew</add> idea <add>Hebrew</add>
                as two words <add>Hebrew</add> this I should like<lb/> to know does the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> of <add>Hebrew</add> requires a <add>Hebrew</add> and a
                    <add>Hebrew</add> in the <add>Hebrew</add> Signifying<lb/> as <add>Hebrew</add>
                like 14-4 <add>Hebrew</add> and 15-23 <add>Hebrew</add> as<lb/> Truth being not a
                grammarian he begs therefore instruction from<lb/>
                <persName>Mr W.</persName> who commenced with <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
            <p>6<add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr. W.</persName> find fault with <add>Hebrew</add> Saying “who have heard
                of such a<lb/> thing” why does not <persName>W</persName> reminds a
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> also a <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> (<add>Hebrew</add>)
                    <add>Hebrew</add> also <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> Truth thinks that
                    <add>Hebrew</add> being divided into 3 Classes viz.<lb/> 1st <add>Hebrew</add>
                to Receipt, or to Delivery 2nd Deliverance including the idea<lb/> the reception of
                    <add>Hebrew</add> in accordance of the two<lb/> words <add>Hebrew</add>, 3 the
                Kabbalah composes of Mysticke Meta-<lb/>physical with Biblical &amp; Divinity's
                explanations, <del>morer</del> moreover<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> explained in a certain volume edited in the year <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> then <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p>this being also <add>Hebrew</add> which Created the fun of <persName>Mr.
                W</persName>:/ through the above not intended by Truth as <add>Hebrew</add>,
                but<lb/> as Stated at the Commencement of Answer b, being the<lb/> latter to show
                    <persName>Mr. W</persName>: what also can be understood by
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> Easy to say Say if you know it”</p>
            <pb n="3V"/>
            <p><persName>Mr. W.</persName> asking where is Truth, in the idea that all what was<lb/>
                Said by Truth in untruth, truth is to be found<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> also 8-39 <add>Hebrew</add> moreover<lb/> did not Truth comes
                forth from <placeName>New York</placeName> and being<lb/> always ready to discuss
                with <persName>W.</persName> and is not truth in <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> also
                    <add>Hebrew</add>” but as being no Grammarian has<lb/> not the <add>Hebrew</add>
                of <add>Hebrew</add> a <add>Hebrew</add> an definite article does<lb/> not the
                    <add>Hebrew</add> Signifying a certainty merely a thing spoken of,<lb/> Surely
                then it would Signify the Beth-Din here composed<lb/> of <persName>Mr. L</persName>:
                    <persName>W</persName>: <persName>Mule-f</persName>:.... and <add>Hebrew</add>
                the German Translation<lb/> coming for in the Occidents for some time ago, for what
                purpose was<lb/> that <add>Hebrew</add>
                <sic>organised</sic> for <add>Hebrew</add> such things <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> or in
                regard of <add>Hebrew</add> above mentioned <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add></p>
            <p>if the Beth-Din's object has been <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> would not this require more
                individuals enlightened in<lb/> Talmud and Poskim etc. does not our Talmud at the
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> Says <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> would not <hi rend="underline"
                    >this</hi> Beth-Din be that <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> but as a grammarian as
                    <persName>Mr. W</persName>: is not that <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> only a
                    “<add>Hebrew</add>” according the Grammarians<lb/> as <persName>Mr.
                W</persName>: is or <sic>predends</sic> to be?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"> 8. <persName>Mr. W</persName>: remark about <add>Hebrew</add> and
                    <add>Hebrew</add> undoubtedly the<lb/> love to our God and the love to our
                neighbour is a Separated<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add> The desire of him who loves and him<lb/> that will be loved namely
                the active <add>Hebrew</add> and the pass: <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> is, a uniting or
                combination with their bodies or with their<lb/> inner heart one to another, even if
                the uniting of their bodies<lb/> fails, Still their hearts are united like a
                    <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> as our <add>Hebrew</add> Said <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> thus
                    f<add>?</add>gertively <add>Hebrew</add> like the love of <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, another circumstance is in <sic>extence</sic><add>?</add>
                namely<lb/> between two entirely <sic>unaqcuainted</sic> individuals, having
                Such<lb/> a love to each other and a uniting occurs only by name<lb/> or rather
                reputation still a love is there as a <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, Certainly than by being frequently acquainted</p>
            <p rend="Note:">The letter cuts off here.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
