<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De La Motta, J.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP20-1061</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De La Motta,
                            J.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_1061_001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_1061_002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_1061_003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="leeser_20_1061_004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="Letter"
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="true"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p>for the "interment of such Israelites as may purchase<lb/> lots there" are a
                    <add>?</add>ding to <persName>Mr Cohen</persName> the amount<lb/> paid by him
                for <sic>encloseing</sic> it with a small <hi rend="underline">wooden</hi><lb/>
                railing, the said portion to be subject as the rest, to<lb/> the rules in a
                expectation prescribed by the city council,<lb/> all this was done without the
                knowledge con-<lb/>-sent of the congregation or any of the constituted<lb/>
                officers; a few moments after this Ordinance was thus<lb/> hurried through, an
                obscure number of the Be<add>?</add> intro-<lb/>-duced a resolution to close up the
                congregational come-<lb/>-<add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr. Hertz</persName> a member of council being present im-<lb/>-mediately
                opposed it in such warmth as to induce the<lb/>
                <del>B<add>?</add> of <persName>Alderm</persName> the</del> man of the resolution to
                withdraw it<lb/> thus as you may suppose caused much excitement in the<lb/>
                congregation, it is no doubt the object of the instigators<lb/> of this outrageous
                and <add>?</add> act to get the city council<lb/> to close up on Beth
                    Hyams<add>?</add> this I do not fear will be<lb/> accomplished as it is on the
                outskirts of the city. This<lb/> object no doubt is to force us out, to the
                Christian Cemetery<lb/> for it is certainly are, Last <date>Saturday</date> after
                    <persName>Mr Ramsela<add>?</add></persName><lb/> has got through with his sermon
                he <sic>publickly</sic> an-<lb/>-swered from his place that this new cemetery would
                be<lb/> consecrated this day. This came on me as well as others<lb/> like a clap of
                thunder in a cloudless sky, he <add>?</add><lb/> me a word of his intuition to do
                such an outrage<lb/> upon the feelings of a large portion of the congregation<lb/>
                the next day I called a meeting of the <add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>and <persName>Mr. Resinsila<add>?</add></persName> conduct came up on a motion<lb/>
                for a resolution of censure. This was opposed ve-<lb/>-hemently by <persName>Mr Sol
                    Cohen</persName>, and of course I came<lb/> in for a large portion of his alone,
                to my regret<lb/> the <add>?</add> of the resolution withdrew it; so as I<lb/>
                suppose that afterward will consecrate a service then<lb/> at Judische in this
                country than has ever been<lb/> a <add>?</add> in this Country, who ever heard of
                a<lb/> Beth hyan being under the control of a Christian<lb/> Board, still this man
                who has been selected as<lb/>
                <sic>an</sic> spiritual guide and who when he came here<lb/> called himself an
                orthodox Jew, I think his Ortho-<lb/>-doxy more than <persName>Mr.
                    P<add>?</add></persName> for he practices<lb/> what he preaches, but
                    <persName>Mr R.</persName> comes with deceitful<lb/> countenances; Now let me
                ask you my friend<lb/> can I consistent with the feelings of a true Israelite<lb/>
                retain my office with such a Hazan; he is to<lb/> remove the body of his child from
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName> and<lb/> bury him in that new burial place,
                and many<lb/> who like the originator of this now ask to<lb/> be buried in a
                "sustainable place" will remove<lb/> the bodies of their deceased friends from its
                repose<lb/> to this new place contrary to our law, now also<lb/> to remain in office
                it would not permit them<lb/> as they say they will do so at all hazards and<lb/> I
                have no <add>?</add> to present them committing a<lb/> sin like that, it is but
                therefore for me to retire<lb/> before they do. I have thus given you a
                statement</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>of facts I cannot tell you all I feel on the<lb/> subject, it has made me such, It
                will very<lb/> naturally be asked as soon as this outrage is<lb/> known who was
                Parnas at the time and why<lb/> did he permit it; will you my friend do my<lb/>
                memory the justice should I then be removed<lb/> from this world to tell the world
                the facts<lb/> as here stated, and that I did all I could to<lb/> prevent it and
                that having failed to do so, I<lb/> resigned my station, held in a congregation<lb/>
                which I <add>?</add> my time many and sacrificed<lb/> my health in aid of its
                pursuits. It grieves me<lb/> beyond measure that for all my labors and<lb/>
                <add>?</add> anticipations such should be the result<lb/> but I have the consolation
                of knowing that I have<lb/> performed my duty; and I can leave my pos<hi rend="sup"
                    >n</hi><lb/> with clean hands. I have thus my friend<lb/> unburdened myself to
                you and know that<lb/> when the time comes and you should be in<lb/> the land of the
                living you will do my memory<lb/> justice. I perceive with much surprise<lb/> from
                the proceedings of the late <add>?</add> of the remains<lb/> of <persName>Mr
                    Town</persName> that you were a Delegate from<lb/>
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>. I suppose from what I saw in the<lb/> Occident that
                    <persName>Mr Hart</persName> and yourself were to be<lb/> Delegates, from your
                city otherwise I should have<lb/> been most happy to have appointed you to<lb/>
                represent our congregation. <persName>Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> A.
                    Kursheedt</persName></p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>and <persName>Mr J Soria</persName> were the delegates appointed<lb/> to represent
                us. The latter, being unwell could<lb/> not go. I have <sic>writen</sic> you a long
                letter<lb/> with a pardon of one <add>?</add>, answer<lb/> me at your
                    <sic>leasure</sic> and believe me as ever<lb/> Your sincere friend</p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">J. De La Motta</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
