<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>
				
				</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<p>
				
				</p>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>
			
			</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>
					
				</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>
					
				</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note>
				
				</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
					<msDesc>
						<msIdentifier>
							<country>USA</country>
							<region>PA</region>
							<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
							<repository>LSKAP</repository>
							<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
							<idno>LSKAP0084</idno>
						</msIdentifier>
					</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R" facs="LSKAP0084_1R.jpg"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
				<date>17. Jany. 1826</date>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The final <sic>enquiry</sic> after my arrival here this morning<lb/>
				was the long lost bundle for <persName>Gen. Lingan</persName> as yet no such<lb/>
				package is within recollection and our friend <persName>Cohen</persName> was<lb/> by
				no means negligent in making applications. he still<lb/> says that some information
				of it may reach him when<lb/> it does you may rely upon his attention to forward it.
					<hi rend="underline">My</hi> impression is that it has been too long
				undiscovered<lb/> to be regained soon. however&#44; like all pious souls&#45;<lb/>
				we shall hope for the best.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Another commission I<lb/> had to execute for <persName>Ms.
					Jacobs</persName> in this place&#44; which<lb/> has proved fruitless and which I
				wish to mention<lb/> to <persName>Abba</persName> that she may convey the same to
				her&#8212;<lb/> The articles she desired me to get for her I have very diligently
					<sic>enquired</sic> for with the assistance of a friend<lb/> but cannot be
				procured. I will bear it in mind when<lb/> I get to <placeName>N. Y.</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">On <sic>sunday</sic> we had a tolerable pleast.<lb/> day down
					<placeName>James&#39; River</placeName> reach <placeName>Norfolk</placeName>
				about 11 at night<lb/> ate breakfast with <persName>Mr. Sol. Marks</persName>&#44;
				and took passage<lb/> at 11 on board the <rs>Virginia</rs>. the prospect of a quick
				&#38;<lb/> favorable passage was not promising. the wind being</p>
			<pb n="1V" facs="LSKAP0084_1V.jpg"/>
			<p>blustering. tho after under way for a few hours the<lb/> wind changed and with the
				exception of its being cold<lb/> we passd.<add>&#63;</add> a pleasant time. and
				arrived one hour sooner<lb/> than usual. On <date>Thursday</date> morning at
					<add>Hebrew</add> I shall take<lb/> stage for <placeName>Phila.</placeName> from
				which place I shall write to Mama<lb/> all particulars about family affairs. So
					thus<add>&#63;</add> far I have<lb/> opened correspondence with <hi
					rend="underline">you</hi> in detail of my journey&#8212;.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I hope that you and <persName>Meyer</persName> will lend all aid to
				keep<lb/> matters easy at home. dont let the folks starve for want of<lb/> good
				poultry. and by all means omit scolding at <persName>Julia</persName>.<lb/> and
					<sic>whiping</sic>
				<persName>George</persName> when they <sic>dont</sic> walk straight.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Great preparations I seem to be making among the wedding<lb/> folk
				at <placeName>Norfolk</placeName>.</p>
			<closer><salute><p rend="indent(1)">You will remember me to one and<lb/> all of the family. With best
				wishes for yourself.</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)">Yrs&#58;</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)">
				<hi rend="underline">
					<persName role="author">Dan. Judah</persName>
				</hi>
			</p>
			<pb n="2V" facs="LSKAP0084_2V.jpg"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<addressee>Mr. Isaac Leezer</addressee>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">Care of <persName>Dan&#58; Judah &#38; Co.</persName></p>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<placeName>Richmond</placeName>
			</p></salute></closer>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
