<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Pleasants, T. S.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0220</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Pleasants, T. S.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Beaver Dam, VA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1829-06" source="" attested="yes">June 20, 1829</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0220_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0220_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0220_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0220_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
			<p rend="indent(7)"><placeName>Beaver dam</placeName> <date>June 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1829</date></p>
				<p>My dear friend&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">I intended to write in the course of a few days&#44; tut the<lb/> note which I recd yesterday&#44; induces me to write immediately&#44; and to offer<lb/> some apology for my not calling on thee while in <placeName>Richmond</placeName> last week.  I left<lb/> home at a time that ill suited my convenience&#8212;though I full promised<lb/> myself the pleasure of an interview with thee.  After doing my little<lb/> business&#44; I was so tired &#38; exhausted&#44; and had so little time left&#44; that<lb/> I concluded&#44; very reluctantly&#44; to satisfy myself with a call on <persName>B. H.<lb/> Judah</persName> at the museum&#44; and to leave with him a message for thee&#44;<lb/> stating my disappointment &#38; regret at being deprived of the pleasure of<lb/> seeing thee.  Had I received the least intimation while there&#44; that thou<lb/> wouldst be down&#44; I would have remained.  But I did not know that<lb/> he sent thee word&#44; neither do I yet&#59; but I presume so&#44; from the fact of<lb/> thy hearing I was there.  I hope therefore&#44; my friend&#44; thou will ascribe my not<lb/> calling on thee to the right cause&#59; for I assure thee it would have given me the<lb/> highest gratification to see thee&#44; if I could have found time to have an hour or<lb/> two of conversation with thee.  I should have <sic>staid</sic> longer at the museum with<lb/> our friend <persName>B. H. Judah</persName>&#44; with whose urbanity I was highly pleased&#59; but we<lb/> were interrupted by visitors&#44; &#38; as I expected his duty required he should<lb/> wait on them&#44; I withdrew.  He appears to be a man well versed in Hebrew<lb/> learning&#44; &#38; of much intelligence&#59; but above all he possesses I think in a<lb/> great degree&#44; the virtue of charity&#59; the brightest gem which can adorn the<lb/> profession of religion.  It is truly gratifying to meet with a man of such<lb/> enlarged views&#59; &#38; the last <sic>enquiry</sic> I would make concerning him&#44; would be&#44;<lb/> to what particular profession he belonged&#63; for where we see virtue &#38; charity &#38;<lb/> humility abound&#44; we should never avil<add>&#63;</add> about particular modes of belief.<lb/>  Those amiable feelings&#44; are in all&#44; the legitimate offspring of the divine perfection&#44;<lb/> the influences of which are universal&#44; in proportion to the reciprocal action<lb/> on the part of the creature.  Such being the impressions I feel towards him&#44; I was<lb/> sorry to be interrupted&#44; especially as I wished to gain some information from</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>an authentic source of the present state of the Jews&#44; their manners &#38;c.  While in<lb/> conversation he offered me a controversial work&#44; the letters of <persName>D. Levi</persName> to <persName>Dr.<lb/> Priestly</persName> on the merits &#38; evidences of their respective religions.  I did not intend<lb/> to write to thee until I had done reading it&#44; but having finished the first series<lb/> &#38; made some progress in the second&#44; I can form some judgment of its execution.<lb/>  He is a writer of very considerable talent&#44; and great ingenuity.  His exposition of<lb/> the prophecy of <persName>David</persName> was new to me&#58; as well as some of his translations of<lb/> Hebrew terms&#59; of which however I am no judge.  The common mass of mankind<lb/> has to depend very much on the learned for a correct interpretation of many<lb/> passages of scripture&#44; and when they differ among themselves&#44; what are the ignorant<lb/> to do&#63;  &#8220;Who shall decide where doctors disagree&#8221;&#63;  As long as this is the case&#44;<lb/> controversy must be endless&#44; in respect to particular doctrines&#59; and we must<lb/> therefore be left to do that which we know to be right&#44; by cultivating every<lb/> virtue&#44; doing injury to none&#44; and <sic>practising</sic> all the good we can.  This is the<lb/> end&#44; doubtless&#44; of the law &#38; the prophets.  Indeed&#44; my friend&#44; I delight to contemplate&#44;<lb/> the <hi rend="underline">practical</hi> exhibition of those sublime principles which ought to regulate our<lb/> lives&#44; for more than the mere profession of them.  To return to <persName>Levi&#39;s</persName> work&#44;<lb/> I think many of his arguments against the new testament might be<lb/> readily answered.  Sagacious critics may no doubt be able to make<lb/> many things appear absurd&#44; which are founded on truth.  For a controversial<lb/> writer though&#44; he is very exempt from bitterness&#44; and I am reading his book<lb/> with a good deal of interest&#59; for I am always pleased to see both sides.<lb/>  Many of his strictures are very just on the Christians&#44; particularly when he<lb/> speaks of the animosity between different sects&#8212;a fact which I confess gives<lb/> a powerful advantage to our opponents&#44; and which has sometimes almost<lb/> disgusted me with the name of Christian.  This has been the rock on which many<lb/> have split in their search after  truth&#44; when they judged of the Christian religion<lb/> by the acts of its professors&#59; thereby denying such a principle as vital&#44; redeeming<lb/> religion to exist in any people.  But as <persName>D. Levi</persName> himself candidly &#38; zealously<lb/> admits&#44; the new testament does not <sic>authorise</sic> such <sic>abberation</sic> from the law<lb/> of moral rectitude.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I should have answered thy last valued letter&#44; received some weeks<lb/> since&#44; but that I flattered myself I should have had the pleasure to acknowledge<lb/> it in person.  I can only account for our friend <persName>J. P. Staker&#39;s</persName> not writing from</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>the circumstance that he received an important appointment immediately on<lb/> his return home in the <placeName>Baltimore</placeName> rail Road Company&#44; which together with the<lb/> arrangements previous to entering upon its duties occupied nearly all his time.<lb/>  Indeed I have only received a very few lines&#44; at a time&#44; from him since he left<lb/> me&#44; though when he is at leisure I get a letter from him almost every week.<lb/>  I am sorry now he did not leave his letter with me&#44; to copy &#40;as he wrote it in<lb/> a hurry &#38; it required a few corrections&#41;&#44; but I thought he could do it himself much<lb/> better.  I have written to him about it&#44; but have received no answer yet.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I assure thee my dear friend&#44; I feel very much gratified that my correspondence<lb/> should&#44; on account of the spirit of moderation which I sincerely felt&#44; have recd.<lb/> such a compliment from a Jew as it did from thy friend <persName>Jacob Mordecai</persName>.  It<lb/> is a very desirable thing to gain the respect of our opponents&#44; so seldom the<lb/> fruit of religious controversy.  Hard names are never productive of any benefit.  I<lb/> think I have informed thee before&#44; of the pleasure which the perusal of thy letter<lb/> by one or two of my friends afforded them&#44; one of whom congratulated me on the<lb/> agreeable result of gaining a friend instead of making an enemy by religious<lb/> disputation.  When I quoted the passage from Deuteronomy in my last letter<lb/> I was not fully aware that it was so literally complied with by the Jews.<lb/>  I thought however&#44; &#38; I still think&#44; that <hi rend="underline">literally</hi>&#44; the words &#8220;when thou liest<lb/> down &#38; when thou risest up &#38; when tho walkest by the way &#38;c&#8221; might embrace<lb/> almost ever division of time.  I did not intend to convey the idea that it<lb/> was impracticable to love God above all things&#58; by no means.  I hope &#38; believe<lb/> it is attainable both by Jew &#38; Gentile.  If I recollect right&#44; there were certain<lb/> parts which I underscored&#44; some of which I thought it would be difficult to<lb/> comply with&#44; particularly that which requires the commandment to be placed as front<lb/>lets between the eyes.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I learned from <persName>B. H. Judah</persName> the probability that thou mightest take charge<lb/> of the Jewish Congregation in <placeName>Philada</placeName>.  If this be so&#44; and it should compel<lb/> thee to leave <placeName>Richmond</placeName> before I go down again&#44; it will produce a lasting regret<lb/> on my mind that I did not see thee when I was down.  If the offer should<lb/> be accepted I yet cherish the hope that I may have the pleasure of seeing<lb/> thee before they departure.  I shall be glad to know they decision on the subject.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I recd. The whig thou sent me some weeks since&#44; but did not get the<lb/> letter which accompanied it.  Please to give my respects to <persName>B. H. Judah</persName><lb/> and believe me to be very sincerely thy friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">T S Pleasants</persName></p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
			<p rend="indent(5)"><addressee>Mr. Isaac Leeser</addressee>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)"><placeName>Richmond</placeName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
