<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Bomeisler, Evelyn</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0156</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Bomeisler, Evelyn</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0156_1r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0156_1v.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0156_2r.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="LSKAP0156_2v.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><add>&#63;</add></p>
				<p rend="align(center)">The Eighth Anniversary Meeting of the Jewish Foster</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">Home Society of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">Report</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Another circle of months is perfected since our<lb/> last anniversary&#44; and trusting to enlist your earnest<lb/> interest and reawaken your sympathies we present to<lb/> the friends and members of &#8220;The Jewish Foster Home Sy&#8221;&#44; the<lb/> Eighth Annual record of its progress&#44; condition and<lb/> requirements.  To relieve distress&#44; to rescue innocence<lb/> from temptation&#44; to inculcate upon the minds of those<lb/> committed to our charge a knowledge of our holy<lb/> faith&#44; and in so doing foster in their hearts a love and<lb/> veneration for its sacred teachings &#38; obligations and<lb/> prepare them for all moral and social responsibilities<lb/> that may await them&#44; are the objects and aim of the<lb/> Institution&#44;&#8212;considerations that appeal equally to our<lb/> pride and principles&#44; and constitute the superstructure<lb/> that can be perfected only by the combined efforts<lb/> and influence of our people in giving aid&#44; strength<lb/> and substantial permanency to its foundation&#8212;<lb/> as unity is the watch&#45;word of our nation&#44; so should<lb/> unanimity be the main spring of our associated<lb/> charities.  A noble bridge spanning one of the<lb/> beautiful rivers of our own state becomes more secure<lb/> more stable in proportion to the pressure brought<lb/> to bear upon it&#8212;beautiful would be our record<lb/> if in our emergencies our friends would willingly so</p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>exert their energies and capabilities that we might<lb/> feel the assurance of a firmer more enduring<lb/> establishment.  The increased rates of provisions &#38;c<lb/> tell seriously &#38; ominously upon our means&#8212;the<lb/> detailed account of the Treasurer will give the financial<lb/> state of the Society&#8212;we have been obliged to dispose<lb/> of <add>&#63;</add> stock&#44; which was effected</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Our receipts inclusive of donations and subscriptions<lb/> <add>&#38; a balance of last year of 361.19</add> amount to &#36;<del>2260.64</del>2499.45&#44; the expenditures of the Society to #2460.64<lb/> balance 245.29 Owing to the unfortunate state of our Country&#44;<lb/> the subscription from our Southern friends is very limited&#8212;<lb/> To our Triennial Subscribers we return our cordial<lb/> thanks&#8212;&#44; their obligations expire with this year&#44;&#8212;<lb/> it has been suggested that in view of our present<lb/> need&#44; many would be induced to continue their<lb/> subscriptions for a renewed limited period&#8212;we<lb/> respectfully present the matter for your consideration.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Since our last meeting children have been admitted<lb/> into the Home&#8212;three have been removed their parents being<lb/> enabled to maintain them&#44; &#8212;one has been indentured to a<lb/> trade&#8212;Another has been called from our band under<lb/> sad circumstances&#8212;from the midst of the youthful<lb/> family of the &#39;Home&#39;&#44; a bright little boy of nine years of<lb/> age was summoned to his Heavenly home&#8212;he died<lb/> suddenly from internal injuries received from a fall&#44;<lb/> while on his way to school&#44; and notwithstanding<lb/> the most careful attendance of the physician and</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
				<p>the motherly kindness of the matron&#44; his case proved<lb/> beyond the reach of all human skill&#8212;His <add>The</add> funeral<lb/> arrangements were conducted by his relatives and members<lb/> of the <del>Board</del> Home&#44;&#8212;the <persName>Rev. S. Morais</persName> addressed the children<lb/> impressively on the occasion&#44; when with the usual last<lb/> rites&#44; his remains were interred in the <placeName>Federal St</placeName><lb/> cemetery&#44;&#8212;the lot was presented by the Congregation Mickve<lb/> Israel.  Since our organization five boys have<lb/> attained their religious majority&#44; which in each case<lb/> has been solemnized in synagogue and joyfully<lb/> celebrated at the Home&#8212;it has been the privilege of the<lb/> young Bar&#45;mitzvah to invite all his seniors who may<lb/> have left the Institution to enter upon life&#39;s duties&#44; to<lb/> celebrate the day with him at the Home&#8212;the affectionate<lb/> intimacy existing between those whose paths are now<lb/> cast in separate places&#44; which these re&#45;unions tend<lb/> to strengthen&#44; will we hope be life&#45;long and useful<lb/> in its consequences.&#42;  All accounts of the boys who<lb/> have been indentured are entirely satisfactory&#8212;the<lb/> eldest now in his 18th year&#44; appropriates a regular<lb/> monthly allowance to his mother&#8212;his term of apprenticeship<lb/> expired some time since&#44; but he still remains with<lb/> his employer from whom he receives the kindest<lb/> paternal care.  Two boys yet remain in the Institution<lb/> who are of a suitable age to be placed to a trade&#44; as<lb/> soon as an eligible situation can be secured for<lb/> them.  We are happy here to express our warm</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>appreciation of the ability and fidelity of the matron<lb/> she exerts a most <sic>happyfying</sic> influence upon the<lb/> children so intimately dependent upon her.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We regret having been obliged to dispense with the<lb/> useful services of <persName>Mrs. M. Dormitzer</persName> as a manager of the<lb/> Society&#8212;&#44; the Board cordially unite in an expression<lb/> of kind wishes for her perfect restoration to health.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">A legacy of &#36;50 has been bequested to the Society from<lb/> the benevolence of <persName>Mrs. B. Spanier</persName>&#44; deceased.  Twenty dollars<lb/> were realized by the disposal of a tasteful ornamental<lb/> sofa&#45;cushion&#44; presented by <persName>Mrs. J. L. Filerance</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">To <persName>Dr. A.C. Bournonville</persName> we would express our reserved<lb/> obligations&#8212;he is unwearying in his attention&#44; and<lb/> unremitting in his kindness.  From the German Ladies<lb/> Sewing Society we received a handsome donation of<lb/> clothing&#8212;we are extremely indebted for their contributions<lb/> during this and the preceding year.  We would also<lb/> make acknowledgments to <persName>Dr. D. Roberts</persName>&#44; Dental Surgeon&#44; to the<lb/> Hebrew Education Sy&#44; and to all friends from whom we have<lb/> received gifts or services.  To <persName>Mr Alfred A. Allen</persName>&#44; Conveyances&#44; we<lb/> are indebted for gratuitous services and disinterested<lb/> exertions<add>&#63;</add> in behalf of the Home.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We earnestly ask the protection of the Most High<lb/> trusting that <sic>that</sic> His kind Providence may shield<lb/> &#38; bless us now &#38; evermore.</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)">&#8212;<persName role="author">Evelyn Bomeisler</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(6)">Sec.</p>
				<p>&#42; For instruction &#38; preparation of <add>two of</add> the boys<lb/> for the reading of their Bar Mitzvah portions&#44; we<lb/> are deeply indebted to <persName>Miss S. C. Peixotta</persName>&#44; who kindly<lb/> and opportunely volunteered her efficient services.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
