<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Judah, David</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0219</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Judah, David</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Richmond, VA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1829-06">June 26, 1829</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0219_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0219_1v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 1 sheet <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">Tall. <date>26 June. 1829</date>.</p>
            <p>Dear <addressee>Isaac</addressee>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Your <del>mms.</del> came safe to hand. not having entire<lb/>
                confidence in my own opinions upon the merits of your work, I deemed it<lb/> much
                more to your interest to forwarded to <persName>Mr. Etting</persName> (a man high in
                society<lb/> and fully competent to judge whether the work ought to be farther
                revised<lb/> and corrected, as by a single remark in your letter I suspect it does.
                    <persName>Mr Mordecai</persName><lb/> ought never to have permitted it to pass
                from his hands without having it in<lb/> every shape alike honorable to yourself and
                to the public hence he ought to<lb/> have pointed out all its errors to you which he
                had remarked to <persName>Mr. Peioxato</persName>-<lb/> It is a work of too much
                importance to be lightly cast off and put to pass-<lb/> and believe me your
                reputation will sink or swim by its success. Therefore<lb/> be not to precipitate in
                your <sic>writes</sic> to have it published till you are thoroughly<lb/> convinced
                by the decisions of others competent to decide upon its merits that<lb/> honor and
                profit is to be the result. <sic>Where</sic> I in your place I would solicit<lb/>
                every investigation and leave not a loop to hang a doubt upon for criticism<lb/>
                either in style spelling or punctuation, but let every thing bear you forward.<lb/>
                These remarks are in the truest spirit of friendship, for I am looking always<lb/>
                forward and never satisfied with the present. So shall I look towards you.<lb/> I
                hope to see you take a high and honorable stand in the literary world for<lb/>
                yourself and our society. I fear also that your ambition and the warmth of<lb/> your
                friends will make you o'er leap the bounds of prudence. A stability of<lb/>
                character is wanting <persName>Isaac</persName> in all men who come before the
                public and<lb/> this world is more apt to judge harshly than favorable of us. I am never<lb/>
                <add>?</add> for repassing<add>?</add> the vigilance and perseverance of youthful
                ambitions, go on<lb/> to the very summit, but each step must improve as you
                progress—let but<lb/> the basement be punishment you bring so you have every thing
                to expect.</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>I shall take occasion on <date>Sunday</date> next to go out to <persName>Mr.
                    Etting</persName> he will then<lb/> have got so far into the work as to give
                some opinion upon it be it what it may<lb/> favorable or otherways. I shall feel it
                my duty to express it to you in the most liberal<lb/> manner, for having accepted of
                my duties to aid you thro this business and “leaving<lb/> you to act as I think
                best” I am decidedly of opinion that this shall be no<lb/> hurry off matters. <del>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del> of so much importance. If the course which<lb/> I suggest is not
                    <sic>compatable</sic> to your wishes, say so, and I will forward it to
                    <placeName>Philad</placeName>-<lb/> to <persName>Mr. Piexotto</persName> or
                return it to you without taking any farther interest then being<lb/> permitted to
                subscribe for a few copies. For altho I have been crooked in my<lb/> affairs
                generally, much of that was the result of friends and friendly <sic>advise</sic>.
                Seldom<lb/> when I think on serious matters that I am not correct in my views, therefore<lb/>
                <persName>Isaac</persName> draw your attention to that rock which many have split
                upon.</p>
            <p>I shall now rest till <persName>Mr. Etting</persName> has gotten through with the
                work, then I shall<lb/> over look it myself, and, as far as I can, so will I express
                myself to you. I shall<lb/> be absent about three weeks but the nos shall be kept
                safe in my absence<lb/> and nothing shall go contrary to your desires in any
                arrangmt. which I may<lb/> make with the publishers.</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">With best affections.</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">Yrs.</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">
                <hi rend="underline">
                    <persName role="author">Dav. Judah</persName>
                </hi>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
