<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Schwarz, Joseph, Rabbi; Levy, Jadok, Rabbi</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP0295</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Schwarz, Joseph, Rabbi; Levy, Jadok, Rabbi</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">&#8220;the Friends of the Israelites of Palestine&#8221;</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1849-08" source="" attested="yes">August 1849</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1849-08" source="" attested="yes">13 Elul 5609</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_kaplan_20_953_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 2 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1R"/>
				<p>make with this<lb/> and the certificates about<lb/> three pages&#44; and print<lb/> 200 copies&#44; or 8 quires<lb/> on letter sheet<lb/> <hi rend="underline">new</hi> <add>&#63;</add>.</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">To the <addressee>Friends of the Israelites of Palestine</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Knowing that the descendants of <placeName>Israel</placeName> have not relinquished<lb/> the ancient character of benevolence for which they have been<lb/> always distinguished the undersigned messengers from the <placeName>Holy<lb/> Land</placeName>&#44; beg <add>&#63;</add> to lay before you the following statement&#44;<lb/> in the full hope that it may incite you to aid the small rem<lb/>nant yet residing in the country over which once ruled chiefs<lb/> and princes governing in the spirit of our religion&#44; and when<lb/> spoke the ports and prophets of our own race in a language<lb/> never to be forgotten.  It was owing to our transgressions that<lb/> we as a nation were banished from that land&#44; where formerly<lb/> <del>there</del> reigned plenty and elegance&#44; but where now all in desolation<lb/> and ruin.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">For several centuries after the destruction of the Temple<lb/> and the final expulsion of the people after the unsuccessful strug&#45;<lb/>gle for freedom under the guidance of <persName>Bar Cochaba</persName> against the<lb/> legions led on by the captains of <persName>Aelian Hadrian</persName>&#44; the Israelites<lb/> were not permitted to dwell in their own patrimony&#44; the <add>&#63;</add> of their<lb/> fathers was not permitted to be hidden by them&#44; as though the<lb/> presence of the Hebrew would be signal for rebellion&#44; and recall<lb/> the ancient freedom which was making into decay under the<lb/> despotism of the Roman Emperors <add>and only on the payment of a ton were they permitted to repair singly to<lb/> the ruins of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> to weep there over the subversion of their state and were<lb/> when compelled there to return again to their<lb/> exile homes.</add>  But with the over throw<lb/> of the Christian powers by the <persName>Mohamed</persName> and many Jews gradually<lb/> sought the desolate fields of their own land&#44; and established themselves<lb/> in its waste places amidst fear and trembling.  This land pro&#45;<lb/>tected though oppressed by the followers of the Koran.  And when the<lb/> crusaders in their mad attempt to become what they <add>&#63;</add></p>
			<pb n="1V"/>
				<p>the burial place of the founder of their religion made war against<lb/> the Saracens&#44; the Israelites were found stoutly defending the <placeName>Holy City</placeName><lb/> by the side of their <sic>Moslim</sic> protectors&#44; and when <del>the city</del> it was at length<lb/> taken&#44; the blood of our brothers flowed like water in its streets&#59;<lb/> and reeking with slaughter the Christian knights returned thanks<lb/> for the victory which they fancied would secure them the possession<lb/> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> &#38; <placeName>Palestine</placeName>.  But their reign was brief&#44; and the<lb/> <persName><sic>Soltan</sic></persName> of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>&#44; <persName>Saladdin</persName>&#44; recovered what his predecessor had<lb/> lost&#44; and ever since <placeName>Palestine</placeName> has remained the p<add>&#63;</add>tion of the<lb/> followers of <persName><sic>Mahomed</sic></persName>.  Although under them too an lot<lb/> has been exceedingly grievous&#44; exposed as we are to the rapacity<lb/> of the Pachas and the <add>&#63;</add> of the Arab plunderers who<lb/> have infested the land from time immemorial&#58; still the land of<lb/> <placeName>Israel</placeName> has been a place of refuge to us in many a trouble&#59;<lb/> and when the inquisition of <placeName>Spain</placeName> induced the <persName>king and queen</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Castillo</placeName>&#44; <persName>Ferdinand</persName> &#38; <persName>Isabella</persName> to expel the Jews from the<lb/> <placeName>Iberian Peninsula</placeName>&#44; followers as they soon were by the <persName>king</persName><lb/> of <placeName>Portugal</placeName>&#44; thousands turned their steps to the st<add>&#63;</add> <placeName>Pa&#45;<lb/>lestine</placeName>&#44; and became the founders of the Portuguese congrega&#45;<lb/>tions still existing there&#44; and the carried with them as to<lb/> other parts of <placeName>Turkey</placeName>&#44; the language of <placeName>Spain</placeName> which still<lb/> continues their vernacular lingue.  By de<add>&#63;</add> other<lb/> emigrants from <placeName>Africa</placeName>&#44; <placeName>Poland</placeName> &#38; <placeName>Germany</placeName> joined them&#59;<lb/> and all along with a holy devotion&#44; amidst every <add>&#63;</add><lb/>tion to the place of the sepulchre of their fathers&#44; a land<lb/> endeared to every son of <placeName>Israel</placeName> by the great deeds which were<lb/> wrought there in their behalf.</p>
			<pb n="2R"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)">A <persName>Don Joseph Caro</persName>&#44; a <persName>Rabbi Isaac Luria</persName> and the great names<lb/> have flourished from time to time in the genial clime of the<lb/> land of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; <add>&#63;</add> the migrations of which we have just spoken&#59;<lb/> but with all this the Israelites there are subject to great many<lb/> deprivations&#44; and are necessarily dependent on the aid of others<lb/> for their support.  It is not now as formerly&#44; that the whole land<lb/> is covered with villages and farms&#44; and every foot of ground ren&#45;<lb/>dered productive by the industry of man&#59; for the far larger number of towns<lb/> are totally destroyed&#44; and the land is waste because there are<lb/> no inhabitants to cultivate it.  The terraces on the hills which<lb/> produced food in abundance have been washed away by<lb/> the winter rains&#59; since the industry of the husband man has<lb/> ceased to guard them against destruction&#59; and what land<lb/> is still productive lies fallow because of the wandering<lb/> <sic>Beduin</sic>&#44; who loves to reap when he has not sowed.  Com&#45;<lb/>merce is scarcely known&#59; <del>&#63;</del> navigation is not attended to&#59;<lb/> the mechanic arts are not needed in a country when the inha&#45;<lb/>bitants have so few wants as the roving Arabs who now dwell<lb/> there&#59; <sic>wherfore</sic> with all their efforts it is almost impossible for<lb/> the few Israelites&#44; who chiefly dwell at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>&#44; <placeName>Hebron</placeName>&#44;<lb/> <placeName>Z<add>&#63;</add></placeName> <placeName>Tiberia</placeName> to obtain a livelihood.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It has accordingly been the practice of European Jews to<lb/> aid their brothers in <placeName>Palestine</placeName> with annual donations&#44; to collect<lb/> which messengers were sent out to bring the funds to the managers<lb/> in the chief cities just named.  But the expenses attending this<lb/> mode are evidently very great&#44; and to obviate this&#44; the undersigned<lb/> accredited messengers from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> have been instructed to appeal<lb/> to all congregations in <placeName>America</placeName> to organize a permanent relief</p>
			<pb n="2V"/>
				<p>fund&#44; to consist of free will offerings&#44; annual collections and stated<lb/> contributions&#44; which are to be forwarded to such persons as the<lb/> Israelites of this country may themselves designate&#44; and distri&#45;<lb/>buted in good faith and impartially among all who stand in<lb/> need of assistance.  The subjoined certificates will at once show that<lb/> a number of influential persons in this country have already offered<lb/> their services&#59; and we hope that you will induce your congregation or<lb/> immediate friends to be active in the cause&#44; and to send out through<lb/> a committee in your own neighborhood or the various gentlemen<lb/> here named in <placeName>New York</placeName> and <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> any fund you may collect.<lb/>  The Portuguese congregation in <placeName>New York</placeName> have already appropriated &#36;25<lb/> per annum&#59; other bodies in that place have followed with similar donations<lb/> and all this independently of the Hebra <add>Hebrew</add> whose object it is to<lb/> aid the poor of the <placeName>Holy Land</placeName>.  In case our appeal is responded to&#44;<lb/> we can assure our brethren in <placeName>America</placeName> that the congregations<lb/> in <placeName>Palestine</placeName> will not send out any more <del>any</del> special<lb/> messengers&#44; wherefore <del>they</del> you will not hereafter be troubled by <del>any</del><lb/> personal applicants.  Due notice will be given as soon as possible<lb/> of the distributing commission to be appointed in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>&#44; and we<lb/> can give the most positive assurance that the wishes of the donor shall<lb/> be faithfully carried into effect.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><add>&#63;</add> the blessing of God on you all we sign ourselves</p>
			<p rend="indent(5)">your brothers</p>
			<p rend="indent(6)"><persName role="author">Rabbi Joseph Schwarz</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(6)"><persName role="author">Rabbi Jadok Levy</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(6)">messengers from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName></p>
				<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date>Elul 13th. 5609</date></p>
			
			<div>
				<p><ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_7_7.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume 7 No. 7 pages 345 through 348. Click here to view.</ref></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
