<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">W.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0234</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">W.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0234_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0234_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0234_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0234_2v.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">To the Editor of the Occident!</p>
            <p>Rev. Sir!<lb/> In the <date>April</date> Number of the Occident<lb/> I found an
                article by one who adopts <add>אמת</add> for his name,<lb/> but it is indeed the
                first time, that I see “truth” controdic<lb/>ting itself, a <sic>fictious</sic>
                truth is the newest of all the<lb/> phantomes of the modern time. Permit me, Sir, to
                state<lb/> some words against that article. The highly learned<lb/> “truth” expounds
                (page 5) “The Occident cannot signify<lb/> news or light from the western states,
                but <add>?</add> to instruct<lb/> „the Israelites.” I suppose in my humble opinion,
                it is the<lb/> very problem of a jewish journal to represent the present<lb/>
                history of our people as much as accessible, all other articles<lb/> are a mere
                addition to attire the pamphlet, or a history<lb/> of hebrew literature of the day,
                causes and <sic>consoquences</sic> of<lb/> the ruling spirit of the age. Truth will
                find the motto<lb/> of the Occident <sic>corrosponding</sic> with my views about
                Journalism,<lb/> if he merely considers, that old latin proverb: Historia<lb/> mater
                vitae est. History is indeed the teacher of life and<lb/> the best conductor through
                the career of life; History is<lb/> a second and very distinct revelation. God
                placed <persName>Moses</persName><lb/> on a rack, where he should learn to know God
                by His<lb/> divine Attributes. <persName>Maimonides</persName> calls that rock
                “nature”<lb/> and I add to it “History” both of them reveal the God of<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> in His Glory and Majesty. <persName>Tages'</persName>
                “Truth” says: “and<lb/> „thirdly how to conduct themselves towards their
                neighbors<lb/> „which latter duty includes, according to the Talmud, the
                    <sic>observence</sic><lb/> „of the whole religion” I most
                    emphilically<add>?</add> object against<lb/> such an atheistical statement,
                where, O <sic>fictious</sic> truth! Where<lb/> is <date>Sabbath</date>, Festivals,
                Milah, Shehite, Tefilin, Mesusah,<lb/> Zizith, Pidyon Bechar, Mazah and many other
                commands<lb/> understood under, love they neighbor? He pleases to translate<lb/> the
                word of the Talmud <add>ואהבת לרעך כמוך זו כלל גדול שבת</add>, And thou<lb/> shalt
                love they neighbour as thyself, is the principal<lb/> command of the law; but every
                one will understand that the<lb/>
                <add>ש of שבתורה</add> could be spared, I presume, it ought<lb/> to be translated:
                Love thy neighbor as thyself is one of<lb/> the grand principles of our law, but
                there are still others</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>principles and germs, as: love God, be holy etc but they are<lb/> above the horizon
                of many people, as it was the case<lb/> with the Prosalite demanding of
                    <persName>Hillel</persName> to learn him all<lb/> the Torah while standing on
                one foot. Does perhaps Truth suppose<lb/> we shall learn to love our God to become
                fit and willingly<lb/> to love our neighbour? Now, Sir, we love our neighbour
                in<lb/> order to learn to love also our God, then the latter is a<lb/> higher
                principle than the former. Or does he suppose, that we shall be holy in order that
                our manners and feelings<lb/> towards our fellow-mortal should be pure? That is
                the<lb/> beginning but the end of it shall be: to serve God with a<lb/> pure heart
                with a spotless mind. “Truth” <del>is</del> does not know<lb/> neither the true
                problem of Journalism nor the principles<lb/> of our religion. His views are clearly
                those of a Chabasnic<add>?</add><lb/> Chasid, or with english words of a jewish
                methodist,<lb/> as they have been masterly described by <persName>Dr.
                    Lilienthal</persName>,<lb/> ignorance, arrogance and <sic>hypocracy</sic> mixed
                up with a good<lb/> portion of superstition and prejudice are the attributes of
                the<lb/> majority of the so called Chasidim in Tolland and Rupia,<lb/> but
                    <persName>Dr. Lilienthal</persName> treated them with too much modesty,
                therefore<lb/> the representative of that class in <placeName>America</placeName>
                charges him<lb/> with the tendency to break down the fences of our sages.<lb/> He
                did not <sic>proof</sic> his arrogant presumption, not because<lb/> he would not,
                merely because he could not. We shall<lb/> petition the Congress at
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, to call Truth to<lb/> the Censorship for the
                american jewish press, and we<lb/> will soon have a prompt Zianmächter. Next<lb/>
                Truth comes out with his well studied phraseology against<lb/> the advertisement of
                the <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <sic>congrigation</sic>, he is<lb/> aversed to their kind of reading the Bible, and
                his argument<lb/> to condemn them is, that the annual reading was already
                intro=<lb/>duced by Ezra, <add>נקרא ומתורגם</add> is also a doctrine of
                    <persName>Ezra</persName>
                <add>שלחו מרים</add><lb/> is another doctrine of <persName>Ezra</persName>, who
                entitled us to violate these<lb/> doctrines? none under heaven, even not Truth. He
                thunders<lb/> about their <sic>pasion</sic> to read the Bible, but against the
                organ<lb/> in the Synagogue, english prayers <add>?</add> he knows of nothing<lb/>
                to state about. How ignorant is Truth”!</p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>He comes out in a particular manner against the violation<lb/> of the second
                festivals; page 8 he says, that God commanded<lb/> You shall not add to nor
                diminish! Thou shalt not<lb/> turn from the word to the right or to the left!
                then<lb/> he gives as the reason of the second festivals <add>משנה</add>, that
                is<lb/> indeed below criticism. I will not rectify the steps of<lb/> the
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <sic>Congrigation</sic>, I will but show how short-<lb/>sighted “Truth” is, there
                are much better reasons in the<lb/>
                <add>חכמי התלמוד</add> for the second festival but Truth did not know<lb/> them;
                there are reasons, which do not <sic>controdict</sic> the<lb/> above mentioned
                biblical quotation but “Truth” knows<lb/> nothing of them. Then Truth thunders
                against the articles<lb/> of <sic>Talmid</sic> and <persName>H. G.</persName>,
                supposing they should have discussed<lb/> their disagreements in their own study
                    <sic>privatly</sic> among<lb/> themselves. These articles have been published
                for the purpose<lb/> to ashame all those omniscient and all-understanding<lb/>
                <sic>schoolars</sic> like “Truth”, that they are not mindful enough<lb/> to write a
                single word in <sic>defence</sic> of their own religion.<lb/> “Truth” refers
                    <sic>Talmid</sic> to the <add>חכמי התלמוד</add>, but, Sir, what<lb/> say the
                    <add>אתרוגים מורכבים</add>? If you know it, you may say it, that<lb/> also the
                public may know it and <sic>Talmid</sic> be controdicted.<lb/> A jewish Journal
                publishes <persName>Clesphamons</persName> articles against<lb/> Judaism, based
                altogether upon one error, the Editor<lb/> published them to awaken the sleeping
                    <sic>schoolars</sic> of the<lb/> western hemisphere, and—O pity! O tempers! O
                mores!<lb/>—“Truth” arose and wishes, a journal of this enlightened<lb/> age shall
                fill up its columnes with discussions about<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, about Lard Oil, shall teach the people<lb/> a better knowledge of
                the hebrew, Jemara and Kebalah—<lb/>
                <add>?</add>balah—did you hear it? There is the Chahatnic Chasic</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>It is a pity to meet such dark midnights under the sun<lb/> of this all-exploring
                age, and I deem it proper to disclose<lb/> to the public eye how dark this midnight
                is; therefore<lb/> you may please to assert this in the next number<lb/> of the
                Occident, but if you can not, you may please<lb/> to send it back to me, for I am
                sure that during<lb/> a space of two months other people will address<lb/> that so
                called Truth. I should have signed my name justice but I am truly your friend</p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">W.</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="The following is written sideways in the center of the page."/>
            <p>
                <hi rend="underline">
                    <addressee>Rev. Mr. Is. Leeser</addressee>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Editor of the Occident</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <placeName>
                    <hi rend="underline">Philadelphia</hi>
                </placeName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
