<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY % teibase SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schema.dtd">
%teibase;
<!ENTITY % teiext SYSTEM "http://bslw.com/UPENN_TEI_schext.dtd">
%teiext;
]>
<TEI>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Halevi, Joseph L.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSKAP</repository>
						<collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American Judaica</collection>
						<idno>LSKAP_NC-25</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Halevi, Joseph L.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1852-08" source="" attested="yes">August 1852</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_1.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_2.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_3.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_4.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_5.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_6.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_7.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_8.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="leeser_05_2011_nc_25_9.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>8 pages on 8 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="restricted">
								<p>Restricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p><hi rend="underline"><add>Yiddish</add>&#45;<add>German</add></hi></p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><date><hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi>&#44; Pericope E Keb</date>&#44;</p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><date>&#40;August&#41;&#44; 1852</date>.</p>
				<p>May he go up upon the heights of good fortune<lb/> and find deliverance from all the evils of the<lb/> time&#44; etc. etc. my dear and accomplished friend&#44;<lb/> <persName>Rabbi Itzik Leeser</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Almost three months have passed since I<lb/> received your very welcome letter for which I owe you<lb/> an answer.  I blush with shame over this delay&#44;<lb/> and beg your forgiveness for it.  Your correspon&#45;<lb/>dence with your trusted friend&#44; <persName>Shaftstone</persName>&#44; with<lb/> which you honored me&#44; has increased tenfold my<lb/> respect for you and I shall never fail to reveal&#44;<lb/> whenever it be possible&#44; this high esteem and re&#45;<lb/>spect by word or deed.  For the most part the cause<lb/> of my prolonged silence has been the following&#58;<lb/> you suggested to me that I must prepare myself<lb/> for an attack of even greater men than <persName>Ben Yehuda</persName> and <persName>S. A.</persName>&#44;<lb/> for I considered it unworthy to reply to their<lb/> stupid criticism.  I was anxious for the publication of<lb/> the apology &#40;or explanation&#41; which I had sent to you&#44;<lb/> in order to see the criticism which would follow it.<lb/>  Now  I have the pleasure to see my article in <del>your</del> two<lb/> monthly issues.  While the second month&#39;s issue was not<lb/> yet here we already received in the &#34;Asmonean&#34; a<lb/> translation of it in English.  I understand nothing<lb/> about this&#44; but my son&#45;in&#45;law&#44; <persName>Mr. Widenthal</persName>&#44;</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">2</p>
				<p>who is a mater of both languages&#44; told me<lb/> that it was a good translation&#44; except for one<lb/> point&#44; namely&#44; the expression &#34;For the sake of making<lb/> her angry&#34; was not translated in the meaning I in&#45;<lb/>tended to give it.  Now the <del>intro</del> editorial note says<lb/> that the next issue will contain their comments.<lb/>  I look forward to these with eagerness&#44; for I was<lb/> never afraid and am not afraid now of this thing.<lb/>  But three weekly issues have already <sic>appeered</sic><lb/> in <placeName>New York</placeName> and not a line about this.  <del>That you</del><lb/> As to the matter of your <del>advice</del> desire not to print the omitted<lb/> point with regard to <persName>Kalisch</persName>&#44; we shall for the moment<lb/> declare a truce&#44; until the matter is further clarified.<lb/>  In reality he deserves no consideration.  I hope<lb/> one other point will come to my defense&#8212;namely<lb/> that I know I have not acted contrary to Biblical<lb/> law.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Among other things&#44; you write that I have<lb/> won much&#44; in that my name has become known<lb/> throughout the land.  I don&#39;t put too much<lb/> value upon that&#44; for I <del>do not consider it</del> am not inclined to<lb/> draw <sic>wordly</sic> advantage out of my inadequate<lb/> knowledge.  I have&#44; moreover&#44; decided to find<lb/> support in the first virtues mentioned in &#34;Abot&#34;&#42;<lb/> where it is written&#59; &#34;Make a fence for the Torah<lb/> and raise up many pupils&#34;.  I believe that<lb/> through the latter part the former can be fulfilled.  If I could<lb/> only get pupils&#44; I would gladly train them<lb/> in Gemaroh.  Medieval legalists&#44; as well as</p>
				<p rend="The following is written in the left column.">&#42;Ethics of<lb/> the fathers.</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><hi rend="underline">3</hi></p>
				<p>in Bible and Hebrew grammar&#44; and devote<lb/> with them several hours daily in these studies.<lb/>  This would be a highly appropriate time for it&#44;<lb/> if you would be good enough to include&#44; in<lb/> your next issue&#44; the advertisement given<lb/> by me at the end &#40;of the letter&#41; and if you<lb/> would at the same time ask other magazines<lb/> to include the same announcement.  I<lb/> would&#44; with the greatest pleasure&#44; see to it<lb/> that I become useful in this way&#44; and&#44; in<lb/> this way&#44; the statement would be fulfilled<lb/> in myself&#44; &#34;I have learned much from my<lb/> teachers&#44;  more from my friends&#44; and most<lb/> from my pupils.&#34;&#42;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">How soon do you expect to begin work<lb/> on your Bible&#63;  If there is anything you&#39;d<lb/> like to request of me&#44; I&#39;ll be happy to serve<lb/> you.  From now on I wish to consider you one<lb/> of my best friends and I beg of you to have<lb/> similar feelings of friendship.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Let us talk to each other as one man<lb/> to his brother and to my good friend&#44; with<lb/> regard to your words which sound sweet to my<lb/> ear.  For you have been receiving the insults<lb/> and the shame so that sins might be forgiven<lb/> and evil ended.  How good and how sweet it is to</p>
				<p>&#42;From the &#34;Ethics<lb/> of the Fathers&#34;.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">4</p>
				<p>think such thoughts&#33;  As our sages said&#44; &#34;A<lb/> man should always be among those who are<lb/> insulted&#34;&#42;  And <persName>Rabbi Meir</persName> says&#44; &#34;Always<lb/> always be thou lowly in spirit.&#34;  But know&#44; my<lb/> dear brother that&#44; &#34;He who takes a ritual bath<lb/> while he has a reptile in his hand&#44; the ritual<lb/> bath is invalid&#34;.  &#40;According to Talmudic law&#44;<lb/> touching a reptile makes one unclean and a man<lb/> requires a ritual bath in order to make himself clean<lb/> again.  <persName>S. G.</persName>&#41;.  Therefore&#44; keep far away from evil<lb/> speech and you will be considered pure by God<lb/> and man.  &#34;Who is the strong man&#63;  He who con&#45;<lb/>trols his desire&#44; and is master of his spirit.&#34;<lb/>  <persName>Solomon</persName>&#44; the wisest of all men said&#44; &#34;Guard<lb/> your heart more than you guard anything else&#44;&#34;<lb/> To me the surprising thing is&#44; why did you not<lb/> bring the dear woman under the wings of God&#63;<lb/>  &#40;Why didn&#39;t you make a proselyte of her&#63;  <persName>S. G.</persName>&#41;  And<lb/> in this way you could easily have stopped up the<lb/> mouth of all those who spoke evil and could<lb/> have dwelt without quarrel and undisturbed<lb/> with the men of your congregation.  Forgive me&#44;<lb/> my dear friend&#44; for my unnecessary advice.<lb/>  It is given to you from the depths of the<lb/> heart of a faithful friend.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I call your attention&#44; herewith&#44; that<lb/> this week I received a letter from <placeName>NY.</placeName> signed<lb/> <persName>Menachem</persName>&#44; son of <persName>Leib</persName>&#44; <persName>Goldschmith</persName>&#8212;and<lb/> in German&#44; <persName>Emanuel Goldsmith</persName>.  He writes</p>
				<p>&#42; The end of this Talmudic statement is&#44; &#34;But never among<lb/> those who do the insulting.&#34;</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">5.</p>
				<p>he wants to have the back numbers<lb/> and he said no&#44; only the current<lb/> issues.  I believe your old subscribers<lb/> will take it again.  If you send<lb/> me the list&#44; I shall take steps<lb/> in that direction.</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">6.</p>
				<p>from these experiences&#44; I note that our youth<lb/> is unfortunately far away from the works of our<lb/> exalted faith&#44; namely the Talmud&#44; the legal<lb/> commentators&#44; as well as the Hebrew language.<lb/>  Since I am endowed by the almighty with<lb/> children who conduct a business out of which<lb/> I draw an honorable livelihood and since<lb/> I want to spend the rest of my life as a<lb/> true servant of God&#44; I know of no way I can<lb/> be more useful than by spreading the<lb/> knowledge of God&#44; as our sages say&#44; &#34;The<lb/> study of the Torah outweighs everything.&#34;<lb/>  In another place it is written&#44; &#34;Great is<lb/> study&#44; for it brings deeds in its wake.&#34;  I<lb/> have made the following decision which I<lb/> herewith announce.  Parents&#44; who have the<lb/> fear of God in their heart and have sons<lb/> above the age of 12&#44; and if these sons<lb/> have the desire and ability to undertake<lb/> Jewish studies&#44; may bring them here<lb/> where I shall hold session between<lb/> three and four hours daily in Gemarah<lb/> and commentaries and the study of the<lb/> Hebrew language.  The parents need<lb/> supply only <del>the cost of</del> expenses&#44; lodging&#44;<lb/> and books.  I shall do the rest without<lb/> pay and conscientiously.  If there bye any<lb/> students without means to supply<lb/> themselves with the things mentioned above&#44;</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><sic>5.</sic></p>
				<p>with a great deal of flattery&#44; praises my<lb/> articles in your magazine&#44; informs me<lb/> that he&#44; too&#44; sent something to be published by<lb/> you in the same <del>conn</del> connection&#44; but that<lb/> you refused to accept it.  He is considering<lb/> sending the same thing to a magazine in<lb/> <placeName>London</placeName>.  He asks me for a reply which I<lb/> shall send him next week.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I submit the announcement<lb/> which I should like to have published.<lb/>  If in translating it into English you find<lb/> some changes necessary&#44; I am satisfied<lb/> to have you make them&#44; since you are<lb/> better fitted than I to understand<lb/> such matters.  I beg for your friendly<lb/> reply and remain forever&#44;<lb/>  Your respecting and loving friend&#44;</p>
				<p><persName role="author">Joseph Halevi</persName></p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Announcement</hi></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I cast a glance at the leadership of<lb/> Jewry in <placeName>North America</placeName> and to my sorrow<lb/> discovered that our religion is <sic>disterted</sic> here<lb/> more than in <placeName>Europe</placeName>.  For the sake of gain the<lb/> <date>Sabbath</date> is violated by many and many<lb/> ceremonial laws trodden under foot.  Aside</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><sic>7.</sic></p>
				<p>I hope to be able to place them with<lb/> kindhearted Jews resident here&#44; of whom<lb/> there are more than 120.  In accordance<lb/> with the same plan as is used in <placeName>Europe</placeName><lb/> where there are Yeshivoth and Gymnasia.<lb/>  Such children will also be able to acquire<lb/> information or knowledge of English&#44; since<lb/> a university for all <sic>all</sic> sciences has been<lb/> established here and is just beginning.<lb/>  I must add that the one condition of this<lb/> invitation is that the children speak the<lb/> German language&#44; since I do not know<lb/> English.  I hope that when this wish of mine<lb/> comes into effect&#44; it will soon show<lb/> general usefulness&#44; and that this free<lb/> school will bloom forth like a green tree<lb/> and produce sweet fruit.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The beginning of this project may<lb/> take place on <date>Rosh Hodesh Heshvan&#44;<lb/> &#40;October&#41; 1852</date>.  <persName>Mr. Field</persName> will soon send you<lb/> my article about the community here.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
