<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Illoway, Henry</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSKAP</repository>
                        <collection>The Arnold and Deanne Kaplan Collection of Early American
                            Judaica</collection>
                        <idno>LSKAP0229</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Illoway,
                            Henry</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-10">October 24, 1863</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0229_1r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0229_1v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0229_2r.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0229_2v.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="LSKAP0229_3r.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Restricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1R"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                <date>October 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/63</date>.</p>
            <p>To <addressee>Revd. Isaac Lesser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Editor “Occident”</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>Revd. Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Excuse my giving vent to painful feeling<lb/> which I can not
                restrain any longer. Can a son be silent<lb/> when he sees his father slighted by
                one whose respect and<lb/> admiration he deserves? Remember Revd Sir, how often<lb/>
                my venerable father appeared before the bar of public<lb/> opinion to advocate and
                defend you against the rude at=<lb/>tacks of <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> &amp;
                Co.! Remember how often<lb/> my father proclaimed you in all the Jewish
                periodicals<lb/> as the only faithful advocate of true Judaism, as the<lb/> restorer
                of our Religion and Gonfalonier<add>?</add> of truth in this<lb/> country! But you
                have not a single word to say in<lb/> his favor, when his enemies try to slander him
                by false<lb/> and unfounded reports. You asked some time ago, for the<lb/> reasons
                of his leaving <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, and I gave you<lb/> pure wine,
                the pure truth, without the least admixture<lb/> of untruth: what did you however
                write about it? You only<lb/> heaped slander upon slander; you wrote, “you received
                a<lb/> communication in favor of <persName>Dr. Illowy</persName>, but you have
                no<lb/> trust in it”, this is the essence, if not the words of your<lb/> report. You
                have no trust in my father's good character, (may<lb/> I presume Revd Sir to
                inquire, what is the cause of this doubt)<lb/> though you had already been informed
                by the Secretary of<lb/> the Cong in <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, that in
                spite of the malicious report</p>
            <pb n="1V"/>
            <p>published in the Deborah, my father was unanimously, not one<lb/> voice dissenting,
                elected, and not by vote but by acclamation.<lb/> Why not one voice against him? Why
                so most honorably elected,<lb/> Because the people in
                    <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName> heard from most trustworthy<lb/> men from
                    <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, that my father resigned his situa=<lb/>tion
                for the only reason, that he would not sell his conscience<lb/> for money.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You read the remarks of <persName>Revd. Isaacs</persName>; still
                you<lb/> doubted. It was not unknown to you that the friends of my<lb/> father in
                    <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> had presented him when leaving this<lb/> City
                with a most costly silver pitcher and waiter; still you<lb/> doubted, ignoring all
                these evidences. You know my father<lb/> since fifteen years, you know him firm as a
                rock; he never<lb/> changed or altered his principles from fear of losing or for
                the<lb/> sake of making money as your friends in <placeName>Hartford</placeName>,<lb/>
                <placeName>Rochester</placeName> and other places have done. No! My father<lb/>
                fears nothing, he has his trust in God, and when he trust=<lb/>fully gave up his
                situation and my Dear mother lamented what<lb/> will we do now, he said with
                    <persName>King David</persName>
                <add>אוכל טרפה בפרהסיה</add><lb/>
                <add>הפורשים מדרכי האחרונה והאחת והמוכרים אמונתם בעד ככר לחם</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your remarks in the last number of the Occident did<lb/> not hurt
                neither me (though I felt bad) nor my honored fa=<lb/>ther; thank God, he stands
                above the level of all his enemies<lb/> neither did they give you any credit for
                them<lb/> your best friends<lb/> blamed you and laughed at you saying: “<persName>Mr
                        <sic>Lesser</sic></persName> is afraid<lb/> of spoiling his game with either
                party, especially with <persName>Gutheim</persName><lb/> though he is an <add>איש
                    כשר וראויה להיות מגן הדור ונשיא בישראל</add>; would
                    <persName><sic>Lesser</sic></persName> be with twenty<lb/> years younger he
                would yet become the advocate of reform.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Let me ask you <persName>Mr<sic> Lesser</sic></persName>, you
                congratulated <placeName>Hartford</placeName></p>
            <pb n="2R"/>
            <p>to the successful election of mayor, <placeName>Rochester</placeName> of
                        <persName>Grinsburg<add>?</add></persName><lb/>
                <placeName>St Louis</placeName> of <persName>Vidaver</persName>, though you know all
                these formen<lb/> well, that they are men <add>זרח לך אשת וכו</add><lb/>
                <add>תלמוד מתלמיד כל עם הרשע</add>; still you flattered these men, promised the
                world a<lb/> great future which <sic>judaism</sic> had to expect from them, and<lb/>
                how much good the respective congregations will derive from<lb/> the activity of
                these Rabbis. You knew <persName>Vidaver</persName> better<lb/> than any man in
                    <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>, still you recommended him<lb/> as an <add>מקוה
                    שבחו בא לידי גנותו</add>. He is a strict <hi rend="underline">orthodox</hi><lb/>
                You had to advocate him. Send your ears to <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> and<lb/>
                you will hear what he is; a religion maker and a <add>גרים</add> he was<lb/> long
                ago for he fulfilled the word <add>שם ובמרחקים</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">How much had you to say and how much good did you promise<lb/> that
                the Cong. of <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> had to expect, when they elected<lb/>
                <persName>Cohen</persName>, who was well known as a <add>ואני נותרתי לבדי נביא
                    להם</add>; but you<lb/> had nothing, not a single word to say when <persName>Dr.
                    Illowy</persName> was elected<lb/> by the Cong. in
                    <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, and not alone that, but in the
                secretary's<lb/> report published in your paper, you malignantly left out the word<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">“unanimously”</hi>. You will find it in the “Messenger and
                Israelite,”<lb/> and your remark on an other page was more slander than praise,<lb/>
                it was such a praise as slanders bestow, <add>צדיק</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Thank God my father is too well known in the old and<lb/> new word
                as to stand in need of the praise of <hi rend="underline">any</hi> american<lb/>
                journalist.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Yes my dear Sir, if you had something to say against my<lb/> father,
                you would be immediately at hand to condemn him or to<lb/> kindle the flame of
                discord against him.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When my father had the courage to declare a rich
                <add>פושעים</add><lb/> you forgot yourself and dared set up your
                    <sic>judgement</sic> against him.</p>
            <pb n="2V"/>
            <p>Still my father did not use the expression which <persName>Wise</persName><lb/> used
                several times against you and <persName>Isaacs</persName>; my father is too<lb/>
                pious, too honorable and too much of a gentleman. It was<lb/> satisfaction enough
                for him if five <hi rend="underline">learned</hi>
                <sic>Rabbies</sic>, the<lb/> greatest men in, and the lights of,
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, <persName>Seligman Bamberger</persName><lb/> of
                    <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>, <persName>Dr Hinsch</persName>,
                        <placeName><sic>Franfort</sic></placeName>, <persName>Dr Lehman</persName>
                <placeName>Mainz</placeName><lb/>
                <persName>Dr Tilchenfeld</persName>
                <placeName>Düsseldorf</placeName>, and <persName>Dr Hildesheimer</persName>
                <placeName>Eisenstadt</placeName><lb/> all of them, like one voice, came out
                spontaneously, without being<lb/> called upon, and approved the action of my father
                in the most<lb/> laudable terms.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When my father wrote against the manufactory of <add>לכבוד
                    עצמו</add>, who<lb/> dared come out against him, with argument founded not upon<lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add>, but upon “COMMON SENSE”—<persName>Isaac Lesser</persName>”. Just
                as<lb/> if my father would be a thorn in your eye because he can say<lb/> with
                    <persName>Elijah</persName>
                <add>Hebrew</add>; because he is the only Ortho=<lb/>dox <sic>Rabby</sic> in this
                country you would like to see him pushed<lb/> aside. Oh! great righteousness!—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Believe me Sir, that I am convinced that my worthy<lb/> father whom
                I expect home every day would not approve of<lb/> my letter, for when he sent you
                just before leaving <placeName>N. O.</placeName><lb/> your $20.00, I told him to
                write you the cause of his<lb/> leaving <placeName>N. O.</placeName> since you once
                remarked that you would like<lb/> to know it, he answered, I do not wish to be
                heralded as <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> let the world think every one just as he pleases.
                I however<lb/> can not see the man, who pretends to be <add>the</add> advocate, the
                champion<lb/> of Orthodoxy, play a false game, recommend <add>Hebrew</add> to
                orthodox<lb/> Congs. As if you would not know them better.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">How great was your joy and hope when <persName>Cohen</persName> went to<lb/>
                <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, but you are stricken with blindness and
                deafness</p>
            <pb n="3R"/>
            <p>when you should come out with the truth. I confess it, that when<lb/> my father wrote
                us last week from <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>; that <persName>Dr.
                    Wise</persName>,<lb/> when seeing that the people in
                    <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName> rush from all the Synagogues<lb/> to hear him
                and that the crowd in his synagogue is so great every<lb/>
                <date>Sabbath</date> that many must remain in the vestibule for want of room<lb/>
                    within<del>g</del> and that his (<persName>Wise's</persName>) reports were
                declared, by the most respectable<lb/> men of this city who passed through there, as
                contrary to the truth<lb/> he began to make friendship with him and invited him to
                assist him<lb/> (<persName>Dr. Wise</persName>) in performing the marriage
                ceremonies at the wedding of his<lb/> daughter which will take place on the
                    <date>1st.</date> inst. and which invitation<lb/> was accepted by my father
                should he be present in <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>, that<lb/> I thought at
                first of bringing this letter to your notice through<lb/> the columns of the
                Israelite, but knowing that my father would<lb/> disapprove it, for he never likes
                to come out publicly against any one,<lb/> if it is only <add>Hebrew</add> and not
                for the sake of religion, therefore<lb/> I took this method and speak to you like
                man to man.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Hoping that you may be able to answer satisfactorily<lb/> all these
                questions</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">I remain Revd Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">your most obedient Servt.</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <persName role="author">Henrry Illowy</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
