<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item200</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1847-08" source="" attested="yes">5 August 1847</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1847-08" source="" attested="yes">5 August 5607</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item200_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item200_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item200_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item200_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>&#44; <date>August 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 5607 &#40;1847&#41;</date></p>
				<p>My dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You have just cause to be surprised at my silence&#44;<lb/> but my numerous duties and engagements prevent me from answering<lb/> both correspondents&#44; and even family letters.  To make up for lost<lb/> time I intend sending a long letter&#44; and will endeavor to continue writing<lb/> to one whom I hold in the highest esteem.  I send herewith the corrected<lb/> copy of the Road to faith and intend presenting it to your publication<lb/> society&#44; if it is worth their acceptance&#59; with this condition that they will<lb/> always supply me at the publication price.  I have added little or nothing<lb/> and made but few <sic>Emendations</sic>.  Of the former I specify the <del>ten com&#45;</del> maimonidean<lb/> <del>mandments</del> creed&#44; of the latter&#44; very little will meet your eye of an unsatisfac<lb/>tory nature.  You are at liberty to correct any text I have not translated<lb/> properly&#59; <add>Hebrew</add> has been rendered &#8220;I will turn the nations<lb/> to pray with pure lips&#8221; instead of the <sic>authorised</sic> version&#44; I will render pure<lb/> the lips of the people.&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It grieved me to notice the useless discussion&#44;<lb/> in the valuable pages of the Occident on the question of west Indian<lb/> citrons.  Had the writers who so dogmatically insisted upon their being<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add> grafted&#44; been at all acquainted with the <placeName>Antilles</placeName>&#44; they would<lb/> never have breached the matter.  In these <placeName>Islands</placeName> too much attention<lb/> is devoted to the staple production&#44; as sugar&#44; coffee &#38;c to allow a<lb/> laborer&#39;s time to be wasted on the improvement of fruit trees.  Of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName><lb/> especially I can assert most positively that the Citron grows in its<lb/> original state&#44; either where it was first planted&#44; or where the wind has<lb/> scattered the seed&#44; and it has taken root.  The same may be said of all<lb/> fruit trees&#44; they are met with on all the estates&#44; but no care is bestowed<lb/> on them.  The orange and shaddock and perhaps the line&#44; may&#44; now that<lb/> estates owners try to make every thing profitable on their lands&#44; receive<lb/> a share of attention&#44; but the citron and others of that family are useless <del>to</del><lb/> except for making preserves&#44; and grafting for that purpose would not pay<lb/> the cost of oranges&#44; shaddocks&#44; and lime juice are exported&#44; citrons grow and<lb/> rot on the trees they may be had for the asking.  The whole expense is confined<lb/> to gathering bringing them to town&#44; packing&#44; and freight to the states.  One<lb/> of our brethren in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> used to send an annual supply to the syna&#45;<lb/>gogues by his slaves&#44; free of cost&#44; the present possessor of his estates<lb/> permits any one to pluck citrons&#44; who will send for them.  They grow only<lb/> in the mountainous districts&#44; and labor being high&#44; people demand good<lb/> wages to walk the distance&#44; and bring them to town.  Of late years&#44; <persName>Mr. Kursheedt</persName><lb/> was supplied from a quarter near<del>er</del> to <placeName>Kingston</placeName>&#59; but the citrons from that<lb/> place were neither as handsome nor of so good a quality as those from<lb/> the lofty <placeName>Port Royal</placeName> mountains.  <persName>Mr. Levy</persName>&#44; the gentleman who resides there&#44;<lb/> and his uncle before him&#44; were both men of strict religious principles.  As<lb/> natives of <placeName>Europe</placeName>&#44; and perfectly acquainted with the peculiar citrons<lb/> permitted to be used&#44; they never grafted the trees.  It must also be<lb/> recollected that our Portuguese brethren in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> were presided over for many<lb/> years by eminent Chachamine<add>&#63;</add>&#59; the chief <persName>Chacham De Cordova</persName>&#44; an eminent<lb/> scholar in biblical and profane knowledge&#44; and whose manuscript<lb/> writings attest his profound acquirements.  Surely&#44; these pious &#38; orthodox<lb/> persons would not have sanctioned the use of grafted fruit.  Either then<lb/> the learned in <placeName>America</placeName> have passed an erroneous judgment&#44; or all the Chachamin<lb/> in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> were wrong&#44; or spurious citrons have been shipped to your<lb/> congregations and packed off as genuine fruit.  One thing must be borne<lb/> in mind that in <placeName>Europe</placeName> the citron is well tended&#44; in the <placeName>west Indies</placeName><lb/> neglected&#44; and the difference of appearance has been imputed to grafting&#44;<lb/> which I again repeat is not <sic>practised</sic> in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>&#44; whence you have<lb/> heretofore been supplied.  You are at liberty to make use of this information<lb/> and name me as the author.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You have written <persName>Mr. Wolff</persName> again on the<lb/> subject of my reply to the attack on confirmation&#44; but it has been</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>delayed so long&#44; that it has now lost its interest.&#8221;  At the time the<lb/> articles appeared&#44; it was my intention to have replied&#59; and the whole was<lb/> sketched out and only wanted writing <del>it</del> fully&#44; when the shameless conduct<lb/> of <persName>Mr. Naar</persName> and his confederates in attempting to discharge me from my<lb/> post called forth all my energies to defeat their machinations&#44; and left<lb/> me little leisure and less inclination for so trifling a matter.  Success<lb/> attended my efforts&#59; and an administration&#44; whose supporters only sought<lb/> to do the congregations as much mischief as possible&#59; was turned out to make<lb/> way for better men.  Whilst this was in progress&#44; and my daily bread at<lb/> stake&#44; when the prospect of having to go and seek a living elsewhere stared<lb/> me in the face&#44; could you suppose that I should sit down composedly<lb/> to reply to an opponent whose object and motive in assailing me arose<lb/> from malice&#63;  And had I done so&#44; would my words have been free from<lb/> asperity&#63;  Smarting under wrong&#44; would there not have been too much<lb/> bitterness in my reasoning&#63;  <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> was before me&#44; my resignation<lb/> there too recent to have been forgotten&#44; and the unhappy circumstances which<lb/> caused it were remembered.  And was I further to commit myself&#63;  Was I<lb/> to answer a man who is a model of infidelity and unbelief&#44; who does not<lb/> observe a single day in the year&#44; as tho&#39; he had been a sincere &#38; upright<lb/> Israelite&#63;  Must I not necessarily have exposed his hypocrisy&#44; and shown<lb/> that his solicitude <del>about</del> for our religion had its source in dislike to me<lb/> personally&#63;  I must have exposed the whole affair to vindicate confirmation<lb/> and myself&#44; and this step would have widened the breach in the congregation<lb/> and led to further aggravation and ill feeling.  <persName>Mr. Naar</persName> and I are now<lb/> reconciled and I hope soon by prudence and circumspection to restore<lb/> peace and good will among all parties&#44; except <persName>Mr. M. B. Simmonds</persName>&#44; whom<lb/> every one despises and dislikes&#44; and who is a bad hearted man.  All his<lb/> talent&#44; and he has much&#44; can never reestablish him in the favorable<lb/> opinion of the public.  Meanwhile I have not been idle&#44; but have been<lb/> preparing to strengthen and improve my position.  Again&#44; necessity has<lb/> compelled me to open a school&#44; to give me bread&#44; in case of rupture or<lb/> discontent in the congregation&#44; necessity&#44; not choice&#44; has driven me to it for<lb/> I had hoped to sit down here and labor for the welfare of my flock as in<lb/> <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>.  I have not been altogether unsuccessful.  In another quarter<lb/> also I have been endeavoring to make provision for future subsistence.  All<lb/> these projects trench upon my time&#44; and exclusively with the writing of sermons engage my attention.<lb/>  Depending on the faith of the congregation&#44; I sent for my mother in law and<lb/> her mother who is eighty years old&#44; and cannot easily move from place<lb/> to place.  Cares have multiplied you see and <del>have</del> restrain my will&#44; else<lb/> I would not be in <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>.  I detail&#44; that you may make allowance<lb/> for my silence&#44; and not attribute it to indolence or indifference.  The good<lb/> effects of confirmation have more and more convinced me of its great<lb/> utility and tho&#39; I have altered some of the formalities&#44; I am not prepared<lb/> to abandon it.  But why&#44; let me ask&#44; were not your observations <sic>levelled</sic><lb/> against the ceremony&#44; <del>&#63;</del> replied to by <persName>Dr. Lilienthal</persName>&#63;  He is not incapable<lb/> of defending it&#44; and its advocacy concerns him who has the spiritual<lb/> care of thousands&#44; more than poor me who have only 3 or 4 hundred to guard.<lb/>  His reasons I cannot divine&#44; unless he thought <hi rend="underline">your arguments</hi> irrefutable&#44;<lb/> which&#44; in my opinion&#44; the are not.  It does not appear&#44; that in your long<lb/> ministry&#44; you have been able&#44; without confirmation&#44; to introduce a more<lb/> serious observance of the <date>sabbath</date> in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#44; or the abolition of<lb/> mixed marriages&#44; or the foundation of Jewish Schools.  In <placeName>Jamaica</placeName><lb/> I did not resort to confirmation&#59; I accomplished all these objects without<lb/> it&#59; here however I find it a useful instrument in keeping the sheep within<lb/> the fold&#59; and thro&#39; the children have wrought upon the parents so that some<lb/> determined <date>sabbath</date> breakers have been won from their evil courses.  That confirmation<lb/> has answered the purpose I intended it to serve&#44; knowledge of our religion to<lb/> the young&#44; reflection upon past misdeeds and serious resolutions to amend on<lb/> the path of the old.  Its value has been tested here&#44; and found beneficial&#44; and as the<lb/> most orthodox&#44; as <persName>Plessuer<add>&#63;</add></persName>&#44; say&#44; <persName>Adler</persName> and others are in its favor&#44; it cannot be<lb/> termed heterodoxical.  I do not pin my faith on it&#44; but with God&#39;s help&#44; I hope<lb/> to further its <del>already</del> usefulness.  No child shall be called to the sepher who is<lb/> ignorant of the fundamental principles of Judaism but yet <hi rend="underline">I</hi> will not make<lb/> confirmation compulsory&#44; the <persName>king</persName> of <placeName>Denmark</placeName> will however do so.  It may suit<lb/> the unbeliever to disapprove of it&#44; because he reveres nothing&#59; this cause&#44; added<lb/> to personal ill will to me and <persName>Mr. Wolff</persName>&#44; was the reason of <persName>Mr. Naar&#39;s</persName> philippic.<lb/>  It grieved me to find your powerful pen enlisted in the service of irreligion&#44;<lb/> but your dislike of any thing approaching reform instigated you to throw<lb/> disparagement on a valuable aid to our religion in these times when license</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>of speech&#44; thought&#44; and conduct is dignified by the name of liberty of<lb/> conscience and action.  I cannot account for your championship in any other<lb/> manner.  There were points in <persName>Mr. Naar&#39;s</persName> communication savoring of the grossest<lb/> infidelity&#59; whoever read it must have been convinced that it emanated from a<lb/> rank Deist&#59; yet how bland were your corrections of those points&#44; and how determined<lb/> your onslaught on confirmers and confirmation.  The pages of the Occident may yet&#44; on<lb/> some future occasion be open to my advocacy of confirmation&#44; when my mind is less<lb/> harassed&#59; and be assured that the past will not then be forgotten.  Till then&#44; I resume<lb/> my <sic>defence</sic> of the <hi rend="underline">promise</hi>&#44; not the <hi rend="underline">oath</hi> <del>taken</del> made at the first ceremony&#44; and shall be<lb/> able to produce the warrant of scripture for its introduction.  Polemics do not<lb/> appear to be <persName>Mr. Naar&#39;s</persName> forte&#59; politics whether discussed in caucus&#44; stage <sic>waggon</sic>&#44;<lb/> or groggery are more suited to his taste&#44; else he would not have made himself<lb/> so ridiculous by stating that the <hi rend="underline">Immortality of the Body</hi> instead of its <hi rend="underline">resurrection</hi><lb/> was one of the doctrines <hi rend="underline">he</hi> could not approve of.  Shade of <persName><sic>maimonides</sic></persName>&#33; dost<lb/> thou not feel rebuked <del>at</del> by the superior understanding of the Quondain<add>&#63;</add> mayor<lb/> of <placeName>Elizabeth Town</placeName>&#63;  But my dear <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>&#44; you will never be able to write<lb/> down confirmation&#59; it will maintain its ground and spread itself in <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> as elsewhere&#44; and time may yet behold in you and of its warmest defenders<lb/> one word more on this subject&#59; refer to the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> no of the First Fruits&#44; and note<lb/> that confirmation had my best wishes&#44; before the thought of <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> entered my<lb/> mind.  You will find an article headed Bar&#45;Mitzva or Confirmation in which<lb/> I expressed a desire for its adoption in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Your last letter was exceedingly interesting.  The sketch of<lb/> <persName>Rabbi Moshe Katzenellenbogen</persName> so graphic and illustrative of the Jewish charac&#45;<lb/>ter and studies in <placeName>Poland</placeName> and <placeName>Russia</placeName>.  Your opinion is correct of our people&#39;s<lb/> being the most clever among mankind.  Even if their studies are not practically<lb/> useful in a busy world&#44; they sharpen the intellect and fit <del>then</del> the mind for<lb/> understanding any thing.  A Polack or Russian Israelite having once obtained<lb/> a little refinement and polish is able to make his way in any pursuit whether<lb/> literary&#44; scientific&#44; or mercantile.  It yet remains to be seen what effect<lb/> the immense immigration of our people into the states will have on religion<lb/> generally.  The problem will be solved in the western world whether<lb/> Christianity shall not fall at the feet of Judaism.  On that continent where<lb/> the fullest liberty meets the most rigorous despotism of body and mind&#44; where<lb/> American and Russian institutions border on each other the truth of prophecy<lb/> will first enlighten man&#44; and its accomplishment take place.  Whilst every<lb/> Jewish heart bleeds at the miseries of our Russian brethren&#44; it is apparent<lb/> that some great change is at hand in the fortunes of our people.  <persName>Nicholas</persName><lb/> is not influenced by any other motive to act as he does towards them and<lb/> the Catholics&#44; than to acquire absolute <del>dominion</del> rule over the consciences<lb/> of his subjects and to make them all conform to one religion as they obey<lb/> one sovereign who is solo master of their lives <del>of his</del> and liberties.  It seems<lb/> as tho&#39; he spoke <del>in</del> the language of an ancient oppressor <add>Hebrew</add>.<lb/>  It is a mighty and gigantic project displaying his daring genius not even<lb/> <persName>Antiochus Epiphanes</persName> dared to go so far.  <persName>Nicholas</persName> wars not against<lb/> Judaism alone&#44; he takes <del>up</del> arms against Christendom &#38; mohammedan<lb/>ism.  Our generation will not witness his success or that of his successors&#59;<lb/> but how well does he realize <persName>Ezekiel&#39;s</persName> description of the &#8220;<persName>Prince of Rosh</persName><lb/> <placeName>Meshic</placeName> and <placeName>Tubal</placeName>&#8221; destined to be broken with his multitudes on the<lb/> mountains of <placeName>Israel</placeName>.  Really the longer we live&#44; the better do we<lb/> comprehend scripture&#44; and our ablest commentators were on these<lb/> historical revelations less enlightened than we who cannot hold a<lb/> candle to them in knowledge.  Prophecy sheds a stronger light the longer<lb/> it turns.  When <placeName>Russia</placeName> was an obscure and barbarous country which of<lb/> our commentators could have pointed to it unknown as <del>she</del> it was to be<lb/> the spot whence the last opponent to <placeName>Israel&#39;s</placeName> restoration and peace<lb/> should issue&#63;  At this day&#44; who can scruple to doubt that the <add>&#63;</add><lb/> dynasty was forseen by the prophet&#63;  Depend on it&#44; no prayers&#44; no<lb/> entreaties will sway <persName>Nicholas</persName> from his purpose&#44; no <persName>montefiores</persName> will<lb/> succeed&#59; he will promise&#44; but will not relax his iron determination.<lb/>  He will modify his <add>&#63;</add>&#44; but their end and intention will remain<lb/> the same.  He will possibly permit a larger emigration of those who<lb/> can afford to buy the privilege of departing&#44; but he will not the<lb/> less persevere in his oppression.  Martyred blood will be shed and perhaps<lb/> when that avails not&#44; he will drive <placeName>Israel</placeName> from his land as Pharoah<lb/> did.  In politics the danger is as imminent as in Religion&#44; <placeName>Turkey</placeName> is</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>already in his grasp.  <placeName>Austria</placeName> will succumb&#44; <placeName>Prussia</placeName> will follow&#44; unless<lb/> the German nations combine for common safety.  And whither shall the<lb/> millions of <placeName>Israel</placeName> in these countries fly to for refuge and protection save to <placeName>Western<lb/> Europe</placeName>&#44; or more probably to the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#63;  Therefore the hypothesis<lb/> that <placeName>America</placeName> is to be the chosen soil whereon mankind will first be<lb/> illumined is not so very extraordinary.  Meanwhile let us pray for the<lb/> messiah coming as did our pious forefathers&#44; and await it with devout<lb/> and confident hearts.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Have you yet broken a lance against <persName>Rabbi Wise</persName><lb/> as you anticipated&#63;  I was prepared for something more satisfactory<lb/> and convincing than his logical reasoning in the Occident.  Possibly his<lb/> words have suffered by translation but part of his arguments appear to me<lb/> very contradictory.  For example in page 160 <date>June</date> No of Occident he says.<lb/> &#8220;The chief precept of our religion is to be holy that is <hi rend="underline">to love God</hi> &#38;c.  <hi rend="underline">Inferior</hi><lb/> to this precept is the one to acknowledge God expressed in the first com<lb/>mandment &#38;  If one really acknowledge him we shall love Him and thereby<lb/> become holy&#33;  First <persName>Rabbi Wise</persName> makes the love of God paramount to the<lb/> acknowledgment of God&#44; and in the next line tells us that the <hi rend="underline">effect</hi> of<lb/> acknowledging him will lead us to love Him.  If love then be <hi rend="underline">the</hi> chief<lb/> it must lead to acknowledgment and not acknowledgment to love.  Beside<lb/> I was always taught that acknowledging the Divine Being is the first<lb/> principle <del>to be taught</del>.  In the <add>Hebrew</add> it is so&#59; love of God being a consequence<lb/> of recognizing and acknowledging him the same in the Decalogue&#44; in<lb/> the Creed of <persName>Maimonides</persName> and <persName>Albo</persName>.  The neo&#45;judaical opinions of <persName>Rabbi<lb/> Wise</persName> are not in harmony&#44; on this point&#44; with the law and prophets.<lb/>  Prayers&#44; generally&#44; is subjective&#59; but surely scripture presents many of an<lb/> objective character <persName>Moses</persName> on behalf of <persName>Miriam</persName>&#44; <persName>Samuel</persName> for the people &#38;c &#38;c<lb/> Persons pray for each other disinterestedly hoping that the effect may<lb/> be objective.  &#8220;If the proper object and purpose of prayer&#8221; I quote page 158<lb/> be the reflective effect upon the spirit and heart of him who prays&#8221;<lb/> thus one should never pray for our fellow creatures&#59; all our ideas would<lb/> be confined&#44; in prayer&#44; to our own spiritual and temporal improvement.<lb/>  The subjective and objective effect of prayer is too refined a distinction<lb/> to be understood by the generality of our people&#44; and <persName>Rabbi W.</persName> has not<lb/> explained this difficult point clearly.  Your emphatic objection in<lb/> page 158 has my cordial support.  Of course&#44; <persName>Rabbi W.</persName> wants no temple<lb/> no national restoration&#44; no messiah&#44; he only wants a <add>Hebrew</add>.  Why not<lb/> recommend the mutilation of the prophecies&#44; or the leaving out&#44; when<lb/> revising the law&#44; all such passages as relate to <placeName>Israel&#39;s</placeName> redemption and<lb/> restoration&#44; such as <add>Hebrew</add>.  <persName>Rabbi W&#39;s</persName> opinions are not new to<lb/> me.  The modern reformers generally have attached to the removal<lb/> of evil disabilities and the recognition of Israelites to the rights of<lb/> citizenship&#44; their views of messiah&#39;s coming.  They do not ask much&#44;<lb/> but what conception can they have of the prophecies&#44; if they thus<lb/> confine the future glory of <placeName>Israel</placeName> to the enjoyment of such doubtful<lb/> good&#63;  The conclave of American Rabbins are right however in<lb/> seeking to establish a minhag <placeName>America</placeName>.  It is most necessary<lb/> if only to make Judaism and synagogue worship understood<lb/> by Christians.  I almost shudder at the prejudices which the<lb/> conduct in some synagogues must excite in the Christian mind.<lb/>  Whilst therefore condemning some of the principles evolved by<lb/> <persName>Rabbi Wise</persName> as the mouthpiece of the conclave&#44; the project<lb/> has my best wishes.  Why do you not start up and effect the<lb/> same for the Sephardim of whom you are the head&#44; both by<lb/> length of service&#44; talent &#38;c.  They require it their synagogue<lb/> discipline is exceedingly lax&#44; and needs restoration.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am compelled to conclude abruptly as a vessel<lb/> is just about to sail.  My health is so bad that this letter has</p>
				<p rend="The letter continues written sideways over the previous text&#44; at the left side of the page."></p>
				<p>been taken up 5 or 6 times to be completed.  I enclose the corrected copy of the &#8220;Road to faith&#8221;<lb/> and present it in my name to your publication society.  <persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> sends her love to you<lb/> and regards to all friends whom I will name another time.  Hoping that the Almighty<lb/> will give you health and strength to discharge your ministerial duties during the<lb/> Holidays&#44; and that your prayers on behalf of your congregation and self may<lb/> be heard on high</p>
			<p rend="indent(6)">I am</p>
			<p rend="indent(7)">Yours Truly</p>
			<p rend="indent(7)"><persName role="author">MNNathan</persName></p>
				<p>If you see my friend <persName>Vaz<add>&#63;</add></persName> of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>&#44; tell him not to be angry for I will<lb/> write him very soon.  I hope he is well.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
