<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item154</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Zalma
                            Rehine</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1842-10">19 October 1842</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1842-10">15 Heshvan 5603</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p>Wax seal</p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                <date>October 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Heshvan 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.
                5603</date>.</p>
            <p>Dear Uncle.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I should judge from your letter that when you wrote you had not<lb/>
                received the <add>?</add> liner I had sent you by <persName>Mrs. Lyons</persName>,
                who nevertheless<lb/> had promised to call on you on her journey to her new home.
                But<lb/> I have little doubt that she fulfilled her promise by calling before
                she<lb/> left, and that she likewise told <persName>aunt R</persName> all the
                particulars about<lb/> the wedding. I am well aware that ladies like to hear
                such<lb/> matters; but I am but little acquainted with them to give full<lb/>
                particulars. The wedding however was a tolerably merry one,<lb/> and plenty to eat
                and to drink was set before all the com-<lb/>pany. As usual some affronts were
                given; since some persons<lb/> thought themselves entitled to an invitation which
                was not extended<lb/> to them. Among the rest a cousin of the bride, who expected to
                be <hi rend="underline">unter</hi>-<lb/><hi rend="underline">ferer</hi>, and not
                being asked she and <sic>and</sic> husband did not come<lb/> at all. However this
                you know is not uncommon; I myself staid till<lb/> near one o'clock; as they did not
                sit down to supper till a quarter before<lb/> twelve, and I was expected to stay to
                say prayers. It was rather<lb/> a later hour for me than I liked to remain out of
                bed; but as there was<lb/> no help for it I had to submit.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Old <persName>Mr Wolff</persName> has been at our house for some
                weeks.<lb/> He had a cataract on one eye, and could not see well out of<lb/> the
                other. He had accordingly an operation before<add>?</add> to remove<lb/> the
                cataract from the one eye, already <date>Sunday</date> two weeks ago;<lb/> and as
                yet he has not been down stairs. As my room is I think<lb/> the most convenient in
                the house I gave it up to him; though I<lb/> do not hold him in very high
                estimation, since he is for a European<lb/> as little of a Jew as ever I saw in my
                life. However he too has<lb/> not escaped without his share of trouble. I hope that
                in a week or two<lb/> he may be able to travel southwards as he lives in
                    <placeName>Mobile, Alabama</placeName>; a person sick in a house makes a great
                difference in all arrange<lb/>ments.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>As I am writing a message is brought that <persName>Rachel Pyke</persName>
                    (<persName>Peixotto</persName>) was<lb/> last night confined; but the child is
                dead. I do not admire that couple<lb/> much. I have recommended him to several
                persons to give him goods<lb/> on commission; but he invariably has failed of paying
                over what he<lb/> sold, and so he will get but little more from Jews. He has cost
                me<lb/> besides somewhat like twenty Dollars in money, and more indirectly,<lb/> and
                from me therefore he has nothing to expect. Upon the whole there<lb/> is little
                satisfaction in doing anything for the poor of this community. They<lb/> generally
                eat up what they get; and but small thanks do even fall to<lb/> my share at least; I
                know not how it may be with other people. It<lb/> would not matter much if I were
                rich; but having to work for every cent<lb/> I get, it is rather hard that so many
                make constant claim to the<lb/> little I have, and do it in such a manner that a
                refusal is out of my<lb/> power. I have determined at times not to be liberal; but I
                see no way<lb/> whatever to avoid giving more than I should do for my means.
                Still<lb/> as I am a single man and having no one whom I need work for, it
                makes<lb/> but small odds at last, as I hope with God's Helping to be always able to
                earn<lb/> my living; and if I have this respectably I have no right to ask for
                more.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My intention was to go to <placeName>New York</placeName> last
                    <date>Sunday</date>. But <persName>Mr. S. Pesoa</persName><lb/> was on
                    <date>Thursday</date> &amp; <date>Friday</date> so ill, that the Doctor had no
                hopes of his<lb/> living to the utmost more than 72 hours. But last evening I
                went<lb/> to see him, and he appeared to me not to be quite so sick as that he<lb/>
                might not recover. <persName>Doctor Jackson</persName> happened to come in as I
                was<lb/> going away, and I waited till he was going again, when he asked<lb/> to
                ride down in his carriage, and took me to <placeName>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp;
                    Chestnut Streets</placeName><lb/> (believe in <placeName>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    below Walnut</placeName>); he then told me that there is but small<lb/>
                probability of his recovery, yet there is no symptom which would make<lb/> his
                disease necessarily fatal. So I trust, that the poor young man<lb/> may get up
                again, especially as he has four to five children &amp; a helpless wife<lb/>
                depending for support upon his daily exertions. I thought that the family might<lb/>
                think it unkind in me to leave the city under these circumstances, so I
                    reach<add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>up my mind to defer my journey, though I thereby will in all probabili<lb/>ty lose
                the fine weather which we now have. Next <date>Sunday</date><lb/> I have <add>יאהר
                    צייט</add> for my father and on <date>Tuesday</date> I believe they will<lb/>
                set a tombstone for <persName>Mr Allen</persName>, when his year expires; so I
                shall<lb/> not get off next week either. So you see, Uncle, that my little<lb/>
                excursion depend upon so many circumstances, that I can not even<lb/> leave within
                the week if I feel ever so much inclined to travel.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Have any Baltimorean signed the prospectus for the Occident?<lb/> I
                have about 60 already in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> and vicinity, and
                expect at<lb/> least 20 more; how many there are in <placeName>New York</placeName>
                I shall learn only<lb/> when I get there; as the people there are too busy to
                write.<lb/> I myself would never have thought of a paper for the present;<lb/> but I
                have been induced to give the proposal in consequence<lb/> of solicitation from
                various quarters. Whether the very persons who<lb/> urged me will do any thing
                appears very doubtful; but there is <add>?</add><lb/> consolation if I do not print
                the paper I shall lose nothing by <add>?</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">All your friends desire to be remembered; <persName>Amelia
                    Allen</persName> in particu<lb/>lar told me I must mention her name. It is
                hardly requisite to<lb/> write a page full of names; so I leave you to judge who
                all<lb/> enquire about you. Give my love to <persName>Aunt R.</persName>
                <persName>Rachel</persName>, <persName>Mr Judah</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Mr. &amp; Mrs Block</persName>, the <persName>Ettings</persName>, and all
                our mutual friends.</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">With high regard</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">your obt. Nephew</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
            </p>
            <p>I had last week a letter</p>
            <p>from <persName>Mr. Nathan</persName> of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName></p>
            <p>neither he nor his wife was well at</p>
            <p>the time. He makes an apology for</p>
            <p>not sending <add>אתרוגים</add>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>
                <addressee>Mr. Zalma Rehine</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Care of <persName>Hanover &amp; German</persName></p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">
                <placeName>Md.</placeName>
            </p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">single</hi>. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
