<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item193</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1863-12" source="" attested="yes">11 December 1863</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1863-12" source="" attested="yes">5624</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item193_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item193_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item193_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item193_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>3 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>&#44; <date>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Decr.</date> <add>Hebrew</add> <date>5624&#47;1863</date>.</p>
				<p>My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Your two welcome letters I have not had any time<lb/> to answer until today&#44; and even now I have so much to do with Synagogue<lb/> and school &#40;very small at present&#44;&#41; that I will not be able to afford you all<lb/> the information you may want respecting my course since I have been <sic>hear</sic>.<lb/>  But first let me ask why you address me&#44; one of your oldest friends and<lb/> correspondents by the title of Dr. Sir&#63;  Is it a proof of your altered feelings towards<lb/> <hi rend="underline">me</hi>&#44; or an idea that mine could possibly change&#44; or <hi rend="underline">have</hi> changed towards <hi rend="underline">you</hi>&#63;  &#8220;Reform<lb/> is altogether.&#8221;  I must also premise that your note of <date>Oct. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>.</date> found me on a sick<lb/> bed&#44; and which incapacitated me from public duty for nearly 3 weeks.  It was<lb/> a severe attack of influenza&#44; arising from the sudden change of very hot weather to<lb/> heavy rains and strong north winds.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I left <placeName>Kingston</placeName> on the <date>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Septr.</date>&#44; and arrived here <add>Hebrew</add> on <add>Hebrew</add> about 7 in the<lb/> morning too late for <add>Hebrew</add>.  A large concourse of my members met me at the wharf&#44;<lb/> and accompanied me to the lodgings they had provided and furnished&#44; until I could purchase<lb/> my own things.  After drinking a glass of wine&#44; we went to Synagogue&#44; for me to say <add>Hebrew</add>.<lb/>  On returning home&#44; a letter from some of my lady friends was handed me&#44; together with<lb/> a handsome suit of canonicals&#44; of which they requested my acceptance.  In the evening&#44;<lb/> the congregation being assembled for <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; I was led in by the Presidt. &#38; Vice&#44; seated in<lb/> the President&#39;s chair&#44; while the congregation sang <add>Hebrew</add>.  After which the President<lb/> from the Tebah addressed me&#44; and on concluding&#44; he and the vice led me to the Tebah&#44;<lb/> where I addressed the congregation for 10 minutes or so.  After which I read the Evening<lb/> Service&#44; paid musaph<add>&#63;</add> next day&#44; and preached&#59; <persName>Mr. Maduro</persName> my assistant Reader read the<lb/> second Evening and following day.  I read <add>Hebrew</add> and preached on <date>Kippoor</date> my portion<lb/> was <add>Hebrew</add> &#38; <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; a sermon&#44; and <add>Hebrew</add>.  I did not again preach till <date>Succot&#44; the<lb/> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> day</date>.  We had a large assembly on <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; save on <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; very bad weather&#44; and a<lb/> thin attendance on <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; on which day I had to go to Government House to pay<lb/> my respects to the Governor&#44; and show my loyalty&#44; it being the late Kings&#39; birthday.<lb/>  Since then I have spoken to the people every <date>sabbath</date>&#44; also on the <date>25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Oct.</date>&#44; the<lb/> annual <date>thanksgiving day</date> after the expiration of the hurricane season&#44; on<lb/> which occasion I sent them all home with red eyes and noses.  Except the two<lb/> <date>Sabbaths</date> when I was too ill to leave the house I have spoken the word.  The old<lb/> members declare that I am much improved&#44; whilst the young ones who only remember<lb/> me as children are highly pleased with me.  On last <date>Monday night the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</date> <add>&#63;</add>.<lb/> we had a special service&#44; as the advertisement in the paper stated&#44; as a tribute<lb/> of loyalty&#44; affection&#44; and homage to the memory of the late Sovereign <persName>Frederick VII</persName>.<lb/>  The Synagogue was very tastefully hung in black&#59; the four large pillars having<lb/> black draperies folded around them spirally&#44; the two pilasters at the Hechal&#44; the Tebah&#44;<lb/> large candlesticks&#44; and brass knobs being covered with table trappings.  An audience<lb/> filling every inch of the building &#40;at least 500 persons&#41; consisting of our congregation&#44; and<lb/> a very large number of Christians&#44; assembled at 7 PM.  The Governor and his suite&#44; and several<lb/> heads of departments were present&#59; among the rest&#44; the Presbyterian&#44; Lutheran&#44; and<lb/> Moravian clergymen.  The service began with the chanting of the 49<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Psalm&#44; then</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p><add>Hebrew</add>&#59; after which <add>Hebrew</add> was sung&#44; and the <add>Hebrew</add> lights lighted&#44; and <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> said&#44; Kaddish &#38; Barecha<add>&#63;</add> sung&#44; and <add>Hebrew</add> read with great Emphasis.  I then<lb/> preached from Ecclesiastes v. 8 <add>Hebrew</add> about an hour.  After which&#44; the whole<lb/> audience standing&#44; I recited&#44; in English&#44; the <add>Hebrew</add> for the repose of the kings seal&#59;<lb/> which set all the Danes crying&#44; men and women.  Then followed the <add>Hebrew</add> in<lb/> English&#44; for which the ark was opened by our old friend <persName>Mayer Wolff</persName>&#44; who&#44; as it was<lb/> a public occasion&#44; was dressed in full military uniform&#44; and looked every inch a<lb/> fine veteran soldier.  The whole was concluded with Yigdals&#44; and the <add>Hebrew</add> in<lb/> Hebrew &#38; English&#44; with which we finish all services in the Synagogue.  The whole<lb/> went off with the greatest <add>&#63;</add>&#44; and will do us good here.  I felt highly proud<lb/> of my congregation&#44; for tho&#39; they always behave well in Synagogue&#44; and are not<lb/> excelled by any Jewish Assembly for prayer in the known world in this respect&#44;<lb/> yet on this occasion the whole proceedings were so very orderly and dignified&#44;<lb/> that they could not have been better.  The <sic>chaunting</sic> and responses were particularly<lb/> fine.  As to my sermon it was much applauded by some&#44; and slightly found fault with<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> others&#44; according as they Supposed to be Danes or <del>and</del> Germans.  The <placeName>Holstein</placeName> question<lb/> you may suppose is discussed and debated here&#44; and sometimes with great bitterness.<lb/>  Being no <sic>partizan</sic>&#44; I only spoke of the king as his acts&#44; in giving a most liberal<lb/> constitution&#44; in endeavoring to unite his people&#44; gaining their love and affection&#44; and<lb/> counselling his relative&#44; the king of the Greeks&#44; to do the same fully warranted my doing.<lb/>  Judging him by his public acts&#44; he was in truth a patriotic king&#44; and I took<lb/> advantage of pointing out by the lights of <date><sic>Hanukah</sic></date>&#44; how <placeName>Israel</placeName> valued patriotism&#44;<lb/> which after 2000 years they still continued to celebrate&#44; and how highly they esteemed<lb/> it in others&#44; especially in those who&#44; with power&#44; combined the desire of granting the<lb/> rights of civil and religious liberty to their fullest extent&#44; as was the case with the<lb/> late King.  My bold sentiments have made me &#40;for the <add>&#63;</add>&#41; very popular&#59; and my members<lb/> are consequently pleased that their minister should be well spoken of&#44; and his preaching<lb/> admired.  But I am too old to be vain of Popular applause&#58; yet I am gratified<lb/> that the attempt to do my duty has not been exceeded by any other Clergyman in<lb/> the place.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">With reference to the state of parties in the congregation&#44; affairs are<lb/> much more quietly and peaceably conducted than <del>when</del> they were when I<lb/> was minister here before.  There are a great many young people married and un&#45;<lb/>married who both think and act far differently to what was then the mode.  They<lb/> keep down the turbulent determinedly&#59; for still some of the old l<add>&#63;</add> remains&#44; constantly<lb/> kept in a state of fermentation by one of the most mischievous men I ever met with.  Some<lb/> of these dissatisfied ones wanted no minister at all&#44; because their <add>&#63;</add> would have<lb/> been made larger to support him.  With the exception of a very very few&#44; whom I<lb/> hope by discretion and prudence to gain over&#44; <del>the <add>&#63;</add> </del> the whole body of members is well<lb/> affected to me.  We seldom have less than 150 to 180 persons present every<lb/> <date>Sabbath</date> morning about 20 to 25 every <date>Friday</date> Evening&#44; the same member to<lb/> mincha<add>&#63;</add> on <date>Sabbath</date>&#44; and about 35 or <date>Sabbath</date> Evening.  You will agree with me that this<lb/> is not bad.  I should say that our member&#44; all told&#44; approaches close to 400.</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Our funerals and marriages are conducted with great solemnity.  I have<lb/> had 2 of the former&#44; and one of the latter &#40;celebrated in Synagogue&#41; since my<lb/> arrival.  I spoke on Each occasion.  The marriage was a s<add>&#63;</add>gated one.  The<lb/> parties &#40;both Israelites&#41; <hi rend="underline">had</hi> already been married civilly in <placeName>New Grenada</placeName>&#44; and so it was<lb/> somewhat anomalous.  We anticipated some loud complaints when the new assessmt.<lb/> should be fixed&#44; as the tapes would be so much heavier&#44; but with the exception<lb/> of the <add>Hebrew</add> I before mentioned&#44; who threatened to create a scandal&#44; if his assessment<lb/> was not fixed at the sum he named&#44; there has not been a murmur.  The Representatives<lb/> refused to be frightened&#59; and so he is left to create what scandal he pleases.  But he<lb/> is so much disliked&#44; and Government is so rejoiced at the peaceable turn things<lb/> have taken under the new minister&#44; that he will&#44; no doubt&#44; take care of what he<lb/> does&#44; particularly as he is an arrant coward.  At this moment&#44; the feeling upper&#45;<lb/>most among the Jewish public is the enlargement of the Synagogue&#44; very much<lb/> needed.  For this purpose it is proposed to appropriate the present &#8220;reserve<lb/> fund&#44;&#8221; amounting to <del>about</del> &#36;3000&#44; and make up the deficiency in the required<lb/> sum by subscriptions among Jews and Christians.  Our old friend <persName>Mayer Wolff</persName><lb/> is very enthusiastic on the subject&#44; so are <persName>Dr. Pretto</persName>&#44; <persName>Messrs. Osorio</persName>&#44; <persName>Debatte</persName>&#44;<lb/> <persName>F<add>&#63;</add></persName>&#44; <persName>Cardozo</persName>&#44; <persName>De Solla</persName>&#44; <persName>Lusia</persName>&#44; <persName>Alexr. Levy</persName>&#44; <persName>Myer</persName>&#44; <persName>Piza</persName> and many others.<lb/>  I will keep you posted in the matter as it progresses.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Sunday School will&#44; I hope&#44; very soon be reorganized on its old<lb/> popular footing&#44; and the ceremony of confirmation be again introduced<lb/> agreeably to Law.  There is a good deal of true religious fervor among the<lb/> majority&#44; and a total indifference to religion&#44; its decencies&#44; and obligations among<lb/> a few families.  But with time the latter may come round.  There is work<lb/> enough cut out for me&#44; but&#44; with God&#39;s blessing&#44; I hope to get through it.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">There has been some demand for your prayer books &#40;Sephardim&#41;<lb/> Pentatuech&#44; and small English Bibles.  You can send 25 of the latter&#44; and<lb/> a few of each of the former&#44; by <hi rend="underline">the very first opportunity</hi>.  <date>Sabbath</date> is so<lb/> very near that I cannot venture to write more&#44; and as I was assured<lb/> that my news would be more welcome than any observations I might<lb/> make on the strange conduct of one of your former friends&#44; about<lb/> which you last wrote me&#44; I delay making any remarks on your letters<lb/> till I next take up my pen.  <persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> has not yet joined me&#44;<lb/> but she was still in the same unhappy condition as when I left.<lb/>  About <persName>Miss Aguilar&#39;s</persName> reprinted works&#44; I have been forestalled by the person<lb/> you originally appointed here&#44; but I dare say you will get a good<lb/> subscription list.  I will however do my best.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">May God bless and protect you and keep you in health and<lb/> happiness for many years prays Your friend <add>Hebrew</add></p>
				<p><persName role="author">MNNathan</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
