<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item140</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Albany, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1850-08">19 August 1850</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item140_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item140_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item140_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item140_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Albany</placeName>
                <date>August 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1850</date>.</p>
            <p><addressee>Mr Isaac Leeser</addressee>!</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Rev. Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The moment your Occident came to hand, I<lb/>
                <sic>intentend</sic> to write an epistle as an answer against<lb/> the unjust
                charges and your <sic>comentary</sic> towards <persName>Dr Wise</persName><lb/> but
                several causes and my limited knowledge of the<lb/>
                <sic>english</sic> and <sic>hebrew</sic>, prevented me to do so, as my respect<lb/>
                towards you and <persName>Wise</persName> are so great, that I feel myself<lb/> for
                the present unable to do justice to both, and the<lb/> subject itself. But the
                earnest zeal with which<lb/> I am interested in the cause of Judaism, and the
                love<lb/> of truth make it notwithstanding my duty, to give<lb/> you an impartial
                statement of things as they are<lb/> and for the rest I leave it entirely to your<lb/>
                <sic>judgement</sic> to make use of it or not; it will<lb/>
                <del>take</del> make you little trouble in comparison of<lb/> abilities! The
                Occident is for this moment not at<lb/> my hands and therefore can I only allude to
                it<lb/> by recollection Your heading <persName>Dr W.</persName> and his
                congregation<lb/> it was the whole matter differently from what it is; when<lb/> you
                will read what follows.</p>
            <p><persName>Mr Spanier</persName> lives as I <sic>unterstand</sic> some 6 or 8
                years<lb/> in this place, but never <sic>mettled</sic> with <sic>jews</sic> or
                Judaism,<lb/> and we know that he is not even so very <sic>scrupelous</sic> in<lb/>
                the keeping of the ten commandments. The congregation<lb/> here is like all the
                    <sic>american</sic> composed of Jews of so<lb/> many different tribes as there
                are states in unhappy<lb/>
                <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and consequently (coming to this yet the
                ignorance<lb/> of so many.) the body very <sic>heteregen</sic>!</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Through' the indefatigable exertions of <persName>Dr Wise</persName>, they<lb/> have
                been kept together and all the friends of order of<lb/> and com<add>m</add>on sense
                untied and are the true friends and<lb/> followers <persName>Wises</persName>. But
                as the immortal <persName>Goethe</persName> once<lb/> said, The Elephant must also
                have his house<add>?</add>, there<lb/> still remained some outcasts of society who
                when home<lb/> and idle make it their principle business, to raise<lb/> excitements,
                    <sic>disturbe</sic> meetings &amp;c &amp;c.—The friends of order<lb/> therefore
                thought it best to elect a Parnass who not<lb/>
                <sic>beeing</sic> in daily connections with those and having a<lb/> respectable
                appearance will fit best to make the<lb/> criers silent. They thought themselves the
                better <del>united</del><lb/> suited as their candidate did at any time not
                feign<lb/> the heartiest friendship to <persName>Dr Wise</persName>; and thought it
                possible<lb/> to retain <persName>Mr Wise</persName> who was elected in
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName> as<lb/> their minister.
                    <persName>Wise</persName> was by most of the members<lb/> petitioned to remain
                and with this hope they went<lb/> to the meeting, and moved to send a
                    <sic>comitee</sic> to<lb/> invite him to remain and to increase his salary.<lb/>
                This was the first officiating of <persName>Spanier</persName>, and whilst<lb/>
                declaring that it be the duty of every man to secure<lb/> the services of
                    <persName>Wise</persName>, he opposed the increase of<lb/> the salary, because
                the financial condition of a cong.<lb/> of 150 members would not allow to expend
                $200 more<lb/> 2 years. This was the first jesuitical<add>?</add> act. In a<lb/>
                moment this sum. was raised by private subscription,<lb/> and the president didn't
                allow to put it in the<lb/> minutes. When the <sic>comite</sic>' was selected, the
                honorable<lb/> Pres. Sent 2 of the most vulgar enemies of <persName>Wise</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Wise</persName> who we certainly know acted with pure love<lb/> told me
                that he knows well that he wrongs his<lb/> family, by reaccepting his office, what
                is &amp; but<lb/> poorly paid, on comparison to what was offered to<lb/> him
                    <placeName>Charleston, <sic>Ca</sic></placeName> &amp; by considering that what
                I<lb/> have with pains and sorrow, <add>?</add> up in 3 years,</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>will fall to pieces, the children whom I educated<lb/> will cease to be what they are
                now they seeds of true<lb/> Judaism which I have <sic>platted</sic> in their hearts,
                will<lb/> be in vain makes it my duty to remain.</p>
            <p>You will therefore see the first plan of the order of<lb/>
                <persName>Loyola</persName> was destroyed but as <sic>as</sic> the forge of them is
                constantly<lb/> heated and no medium to Case for a Jesuit (and we know<lb/> them
                very well and must by all the acts from beginning<lb/> to end, of <persName>Mr
                    Spanier</persName> come to conclusion that he is<lb/> an agent of this
                    Teroor<add>?</add> society) the new plan was soon<lb/> fabricated. Convinced as
                the Parnass was, that all the<lb/> decent members are for all and all for one, are
                friends<lb/> of order and of <persName>Dr Wise</persName>, he now appears as father
                of<lb/> the poors, namely there were about 30 to 40 who were<lb/> partly not able,
                partly unwilling to contribute their yearly<lb/> contributions and were therefore by
                law not allowed<lb/> to vote. <persName>Mr Spanier</persName>
                <sic>adressed</sic> the meeting in a heart<lb/>rending language in behalf of them
                and they were released<lb/> from their debts and allowed to partake in all the<lb/>
                privileges with the other members. Before the moon<lb/> had made its monthly
                circulation some of this made<lb/> Spaniards in con<add>n</add>ection with 4
                    <del>baar</del> grogshop keepers<lb/> who are naturally opposed to
                    <persName>Wise's</persName> doctrines, who denounces<lb/> drinking and gambling
                in the boldest manner, came<lb/> out with a complaint if you my friend would
                only<lb/> read these documents, you would be obliged not only<lb/> to laugh at the
                folly, but to <sic>comdemn</sic> our Parnass for<lb/> ever. The principal complaints
                are stiled, <hi rend="underline">it is said</hi><lb/> that <persName>Mr.
                    W.</persName> has done this and that <del>and the</del> and<lb/> when the
                signers were asked about the <sic>containings</sic> of<lb/> their documents, they
                confessed that they <sic>dont</sic> know it;<lb/> they were presented to them, by
                the honorable Parnass<lb/> and Chasan and forced to sign!</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The only foothold the Parnass could make was <del>the</del> upon a trustee<lb/> who
                in opposition to <persName>Mr Wise</persName> opened his store on
                <add>שבת</add><lb/> and was <sic>repremanded</sic> by him. <add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr Spanier</persName><lb/> thought to justified, and when <persName>Mr
                    Wise</persName> stood on his<lb/> pulpit to deliver a sermon the Jesuit walked
                up, and<lb/> wanted to stop him. Our friend with all the presence<lb/> of mind and
                godly inspiration overpowered the assai<lb/>lant in com<add>m</add>encing and
                continuing a beautiful lecture,<lb/> and <del>fea</del> the Pres. fearing the
                vengeance of the<lb/> offended hearers in the <sic>singagogue</sic> left it,
                followed by 5<lb/> or 6 of his worthy companions.</p>
            <p>Where, is there a man or a Jew in the civilized world,<lb/> who would only copy a
                line of such a villain? when<lb/> instructed of his misdeeds?!</p>
            <p>The Parnass was paid and had 3 witnesses, who God alone<lb/> knows their hearts!
                swore to lies! amongst them was<lb/> our misguided Chasan! Amongst others to lead
                the<lb/> judge, in <add>?</add> the wrong way a Parnass <add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr. Y.</persName> was<lb/> cited as a <sic>wittness</sic>, and when asked,
                is it customary<lb/> with the Jews to abuse their ministers <del>ther</del> in
                such<lb/> a manner, he answered, Yes Sir! we do not care<lb/> about our ministers,
                we just as live abuse them as<lb/> not. What do you dear Sir say to this fruit
                of<lb/> jesuitical bribery such a blame upon Judaism in a<lb/> crowded court room?
                The assailant evicts all the<lb/> burdens of false witnesses, was fined and
                reprimanded!<lb/> But do you think man's baseness was stopped here?<lb/> No Sir! The
                trustees were again called together to <sic>expell</sic><lb/> the honorable
                    <persName>Dr Wise</persName> in consequence of the above<lb/> named groundless
                and perfidious charges, but the<lb/> wisdom and blasé plans of the Jesuit,
                wrecked</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
