<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item210</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1860s" source="" attested="yes">1860s</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 11 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">A <date>Thanksgiving</date> Address</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>&#8220;Oh bless our judge people&#44; &#38; make the voice of his praise be heard&#8221; Beloved hearers&#33;  If<lb/> under what circumstance soever it is a moving light to behold the creature in humble<lb/> adoration worship his Creator&#44; the impression upon the heart must be deeper still<lb/> when millions of immortal beings&#44; prompted by community of sentiments&#44; shout a<lb/> hallelujah to their Divine Benefactor&#59; and although the manner in which their tokens<lb/> of gratitude are exhibited&#44; may differ externally&#44; yet when the thought which pervades<lb/> the mind is but one&#44; it will harmonize every dissonance into a sweet accord.  As at<lb/> the touch of the <sic>skilful</sic> musician&#44; all the keys of a stringed instrument&#44; are attuned<lb/> into a unity of sound&#44; which delights the ear&#44; &#38; softens the soul&#44; so does<lb/> gratitude&#44; striking the chords of human hearts&#44; knit them together into a single chain<lb/> of godly affections.  And thus is why&#44; after he had enumerated some of the merciful acts<lb/> of the Deity&#44; the Shepherd King called upon all mankind&#44; to raise a hymn of thanks<lb/> to the Lord God of <placeName>Israel</placeName>.  &#8220;Bless <hi rend="underline">our</hi> God&#44; ye people&#8221; he exclaimed&#44; for ye all are the children<lb/> of his love &#38; the recipients of his bounty.  Because they first acknowledged his name&#44; he<lb/> chose the family of <placeName>Israel</placeName> as a kingdom of priests&#44; but He delights in the praise of every<lb/> creatures that has breath.  It is remarkable&#44; however&#44; that the sentence which precedes<lb/> this summons of the inspired writer&#44; and which we have selected for our text&#44; speaks of<lb/> the watchfulness of Providence in the government of nations&#44; &#38; of his wisdom in thwarting<lb/> the devices of the froward.  I will <del>read</del> cite it that you may ponder thereon&#58; It was thus. &#8220;He<lb/> ruleth by his power for ever&#44; his eyes behold the nations&#44; let not the rebellious exalt themselves&#8221;<lb/>  My Friends&#33;  It is to proclaim that self&#45;same truth&#44; that the pre&#45;beings who populate<lb/> our Commonwealth&#44; have solemnly assembled.  Do acknowledge that their prosperity as Penn&#61;<lb/>&#61;sylvanians&#44; and their greatness as an integral part of a glorious Confederacy&#44; spring <del>forth</del> from the<lb/> fountain of all good&#44; they have readily acquiesced in the pious request of their Governor.<lb/>  They have not convened together&#44; to triumph over the issue of sanguinary battles&#44; they have not<lb/> brought the trophies of recent conquests&#44; nor do they exult at this hour because their sword<lb/> has thinned the ranks of their adversaries&#59; they come not to the dwelling of the Eternal&#44; to rejoice<lb/> over their accession of dominion&#58; no&#44; a nobler incentive actuates the children of the American<lb/> Republic&#59; they meet to thank the Rock of all ages&#44; that He has vouchsafed to show unto them<lb/> also the year his mercy &#38; protection.  And indeed&#44; who can gainsay&#44; when recalling to his mind<lb/> the momentous events which have rapidly succeeded each other&#44; who can gainsay&#44; but that at the<lb/> opening of this year&#44; they foreb<add>&#63;</add> disasters&#33;  The honor of the nation was in jeopardy&#44; our<lb/> heirloom so precious &#38; so cherished&#44; had been polluted &#38; the swords of millions quenched in their<lb/> scabbards who curbed those vehement spirits&#44; that might have hastened to a fatal termination<lb/> a transaction which demanded unparalleled discretion&#63;  God in his mercy.  God &#8220;whose eyes<lb/> behold the nations&#8221; stood at the right hand of the just &#38; averted from them impending<lb/> dangers.  He dispelled the mist which was fast gathering around our horizon&#44; &#38; honor &#38;<lb/> peace continued to harbor wither our territories.  Across the mighty ocean was the olive<lb/> branch wafted &#38; they with whose community of language &#38; community of interests bound with<lb/> us&#44; disavowed their connivance at any act of advised contempt.  But not alone from<lb/> without were the arms of the Lord extended to uphold our national dignity &#38; withhold<lb/> our hand from being imbued in human blood&#44; but written likewise&#44; He proved our stanchion<lb/> in the hour of trial.  A deleterious seed had taken root amidst the salubrious plants<lb/> with which this garden of the <placeName>North</placeName> is replete&#44; it rapidly spread its <sic>venermous</sic> influence&#44;<lb/> &#38; threatened to sap the tree of life&#44; beneath whose foliage&#44; wearied humanity finds<lb/> a restoring shade.  But the air of heaven blighted its growth&#44; so that the stem it<lb/> brought forth&#44; must need wither &#38; die.  Ah no&#33;  God would not suffer this soil <sic>consumated</sic><lb/> to freedom&#44; to become a <placeName>land of Nod</placeName>&#44; where the exile would be denied a tranquil house.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>for this also &#8220;is a land that the Eternal careth for&#44; &#38; which his eyes are even upon&#44; from the<lb/> beginning of the year&#44; even unto the end of the year&#8221;  He has cast a bulwark around it&#44; He<lb/> has girded its walls with strength&#44; He has enriched it with the treasures hid in the earth.<lb/>  The sea offers tributes unto it&#44; &#38; the gold of <placeName>Theba&#39;</placeName> is poured into its lap.  Like ancient<lb/> <placeName>Tyre</placeName>&#44; &#8220;the merchants thereof are true princes&#44; and the traffickers the honorable of the country&#8221;<lb/> They bid them &#8220;surfit messengers&#8221; go&#44; &#38; they return fraught with choicest products of remote<lb/> climes.  With their enterprising genius they have cooled&#44; as it were&#44; their cities &#38; towns<lb/> &#38; with the velocity of thoughts&#44; from one <add>&#63;</add> to its opposite one&#44; they interchange<lb/> their wishes.  But all this <hi rend="underline">Providence</hi> has wrought.  Providence&#44; &#8220;whose eyes behold the<lb/> nations&#8221; had blessed these regions with an ever growing prosperity&#44; but solely because he<lb/> had reserved them as a palladium of persecuted humanity&#44; while the oppressed of the<lb/> earth&#44; shall reap unmolested the fruits of God&#39;s bounty&#44; new viz our &#38; new freshness&#44;<lb/> shall be added to this land of the free&#44; but if theories subversive of the principles of justice&#44;<lb/> should ever be engrafted in their political core then......but no&#44; it shall never occur.<lb/>  &#8220;God is in the midst thereof&#8221; God shall be her daily guardian&#44; that &#8220;the rebellious may<lb/> not exhalt themselves&#8221; O bless <del>our God</del> them ye people&#44; &#38; make the voice of his praise be<lb/> heard &#8220;Already in the brief period&#44; that elapsed since we last entered his courts with Thanksgiving<lb/> the Almighty gave palpable evidence of his <del>watchfulness</del> vigilance over our nations preservation.<lb/>  He has proven to us&#44; &#38; to the world at large&#44; that He will rescue that matchless constitution<lb/> framed by the Sages of this Republic&#44; both from foreign machinations &#38; domestic fanaticism&#44;<lb/> &#38; even letters&#44; when we appeared to verge towards a catastrophe&#44; his pervading spirit directed<lb/> the mind of the American Constituents&#44; that this beloved Union of ours&#44; might not be<lb/> scathed.  But I am warned&#44; that it is not <sic>not</sic> from the pulpit that the political<lb/> events of the day ought to be descanted upon&#44; &#38; truly my brethren&#44; such was not my design.<lb/>  I have cursorily adverted to them&#44; solely to draw therefrom a tribute of thanksgiving to<lb/> our Celestial Benefactor.  May He grant that whenever they recur to our thoughts&#44; the<lb/> feelings they shall arouse may be&#44; like at this hour&#44; <del>a</del> noble pride &#38; heartfelt gratitude&#44;<lb/> for&#44; we cannot too highly value that inheritance which ensures to every one&#44; the free<lb/> exercise of his religious tenets&#44; &#38; the full possession of his inherent rights.  Yet it may<lb/> be&#44; that these inestimable immunities&#44; bequeathed to us by the venerated leaders of the<lb/> revolution&#44; have lost in the sight of their successors somewhat of their excellency&#44;<lb/> for <del>what</del> that which is daily attained without any effort&#44; fails to impress the mind<lb/> with its sterling worth.  He has been ever wont to set at a luxurious table&#44; cannot<lb/> rightly imagine the pangs occasioned by hunger&#59; and <del>are</del> neither can be who has<lb/> ever basked in the sun of liberty&#44; conceive the horrors concomitant with an existence<lb/> drawn in the darkness of tyranny.  But ask it&#44; my friends&#44; ask it of them who<lb/> seek shelter beneath the extensive folds of the star spangled banner&#44; &#38; they will tell<lb/> how invigorating to the mind&#44; how vivifying to the soul is the shadow it overspreads.<lb/>  They who felt the iron arm of despotism&#44; they who saw the noblest of God&#39;s creatures<lb/> caged in dungeons&#44; or scourged by the <add>&#63;</add>&#44; because&#44; like your immortal progenitors&#44;<lb/> they sought to tear their shackles asunder&#44; they will say&#44; how ineffably delight&#61;<lb/>&#61;ful it is to possess the consciousness of one&#39;s independence&#44; to feel certain<lb/> that no man&#44; however great or powerful can&#44; at his will&#44; crush another<lb/> man to the earth&#44; and this consciousness&#44; this assurance&#44; every one of you<lb/> carries within himself.  It will beseem you therefore&#44; to <sic>forego</sic>&#44; one day in the<lb/> year&#44; your worldly vocations&#44; &#38; convey unto the altar of your heavenly Protector&#44;<lb/> sentiments of thankfulness&#44; for &#8220;his eyes which behold the nations&#44; have</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p>Deigned to look down upon you with peculiar benignity.  Through his<lb/> vigilance was your national dignity upheld&#44; your internal peace&#44; maintained&#44;<lb/> and by his grace the stream of your prosperity continued to flow uninterruptedly.<lb/>  But despite the fruition of these blessing which God has supremely granted to us&#44;<lb/> we might&#44; beloved hearers&#63; be not happy.  I do not mean&#44; individually &#40;for amid<lb/> the struggles of life&#44; nothing save an unwavering faith can render us thus&#41; but nationally.<lb/>  If the Almighty &#8220;shut up the heaven that there be no rain&#8221; if the sun instead of ripening<lb/> our products by a general heat&#44; devoured the labor of the husbandman&#44; we would<lb/> lack the principal element of happiness.  It was in view of this incontrovertible fact that<lb/> the chief executive of our state&#44; invited us to publicly avow the mercy of the omnipotent<lb/> &#8220;who has crowned the past year with his goodness&#44; &#38; caused our paths to cross with fatings&#8221;<lb/>  The unusual severity of the winter did not cut off the staff of life.  The vernal season<lb/> was propitious&#44; summer &#38; autumn smiled upon our soil.  Not alone we &#38; our children&#44;<lb/> shall&#44; God willing&#44; rejoice at the teeming of our crops&#44; but nations we know not&#44; will eat<lb/> of our plenteous harvest &#38; be satisfied.  Ought we not then to be thankful&#63;  Contrast<lb/> your thriving condition with that of continental <placeName>Europe</placeName>.  See&#44; how a protracted war has<lb/> drained the sources of wealth&#44; see the lands which might have yielded treasures&#44; lying<lb/> fallow&#44; because the stalworth arms of the <sic>ploughman</sic><add>&#63;</add>&#44; were made <del>the</del> to <sic>weild</sic> the sword.<lb/>  Here&#44; poverty thicken the operatives rise against their rulers&#44; there&#44; they are compelled to<lb/> maintain by their industry&#44; the pageants of an idle aristocracy.  In one place the&#44; so<lb/> called&#44; servitors of religion&#44; fatten upon the hard&#45;earned <del>earned</del> substance of the laymen&#44; in<lb/> another the riches of the country are sent afar off to replenish the coffers of foreign poten&#61;<lb/>&#61;tates.  And ought we not to be thankful&#63;  Ought not the knowledge that our<lb/> opulence is solely ours &#38; our children&#39;s&#44; <del>is</del> that handcraft obtains a commensurate re<lb/>&#61;muneration&#44; that the ministers of religion have no <sic>ascendency</sic>&#44; save in imparting the<lb/> dogmas of these various creeds&#59; that we recognize no master&#44; but Almighty God&#44; ought it<lb/> not I repeat it&#44; to swell our breasts with gratitude&#63;  But you will say&#44; that these<lb/> privileges which we enjoy&#44; are the natural consequences of our pre&#45;eminence in the scale<lb/> of civilization.  I shall not now compete your assertions&#44; but I will merely inquire whether<lb/> it is by adroitness alas that the clouds become pregnant with exhalations&#44; &#38; discharge upon<lb/> our land <add>&#63;</add>ious rains&#44; or whether we can by our ingenuity control light &#38; heat that they<lb/> may subserve our purposes.  So be sure&#44; our cooperation is <sic>needfull</sic>&#44; nay&#44; is indispen&#61;<lb/>sable to render the gifts of the heavens useful to men&#44; but if the former refuses us these<lb/> favors&#44; all the combined efforts of the latter would prove futile &#38; abortive.  Let us then<lb/> own our utter dependence upon the Creator of the universe&#44; &#38; as we have been recom&#61;<lb/>&#61;mended &#8220;bless the Lord our God with unison of thoughts&#44; &#38; make the voice of his praise be heard&#8221;<lb/> for he alone is the author of our maternal &#38; moral advancement.  &#8220;He opens his hand widely&#44;<lb/> to satisfy <hi rend="underline">every living being</hi>&#8221; Yes&#44; by filling our granaries with his goodness&#44; he benefits mankind<lb/> at large&#44; as well as ourselves&#44; for&#44; strangers flock to our shores&#44; &#38; are made participants of<lb/> our affluence.  By sustaining our liberal constitution&#44; he confers a boon alike open &#38; upon<lb/> the human race&#44; because from it&#44; the aliens together with the denizens&#44;derive security<lb/> &#38; peace.  By yearly consolidating the bonds of our Union&#44; despite the machinations of spurious<lb/> children who see their dissolution&#8212;he significantly demonstrates&#44; that he will be unto this<lb/> land of freedom &#8220;a wall of fire round a bout&#8221; &#38; he will be his glory in the midst thereof&#8221;<lb/> Our strength then&#44; my beloved brethren is enormable<add>&#63;</add>&#44; because it is founded upon the execution<lb/> of what is just &#38; true&#59; the republics of antiquity&#44; &#38; throne of medial ages crumbled into<lb/> dust&#44; because egotism &#38; self&#45;aggrandizement were their props.  They reputed <hi rend="underline">themselves</hi><lb/> the source of light&#44; &#38; the rest of mankind their satellites.  <placeName>Greece</placeName> &#38; <placeName>Rome</placeName> deeming<lb/> to have reached the climax of civilization&#44; looked down with disdain upon millions</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>of Gods creatures.  Whosoever was born beyond their domains was styled with the name<lb/> of barbarian.  <persName>Venue</persName> &#38; <persName>Genon</persName>&#44; struggling for supremacy&#44; made the <placeName>Adriatic</placeName> stream<lb/> with blood.  <persName>Pisa</persName> &#38; <persName>Horance</persName> jealous of each other&#44; exhausted their vigor in fratri<lb/>cidal wars&#44; and now of their military prowess&#44; &#38; of <del>theses</del> their vast conquests&#44; the<lb/> memory alone has been left.  But our strength is invisible also&#44; my friends&#44; because it is<lb/> not borrowed from foreign bayonets&#44; but it rests upon the moral sentiment of every free<lb/> citizen.  <placeName>Europe</placeName> is disorganized &#38; disrupted.  Compacts formed but yesterday&#44; are to&#45;day<lb/> barefacedly violated.  Monarchs that seemed to have forgotten&#44; in struggling in the same<lb/> cause&#44; their inveterate antipathies&#44; have proven unfaithful to one another&#59; and now the<lb/> disgraceful sight of a constitutional government leagued with a <sic>grovelling</sic> despotism&#44; is to be<lb/> exhibited to the astounded world.  Why is the history of that continent to be sullied by events<lb/> so opprobrious&#63;  Because its political institutions are rotten to the core&#44; &#38; to prevent their<lb/> downfall&#44; every means&#44; even the foulest&#44; must unscrupulously be resorted to.</p>
				<p>But our strength is invincible&#44; mainly because it is built upon the Rock of all ages.  <hi rend="underline">That</hi><lb/> has ever been our impregnable fortress.  You remember the motto upon the ensign of true<lb/> patriots who fought under the immortal <persName>Warren</persName>.  On one side the words &#8220;Appeal to heaven&#8221;<lb/> were inscribed in blazing characters&#44; whilst on the other&#44; the later device &#8220;Zim branstaht sustinet&#8221;<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> shone&#44; as an evidence of their conviction that the <hi rend="underline">Omnipotent</hi> would have<lb/> wrought their salvation.  And the same faith old prove&#44; amidst all the perils of the<lb/> revolutionary war&#44; the sustaining power of our gallant leaders.  They never despaired of<lb/> success&#44; but uplifted hands they invoked the blessing of the God of battles in their sacred cause&#44;<lb/> hence&#44; when a victory had signalized their progress&#44; or when their enemies <del>war</del> had been<lb/> routed they summoned their brethren to a solemn convocation and together in the dwelling<lb/> of the Eternal &#8220;they made the voice of his praise be heard&#8221;  I know not&#44; whether it is from<lb/> this ancestral <sic>habitude</sic>&#44; that our annual <date>day of thanksgiving</date> derives its origin&#44; but spring<lb/> whence it may&#44; it argues well for the descendants of our magnanimous forefathers&#44; it<lb/> proves that although the pernicious connexion between religion &#38; politics has been for<lb/> ever dissolved&#44; yet the former refulges<add>&#63;</add> with undimmed brightness in the eyes of the sons<lb/> of <placeName>America</placeName>.  It proves&#44; what the enemies of liberty&#44; would fair <hi rend="underline">dis</hi>prove&#44; that<lb/> the true of religion&#44; takes deeper root&#44; thrives more quickly&#44; &#38; sends its ramifications far<lb/> &#38; wide&#44; whenever the dew of heaven irrigates a soil consecrated to freedom.  I call <hi rend="underline">that a</hi><lb/> pure religion&#44; which&#44; like a spring which nature has fashioned&#44; flows spontaneously&#44;<lb/> &#38; such a religion can only be evinced&#44; where the conscience is <sic>untramelled</sic>.  Here therefore&#44;<lb/> tokens of piety&#44; ought to be the exponent of one&#39;s inward sentiments&#44; and when we meet&#44; like<lb/> upon this day&#44; to raise a hallelujah to our Celestial Benefactor&#44; we should lay upon his<lb/> altar a <hi rend="underline">sincere</hi> offering of thanksgiving.  The recollection of past benefits&#44; crowding our<lb/> minds&#44; ought to make our hearts overflow with gratitude &#38; such <del>was</del> has been the purport of<lb/> my address.  I have striven to instill the belief that our prosperity&#44; during the year<lb/> was the immediate effect of the goodness of the Most High.  But He upheld our dignity&#44;<lb/> when it was impugned&#44; that by his unceasing watchfulness was the subtlety of<lb/> miscreants&#44; detected &#38; frustrated&#59; that through his benignity&#44; was our Confederacy spared<lb/> the <sic>calamaties</sic> which afflict foreign climes&#44; &#38; lastly that He has&#44; not alone for our sake<lb/> but for that of afflicted humanity&#8212;whom we call brethren&#44; &#38; whom we generously invite<lb/> to partake of our happiness&#8212;powerfully cemented our glorious Union&#44; that it may endure<lb/> &#8220;as the days of heaven upon earth&#8221;.  Now&#44; my beloved hearers&#33;  <sic>if</sic> I have succeeded in<lb/>  bringing these solemn truths home to your hearts&#44; I may hope to achieve a still greater success<lb/> I may hope to rejoice at the supreme eminence which this city of love&#44; will attain in the<lb/> scale of religious influence.  As in the days of her youth&#44; she was the <placeName>Areopagus</placeName><lb/> where the wrongs against humanity were vindicated&#59; as <del>th</del> at that primeval time of <placeName>America</placeName></p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p>glory&#44; she was the ark of the covenant&#44; towards which the eyes of the faithful<lb/> looked for their deliverance&#44; so will she now&#44; by exhibiting a pious demeanour&#44;<lb/> become a prototype&#44; which millions will strive to copy.  Clinging with<lb/> unyielding tenacity to the charter of her noble Constitution&#44; she will never<lb/> ally herself with proscriptive castes&#59; love is her name&#44; &#38; from love will<lb/> she draw inspiration.  The memory of her unparalleled achievements&#44; during<lb/> four scores of years&#44; will convince her&#44; that whilst she adheres to the<lb/> doctrines of her sages&#44; she shall grow in might &#38; grandeur&#59; but what<lb/> will impel her with greater force to pursue the same course unswervingly<lb/> is the desire of doing what is right in the signs of the Lord God.  In<lb/> the volumes which she reveres has been written &#8220;Love they neighbor as thy<lb/>&#61;self&#8221; &#38; <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> will ever act in pursuance to this hallowed<lb/> commandment.  She will not tear asunder the ties which bind her<lb/> to the whole human race.  She will not <del>drown</del> sink into egotism&#44; &#38;<lb/> disown those who suffer&#44; because the land of their nativity lies beyond<lb/> her boundaries&#44; but kindles with brotherly love&#44; she will stand erect upon<lb/> her &#47; high&#45;places&#44; and &#8220;come&#44;&#8221; will she exclaim &#8220;leave ye all&#44; who eat<lb/> the bread of anguish&#44; &#38; drain the cap of sorrow&#44; come and call the<lb/> choicest fruits planted in my garden&#44; with them shall ye satisfy your<lb/> hunger&#44; &#38; in my teats ye shall dwell in place&#44; for <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> is<lb/> &#8220;the city of righteousness&#44; the city of fidelity.&#8221;</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p>are the laws of righteousness and whose sole defender is peace.  Oh&#33; let us pray for the<lb/> dawning of that joyous day when thirty five reunited States shall offer a national<lb/> thanksgiving&#44; while the symbol of their greatness shall proudly wave over every<lb/> <add>&#63;</add>ome and spire.  Let us pray for peace.</p>
				<p>Parent of good&#33;  we lay prostrate at the footstool of Thy mercy and crave for peace&#44;<lb/> grateful for Thy manifold favors at all times and this year especially&#44; we yet cannot fully<lb/> rejoice in its fruition.  Thou hast verily filled to overflowing the cup of our prosperity&#44; but<lb/> that of bitter sorrow is also brought night to our lips.  The aspect of the dead&#44; the<lb/> agony of the wounded&#44; the moaning of the sufferers&#44; tear our hearts.  From the<lb/> insanguined battle field&#44; from the chilly and dreary camps&#44; from the bereaved and lonely<lb/> hearth&#44; a voice rises unto Thee&#44; O compassionate Lord&#33; and &#8220;peace&#44; peace&#8221; it cries.  Oh I send<lb/> a ray of Divine wisdom to <sic>illumme</sic> the mind of our Chief Magistrate&#44; that he may discover<lb/> the instrument of peace.  Let the gentle spirit of forbearance hover around the Assembly<lb/> of our Senators and <del>&#63;</del> Representatives and guide their deliberations.  Repress the vehemence<lb/> of zealots&#44; and let the feelings of the obdurate be softened by tokens of brotherhood and love.<lb/>  May we speedily throng again.  My holy courts&#44; to thank and praise Thy name&#44; oh most High God&#33; for the longed&#45;for peace of our beloved Union.<lb/> and now I beseech Thee O Lord&#33; to excite within us a sentiment of patriotism&#44; that we may<lb/> enlist our names among those of our beneficent men and women who labor for the sake of our<lb/> defenders at sea and on land.  May our hospitals&#44; our sanitary commissions and our<lb/> soldiers and societies obtain a ready and generous cooperation from those who have been taught<lb/> to believe that &#8220;Charity <del>deli&#63;</del> delivereth from death&#8221; May such be Thy gracious will&#44; O<lb/> Heavenly Creator.  Amen.</p>
				<p>a <date>thanksgiving</date> discourse for the year <date>1864</date></p>
				<p rend="There is an arrow pointing&#44; from the right&#44; at the last line of the text above."></p>
				<p rend="The following text is added in red ink.">This is from another sermon by <persName role="author"><sic>Morris</sic></persName><lb/> NOTE the IDENTICAL writing of not only<lb/> all the page <hi rend="underline">but</hi> especially of the<lb/> word &#8220;<date>THANKSGIVING</date>&#8221; with that on the cover<lb/> sheet of this sermon</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
				<p rend="The first 5 lines of the text are written in red ink."></p>
				<p rend="Note&#58;">ORIGINAL<lb/> size of letter<lb/> by<lb/> <persName role="author">Sabato Morais</persName><lb/> &#40;see attached<lb/> for enlargement&#41;</p>
				<p>at a special meeting of the Faculty of Maimonides College held<lb/> in consequence of the sad<add>&#63;</add> bereavement <del>lately</del> recently sustained by<lb/> the house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; the following preamble and resolution were<lb/> unanimously adopted</p>
				<p>Whereas the demise of the <persName>Revd Isaac Leeser</persName> is deemed by<lb/> each of us a national loss&#44; and whereas it is our conviction<lb/> that the establishing of this institution was principally due<lb/> to the unremitting exertions of our late colaborer&#44; and to his<lb/> constant advocacy of religious education&#44; therefore</p>
				<p>Resolved that we express our feelings of deep sorrow at the<lb/> loss of a man so zealous for the moral welfare of his people&#44;<lb/> so energetic in promoting the culture of human knowledge&#44; so<lb/> efficient as a professor&#44; so exemplary assiduous in the discharge<lb/> of all his duties.</p>
				<p>Resolved that we <del>gladly</del> descry bearing our testimony to the uniform kindness and<lb/> courtesy that marked his official relations with us&#44; and to<lb/> his timely and useful suggestions as <del>the</del> Provost of this college</p>
				<p>Resolved that we will ever cherish his memory as that of a friend&#44;<lb/> and teach <del>our</del> the students of this Institution to revere his <del>memory</del> name</p>
				<p>Resolved that these resolutions be published one of our dailies &#38; in all Jewish<lb/> periodicals&#59; <del>and</del></p>
			<p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">S. Morais</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(5)">sect Pt.</p>
				<p><date>February 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1868</date></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
