<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item201</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">De Sola,
                            Abraham</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Joseph, J.
                            H.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-02">26 February 1851</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 12 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <addressee>J H Joseph Esqr.</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Dear Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">Many thanks for <persName>Mr Leeser's</persName> letter which I read
                with every<lb/> feeling but of pleasure. I shall make no apology to trouble you with
                a further communication—perhaps<lb/> a long one on this same subject, as I desire
                you should know all particulars, and I honestly tell you<lb/> that not only have I
                no objection that you should inform <persName>Mr L</persName> what I say in reply to
                his last to you<lb/> but I am quite content he should read every word following.
                This letter may be seen by one or by a thousand<lb/> I care not, for every one may
                know that I have, and am again ready to aver in the most solemn manner, yes,<lb/> in
                the name of God who made me, that I never sought to injure <persName>Mr L</persName>
                with his congregation—that to the best of my<lb/> judgment I never did or said
                anything to lessen his success &amp; promote my own—that I never had any desire to
                supplant<lb/> him in his situation whilst I thought he stood the least chance of
                retaining it—that it was only with others<lb/> I desired to contest it, and that
                throughout I entertained for him none but sentiments of kindness &amp;
                sympathy—<lb/> how I would not &amp; could not write or say this much for a brother
                or a father did I trust know it was truth—I flatter<lb/> myself I need not assure
                you of this. I do not say that a more <hi rend="underline">experienced</hi> person
                would not have acted differently<lb/> but I do not truthfully say that none could
                have acted with more honesty of purpose, and under the former im-<lb/>pressions that
                after the protracted &amp; serious dissensions between <persName>Mr L</persName>
                &amp; his congr. I could do him no injury to<lb/> act as I did. These are
                protestations, say, but took at the facts.</p>
            <p>As you know I have been in correspondence with <persName>Mr L</persName> since my
                arrival in this country <date>Jany. '47</date>. I need not look<lb/> back to
                    <persName>Mr L's</persName> earlier letters but it is now some 18 months since
                he told me he was not popular (generally with<lb/> his flock &amp; that his
                re-election was by no means sure. The publication of his strictures on his cong. in
                the Oc. <date>October 49</date><lb/> the action taken by them thereupon certainly
                would not be calculated to Open the breach. In a lengthy letter from<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> dated <date>Oct 49</date> I have the full history of his
                Ministry in <placeName>Phil.</placeName> To that date. In this letter <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> speaks of the unmerited<lb/> &amp; powerful persecution he had
                experienced from his opponents—of the impossibility of getting two thirds of
                the<lb/> votes necessary for the <hi rend="underline">repeal of the bond
                law</hi>—under which condition only, <persName>Mr L</persName> writes as indeed he
                had publicly<lb/> printed in the Oc. he would take office. “As I will not sign a
                contract such as was offered there is only the<lb/> alternative of <hi
                    rend="underline">withdrawing fighting to the last</hi>.” Again, he says he
                cannot &amp; will not yield one point, &amp; scorns<lb/> the <sic>adjunta's</sic>
                vote of censure. It is unnecessary to quote other paragraphs from this letter
                expressive of the same<lb/> determination. Thus already some 15 months ago
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> spared me of his determining not to yield to the
                congre-<lb/>gational terms, and so long ago had Is<add>?</add> all the world learnt
                through the Oc. That the congn. had determined not to<lb/> yield to <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> demands—witness the rejection by them of the new bye-law for
                Hazan, offered by <persName>Mr S Solis</persName>, and<lb/> the motion to do away
                with the bond, which latter motion they had uniformly rejected on all other
                occasions<lb/> &amp; by large majorities, as I learn from <persName>Mr
                    C's</persName> letters. On <date>16 Octr.</date>, my earliest leisure, in reply
                to <persName>Mr I.</persName> I took the liberty<lb/> to censure the article in the
                    <date>Octr</date> Occident, plainly telling him that I thought he had done
                exceedingly wrong to hold all<lb/> his cong. to the severe<add>?</add> ridicule of
                the world—that he had thereby laid himself under the imputation of attempting<lb/>
                to gain by threats what he could not by persuasion &amp; argument or influence (This
                was not the language of one desiring him Evil)<lb/> And with respect to the bond I
                said that all with whom I had discussed the matter agreed that in <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> case he being<lb/> known to them 20 years, that it was uncalled
                for &amp; wrong though in the case of a stranger (or newcomer) the cong would<lb/>
                be justified to ask it, though even there the candidates simply subscribing a
                declaration of willingness to be governed<lb/> by existing by-laws would be
                preferable. I have referred to this circumstance at length because when in
                    <placeName>Phil.</placeName> I was<lb/> told I believe (but am not sure) by
                    <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> but it matters not <hi rend="underline">by</hi>
                whom that he had heard (from whom he did not say) that I had written <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> advising him not to sign the<lb/> bond it being beneath the dignity
                of a minister so to do (so as to get him out of the way I suppose!) but when I had
                    sense<add>?</add> of <persName>Mr L's</persName> absence from candidateship
                hereby I<lb/> turned round and was willing to do it myself. A very pretty charge to
                do me injury, but false as Christianity. A concoction<lb/> worthy the most rascally
                Jesuit around us. I am glad to know however that it did not; or could not, injure
                me<lb/> with so right-minded a person as <persName>Mr Solis</persName> to whom I
                know I explained the matter though cannot be sure whether<lb/> I broached it to him.
                The truth is as above. But a little more about this <add>?</add>. I never said I
                would sign the<lb/> bond. If elected I would ask to be excused as I do not admire
                it—but would not refuse signing if the retention<lb/> of the place depended upon it
                    (<del>mind</del> I speak of myself as a new comer) for I would not have the
                power of it<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName>
                <hi rend="underline">now</hi> has. If I signed it I should be doing nothing worse
                than <persName>Mr L</persName> had himself done on several occasions.<lb/> The bond
                I maintain degrades the congregation not the minister. There are many abuses in one
                synagogue government<lb/> which a Hazan must at present submit to. What if a Parnass
                    <hi rend="underline">orders</hi> a Hazan to call up to read to the Sepher a<lb/>
                man notoriously <add>?</add>. Could <persName>Mr L</persName> or any other Hazan
                refuse—he might get off doing so by his influence over<lb/> the Parnass. I could
                point out to you many cases wherein <persName>Mr L</persName> according to the
                present system must<lb/> submit to his <hi rend="underline">rulers</hi> in matters
                of much greater importance than signing the bond and I could show you</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>that he has done so. This does not say that we should not agitate by mouth &amp; pen
                to destroy these abuses. I believe<lb/> from my little experience that a Minister
                would by affectionate remonstrance, &amp; reasoning would soon (had he even a<lb/>
                little more influence than a stick) induce his flock to do away with so useless to
                say the least of it, a by-law<lb/> And I say further that it appears to me many
                would in <placeName>Phil</placeName> be willing to do away with the law but not<lb/>
                for <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>. Perhaps the new incumbent might get them not to
                ask him. <persName>Mr L</persName> was not asked I believe for the first<lb/> few
                years—he says because his enemies wished to serve their own purpose. But to continue
                with my letter<lb/> In conclusion I advise <persName>Mr L</persName> to take special
                care what he did &amp; above all not to write anything in his Oc. about<lb/> his
                cong. something as absurd the idea that he should put with them because of this bond
                business when in '41 (I believe)<lb/> the same thing occurred as you are perhaps
                aware and <persName>Mr L</persName>
                <del>signed</del> contrived by a <hi rend="underline">ruse</hi> which he afterwards
                regretted, to satisfy<lb/> them. In this letter I also offered to confer with you on
                the matter for <persName>Mr L's</persName> benefit, not doubting you would do all
                you<lb/> could in his behalf &amp; asked him permission to do so. On <date>3<hi
                        rend="sup">rd</hi> Dec</date>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> sends me copy of intended by law tells me your
                interference<lb/> would be useless, &amp; that any would be unpalatable to him. On
                    <date>March 27, 1850</date>, <persName>Mr L</persName> writes me “the die is at
                length<lb/> cast &amp; the congregation have resolved to advertise for a successor,
                after having endorsed the vote of censure of the Adjunta<lb/> &amp; refusing to
                repeal the bond law—appointing salary &amp; term of office for the successor.
                    (<persName>Mr L</persName> does not write me he wanted<lb/> a life term of
                office) on hearing of this fatal &amp; decisive step I wrote <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> (<date>9 April 1850</date>) expressing my surprise<lb/> &amp;
                regret at this intelligence, stating candidly however that I did not think this
                determination was come to by<lb/> the congregation because of the bond &amp;c but
                because “their spirit was not with him” i. e. that they did not care for him<lb/>
                and I as candidly intimated (also by a Hebrew <add>?</add>) that the breach was past
                healing, but to prove my esteem<lb/> I would, <hi rend="underline">did he
                    concur</hi>, get up a memorial (with <persName>Rev S M Isaacs</persName>) to be
                signed by the Jewish ministry generally<lb/> in his favor, I also asked him to point
                out to me how I could be of use to him. This letter brings up our
                corres-<lb/>pondence on this subject to about 2 months before the day appointed for
                election (viz <date>16. June</date>) And here let me ask you<lb/> whether it is
                strange I should begin to think that <persName>Mr L's</persName> chance of
                reconciliation or reelection was becoming<lb/> more &amp; more desperate (If I
                mistake not you were of opinion that <persName>Mr L</persName> would not have the
                least chance after his<lb/> article in <date>October</date> Occident) when in almost
                every letter for about 2 years he had told me so himself! Is it strange<lb/> I
                should entertain this idea when he more than once had told me the power of his
                enemies was too great to allow<lb/> him to suppose he would ever gain the 2/3rds he
                required to carry his measures, when he had informed the public that<lb/> he would
                not take the place but on his own terms, &amp; when they had also assured the public
                through the press<lb/> that he should not have it but on theirs &amp; by asking for
                others to fill the office (in their advertisement) showed that they cared not
                for<lb/> him to remain—when I knew he must either disgrace himself by giving the lie
                to his public &amp; private protestations<lb/> or stoop to the congregation (&amp; I
                had too high an opinion of his honesty to suppose he would do either) and when<lb/>
                I could not but know that the cong would not yield to him, as they had always &amp;
                uniformly upheld the bond<lb/> and when I viewed in conjunction with all this the
                continually increasing bad feeling between <persName>Mr L</persName> &amp; his
                flock<lb/> his strictures, their votes of censure &amp; determined opposition the
                former not trifles to a man of spirit, was I<lb/> so wrong in thinking <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> stood little or no chance of again occupying his old position. And
                could I desire his<lb/> injury let me also ask when I strongly advised him not to
                make the press the vehicle for his complaints<lb/> to be careful that he gave his
                enemies no farther advantage over him by losing temper &amp;c. Thus far I think even<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit that I have acted aright &amp; that my
                conclusions were by no means unnatural. To return On<lb/>
                <date>22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> April</date> I received <persName>Mr L's</persName>
                reply dated <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date>. He would permit my combining with
                    <persName>Isaacs</persName> &amp;c for the memorial “but<lb/> he knew it would
                be of no avail the influence on the other side being too great.” On the <date>23<hi
                        rend="sup">rd</hi></date> the day I received <persName>Mr<lb/>
                    L's</persName> letter I addressed <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> stating the
                case &amp; my conviction that “a respectfully worded memorial” I quote from my<lb/>
                letter to <persName>Mr I.</persName> “to be written by you &amp; signed by all of
                us” would do good, inviting him to take the initiative thinking<lb/> that both from
                age character &amp; influence he and not I was the man, &amp; because he was
                    <del>more</del> intimate with more<lb/> ministers than I. I received
                    <persName>Mr I's</persName> reply dated <date>26 April</date>. I omitted to
                state that <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> in his letter of <date>10</date>
                <add>?</add> me<lb/> that <add>?</add> I had already offered his services as
                mediator which he declined as useless but made no objection to a<lb/> combined
                action. <persName>Mr I</persName> however in this letter stated that it would now be
                perfectly useless. He writes<lb/> “I would gladly co-operate could <del>I</del> we
                achieve any good but knowing that none can be effected our time is<lb/> too valuable
                &amp;c” Does this answer <persName>Mr Leeser's</persName> charge that instead of
                attempting to make peace I was getting<lb/> up certificates” I have asked for no
                certificates up to this date. After such dampers from <persName>Messrs
                    Leeser</persName> &amp; <persName>Isaacs</persName><lb/> I thought it useless to
                persevere, and am of opinion now that I thought rightly. The same post that
                brought<lb/> me <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> letter brought me several
                communication from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, informing me among other
                things<lb/> that <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> had publicly stated I was the only
                person competent to succeed him (In my ignorance I thought,<lb/> that <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> not being willing longer to remain, was believed the curtain
                    <del>doing all he</del> recommending me)—again<lb/> that a large portion of the
                members desired me to apply—that certain parties had declared themselves my
                suppor-<lb/>ters, and though there would be other candidates (one was already
                however even if he had not applied viz <persName>Ellis Lyon</persName>)<lb/> still
                “there was none on the continent of <placeName>America</placeName> to oppose me.”
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> laughs at the idea of <persName>Mr
                    Lyons</persName><lb/> standing any chance of success. But I who have seen much
                more important congregations than <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> choose a
                    <add>?</add> because he had a fine voice did not think <persName>Mr
                    Lyons</persName> so laughable an opponent especially<lb/> as I heard he had
                family influence in <placeName>Phil</placeName>, which my ignorance then
                exaggerated, and I also know that his</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>brother whose influence through his congregation I thought might be great would also
                canvass for him. A member of my<lb/> congregation also had received a letter from
                his friends in <placeName>Phil</placeName> stating the same things. He showed me the
                letter I saw I<lb/> must apply without loss of time. I communicated with all my
                friends here (you &amp; <persName>Mrs Joseph</persName> were then<lb/> absent from
                    <placeName>Montreal</placeName>, and one &amp; all advised me as he had
                done—ridiculing any objections. They said “<persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/>
                <sic>cant</sic> be so unreasonable as to find fault with you ( I did not say that he
                would, at me remark <hi rend="underline">en parenthese</hi>)<lb/> for seeking for a
                situation he cannot &amp; will not longer hold. To suppose that the congregation
                will yield to him<lb/> he not being generally liked and not being altogether in the
                    <del>wrong</del> right, is absurd. <hi rend="underline">If the place had not
                    been advertised</hi><lb/> &amp; you solicited to apply, you might then hesitate.
                But now, hesitate, &amp; others will not.” Such was the language<lb/> of my friends
                both here &amp; elsewhere. I confess it was not without its effect on me. But what
                had greater effect on me was<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L's</persName> letter of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date>
                already referred to as that wherein he gives me leave to combine with
                    <persName>Isaacs</persName> for the memorial. He (<persName>Mr
                L</persName>)<lb/> commences by telling me that all my efforts would be useless in
                his behalf as far as his ministry is concerned, he could<lb/> not <hi
                    rend="underline">imagine the possibility of his being elected on terms agreeable
                    to himself</hi> (and yet, let me here remark in his last<lb/> letter to you he
                says as much that I am the other candidates <del>were</del> the cause of his not
                being elected. What had I staid<lb/> away—another would have come forward. To
                suppose that none would (who perhaps did not care one <add>?</add> for <add>?</add>)
                is<lb/> childish &amp; absurd But before any one had any idea of coming forward
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> plainly says he cannot imagine the possibility of his
                reelection on his terms. This being the case <persName>Mr L</persName> waited he
                owed it to his character both as a man &amp; a Jew <hi rend="underline">to retire
                    to</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">private life</hi>. Again says <persName>Mr L.</persName> “<hi
                    rend="underline">My engagement is precluded by the wording of the
                    advertisement</hi>.” Now my firm impression<lb/> from the forgoing was (as it
                would have been I think of every <sic>imprejudiced</sic> person that <persName>Mr.
                    L</persName> seeing he stood no<lb/> chance of success gave up the contest, and
                that with the great encouragement held out to me, and the persuasions of<lb/> my
                friends—honest thinking men too, I was now fully justified in doing what I heard
                    <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> &amp; others had already<lb/> done or was caring
                to do—and apply for the office—informing <persName>Mr L.</persName> thereof at the
                same time. But I will tell you<lb/> what I did presently. If I had any doubts as to
                the hopelessness of <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> cause the anonymous pamphlet which<lb/>
                <persName>Dr David</persName> and I received (on <date>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    April</date>) would have dispelled them. I would most assuredly, not at all
                refer to this pamphlet but that<lb/> it contains extracts of the minutes of the
                Cong. the truthfulness of which none has challenged. From these minutes I<lb/>
                learned what <persName>Mr L</persName> had never informed me—that in addition to the
                insurmountable obstacle of the bond, there<lb/> were other difficulties equally
                insurmountable (as the votes showed). <persName>Mr L</persName> had declared at the
                meeting of <date>24 March/50</date><lb/> through <persName>Mr A Hart</persName> that
                unless the tenure of office was during good behaviour (for life) <hi
                    rend="underline">he would not be a candidate</hi>, but<lb/> would remain 6
                months after expiration of his present term to afford the cong. an opportunity to
                get a successor not<lb/> withstanding which <hi rend="underline">the cong settled
                    the term at 10 years</hi>. Now would I be wrong in concluding from this
                circumstance<lb/> what <persName>Mr L</persName> himself wrote me “It was evident to
                me,” he says with reference to this meeting not this particular vote,<lb/> that my
                dismissal from office was resolved on. So I thought. The particulars of the term of
                office discussion<lb/> I did not learn from <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>. Now I
                could not think so ill of <persName>Mr L</persName> as to suppose that he would act
                contrary<lb/> to his declaration at the meeting &amp; accept 10 years, nor did I
                think, knowing that a large majority (including some who did<lb/> not ever to insist
                upon the bond as I afterwards heard) had determined <hi rend="underline">not to
                    grant</hi> the life tenure, such having<lb/> been the policy of the Kahal, as I
                learn from the extracts of the minutes; ever since they first had a regular
                Hazan<lb/> because as they assert (<date>Nov/42</date>) “a frequent occurrence to
                the election of their officers is the best check upon them.” I do<lb/> not desire to
                bear me the apologist of this assertion, but that such is the opinion of the
                majority of the <placeName>Phil.</placeName> Cong. I <sic>dont</sic><lb/> this
                moment sincerely believe. And in the very first letter received from <persName>Mr A
                    Hart</persName> he informs me that in the event<lb/> of our <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> not being a candidate (Let <persName>Mr L</persName> know that
                others besides me could use this expression) on <date>16 June</date> they would<lb/>
                reduce the term of office probably to 3 years. From all this I become convinced that
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> stood not the least chance<lb/> of election
                (especially as the cong would not, as he wrote me, “even hear him in his defence”) I
                also thought I had a<lb/> chance of being chosen—and that if I did not apply other
                persons—whitewashed Germans—would, leaving <persName>Lyons</persName><lb/> out of
                the question. Events prove my conjecture right. <persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> no
                doubt a learned &amp; estimable man—but still<lb/> as much a Portuguese Hazan as I
                am a German—has read as candidate in the synagogue Mikveh Israel (so I hear.) In
                his<lb/> letter of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date> I must not omit to
                state <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> told me he was then going (in the course of the
                week) to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and that it was “likely<lb/> enough that
                before my answer could reach him he would have left <placeName>Phila.</placeName>”
                He said moreover he could not call at<lb/>
                <placeName>Montreal</placeName> as he had intended but would hasten to be back by
                the day of election. On <date>23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> April</date> immediately
                on<lb/> receipt of <persName>Mr L's</persName> of <date>10<hi rend="sup"
                    >th</hi></date> I addressed <persName>Mr L</persName> directing one letter to
                    <placeName>Savannah</placeName> &amp; <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> (he had
                supplied me on <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> with<lb/> these addresses)
                    <del>in care<persName> J I</persName>
                    <add>?</add>
                </del> as <persName>Mr L</persName> might have left <placeName>Phil</placeName>
                before he could receive my letter. If you recollect<lb/> you sent me a slip of paper
                it came with the Oc. Whereon <persName>Mr L</persName> tells you he was not going
                yet, <del>?</del> for a few days. I believe<lb/> then it was a couple of
                days—perhaps one—after I had written <persName>Mr L</persName> to <placeName>N.
                    O.</placeName>—where you sent me the slip. <del>?</del> I then<lb/> wrote
                another letter to <placeName>Phil</placeName> thinking it might reach him before he
                left. I don't know the date of this<lb/> as it contained pretty much what I wrote in
                the one to <placeName>N. O.</placeName> I did not keep a copy of it. Both letters
                were<lb/> written in the desire not to do anything without <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> knowledge, &amp; so, afterwards, I would not have moved<lb/> a
                single step without his knowledge &amp; he might have guided me for his advantage,
                but that—he would not.<lb/> In these letters I told <persName>Mr L</persName> that I
                was convinced now that his connection with his congregation would be<lb/> at last
                severed. In this case I had determined I told <persName>Mr L</persName> to
                    <del>take</del> adopt the advice of my friends &amp; to write (which<lb/> I did
                by the same post which took <persName>Mr L's</persName> letter) to <persName>Mr
                    Hart</persName> acquainting him with my desire to be<lb/> considered a candidate
                for the office <hi rend="underline">in case <persName>Mr L</persName> was not &amp;
                    only in such case</hi>. <persName>Mr L</persName> says in his last letter</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to you that had I truly desired to <del>?</del> consult him I should have written to
                no one (not to <persName>Mr Hart</persName>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> means I<lb/> suppose) before applying to him. I never
                    <del>?</del> wished to consult <persName>Mr L</persName> as to the propriety of
                making a qualified application<lb/> The propriety of this step under the
                circumstances appeared to me to be too evident. I had no doubt of its propriety<lb/>
                &amp; therefore did not ask <persName>Mr L</persName>, I only asked him to guide me
                aright <hi rend="underline">for his advantage</hi>, not to tell me what<lb/>
                    seems<add>?</add> right honorable or religious to do. Thank God, I know my duty,
                my eyes were opened not jaundiced.<lb/> None of my friends had any doubts of the
                propriety of my conduct, nor had any of the Jewish Ministry with<lb/> whom I
                    correspond—<hi rend="underline">nay none has been expressed to me even by
                        <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> himself either by pen or mouth</hi><lb/>
                This I shall now show. The gentlemen I addressed for certificates a few days after I
                had written <persName>Mr L</persName> I was going <add>?</add>,<lb/> were
                    <persName>Messrs Lyons</persName>
                <persName>Raphall</persName> &amp; <persName>Wise</persName>.
                    <persName>Isaacs</persName> I did not ask for any I believe, through some
                inadvertence. <persName>Mr Lyons</persName>,<lb/> (who in <add>?</add> to
                    <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> I forgot to say I wrote to advise about
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> &amp; his cong.) wrote me that he desired<lb/> I would
                excuse his interest as he must devote it to his mother who had already bespoken it.
                Now if he thought it<lb/> right in his brother to apply he could not think it wrong
                in me—and I have good reason else, to know he did not.<lb/>
                <persName>Dr Wise</persName> writes me a very complimentary letter &amp; would
                recommend me at <placeName>Phil</placeName> but says that his recommendation<lb/>
                would do <del>him</del> me more inquiry than good desired as he was as a heretic but
                adds <persName>Dr W.</persName> go to <placeName>Phil</placeName>, let them<lb/>
                hear your intentions show them your abilities &amp; you will be elected—the best
                recommendation is your<lb/> own self.” Subsequently <persName>Rev D. A De
                    Sola</persName> (as just and good a man as any of us) approves highly my
                design<lb/> and bids me God speed. <persName>Rev Ansel</persName>
                <add>?</add> of <placeName>New York</placeName> most heartily wished me (when in
                    <placeName>N. Y</placeName>) success. <persName>Rev S M<lb/> Isaacs</persName>
                after waiting <add>?</add> that “all we could &amp; might have done (when we
                corresponded about the memorial).<lb/> had been destroyed by the congregation
                pamphlet” adds “your intention to become a candidate <hi rend="underline">is
                        <add>?</add>dedly</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">correct</hi>” and after some characteristic kind remarks adds
                “let me at once assure you of my readiness to<lb/> serve you. Your competition is I
                suppose <persName>Ellis Lyon</persName> &amp;c &amp;c. <persName>Rev David
                    Meldola</persName> chief Rabbi of the Portuguese<lb/> congregation,
                    <placeName>London</placeName> before and often he had written <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> offering his services to make peace between him and<lb/> the
                congregation most earnestly wishes my success and earnestly &amp; affectionately
                advises me to do all<lb/> I can for myself. I don't know whether <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> may consider this quote compatible with the letters <persName>Mr
                    Meldola</persName><lb/> wrote him. I think it is. He would like to see
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> remain if possible &amp; so would I. He does not think
                I<lb/> am wrong, however, in doing what I have done. Nor do I. His last letter to me
                on this subject was written <date>22nd<lb/> Novr.</date> last, about the same time
                he addressed <persName>Mr L.</persName> I should also state <persName>Mr
                    Meldola</persName> has heard all particulars from <persName>Mr
                Leeser</persName><lb/> Here there were some of our most prominent &amp; respectable
                ministers opposing my application. Surely <persName>Mr L</persName> will<lb/> not
                say they are all <persName>Baals</persName> prophets—he the only true one. How they
                thought it would have injured <persName>Mr L</persName> they would<lb/> not have
                advised as they did. They were quite aware of all attending circumstances.
                    <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> writes me<lb/> (<date>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>
                    May</date>) he <sic>enclose</sic> a testimonial which he hopes, will meet my
                views, but can only offer one his influence in <placeName>Phil</placeName><lb/> in
                case <persName>Mr L</persName> declares his intention not to accept the place even
                if elected. (<persName>Dr R</persName> apparently was not then aware<lb/> that
                    <persName>Mr L</persName>
                <hi rend="underline">had refused</hi> accepting office except under conditions
                frequently &amp; <add>?</add> absolutely <add>?</add>) how declining<lb/> to use his
                influence in my behalf but under certain conditions—to which only the latter
                amounts. (The letter<lb/> I have, &amp; is at <persName>Mr L</persName> service
                should he ever wish to see it—during this is not tantamount to “writing me<lb/> not
                to apply for <persName>Mr L's</persName> place” as <persName>Mr L</persName> says
                the Dr told him he did. This letter is the only one I have heard of the<lb/> Dr
                since &amp; I will leave it to any one to decide whether it contains one word
                recommending me not to apply.<lb/> Besides <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> could not
                have written to advise me not to do a thing he knew I (perhaps others) had
                already<lb/> done, nor would he have supplied me with a testimonial the design of
                which as he well knew was to <add>?</add> my views<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName> as I wrote him in asking for it. I did not see
                    <persName>Dr A</persName> nor any one but a <add>?</add> on arriving in
                    <placeName>New York</placeName> from<lb/>
                <placeName>Montreal</placeName> since I went almost immediately from the boat to the
                cars, but on my return to <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> I <add>?</add> with the
                Dr<lb/> who said you know I would do much to serve you but you must not apply for
                    <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> place (This was after<lb/> I had been in
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName>, recollect, &amp; had corresponded with <persName>Mr
                    Hart</persName>) I said I most assuredly did not desire to take <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> place<lb/> from him—and after stating to him <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> true position, I added I have not the same scruple to take it
                from other<lb/> candidates. What are there other candidates asked the Dr, there are,
                I said, and I knew this when I applied<lb/> or I would not have moved at all in the
                matter. Ok then, said <persName>Dr R</persName> that is a very different thing—that
                alters the case<lb/> and we will say nothing more about it” No doubt <persName>Dr.
                    R</persName> will also remember this conversation if recalled to him.
                    <del>?</del><lb/> Enough of this matter. I am at least guiltless of acting in
                opposition to any recommendation of the Dr for he gave<lb/> me none. There was
                another reason why I did not delay writing <persName>Mr Hart</persName> till I heard
                again from <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> after telling him I had made qualified
                application. It was this. I was by no means <add>?</add>; my letter would<lb/> reach
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> in <placeName>Phila.</placeName> He was not himself,
                as he wrote me on <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> Now before I could have got
                a reply from<lb/> the <placeName>South</placeName> supposing <persName>Mr
                        <add>?</add></persName> to have answered immediately some 6 or 8 weeks must
                have elapsed which would<lb/> have prevented my qualifying myself as candidate by
                visiting <placeName>Phil</placeName> &amp; reading one <date>Sabbath before 16
                    June</date>.<lb/> (<hi rend="underline">En passant</hi>—This is the custom in
                most synagogues—I had hoped &amp; intimated as much by letter to
                    <persName>Hart</persName>.) that<lb/> it would have been departed from me my
                case but all <persName>H</persName> wrote I also must submit. Hence my visit to
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName><lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> writes you in his last My disclaimer in case he should
                apply was no disclaimer at all as he had written<lb/> me he would not accept the
                terms proposed. Then if <persName>Mr L</persName> refused the terms proposed it was
                stating he would<lb/> not be a candidate, and that others might be <add>?</add>
                would accept the terms, and I would in such case<lb/> (as I had determined) have
                acted on my first communication to the cong, &amp; accepted if elected what
                    <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> refused. But see what I wrote to <persName>Mr
                    Hart</persName> &amp; the cong. and judge better or not I disclaimed my<lb/>
                desire to oppose <persName>Mr L.</persName> In my first letter to <persName>Mr
                    Hart</persName> sent with that to <add>?</add> informed <persName>Mr
                    Leeser</persName> thereof</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">2.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I write, “Should <persName>Mr L</persName> solicit for himself once
                more their suffrages I should consider it my duty not to contest them<lb/> with him
                but at once retire before one whose attainments &amp; prior connection with you
                doubtless entitle him to your support<lb/> not only before me but before all who may
                apply &amp;c **I cannot but express my sincere hope that you &amp; your present
                talented<lb/> Hazan may yet for many years be peaceably &amp; profitably connected
                together &amp;c” And on the <date>10 June</date> I addressed a letter to the<lb/>
                <placeName>Phila.</placeName> congregation through <persName>Mr A Hart</persName>
                which that gentleman acknowledged on the <date>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> and
                writes me should be recd on the meeting<lb/> of <date>16<hi rend="sup"
                    >th</hi></date> as I had requested it should to the congregation. In this I
                write the cong that as I heard when in <placeName>Phil</placeName>
                <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> would probably be a candidate, I called their
                attention to the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> letter written <persName>Mr Hart</persName>
                and add “should this prove true<lb/> I must beg to request that I be not put in
                nomination against him &amp;c. Now if the terms just quoted from my letters did<lb/>
                not amount to a disclaimer of candidateship were <persName>Mr L.</persName> on the
                field then I don't know what would. <persName>Mr L</persName> may doubt my
                having<lb/> attached my credence to the report of his intention to accept office
                after what has passed, but I did nevertheless, knowing and<lb/> I say this not
                disrespectfully of <persName>Mr L</persName>, knowing that he had before signed the
                bond under circumstance certain modifications<lb/> (and I presume the minutes of the
                cong more especially of <date>16 May 1841</date> &amp; <persName>Mr L'</persName>
                letters to me are sufficient proof of this) although<lb/> he had at first <hi
                    rend="underline">determined not to do so</hi>. But it is evident <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> did not &amp; does not give me credit for any honesty of
                purpose<lb/> he views my reservation as a mere plead and does not believe that had
                his friends been able to do what some told<lb/> me when in
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName> and <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> after I had left
                also, they desired to do, viz so notify the terms that <persName>Mr I</persName>
                could become<lb/> a candidate. <persName>M. L</persName> cannot believe that, under
                these circumstances I would have retired in his favor what I most<lb/> assuredly
                would. The extracts from my letters to the <placeName>Phil</placeName> cong. may be
                sufficient answer to <persName>Mr L's</persName> question<lb/> How could I have
                injured my cause by advocating him, Will not any dispassionate person at once
                see<lb/> that by sending in on the day of election <date>16 June</date> (&amp;
                before, also an intimation that I would retire did <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/>
                stand for election—that I might hereby <hi rend="underline">cool</hi> my
                supporters—that I might be considered as hinting that the cong<lb/> had not behaved
                as generously as they should to <persName>Mr L.</persName> &amp; that consequently I
                might have disgusted those who<lb/> would not grant <persName>Mr L</persName> what
                he wanted. This risk I would have been an idiot not to force, but I wrote<lb/> so
                nevertheless, though I knew many might tell me that it was for <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> to move in the matter—that I had no<lb/> right to refer to him at
                all. I do not mean to say that it was by these means &amp; on this occasionally
                that<lb/> I advocated <persName>Mr L's</persName> cause—there were other occasions
                when I probably did myself no good to speak as I<lb/> did of <persName>Mr
                    Leeser</persName>—but I am not a <persName>Jack Brag</persName> nor is it
                necessary at all I should refer further to this subject<lb/> at present.
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> however probably thinks I spoke ill of him whenever I
                could. That he thinks me<lb/> capable of hating him in my heart &amp; doing him all
                the mischief I can I infer from his gratuitous remarks<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">Perhaps if <persName>Mr De S.</persName> had written that
                    anonymous pamphlet &amp;c</hi>” <del>I ask</del> “he would have gained the
                influence<lb/> of <persName>Mr Phillips</persName>. Let me say in justice to the
                    <persName>Messrs Phillips</persName> that not one of them spoke to me
                disrespectfully<lb/> or angrily of <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>, or entered into
                any details as to what had passed between him &amp; his congregation. They<lb/> said
                nothing more severe of <persName>Mr L</persName>, &amp; I think not so much as his
                best friends did. But to return, <persName>Mr L's</persName><lb/> friends <hi
                    rend="underline">were not able</hi> to carry for <persName>Mr L</persName> on
                    <date>16 June</date> what he wanted. This he ought, perhaps, <add>?</add> know.
                True<lb/> there was a small majority (as <persName>Mr L</persName> writes) willing
                to elect him Hazan still this very majority would not<lb/> give him all he asked. So
                now he would have voted for the repeal of the bond law would not be willing<lb/> to
                grant a life term of office. Some voted thinking <persName>Mr L.</persName> observed
                at least the compliment of being<lb/> elected, since he declared he would not submit
                to the conditions—in short this majority were much divided<lb/> in opinion &amp; had
                they elected <persName>Mr L</persName> it would have amounted to nothing. Had they
                all been content to give<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> all he asked what prevented them electing him &amp; then
                altering the terms to suit. But instead of<lb/> postponing because of the threats of
                certain members withdrawing, they subscribed because it was impossible<lb/> to
                obtain two thirds of the votes for repeal of the bond which first of all
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> required. I am warranted in this<lb/> assertion by the
                assurance of many and by communications received from some of <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> staunchest supporters<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> has therefore deceived himself as to the true cause of his
                want of success on <date>16 June</date>.<del>probably</del> In his<lb/> last letter
                to you he says the reason of his new success was that “as others applied, the
                congregation<lb/> thought his remarks were founded in mere caprice and hence would
                not grant them.” <persName>Mr L</persName> does not<lb/> say much here for the
                strength of mind &amp; penetration of the meeting of <date>12 June</date> thus to be
                    influenced.<hi rend="underline"> And</hi> I<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">cannot at all reconcile</hi> this assertion of <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> with his former assertions to me that he knew his dismissal<lb/>
                from office was resolved upon, &amp; that he could not imagine the possibility of
                being re elected on terms<lb/> agreeable to himself <hi rend="underline">as he wrote
                    me long before I or anyone elected applied</hi>. Nor can I quite reconcile it
                with<lb/> his former assertion in this his last letter to you that it was “<hi
                    rend="underline">in consequence of the threats</hi> &amp; false<lb/>
                representations of “certain parties that he failed. Now today that <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> friends sacrificed him because<lb/> of the threats of withdrawal
                is to say that they acted with gross stupidity for they must have known<lb/> they
                would have to sacrifice him for the same reason in <date>April</date> when too those
                of <persName>Mr L's</persName> opponents<lb/> who could not be present in
                    <date>June</date> would probably then attend. Therefore it seems improbably they
                should<lb/> have voted with the others on this account. <persName>Mr L</persName>
                can rest no proof of the truth of his suspicion than the<lb/> reason for postponing
                is what he says because this statement in the <date>Nov.</date> Oc. remains
                    <sic>uncontradicted</sic><lb/> who should contradict it? And is the Occident the
                vehicle to give such discussions to the world?<lb/> And if <persName>Mr L</persName>
                be correct in his idea that certain parties (when I had those <add>?</add> his
                    <add>?</add> friends)<lb/> really did not desire his success because of young
                    <persName>Allan's</persName> sake, then the more <add>?</add> I proved<lb/> to
                be in the remarks made above. And in this connexion<add>?</add> let me also state
                that the adoption of the<lb/> pamphlet by the congregation containing some reference
                to a man (<hi rend="underline">purporting to be from the minutes of the
                Congrg</hi></p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and which almost looks as if the the principles of <persName>Lyola</persName> or
                    <persName>Liguori</persName> had been <del>?</del> brought into practice<lb/>
                when I <sic>learnt</sic> that this had been fathered by the cong (I believe on the
                        <date>28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date>) I again saw how<lb/> little
                chance <persName>Mr L</persName> had of re-election. And because I saw this and
                because when <persName>Mr L</persName> told me<lb/> constantly himself that he stood
                no chance and should as in duty bound retire, he now I may almost<lb/> say hates me
                because I believed &amp; read in earnest what he told me, and in this belief tried
                that I should<lb/> have a chance as he had none. <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>
                would not &amp; could not have the place himself nor did he<lb/> desire I should.
                Hence his silence to me, as I conclude. But was this friendly magnanimous or<lb/>
                kind or candid. What would I and <hi rend="underline">many others</hi> have said had
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> after assuring me so constantly<lb/> that he had no
                hopes for himself, as had he added, therefore as I have so often professed the
                great<lb/> desire I have to bring you <sic>promnently</sic> before the public I will
                    <del>tell</del> ask my friends if they cannot<lb/> modify the existing
                conditions of office, to do all they can to forward my friend. And in the<lb/> mean
                time I advise you to do so &amp; so. <sic>Dont</sic> go to
                    <placeName>Phil.</placeName>
                <sic>Dont</sic> correspond &amp;c. <persName>Mr L</persName> says he would<lb/> not
                advise me” why not. Why not do as much to me if he were my true friend as he
                did<lb/> for <persName>Mr Morais</persName> after the latter had applied for
                    <persName>Mr L's</persName> situation, and tell me through a<lb/> as he
                    <del>told</del> wrote a friend of <persName>Morais</persName> he would not
                advise him to come out here. This was written<lb/> no doubt in friendly feeling, but
                he did not show the same friendly feeling to me. Both had equally<lb/> applied. I
                have good cause then (and not only in this particular instance) to say as I<lb/>
                wrote <persName>Mr Solis</persName> in very bitterness of feeling that had
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> acted with the same candour<lb/> as he <persName>Mr
                    S</persName> had (<persName>Mr S</persName> had acquainted me a short time
                before the election what the<lb/> intentions of <persName>Mr L's</persName> friends
                were for that day) that I would have then been in a<lb/> very different position
                with respect to their congregation. And so, I solemnly assert, I <add>?</add><lb/>
                For had <persName>Mr L</persName> said do this I would have done it—do that, &amp;
                it should have been executed.<lb/> Even supposing for a moment that I was the first
                candidate in the field <hi rend="underline">which I was not</hi><lb/> is it possible
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> could believe that <persName role="author">Abraham De
                    Sola</persName> had not applied, <persName>Rosenfeld</persName>
                <persName>Lyons</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Morais</persName> or others would not have done so. And he himself admits
                that there was or is a party<lb/> desiring <persName>Mr Allan</persName>. As
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> says so say I, They <del>did not</del> opposed
                (covertly perhaps I may add) <persName>Mr<lb/> Leeser</persName>, so that
                    <persName>Mick Allan</persName> ought ultimately be appointed. (<hi
                    rend="underline"><add>?</add> a son <add>?</add></hi>) Hence had<lb/>
                <persName>A. D. S.</persName> not been there <persName>M. Allan</persName> would.
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> also states to you he knew beforehand that<lb/> I
                should not succeed would be the result of my application. It would have been more
                candid in <persName>Mr L</persName> had he told <del>me</del> this before I
                went<lb/> to <placeName>Phila.</placeName> And if <persName>Mr L</persName> knew
                this before hand he cannot with any justice say that I had <add>?</add> not<lb/>
                come forward he would have conquered—for a fact favor the fact that others were in
                the field before me<lb/> &amp; therefore left me no choice unless I would see some
                one besides <persName>Mr L</persName> or myself in the office—<lb/> —if the cong had
                determined what the issue should be, why I nor any other candidate could<lb/>
                control it. That my friends in <placeName>England</placeName> should ask
                    <persName>Mr A Franklin</persName> to support my claims will not<lb/> seem
                unnatural to many—but they were not so like led<add>?</add> or advised to do so by
                me. And this leads<lb/> me to say how deeply indignant I felt at <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> insinuations (since <sic>learnt</sic>) that I supplied<lb/> the
                Jewish papers with the various paragraphs headed
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>. I solemnly assert<lb/> and defy contradiction
                that to the Jewish Chronicle I never sent a line since the election,<lb/> was first
                talked of, nor to the Asmonean either. I challenge either editor to say I have<lb/>
                But let <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> claim what his false friend so unjustly
                    aspersed<add>?</add> really did do, though<lb/> he never boasted of any well
                intentioned act performed by him for <persName>Mr L.</persName> I should not have
                mentioned<lb/> this but for the charge against me. <persName>Mr Lyons</persName>
                wrote me when starting his paper, asking me more<lb/> than once to support it and
                write for it. Attached to the Occident however I would not write for<lb/> it, and so
                wrote <persName>Mr L</persName>, I have since altered my determination because young
                    <persName>Mr Allan</persName> who is as<lb/> one of the agents for the Asmonean
                in <placeName>Phil</placeName> told me <persName>Mr L</persName> had mentioned to
                him (what I wrote in<lb/> confidence to <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> respecting my
                intention not to write for the Asmonean <del>the Asmonean</del>. Moreover,
                    <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> has behaved with such extreme<lb/> politeness,
                both in respect to sending me the paper <add>?</add>lously, that I may wait for
                it<lb/> and on several occasions that I feel bound to make some return to him. But
                without<lb/> further digression, the very day after I received the anonymous
                pamphlet <date>21 April</date> I wrote <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> that I<lb/> had
                received it—that no doubt a paper war would now cause but I entreated him for
                the<lb/> sake of all parties to close his columns to any &amp; every communication
                on the subject of the election<lb/> as it would be a disgrace (<add>חלול השם</add>)
                that his <add>?</add> readers should become acquainted with<lb/> these internal
                dissensions. I said he would not regret granting my request but that hereafter
                he<lb/> would see cause to congratulate himself upon his moderation when he saw what
                anarchy<lb/> had been thereby avoided. In reply <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> writes
                me “Your letter requesting me to <sic>withold</sic><lb/> from publishing any remarks
                upon the emente<add>?</add> between the <placeName>Phil</placeName> Cong &amp;
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> did not reach me except the short<lb/> notice of the
                pamphlet alluded to was in <add>?</add>, but it was so guardedly worded that
                not<lb/> the slightest inference could be drawn by parties not knowing of the
                publication of the <add>?</add><lb/> as to what the Asmonean alluded. <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> adds that altho' he owed nothing to <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>
                for courtesy<lb/> in ushering the Asmonean before the Jewish public, <hi
                    rend="underline">still he would not suffer private</hi></p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p><hi rend="underline"><add>?</add>ique to interfere</hi> &amp;c” But <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> published a Review of a Review (from kind &amp; honorable motives
                there can<lb/> be no doubt, yet I have reason to believe that that production did
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> considerable harm. This<lb/> was not writing scraps
                for the Jewish papers against <persName>Mr L.</persName> I must not omit to state in
                this connection<lb/> that in writing <persName>Mr Lyon</persName> about some
                business matter connected with the Asmonean (I believe among other<lb/> things I
                gave him <persName>Mr Aschers</persName> name as subscriber at that year's request
                (I told <persName>Mr L</persName> just as I told all<lb/> the world at the time that
                I was applying for the office of <placeName>Phila.</placeName>—this was the extent
                of my information<lb/> to him. <persName>Mr Lyon</persName> very kindly however
                added some complimentary &amp; recommendatory remarks—of the <add>?</add><lb/> was
                written by <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> not by me, but a single <del>?</del>
                communication did I send to the Jewish papers on this subject nor <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> cant be surprised that I should acquaint <persName>Mr
                    Lyons</persName> what he would have heard from <placeName>Phil.</placeName> and
                apart<lb/> from my letter to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> I no secret of my
                intentions &amp; wishes—Had I deemed them dishonorable<lb/> I might have done so. I
                therefore wrote <persName>Mr S. Solis</persName> (before I went to
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName>) with whom I was slightly acquain<lb/>ted in
                    <placeName>England</placeName>—the only one I knew ever so slightly in
                    <placeName>Phil</placeName>—and whom I knew to be a zealous &amp; able<lb/>
                supporter of <persName>Mr L</persName>, both in the meeting room &amp; in the
                Occident I <del>told</del> wrote <persName>Mr S</persName> (<date>1 May</date> I
                think) that <hi rend="underline">should</hi><lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> persist in his intention to retire from office,” I hoped
                that he (<persName>Mr Solis</persName>) would consider my<lb/> next worthy his
                support. I have made this communication so very long that I feel I<lb/> am
                trespassing on your kindness &amp; should conclude. Still I must ask leave to touch
                briefly upon a<lb/> few more subjects requiring notice. When in
                    <placeName>Phila</placeName> I sought not to do, what is usual for candidates
                to<lb/> do under the present wrong system—to canvass the Cong. I went these avowedly
                to qualify myself as a candidate<lb/> by reading <hi rend="underline">once</hi>
                &amp; preaching in the Syng again. To <add>?</add> I would not defend, hence apart
                from suffering<lb/> from slight indisposition I read with less gusto than I would on
                an ordinary <date>Sabbath</date> here. I did not conceal<lb/> why I went—hence I
                plainly told them in Synagogue what my intents of the office were &amp; how I
                would<lb/> discharge them should I ever be their Minister. Some comprehensive minded
                individuals and being<lb/> of course very unprejudiced thought I reflect on
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> because I said it was the duty of a Minister<lb/>
                to visit his flock, which <persName>Mr L.</persName> usually did not, and which I
                knew at the time I was speaking<lb/> as the dog who now sits at my feet does.
                    Haugh<add>?</add>! Fortunately people are not all equally thin skinned<lb/> But
                having read once I resisted all importunities (which were not a few) both of my new
                found friends<lb/> and <persName>Mr L's</persName> supporters also (<persName>Mr S
                    Solis</persName> also advised my reading again) and to the disappointment
                of<lb/> many I would not read or preach again, but left <placeName>Phil</placeName>
                just in time to go to <persName><sic>Lyn</sic></persName> in <placeName>N.
                    York</placeName> on<lb/>
                <date>Friday</date> Evening—That I did not do myself justice hereby I know just as
                my friends told me, for the<lb/> times are so very different form the
                    <placeName>London</placeName> Minhag which we here follow for other
                reasons—but<lb/> enough, I paid <add>?</add> to those hospitable friends who made my
                stay in <placeName>Phil</placeName> so pleasant—went<lb/> to see Girard College.
                Fine arts exhibition, &amp; some of the lions of the Quaker-city, and left to make a
                few<lb/> days stay in <placeName>N. York</placeName> where I had not yet been able
                to stay to see my many friends there. Even from <placeName>N. Y</placeName><lb/> I
                hurriedly departed. I wanted to get back to my charge &amp; my books. As far as my
                interests were concerned I made<lb/> a careless stay in
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>. But no matter let me conclude my notice of
                    <persName>Mr <sic>Leesers</sic></persName> letter. I made no<lb/> assertion to
                    <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> that the above or what else I could say
                    <del>what</del> would I justify. <persName>Mr L</persName> writes he was
                Hazan<lb/> till <date>27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Septr</date> and it would been time
                enough (for me) to apply when he had withdrawn. But did <persName>Mr L.</persName>
                consider when he<lb/> wrote this. The election was fixed for <date>16<hi rend="sup"
                        >th</hi> June</date>, 3 months before <persName>Mr. L</persName> time
                expired. An application in <date>September</date> I might<lb/> naturally conclude
                would meet with the answer. Sir you are three months too late. We have appointed one
                who applied at the<lb/> time we advertised. “then” writes <persName>Mr L</persName>,
                my influence would have been at his disposal. Would it have been too much in
                    <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/>
                <add>?</add> was, till my application, my true friend writing to me, (after stating
                as he had that he had no hope of election) Do you apply<lb/> when my term is
                expired, &amp; my influence shall be at your 'disposal.” I of course, felt the
                absence of so friendly an act. <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> writes I was
                “desirous' to get his place (<del>?</del> &amp; at the same time <add>?</add> to
                retain his good opinion. “but adds <persName>ML</persName>”<lb/> this was
                impossible” Why so, I ask, I did not make or in my way promote the state of ill
                feeling between <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> &amp; his congregation. It was not
                through my influence that the Cong. outvoted <persName>Mr L</persName> (for he says
                their conduct<lb/> amounted to depriving him of his office) Why should <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> have formed a bad opinion of me because I was desirous<lb/> of
                having what he would not. <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> does not say I have same
                against him past forgiveness, I solemnly<lb/> assert that I never sinned against him
                at a “<del>with</del> in thought, and if I did in deed, it is unknown to me.<lb/>
                This will be my unchangeable conviction” till my last hour, I do not say I may not
                have unintentionally<lb/> erred in one or two trivial matters, but for the life of
                me I cannot see, after <add>?</add> all I have done<lb/> not now only but a
                    <add>?</add> times, I cannot at all see that I did him any serious harm. I
                am<lb/> convinced that had I never lived <persName>Mr L</persName> would not in
                consequence have been restored. This has been my<lb/> conviction since <date>October
                    1849</date>—a sorrowful one it was, and truly sorry am I even now to know
                it.<lb/> I can in all truth say I had rather see <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>
                retain his situation, than that I should be elected<lb/> or any other divine man
                chosen. “But I must acknowledge,” continues <persName>Mr L</persName>, “that I have
                been greatly disappointed<lb/> in <del>him</del>
                <persName>Mr. R. S.</persName>” But have I had no cause to be disappointed in
                    <persName>Mr L.</persName> I am sure I have. Let me read one<lb/> most trifling
                circumstance only, and I am strongly of opinion, unless I am even to a greater
                extent mistaken,<lb/> that <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit, he would not have
                so acted in a cool moment. In his notice of the<lb/> meeting of <date>16 June</date>
                (see Occident of <date>July 50</date>) <persName>Mr L</persName> in an article
                worthy the <add>?</add> of <placeName>New York</placeName></p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and not <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>, is guilty of a most gross &amp;
                    <sic>petulent</sic> attack upon me. Well do I recollect now<lb/> the feelings of
                surprise pain &amp; indignation with which I read it but now I regard it only as a
                proof of<lb/>
                <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> impetuosity which leads him to say &amp; write what
                he must afterwards regret. But let me <del>?</del><lb/> refer briefly to this
                article. <persName>Mr L</persName> says “<persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> we
                understand only applied in case the present<lb/> minister was not a candidate.” Is
                it possible <persName>Mr L's</persName> informant did not tell him that on the<lb/>
                <date><hi rend="underline">16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of June</hi></date> the day
                appointed for the election I also sent in a letter to the Congregation stating
                that<lb/> I desired not to be put in nomination <add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> a candidate! This letter of mine <persName>Mr
                    Hart</persName> assured<lb/> me on its receipt, should be read to the Cong. I
                was therefore a matter of sufficient notoriety. Why then say<lb/> for
                    <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> more than he said for me. Overlook both, but
                don't do an injustice to one. That <persName>Rosenfeld</persName><lb/> behaved
                better on <date>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date> than I, it is impossible for
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> to prove for to use <persName>Mr L's</persName> own
                words “He<lb/> knew (that is <persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> knew) that his
                reservation or disclaimer was no disclaimer, since he<lb/> also knew that I <add>i.
                    e. <persName>Mr Leeser</persName></add> would not apply under the conditions “as
                all the world did. Why then favor<lb/>
                <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> more than <persName>De Sola</persName> by recording
                to the credit of the <del>?</del> former what the other also should have<lb/>
                received credit for and would had <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> when he then wrote
                been the <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> of other cooler<lb/> moments. Hereby
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> caused me to think what others have also thought, that
                in his anger he<lb/> desired to injure me. For <add>?</add> acct the election had
                not then been held,but postponed, consequently<lb/> this implied charge of a want of
                consideration for <persName>Mr L</persName> &amp; some other <sic>inuendos</sic>
                equally unfounded<lb/> &amp; uncalled for notice presently were calculated to do me
                harm with some in <placeName>Phila.</placeName>
                <persName>Mr De S.</persName>
                <add>?</add>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> in<lb/> the Occident was the only one of the candidates
                who had been to <placeName>Phil</placeName> &amp;c during the late absence of
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> I was not the only one who thought that had
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> left out the words during the late absence of
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> it would have been more fair &amp; dignified
                on his part since some not acquainted with the true state of<lb/> affairs might have
                imagined that I went to <placeName>Phil</placeName>, knowing it was not correct to
                go there, &amp; not desiring<lb/> to meet <persName>Mr L</persName>, went behind his
                back, covertly slyly like a thief. Those who know me <add>?</add> well<lb/> imagine
                how my heart beat, &amp; ears tingled where I thus read &amp; thought. Instead of
                avoiding <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> I did all I could to see him. I delayed
                going to <placeName>Phil.</placeName> as long as possible, though you know certain
                parties<lb/> not members of the congregation telegraphed me that it was important I
                should go at such a such<lb/> a time—again that I should go for
                    <date>Pentecost</date>, which I nevertheless did not mind but waited<lb/> as
                long as I could consistently with <persName>Mr Hart's</persName> recommendation so
                that I might see <persName>Mr L</persName>, who, I thought<lb/> would by that time
                be returned. And indeed the answer to my particular inquiries; at <persName>Mr
                    L's</persName> residence<lb/> also I was told he was daily expected. As I before
                told you I would not to please friends, or <sic>teaze</sic><lb/> enemies stay to
                read another <date>Sabbath</date> in <placeName>Phil</placeName> though strongly
                recommended so to do but I wrote a few lines<lb/> and if I forget not also told the
                lady I saw at <persName>Mr l'</persName> house, to inform <persName>Mr L</persName>
                I should stay a few days<lb/> in <placeName>New York</placeName> so that I might see
                him, I think I said how long I should stay &amp; I asked him to<lb/> telegraph me as
                soon as he arrived as I desired much to see him. I do not know whether <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> did arrive<lb/> while I was in <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> but had
                we met, I think we should not have been so many months alienated to come<lb/> twice.
                The Oc says and his (my) testimonials which were extensively circulated (among the
                voters only<lb/> I believe) in a hand bill (Either I did not yet know the meaning of
                hand bill or I was right in supposing) <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> intended it as
                a sneer on my circulars, which in <placeName>Europe</placeName> or say
                    <placeName>England</placeName> it is always the custom to send e. g.
                    <persName>Dr<lb/> Raphall</persName> sent them when he applied for the
                lectureship at the <placeName>Dukes Place</placeName> Synagogue in
                    <placeName>London</placeName>. All the candidates<lb/> did when applying for the
                office of Hazan in <placeName>London</placeName>. It was an inadvertence for which I
                afterwards blamed myself<lb/> much that I did not send one to <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> (he says in the Oc a copy reached him through the kindness of a
                friend)<lb/> for I should with my then feelings certainly have done so just as I
                sent then the gist of my letter to <persName>Mr Hart</persName><lb/> but I sent the
                parcel on to <placeName>Phil</placeName> I could not afterwards procure one.
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> says <persName>Mr De S's</persName> testimonials<lb/>
                were highly creditable to <add>?</add> But I &amp; others too thought this no
                praise—no kind words, for none<lb/> could say otherwise. And if all our doubt, if we
                had any were removed by <persName>Mr L</persName> himself who labored<lb/> hard to
                show, altho' he did not plainly say that these testimonials were only given me as a
                matter of favor<lb/> Thus <persName>Mr L.</persName> says they were signed by the
                    <persName>Rev D. Meldola</persName> (This name would be sufficient, as
                every<lb/> reader of the Occident knew who <persName>Mr Meldola</persName> was,
                since a few numbers back there was a <add>?</add><lb/> of a Catechism he published
                or if this readers must know who <persName>Mr M</persName> his say he is
                    6<add>?</add><lb/> Rabbi of the Portuguese Jews in <placeName>London</placeName>
                but no <persName>Mr L</persName> gives his title the maternal uncle of<lb/>
                <persName>Mr De S.</persName> The inference from this must be obvious. Again next
                “by <persName>Dr Lowe</persName> his preceptor<lb/> (of course a preceptor would cry
                up his pupils) next “by <persName>Dr A Benisch</persName>, says <persName>Mr
                    L</persName>, “once Editor<lb/> of the voice of Jacob (why not style him what my
                “handbill more properly calls him, Professor<lb/> of Hebrew at the Jews Institution
                at <add>?</add> Hall author of &amp;c &amp;c but no, he was author of<lb/> the voice
                of J. &amp; <persName>Mr D S</persName> “assisted him in his labours says
                    <persName>Mr L.</persName> The influence is that in return<lb/> for my kindness
                the Dr gave me a testimonial at all events he was particularly intimate with<lb/> me
                &amp; would not refuse, next writes <persName>Mr L</persName>, but <persName>Dr
                    Raphall</persName>. Now it might be naturally<lb/> thought that it would be
                quite unnecessary to say who the eminent <persName>Dr Raphall</persName>
                was—however<lb/> as he was to the American Jewish community among whom he had but
                lately been elected Minister<lb/> with much <add>?</add> as well as <persName>Mr
                    L.</persName> but <persName>Mr L</persName> thought otherwise. He therefore writes<lb/>
                <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> who was associated in various literary labours with
                    <persName>Rev David De Sola</persName></p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3.</p>
            <p><add>?</add> of <persName>Mr A D. S.</persName> of course the Dr in his good feeling
                for the father—his old friend<lb/> would favor the son with a testimonial. Thus then
                might one not unnaturally infer that all<lb/> my testimonials were given me because
                all the donors were friends or relatives. The testimonial of the<lb/> late venerable
                &amp; talented <persName>Michael Josephs</persName>—one of the greatest Hebrew
                scholars &amp; writers among the Jews of<lb/>
                <placeName>England</placeName>, <persName>Mr L</persName> did not comment upon or
                take any notice of at all. I could not but think that <persName>Mr L</persName>
                thereby<lb/> rendered himself open to a charge of want of <sic>candour</sic>, since
                one might naturally conclude that as he did<lb/> not know in what relations
                    <persName>Mr Josephs</persName> &amp; myself were since he could not say
                    <persName>Mr J</persName> was my preceptor<lb/> or co-laborer, or a co-laborer
                of my father, or even a particular friend he ignored the testimonial lest his<lb/>
                readers should think that at least one man gave me a good character who had no
                motive for doing so enough<lb/>—couple this with what I have already written &amp;
                say whether I too have not cause to be disappointed in <persName>Mr
                L.</persName><lb/> Say openly in your magazine or where you will that I have done
                you an injury. I can then defend myself—<lb/> but do not stab me like an Italian
                bravo—do not blast my reputation &amp; character unnecessarily <persName>Mr
                    L</persName><lb/> may say I have fancied all this but the facts are too
                stubborn. Believe me, dear sir, before I had said or<lb/> hinted anything about it
                more than one expressed themselves indignant at such treatment &amp; strongly
                advised<lb/> me to reply to it either in the Asmonean or by circular, but altho' I
                felt myself injured &amp; knew if I<lb/> replied all would give me right in my
                strictures on this article—still I had too much self pride so to do.<lb/> And this
                is the reason, let me tell you <hi rend="underline">en passant</hi> that I have
                determined not to write more for the Occident<lb/> and was sorry that an article of
                mine appeared after the publication of the above notice so that people might<lb/>
                suppose I was still a correspondent—but which in truth I cannot be until something
                more shall have<lb/> passed in explanation between the writer of that injurious
                article &amp; myself. That it has done me no good<lb/> I am sure. Let <persName>Mr
                    Solis</persName>—the friend to whom <persName>Mr L</persName> thinks I have
                maligned him—a just &amp; candid friend himself<lb/> a correspondent of the
                Occident—let him decide—&amp; I am sure he will not say I am altogether wrong. Your
                opinion<lb/> you need not give for I flatter myself I know it. My efforts such as
                they are for the Jewish cause shall not<lb/> be wanting when I can make them. Hence
                I will write (being forced) for the Asmonean &amp; for any paper not<lb/> under the
                control of an Editor who could thus unjustly &amp; unmercifully attack me. I am
                fully as sensitive as <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>.<lb/> In his last letter to you
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> writes “I would not have reacted so had <persName>Mr
                    De S.</persName> been in my position &amp; I in his.” I think<lb/> he would
                &amp; he ought not to forget the recommendation of our sages “Judge not thy fellow,
                until thou hast been<lb/> in his position. <persName>Mr L.</persName> would rather
                do anything “than undermine a friend.” If <persName>Mr L</persName> wishes to convey
                that I have<lb/> done or attempted to do so, I repel the accusation with
                indignation, and deny its truth by all that is sacred. <persName>Mr
                L</persName><lb/> also says “to be in league with them whom he knew to be my enemies
                is no test of friendship” I, as solemnly<lb/> deny the truth of this allegation. I
                never have been in league with any one to injure <persName>Mr L</persName>, nor has
                any one even<lb/> proposed so dishonorable a thing. I am not so easily made a cats
                paw. No one else would charge me with acting<lb/> so irreligiously. It is an unjust
                change founded on illiberal irreligious suspicions. Let <persName>Mr L</persName>
                prove to you<lb/> or any one that I have leagued with his enemies if he can. He
                surely cannot charge me with this because I<lb/> did not refuse the civilities &amp;
                support of the <persName>Messrs Phillips</persName> whom he told me were his enemies
                for the first<lb/> time just before he went to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>—a
                few weeks before the election. Previously he had never mentioned<lb/> their names to
                me. But I will not say more about this unworthy charge. <persName>Mr L</persName>
                says <persName>Mr D. S.</persName> would do himself<lb/> real honor by acknowledging
                his unintentional error as I am willing to regard it as such, my feelings<lb/> were
                greatly outraged by the manner in which he ought to carry his plan. <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> exhibits, it appears<lb/> to me some inconsistency in this
                statement &amp; it is what I cannot easily reconcile. If I undermined<lb/> him or
                attempted to do so—if I leagued with his enemies to his detriment &amp; if I sought
                to carry<lb/> my plan in so dishonorable a manner as to wound his feelings—all of
                which <persName>Mr L</persName> says I did—how can<lb/> he say at the same time I
                erred unintentionally. I could not undermine or league or plan unintentionally.
                No<lb/> if I did this then I acted not unintentionally, but rascally, &amp; with
                malice <sic>propense</sic>. This is the English of it<lb/>
                <sic>And</sic> therefore I &amp; you &amp; any man of common sense cannot admit that
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> believes I have only erred<lb/> unintentionally,
                while he brings forward (in the same paragraph) such serious charges against me. If
                    <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> would do himself real honor &amp; act with
                the justice he is fully capable to do, he will admit how incon<lb/>gruous his
                statements are, &amp; plainly say that he does not think I leagued undermined flamed
                &amp;<lb/> plotted against him, but that I “<hi rend="underline">erred
                    unintentionally</hi>” only. I on my part am willing to make<lb/> any
                acknowledgment consistent with my convictions of my innocence of desiring by thought
                or deed<lb/> to hurt him. No false pride or obstinacy, or desire to show that I am
                better than my neighbour<lb/> shall <sic>withold</sic> me. And I do not scruple to
                say, and <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> may know it that I am<lb/> truly sorry we
                are not on the same terms we were this time last year. Anything that</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>night cause<add>?</add> angry feeling I have endeavored to avoid in this letter, for
                it is not I who make<lb/> charges, but defend myself I must. I am quite sure that I
                never spoke injuriously or disrespectfully<lb/> (as I could not) of <persName>Mr
                    L</persName> to any. If I have written something in haste, likely in
                    <persName>Mr L's</persName> estimation<lb/> to do him an injury which I am not
                conscious however of having done I am quite ready to make<lb/> all the reparation
                    <persName>Mr L</persName> may require. <persName>Mr L</persName> should
                recollect that being no more than human it is<lb/> quite natural that I should err,
                and that he himself wrote a review of my testimonials which<lb/> is quite open to
                the construction I &amp; others put upon it—that he has erred, &amp; that I
                have<lb/> forgiven it, for <persName>Mr L</persName> may be assured that after its
                first perusal I never had another angry<lb/> feeling on the matter—further than
                thinking I was injured, which did not anger me much as I know<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> wrote it in misconception of all circumstances<add>?</add>
                &amp; in heat—and that from the first day I wrote him. Even before<lb/> I worried in
                    <placeName>America</placeName> until the present moment I have always
                entertained for him feelings of great<lb/> respect regard &amp; kindness and
                    <sic>thugh</sic> I may no longer address him as a friend, still I am his friend
                yet<lb/> Even if wrong, which to the extent <persName>Mr L</persName> has intimated,
                I never can admit I have been—and I do<lb/> sincerely hope that after a
                dispassionate reading of what I have written &amp; which I desire he should see<lb/>
                <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit he has been deceived and ignorant of all the
                motives &amp; circumstances under which<lb/> I acted and that he consequently has
                been somewhat mistaken in what he has written to you<lb/> I could not say as much as
                I have, knowing what <persName>Mr L</persName> has written already to yourself and
                my<lb/> uncle (with whom it is impossible to injure me) I could not in all candour
                &amp; sincerity admit<lb/> that I value <persName>Mr L's</persName> good opinion,
                and desire he should think better of me—as well as he did of old<lb/> did I not <hi
                    rend="underline">sincerely</hi> so desire, since I lay myself open to the charge
                that having <add>?</add>fully offended <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> I know desire
                to conciliate him. Heaven knows I never <sic>wilfully</sic> offended him as I never
                    <sic>wilfully</sic><lb/> injured him.</p>
            <p><persName>Mr Leeser</persName> says in his letter to you “<persName>Mr De
                    Sola</persName> himself cannot regret as much as I do that<lb/> an estrangement
                has taken place between us” but <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> has entirely mistaken
                my feelings<lb/> towards him. He appears to have regarded me as false I therefore
                incapable of entertaining any<lb/> kind feeling towards him. Not so. My
                communication with him during some four years was<lb/> not without its pleasures.
                But it was our intimacy as Israelites, having the same religious<lb/>
                convictions—belonging to the same school working in the same glorious
                cause—having<lb/> kindred tastes &amp; sentiments—it was this intimacy that I
                valued—always conscious (no<lb/> false pride deters me from saying it) that I
                profited by it—as I wrote <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> in I<lb/> think the very
                first letter I was addressed him <add>כל המחובר לטהור טהור</add>—it was the
                sudden<lb/> unexpected severance of this intimacy that I have since regretted—the
                more so that I am<lb/> conscious of never having been guilty of doing that which
                should cause it. Is <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> willing<lb/> to retract his
                serious charges that I have attempted <sic>wilfully</sic> to undermine him—that I
                have<lb/> leagued myself with his enemies—that I have made false protestations and
                acted falsely to him<lb/> and instead of these charges admit after reading the above
                that he now attaches I only unintentionally<lb/> erred against him and bore him no
                malice (as how should I) then I on my part am quite<lb/> willing beforehand candidly
                to admit that in many things I may have acted foolishly both for<lb/> his &amp; my
                interest and that it is quite possible I hurt his feelings as he says, and even
                slightly<lb/> injured him by anything I may unintentionally have done. Any further
                admission compatible with<lb/> the declarations I have already made, I am quite
                willing further to make and questions to<lb/> answer, since it is not a matter of
                indifference whether <persName>Mr L</persName> or any other man thinks<lb/> well or
                ill of me.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Having made this communication so long I must <sic>apologise</sic>
                for stating up so much<lb/> of your time, but it will be the last time I shall ever
                trouble you with so long &amp; tiresome<lb/> a letter on this subject. Indeed it
                will be quite useless and impossible for me to do so since<lb/> should <persName>Mr
                    Leeser</persName> not be willing to admit what I think he in common justice
                &amp; truth<lb/> should I have not one word more to say in the matter as it would be
                a waste of<lb/> time that could be better employed. I am now writing into another
                day and last night<lb/> it was the same for I have been unable to put aside other
                things go claiming my<lb/> attention just now. I would not mind my convenience and I
                think any good<lb/> could come of it, but as <persName>Mr Leeser's</persName>
                retraction of his unfounded charges can be the only good</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>that can satisfy me, I think under the circumstances I would not be right even to
                devote<lb/> a leisure hour further to this subject of which by this time you are of
                course heartily tired<lb/> so I subscribe myself at once</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <date>26 Feby/51</date>
            </p>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_7_7.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume
                        7 No. 7 pages 376 through 378. Click here to view.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
