<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item207</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Hirschel,
                            Solomon</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1836-11">4 November 1836</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1836-11">12 Heshvar 5596</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 8 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Philadelphia (Pennsylvania</placeName>) <date>Thursday
                    Heshvan 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> (Nov. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) 5596</date>.</p>
            <p>To the Rt. <addressee>Rev. Dr Solomon Hirschel</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Grand Rabbi of the Polish &amp; German Jews in
                    <placeName>London</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Honoured Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">The eminent station which you occupy has made your name<lb/>
                familiarly known among us, and the fame which attaches to you as<lb/> an able
                expounder of the holy law with which we are blessed naturally<lb/> makes you
                conspicuous to us even who are separated from your residence<lb/> by the distance
                which the great sea interposes. In this country there is none<lb/> who is authorized
                to give an opinion in contested or uncertain points of<lb/> law, and we are
                therefore compelled upon any emergency which arises to<lb/> decide for ourselves as
                best we can, or to ask an opinion of one another,<lb/> and as our books for
                reference are but few, and our knowledge in these<lb/> matters not being as
                extensive as it should be; I have on mature reflec-<lb/>tion, and upon the advice of
                friends, amongst whom I may mention <persName>Dr. Mr. Ema<lb/>nuel</persName>, whom
                you well know, resolved to place before you several questions for<lb/> your
                decision, and to beg you most earnestly to favour me with your<lb/> reply by the
                earliest possible opportunity, that we may have a certain and<lb/> an authentic
                opinion to go upon in the cases hereafter to be enumerated.<lb/> I myself am a
                native of <placeName>Westphalia in Germany</placeName>, whence I emigrated<lb/> to
                this country in the winter of the year <date>5584</date> when I was seventeen years
                old;<lb/> I had then a slight acquaintance with <add>?</add> having gone through
                    <add>בבא מציעא, ביצה</add><lb/> and a part of <add>חולין</add> and <add>בבא
                    בתרא</add>; with the <add>פוסקים</add> I had as yet not meddled, as<lb/> of
                course I was yet too young at that time for so important a study,<lb/> and after I
                reached <placeName>America</placeName> I was engaged in business, and had
                besides<lb/> neither books nor teachers to help myself further. It is now about
                six<lb/> years and a quarter since I was elected to serve as <add>חזן</add> to the
                Portuguese<lb/> congregation <add>מקוה ישראל</add> in this place, altho' I can
                hardly say that I was suffi-<lb/>ciently qualified, but owing to there being but few
                in this country capable at all<lb/> for this station the partiality of the people
                here called me away from <placeName>Richmond<lb/> in Virginia</placeName> where I
                had lived five years and a quarter with my uncle, an old gentleman</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>who had been settled for many years in <placeName>America</placeName>. Knowing my own
                want of<lb/> proper qualification I would never have consented to serve, if others
                more<lb/> fitting in point of standing, information or other qualities had been
                here; but<lb/> this not being the case, as is proved by there being yet two
                congregations at<lb/> least in this country without a regular <add>חזן</add> I
                consented to serve. During the<lb/> whole time of my being in office constantly
                occurrences have taken place<lb/> which demanded decisions more complicated than my
                own information was<lb/> able to afford. But having in the neighbouring city of
                    <placeName>New York</placeName> a man of<lb/> sterling information and a
                connection of my family by name of <persName>Israel B.<lb/> Kursheedt</persName>, no
                doubt also known to you by reputation, I occasionally<lb/> referred to him. But as
                he is not authorized in the regular way to give<lb/> decisions, and as therefore his
                opinions are liable to be objected to, I now<lb/> address you, as already stated to
                ask of you, which will without doubt be<lb/> a pleasure to you, to assist your
                brethren in <placeName>America</placeName> with your advice and<lb/> counsel in
                their endeavours to worship the God of their fathers in truth.<lb/> Perhaps all said
                hitherto might have been as well omitted, but yet I thought it<lb/> best to inform
                you at once why you are troubled with a letter by one who<lb/> is in all
                    <sic>likelyhood</sic> a perfect stranger to you, for I doubt whether even
                my<lb/> name has ever reached your ears before. In the first place then allow<lb/>
                me to levy a case before you which has recently occurred here, and which<lb/> has
                carried a considerable degree of excitement. You must know that<lb/> from a cause or
                the other things occur here for which it is difficult to<lb/> find a parallel
                elsewhere, and so it happened that a man by name of<lb/>
                <persName>Reuben Etting</persName> living in <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>, where
                there was no <add>מוהל</add> had a son<lb/> born to him about 35 years ago. He sent
                for a <add>מוהל</add> from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> if I am not
                mistaken, and they <sic>alledge</sic> that some accident happened<lb/> to the child
                in consequence of the <add>מילה</add>, which however the family of the<lb/>
                <add>מוהל</add>, who has been dead long before I came to
                    <placeName>America</placeName>, as strenuously<lb/> deny. Be this as it may,
                three sons born to <persName>Etting</persName> after that time were<lb/> left
                uncircumcised, the youngest of whom was however circumcised here after<lb/> he was
                old enough to judge for himself. The elder two however are <add>ערלים</add>, and</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>one of them, named <persName>Benjamin</persName> was married some years back to the
                daughter of a<lb/> gentleman of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> by name of
                    <persName>Joseph Marx</persName>, highly respected for his wealth<lb/> and
                standing as a merchant. I lately saw in this place the gentleman that<lb/> gave them
                    <add>ערלים</add> and he assured me that he did not know that the man<lb/> he
                married was an <add>ערל</add>. Of this however I can not speak with certain-<lb/>ty,
                and I only state it that you may have all the circumstances of the<lb/> case as far
                as known to myself. <persName>Benj. Etting</persName> had born him two<lb/> sons,
                whom he <hi rend="underline">contrary</hi> to the advice of his family, (who are now
                all<lb/> residents in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>,) left <add>ערלים</add>.
                In the beginning of the summer<lb/> he himself went out on a voyage to
                    <placeName>Canton in China</placeName>, and in the mean<lb/> time his youngest
                son sickened and died on the last <date>Sunday in<lb/> Elul</date>.<lb/> Our
                congregation was applied to, to permit the child to be buried in our<lb/>
                <add>בית עליון</add>, and by my advice the Parnass permitted it to be done; I
                conten<lb/>ded that the child was <add>מזרע ישראל</add>, and not worse than
                    <add>מומר קטן שהמיר עם אביו או אמו</add><lb/> of whom it is said <add>אין מתבלין
                    עליו</add>, from which I inferred that<lb/> a <add>יורה דעה סי שמה סנו'</add> he
                may have, not being able to find any thing in relation to <add>קבורה</add><lb/>
                mentioned in the <add>יורה דעה</add>; at the same time I decided that the child
                should be<lb/> looked upon as a <add>קטן שלא הגיע למילה</add>, and that they should
                give it <add>מילה</add> and call<lb/> it a name as it mentioned in reference to a
                child that dies before it is<lb/> eight days old. <persName>Dr. Emanuel</persName>
                made the <add>מילה</add>; but because the parents had<lb/> been <add>פושעים</add>
                and having been warned, I refused to attend the <add>לויה</add>, not being<lb/>
                willing to read the <add>תפלות</add> over such a child. Understand me well,
                venerable<lb/> Rabbi, that on no account would I have presumed to <del>have</del>
                given an opinion,<lb/> if there were any body else here to whom I could have applied
                for advice, and<lb/> thus therefore I was compelled to act, as I have done, altho by
                so doing I<lb/> gave <sic>offence</sic> to those that said the child ought not to
                have been buried<lb/> at all, and others again, and among them the large family
                connection<lb/> of the child, who said I should and ought to have attended the
                    <add>לויה</add>. I<lb/> therefore ask now your opinion, upon the following
                points arising out of this case</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a) Is a <add>יהודי ערל</add> allowed to marry a <add>בת ישראל</add> or not?</p>
            <p>b) Is a “ allowed to have a <add>מצוה</add> or to be <add>עולה לתורה</add> or
                not?</p>
            <p>c) Is he allowed to come to <add>קבר ישראל</add>, and if he is, what is to be done in
                case<lb/> he is full grown and had had an opportunity to take the <add>מילה</add> on
                himself?</p>
            <p>d) Is he entitled to be buried in the regular row or should he be laid <add>חן
                    הצר</add>?</p>
            <p>e) Should the <add>חזן</add> say <add>צדוק הדין</add> over a child like the one
                spoken of, or had he<lb/> better not be at the burial?</p>
            <p>f) Should <add>צדוק הדין</add> and the other <add>תפלות</add> be at all said over
                such a <add>ערל</add> or not?</p>
            <p>g) Are the <hi rend="underline">daughters</hi> of such a man, born to him by a
                    <add>בת ישראל</add> regular<lb/> and <add>חותרות לבא בקהל</add> or not?</p>
            <p>On some of these points I have no draft myself, but to satisfy every one<lb/> both
                who agreed with and those who differed from me of what is really the law I<lb/> have
                asked perhaps more questions than were necessary. In case you answer<lb/> this be
                kind enough also to quote the authorities, if there are any to which<lb/> we may
                refer for future decisions, that we may not be compelled to encroach<lb/> again upon
                your valuable time. I forgot to mention that <persName>Mr. Reuben
                Etting</persName><lb/> has besides the four sons already mentioned a fifth to whom
                he gave regularly<lb/> the <add>מילה</add>, and so it would appear that he may have
                been prevented in the other<lb/> instances by a fear, however idle, of accidents,
                which he believed to have<lb/> occurred to his eldest son. The whole family was very
                much distressed at my<lb/> absence from the burial, and were of course in a
                corresponding degree angry,<lb/> at what they thought a wanton insult offered at
                them. However it must<lb/> be borne in mind that there are four or five more
                families here who are<lb/> situated in the same way, and as there are at least <hi
                    rend="underline">two</hi> grown persons, it<lb/> is absolutely necessary that we
                should have some fixed opinion to go by, that<lb/> we may in future avoid giving
                just <sic>offence</sic> to anyone, for I believe sin-<lb/>cerely if once an opinion
                has been obtained from you or some other great<lb/> teacher in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, but especially you, since you are the only one
                now<lb/> in the countries where English is spoken, it will settle the matter
                for-<lb/>ever; since despite of this professed indifference men may feel for
                religion in<lb/> this country still they have sense enough left and virtue enough
                too to<lb/> submit to a <del>?</del> righteous decision once given, for <add>הרקנים
                    שבך מלאים מצות כרימון</add></p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And having ventured thus far permit me to ask you a few other questions.<lb/> In this
                country there are unfortunately many who have married <add>בנות של ניכר</add><lb/>
                and there are many children descended either by the father or mother's<lb/> side
                from <add>יהודים</add>; you know well what is said <add>קמים גרים לישראל
                כספחת</add>; still<lb/> a great multitude is lost to our people by the great mixture
                which<lb/> has unfortunately subsisted for so many years. I should like
                therefore<lb/> to have a distinct answer to the following question, only premising
                that<lb/> we are in this country permitted to make as many <add>גרים</add> as we
                please.<lb/> I know also that <add>גרים</add> are not likely to be the best
                    <add>יהודים</add> still the confu<lb/>sion arising from the number of females
                particularly who are partly Jews<lb/> causes me to lay this question before you for
                your candid decision and<lb/> sincere reflection:</p>
            <p>First. Would it be lawful in case a <add>יהודי</add> has married a <add>בת אל
                    זכר</add> to<lb/> receive her as a <add>גיורת</add> that the children born from
                such a union<lb/> may be <add>יהודים</add>, or would it be better to leave them go
                altogether<lb/> to destruction, and to refuse them every opportunity of coming
                again<lb/> among us.</p>
            <p>You will easily perceive that this matter is of great importance, and<lb/> if it
                would be legalized might prevent much evil. Further, since there<lb/> are in this
                country very often <add>נכריות</add> who are willing to marry <add>יהודים</add>
                and<lb/> become <add>גיורות</add> before hand, whether under the circumstances of
                the country<lb/> it would be right to take them, knowing what their object is
                in<lb/> joining us. Instances indeed have occurred where gentile women<lb/> would
                have been willing to <del>have</del> become Jewesses, and being refused<lb/> they
                still married and they and their children were afterwards<lb/>
                <add>למכשול ולפוקה</add>, since their daughters afterwards married <add>יהודים</add>
                and so carried<lb/> the sin from generation to generation.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Second</hi>. In what light are children to be regarded whose
                father was a Jew and<lb/> whose mother a <add>נכרית</add>?</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Third</hi>. What must be done to children whose mother was a
                    <add>יהודית</add> and whose<lb/> father a <add>גוי</add>? are they to be
                considered as <add>יהודים</add> without <add>טבילה</add> or must they too</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>have <add>טבילה</add>?</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Fourth</hi>. Suppose a <add>לוי</add> marries a <add>גויה</add>
                and they have children, and afterwards the mother<lb/> become a <add>גיורת</add> are
                the children both before her <add>טבילה</add> to be considered as <add>לוים</add> or
                not?<lb/> I myself have decided that they are also <add>גרים</add> and of course not
                    <add>לוים</add>; but<lb/> I should like to know whether I was right or
                wrong?</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Fifth</hi>. Suppose a <add>יהודית</add> should have children or
                rather daughters by a <add>גוי</add> are<lb/> they <add>מותרות לכהן</add> or
                not?</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Sixth</hi>. Would it be right <add>להתחלה</add> to accept as
                    <add>גרים</add> grown persons whose father<lb/> was a <add>יהודי</add> and whose
                mother a <add>גויה</add>?</p>
            <p>At the present moment I cannot think of more cases concerning<lb/> this point, but be
                kind enough to write out if you can do it without<lb/> too much trouble all the laws
                relating to this important consideration,<lb/> and you will I hope undertake to
                satisfy us in this country, when I assure<lb/> you that there are at least a third
                of all the American families interested<lb/> in it, I refer especially to those that
                live in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>. There are<lb/> also a number in
                    <placeName>New York</placeName> and elsewhere similarly situated, but of<lb/>
                those I cannot speak with as much certainty.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Sometime ago several families from various causes wished<lb/> the
                marriage of their daughters to take place in the morning instead<lb/> of the
                afternoon as usual. The congregation very properly refused<lb/> granting their
                consent to such an innovation. But yet it would give<lb/> us much satisfaction to
                have your decision on this subject also, and<lb/> whether a marriage may take place
                in the morning or not?—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Would a marble basin, hewn out of a solid block, holding a<lb/>
                <add>שעור מקוה</add> filled with water coming by means of fixed machinery from
                a<lb/> river, which water is originally forced up in a reservoir by means<lb/> of
                machine pump be <add>כשר</add> for a <add>מקוה</add>? or would it be considered a
                    <add>כלי</add> and <add>פסול</add>?<lb/> bay water brought into a bath built of
                    <hi rend="underline">stone</hi> or <del>single</del> bricks cemented by<lb/>
                mortar from a river as above be used for a <add>מקוה</add> or are they considered as
                    <add>מים שאובים</add>?</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I should like to ask your opinion upon many other points from time
                to<lb/> time, if you would permit me, to address you occasionally; which I
                trust<lb/> you will grant me, and I assure you, that you still never need blame<lb/>
                yourself for the favour granted. If you can conveniently do it,<lb/> please to make
                your reply in English, that it may be extensively<lb/> circulated. Answer this if
                you can by the earliest packet, since<lb/> not I alone but many other persons are
                anxious for your opinion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have seen with pleasure that <add>חזן</add>
                <persName>De Sola</persName> has undertaken<lb/> a new edition of the Portuguese
                service, since the books formerly issued<lb/> by <persName>David Levy</persName>
                <add>?</add> are not now to be had any more though often inquired<lb/> after. Two
                years ago I wanted to undertake the same labour myself,<lb/> but a <sic>sever</sic>
                illness, the small-pox, kept me confined for several months,<lb/> and my health has
                ever since continued too bad to permit me to<lb/> undertake so heavy a task. Having
                been thus myself prevented by<lb/> the hand of God from accomplishing my design, I
                am glad to see it under-<lb/>taken by one who I hope is fully capable to do justice
                to the work. If it is<lb/> well done, I shall rejoice that it has been accomplished,
                and shall use<lb/> my endeavours, feeble as they are, to forward the author's
                design. If you<lb/> think proper you may communicate this to him, altho' I have
                never<lb/> had the pleasure of hearing any thing about him, till I heard of his<lb/>
                prospectus some weeks since from a bookseller of eminence who belongs<lb/> to our
                congregation, and not till this morning was the prospectus itself<lb/> placed in my
                hands.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am afraid I have detained you too long, particularly by
                matters<lb/> not <sic>relevent</sic> to my inquiries, if so I beg you to excuse me;
                and to<lb/> forgive the errors of a stranger, who speaks to a father and
                teacher<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>; whom he would gladly personally see
                &amp; know. May our<lb/> God preserve you many years in health and prosperity, and
                may there<lb/> never be wanting one in your family to sit on the seat of judgment in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>.</p>
            <p>
                <add>כ"ד עבד אדוני המוכן לשרתו ה"ק יצחק אילן אורי ליפיץ אליעזר</add>
            </p>
            <p><add>בפילאד'</add>
                <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>My address is <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
                <placeName>Philadelphia Pennsylvania</placeName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
