<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Wise, Isaac Mayer</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item194</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Wise, Isaac
                            Mayer</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac ;
                            Samuel, John</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Albany, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="">1851/1853</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item194_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 11 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <hi rend="underline">Tal. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <add>שלא היה בלבי להטיב לאיש פלוני כי אמרו להרע לפלוני ואח"כ התפעל או בא אחר
                    בעדו</add>
            </p>
            <p>God is the most perfect existence, therefore <add>במענה רק אל המלך והתחנו לפניו והמלך
                    חשוב ממחשבותו – עוד לא כן הקב"ה כי לא</add><lb/> no <sic>altaretion</sic> can be
                thought in his divine Character for<lb/> every <sic>altaretion</sic> is a proof of
                imperfection.</p>
            <p>By that prim we learn:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">a Hymns and praises so the Living God shall be the chief<lb/> apart,
                prayers of supplication and respontenie<add>?</add> the second and<lb/>
                <sic>smaler</sic> part of our liturgy. The Talmud itself is of this meaning</p>
            <p>
                <add>במחשבותיו משבותנו כי אנחנו בעל שינוי להסיר ממחשבתו, והדרך ילכו אור באמונתו
                    הקב"ה</add>
            </p>
            <p>Purer words in that reference said the orthodox <add>שומע תפילות כל פה הוא דוקא
                    כשמתפלל שינה את עצמו במחשבה בדיבור ובמעשה</add>.</p>
            <p>After reverend gentleman said the opinion of the Talmud, he<lb/> expressed his view
                about it:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The chief precept of our Religion is: to be holy, that<lb/> is: so
                love God, for this is holiness. Inferior so this<lb/> precept is: to acknowledge
                God, expressed in the first command<lb/>ment of the revelation. If we acknowledge
                God, we love him<lb/> and are holy. Our Holy Thora is the guide to the summit<lb/>
                of this divine Dea<add>?</add>. Philanthropy, kindness and mercy to every<lb/>
                creature both living and lifeless, rectitude for the whole human<lb/> race, a
                powerful dominion above ourselves as well as above nature are<lb/> the ways, which
                our Thora teaches us, to acknowledge the invisible<lb/> Deity by his divine
                attributes. Be as kind and <sic>mercyful</sic> as our<lb/> Thora will it, thus Gods
                benevolence is displayed unto you &amp;<lb/> but <del>who</del> total you will never
                acknowledge him <add>ודהו שומע תפילה וגו'</add><lb/> But yet a way shows no us our
                Thora to aim this holy end, and this<lb/> way is the prayer, and therefore is it the
                most perfect services</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>because it guides directly to acknowledging of God, as our<lb/> Thora said:
                    <add>ברכות לב לעולם יסדר אדם שבחו של הקב"ה ואח"כ יתפלל</add><lb/> (<add>איפא
                    פנימיו אומר אם תפילה של אדם נשמעת אלא בבית הכנסת שנאמר לשמוע אל הרנה ואל</add>)
                If our prayers be Hymns and praises, the<lb/> subjective effect is a direct display
                of God's divine character<lb/> but if our prayers are supplanting or reporting our
                own foo-<lb/>lishness or <sic>weekness</sic> are the direct, and God's omnipotence
                and<lb/> mercy the indirect display. Therefore hymns are the former<lb/> and prayers
                the latter part of our service.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">b</hi> If the effect of prayer is subjective, we want in
                them<lb/> no mediation between God and man, neither of the angels nor<lb/> of other
                spiritual beings.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <add>התפילה במקום הרנה רש"י קלוסו של ישראל שם תהיה התפילה</add>
            </p>
            <p>It is said in the Talmud <add>ברכות דק ד</add><lb/> The <add>ריב"ל</add> and the
                    <add>כאשר נעמוד על סוף כונת התפילה נמצא שיש בה בו בחינות הא' לספר בשבחו של הקב"ה
                    ולהאמין</add> are throughout against the mediation<lb/>
                <add>כי הוא יכול על כול שהוא מלך מלכי המלכים אשר בידו נפש כל חי. ויש עוד בחינה בו
                    שהוא</add><lb/> This is the sublime character of our Religion, displaying<lb/>
                us the purest and most perfect notion of God, of the features<lb/> of his holy
                existence; guiding us the way to his perfection,<lb/> she also represents us the
                possible perfection of man by<lb/> the precepts of the revelation, for only to his
                likeness can<lb/> God speak; by the precepts. In the Likeness of God in his own<lb/>
                image the man was created, sons are you to the Living God,<lb/> our holy doctrine
                taught us the perfection of the human <add>?</add><lb/> that the man is the next
                intellectual being to God, he is his<lb/> son, that he can acknowledge God and serve
                him without one<lb/> mediation. No religion in the whole world possesses those
                high<lb/> terms of truth, trust and eternal hopes. The Psalmist was<lb/> inspired by
                those Deas and sung so lovely <add>ראשונה כפי סברת המוני והוא השגת תכלית מבוקשו, אך
                    אתן שינוי לבתי אדון כל</add>.<lb/> But those high notions make us very easily
                proud or haughty,<lb/> therefore we need to be <sic>remined</sic> of our
                foolishness, meekness,<lb/> transitoriness, invalidity and nullity, that shall be
                done<lb/> by our prayers of supplication and <sic>repentence</sic>, and not<lb/> by
                the notion of the mediation (that was the first reason of it)<lb/> for this is an
                Sea guise strangely to our holy Religion.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p><hi rend="underline">C</hi> If the effect of our prayers shall be subjective,
                our<lb/> service ought to be in the <sic>hebrew</sic> language—for<lb/> this
                language is the tongue of our Prophets, of our<lb/> solemn Psalmists, the tongue of
                our holy scripture.<lb/> yea, the mere <sic>soun</sic> of those words awake our
                heart<lb/> to a holier feeling and higher inspiration, to a<lb/> sublime admiration
                of the most High. There exists no<lb/> language, that possesses a character so
                sublime and ador<lb/>ing, simple and short, easy and living, this is the<lb/> best
                vehicle of our thoughts before God. And again,<lb/> no poetry had so aft and
                manifold the Deity to her<lb/> object, nor sung so solemnly the attributes and
                perfections<lb/> of God, as the <sic>hebrew</sic> did; there is no poetry
                possessing<lb/> those riches of natural picturesque and scenery, which breath<lb/>
                love and admiration in the heart. Those sentimental<lb/>
                <del>sentim</del> sentences of the prophets, those <sic>conserated</sic> and
                deeply<lb/> felt words of the holy Scripture are the best vehicle <del>?</del><lb/>
                to adore our God. And again we ought to understand the<lb/> words of our heart, and
                where is the son of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, who<lb/> understands not the
                language of his Thora? If some<lb/> should be so unhappy to be ignorant in the word
                of his<lb/> holy book, they may weep and study, as our ancestors did<lb/> in the
                time of <persName>Esra</persName>, but for the benefit of some we<lb/> can'nt offer
                the whole</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">D</hi> All those prayers of reaangenie<add>?</add> or curses
                need to be expelled<lb/> of our liturgy, what subjective effect can we expect of them?<lb/>
                <add>שמות לג, כ כי לא יראני האדם וחי</add>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">E</hi> The sabbatical morning-service shall not be
                continued<lb/> above 2 ½ or 3 hours including the sermon, and that of the<lb/>
                festivals not above 3 or 3 ½ hours (Rabbi did not speak of<lb/> a service without
                sermon) It is said in the Talmud, that <persName>Rabbi<lb/> Akiba</persName> and
                    <persName>Rabbi Atarphon</persName> made their prayers<lb/> very short, when
                they ministered in the Synagogue<lb/>
                <add>ברוך ובלבבך לעשותו כי קרוב אליך הדבר מאוד</add></p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>(I am afraid the multitude of <add>חובת הלבבות שער היחוד</add> and the sing-sing of
                    <add>ומת כל אליענו הקרוב עלינו בכל קראנו אליו</add> and<lb/>
                <add>שבת יב</add> shall bad suffer by that)</p>
            <p>Now, my orthodox brother, here are the principles<lb/> of <persName>Rabbi
                    Wise</persName>, according which the new<lb/> liturgy shall appear. Here is a
                mount of<lb/> truths, of Information and conviction, there is<lb/> Tara and
                Philosophy going hand in hand. What<lb/> can in right be said against those truths?
                nothing,<lb/> but so wish the whole liturgy may be to consequence<lb/> of those
                principles, that all the congregations of<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> may adore our God according to those principles,<lb/>
                and the new liturgy may be successful to unite<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName> in <placeName>Amerika</placeName> into one great
                body</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <add>ואלו הן פרקליטיו של אדם תשובה ומעשים טובים</add>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I am <persName role="author">Joseph</persName> your brother</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)"><sic><addressee>Rev. Mr. Elisser</addressee></sic>!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir!</p>
            <p>I send you those ripe fruits of <persName>Rabbi Wise</persName>, that<lb/> the
                reading people may know, what we have to expect<lb/> of this energiral<add>?</add>
                doctor, for it is more than sure, that<lb/> he will give the <sic>impuls</sic> to
                great motions by his active<lb/> spirit and multitude of sciences. He is powerful in
                the province<lb/> of speaking as sublime in his <add>?</add>eas. I have mistakes
                in<lb/> my writing, but I am in haste and pray you to correct it.<lb/> Some
                    <sic>supscribers</sic> of the <sic>occident</sic> I gathered, and next I
                will<lb/> send you the money.</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">I am yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">LJ</persName>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps you can find place for those lines<lb/> in your Journal of this month.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <addressee>B. Samuels Esq.</addressee>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I recommend to you my agent<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. M. Light</persName>, who is authorized to collect<lb/>
                <del>agents of</del> subscribers for the History of the<lb/> Israelitish Nation, and
                wish you to recommend<lb/> him to your friends.</p>
            <p>I shall continue to write on the Jurisprudence<lb/> of the Israelites, and afterwards
                republish it in<lb/> pamphlet form. If you have to make to me any<lb/> remarks on
                this subject I shall be pleased to read<lb/> of you.</p>
            <p>Please to give my best respects to your<lb/> mother.</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">Respectfully yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">Dr Wise</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">
                <placeName>New York</placeName>
                <date>December 26.1852</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <addressee>John Samuel Esq.</addressee>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Being in possession of your<lb/> favor of the <date>12.</date>
                inst., I am sorry that I<lb/> cannot serve you; as usually I have not preserved<lb/>
                the articles on Jurisprudence. I am very lazy in<lb/> this respect.</p>
            <p>Please to inform the judge, that he can find<lb/> a historical development of the
                subject in the<lb/> appendices to each period of my “History &amp;c,<lb/> which will
                be continued in each of the following<lb/> volumes.</p>
            <p>I took the liberty of sending to you ten copies<lb/> of the first volume of my
                History to supply<lb/> you and your friends; since I cannot immediately<lb/> send an
                agent to distribute them.</p>
            <p>Please deposit some copies in a bookstore which<lb/> you think most fit together with
                one of the<lb/> annexed circulars. I sell to bookstores for<lb/> $1,50 per copy.</p>
            <p rend="indent(7)">Most Respectfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">Isaac M. Wise</persName>
            </p>
            <p><placeName>Albany</placeName>
                <date>December 14: 1853</date>.</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>a hundred times, without ever to reason or to think on<lb/> any one subject;
                therefore I bid a farewell to <sic>jewish</sic><lb/> literature, to
                    <sic>jewish</sic> quarrels, to <sic>jewish</sic> struggles, and<lb/> threw my
                whole force upon profane sciences, and I<lb/> shall in a month or two try my fortune
                as a<lb/> philosophic author, <hi rend="underline">an Essay on immortality</hi>
                with<lb/> physical evidences I have nearly finished, and it<lb/> will be published
                right of; if I am not more<lb/> fortunate as a philosophical author than I was<lb/>
                as a rabbi, I shall compile spelling books for<lb/> little children or till the
                ground to earn a living and<lb/> let humbuggers be ministers, teachers,
                professors,<lb/> authors or whatever they chose to be. This may excuse<lb/> for not
                having done what I <sic>promissed</sic>.</p>
            <p>You remembered me or the school of <placeName>Padua</placeName>, and<lb/> that is the
                most serious wound in my heart, which<lb/> you could touch; first all the proud
                hopes, which<lb/> I there entertained, which I see now fade away came<lb/> some
                more, in my mind; secondly it grieves me<lb/> very much, that our
                    <sic>american</sic>
                <sic>jews</sic> could not come<lb/> up to the great idea of establishing such a
                school;<lb/> and third, it grieves me seriously to know, what<lb/> pure Judaism I
                studied there and what a corrupted<lb/> one we have here.</p>
            <p>I wish you give my best respect to your mother<lb/> and to your father.</p>
            <p>I shall be happy to serve you in any way.</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">Faithfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">Your obd't s't</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">
                <persName role="author">Dr Wise</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>John Samuel Esq.</addressee>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <placeName>Albany</placeName>
                <date>March 14. 1851</date>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">Your favor of the <date>12.</date> ins. was duly<lb/> received, and
                I take pleasure in answering you instantly.<lb/> You find the best account about the
                school of <placeName>Padua</placeName> in<lb/>
                <persName>Dr. I. M Josts</persName>
                <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add>; in his <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add> you find only a brief sketch,<lb/> while the former book contains an
                    <sic>authentical</sic> and perfect<lb/> historical account gathered from the
                written documents<lb/> of that school. As to the statement of
                    <persName>Hollam</persName> that<lb/>
                <date>1350</date> be the date of its foundation I have to observe, that<lb/> this is
                by no means correct; for if he refers to the<lb/> rabbinic-cabalistic school, which
                once was a <placeName>Padua</placeName> and<lb/> which was the foundation of the
                present one, we could<lb/> show him in the different prefaces of rabbinical and<lb/>
                cabalistic treatises that this school existed already in<lb/> the <date>10<hi
                        rend="sup">th</hi> century</date>, as you will find in
                    <persName>Josts</persName>; and the<lb/> present one was founded by exiles from
                    <placeName>Spain</placeName>, or<lb/> rather the old one was gradually converted
                into a<lb/> scientific institute by those intelligent <sic>spanish</sic>
                <sic>jews</sic>,<lb/> which was at the commencement of the <date>15<hi rend="sup"
                        >th</hi> century</date>.<lb/> Were I not too much employed otherwise I would
                fur<lb/>nish you with a sketch; but I think it is too interesting<lb/> as that you
                should allow one to do it for you.</p>
            <p>You will be kind enough to excuse me, that I would not<lb/> write any thing about
                    <sic>jewish</sic>
                <sic>juris prudence</sic>; I retired<lb/> altogether from the field of
                    <sic>jewish</sic> literature for various<lb/> reasons. I was beaten every way
                and with all sorts of<lb/> rods; I was decried by all sorts of fanatics, fools, ignorants,<lb/>
                <add>?</add>; I was rejected, abused wherever I opened the door;<lb/> I found that
                men as <persName>Mr. Isaac</persName>, <persName>Mr. Lyon</persName>, <persName>Mr.
                    Rosen-<lb/>feld</persName>, and others, who have knowledge enough to read<lb/>
                the prayers and humbug the world with an assumed<lb/> bigotry, with some dozens of
                every day sentences, which<lb/> they compile to a sort of speech, and repeat
                them</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I hope to give to the world a history of our nation, which<lb/> will fully show the
                important position of <placeName>Israel</placeName> among the<lb/> nations. You see,
                my dear sir, that I did not yet think how<lb/> to publish it, as I was not sure of
                success; but now I<lb/> have made my plan to this effect. As soon as the number<lb/>
                of subscribers is important enough, I shall publish the<lb/> first volume reaching
                to the destruction of the first<lb/> temple. I shall first offer the business to
                    <persName>Mr. Hart</persName> of<lb/>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>; because he, being an Israelite, feels more
                    in<add>?</add><lb/> in the matter than other publishers. If we cannot agree<lb/>
                on the terms for I have about $1500,00 expenses for books<lb/> necessary to the
                purpose—then I thought of going to <persName>Harpen</persName><lb/> or another
                publisher. If I can agree with none I publish<lb/> it myself for my subscribers
                only; for them, after the work<lb/> will be completed, I am sure every publisher
                will buy the<lb/> copy right. It will remain a standard work for the next<lb/> 25
                years. This is my intention, and I see in your letter,<lb/> it will meet with your
                approbation.</p>
            <p>I wish, you would be kind enough, to let me have your<lb/> corrections on the
                Jurisprudence of the Israelites.</p>
            <p>Please to accept of my assurance of my best respect.</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">Truly Yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">
                <persName role="author">Dr Wise</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Albany</placeName>, <date>March 25. 1853</date></p>
            <p rend="align(center)">To <addressee>John Samuel Esq.</addressee>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
            <p>Dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your favor of the <date>24.</date> inst. was <sic>duely</sic>
                received, and<lb/> I take of this early opportunity to thank you for your
                kindness<lb/> which you manifest in the interest taken in my intended<lb/>
                publication. Permit me, dear sir, to give you a short<lb/> history of my history,
                and you will find, that your<lb/> suggestions are really welcome to me.</p>
            <p>I felt for years the necessity of having a complete and<lb/> unfalsified account of
                our nation in the English language,<lb/> wherefore I commenced translating
                    <persName>Jost's</persName> history of the<lb/> Israelites; after I was done
                nearly half with the work<lb/> I notified my attention to the public; but the
                opposition<lb/> against this work was great both here and in
                    <placeName>Germany</placeName>.<lb/>
                <persName>Dr. Frankel</persName> of <placeName>Dresden</placeName>, and
                    <persName>Dr. Sachs</persName> of <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, as<lb/> well as
                    <persName>Dr. Raphael</persName> of <placeName>New York</placeName> and others
                were<lb/> greatly opposed to the work; because, they say, <persName>Dr.
                    Jost</persName><lb/> did not write in the interest of Jews, but to obtain a<lb/>
                professorship. I know this, but I had not the moral<lb/> courage to undertake the
                composition of an original<lb/> work. My friends in <placeName>Germany</placeName>,
                and especially <persName>Dr.<lb/> Frankel</persName> urged the matter upon me; my
                friends here also<lb/> wanted me to try, but every one doubted, that the work</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
