<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item34</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1864-07">3 July 1864</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1864-07">5624</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>
                <date>3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> July 1864 (5624)</date>
            </p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">I am in receipt of your various favors<lb/> and also
                    <date>June</date> Occident with my sermon on the “Citizen
                    <persName>King</persName>.” Your heading it<lb/> thus is no misnomer, and is
                satisfactory. It is very exactly reprinted, and afforded,<lb/> let me hope, pleasure
                to your numerous readers. I am glad you have spoken out plainly<lb/> on the subject
                of a “personal messiah.” The events of the past, and those looming out of the<lb/>
                future do not present anything so favorable to the Jewish mind that it should adopt
                the<lb/> opinions of <persName>Maunheimer</persName> and
                    <persName>Horwitz</persName> on the subject. I, for one, am undesirous of
                abandoning<lb/> the rich hopes of <placeName>Israel's</placeName> return to
                    <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and the universal belief in monotheism
                among<lb/> the families of the earth, together with the reign of absolute peace
                throughout the world,<lb/> and all the priceless blessings attendant thereon, for
                the vague ideas and generalities of<lb/> Jewish neologists. I am for <add>לתורה
                    ולתעודה</add> content to die hopefully <add>אף על פי לתמהיה</add></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">What say you to the “Powenir<add>?</add> party of
                    <placeName>Curaçao</placeName> issuing their shameless caliency<add>?</add><lb/>
                against their brethren! It is very painful to find Jews thus venting their spite, in
                the<lb/> heat of local dissension, to the detriment and perhaps future evil of all
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. I allude<lb/> to their publishing the libel that
                    <add>ולמלשנים</add> is directed against Christians. May the<lb/> consequences of
                disseminating this falsehood not recoil on themselves. The pastoral<lb/> letter of
                    <persName>Rabbi Chumaceiro</persName> you must have seen by this time, as well
                as the “dingy<lb/> sheet” containing the slander. You surely will not suffer your
                pen to be idle in this<lb/> emergency, we all expect to see a scathing answer from
                you on the whole question.<lb/> I had already in the pulpit exposed, in part, its
                other falsity; and intend going on till the<lb/> subject be exhausted. The head and
                front of the party was here a week ago,<lb/> but I declined meeting him or extending
                him any courtesy. I told his friends that</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p><del>with</del> to his and party's views on the subject of synagogal and other
                reforms I would<lb/> not have attacked, but when he and they issued a slanderous
                    impretation<add>?</add> against<lb/> their own flesh and blood, it was time,
                since it affected the reputations of every<lb/> individual Israelite, that their
                ignorance and malevolence should be exposed.<lb/> His name is <persName>Abraham
                    Cohen Henriques</persName>. His chief collaborators and his brother<lb/>
                <persName>Solomon Cohen Henriques</persName>, his brother in law <persName>Augel
                        Jessuron<add>?</add></persName>, a <persName>Doctor
                Henriques</persName><lb/> and a <persName>Doctor Senior</persName>. These are the
                    <add>חמשה טובי עיר</add>. <persName>A. C. H.</persName> writes in Dutch.
                His<lb/> effusions are then translated into French by <persName>Dr. H</persName>,
                and <persName>Augel Jessuron</persName> then<lb/> puts the precious ideas into
                Spanish. But the filtration does not purify the<lb/> feculent matter which
                    gutters<add>?</add> from their pens. It is said that <persName>A. C.
                    H.</persName> came on<lb/> here on a speculative trip to obtain subscribers to
                the party, and contributions to<lb/> their <del>new</del> proposed new Synagogue,
                the worship in which is, sans doute, to eclipse, in its bold<lb/> departure from the
                ancient standards of practice, and that the German and<lb/> American Reformers have
                hitherto established. I do not think he gained<lb/> either subscribers or
                subscriptions and as his attack on the Jews was<lb/> generally denounced in no
                unmeasured terms by even nominal Israelites,<lb/> he could not have gone home
                rejoicing.</p>
            <p>My post here is not an easy one, but I am disposed to accept the<lb/> difficulties it
                presents. Fortunately the By Laws which stipulate that<lb/> the worship shall be
                according to that followed by the Spa. &amp; Portug. Jews, and<lb/> the power the
                Laws invest me with of directing and conducting the whole<lb/> economy of public
                worship, <del>is</del> are obstacles to any sudden or ill considered<lb/> changes in
                the ritual or worship. I can take my stand on these protecting<lb/> defenses, and
                refuse to sanction what the majority of <placeName>Israel</placeName> disapproves
                of. Quietness however reigns at present, yet the time may not be so distant for<lb/>
                the outbreak of disturbances. But I do not apprehend such violence as<lb/> the
                    Porrenir<add>?</add> party have exhibited.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We have had some little display of irreligion not withstanding. Your
                old</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>correspondent <persName>M B. Simmonds</persName>, now poor no longer, but rich in
                worldly goods,<lb/> has been staggered by <persName>Colenso</persName>, and openly
                declares himself a <hi rend="underline">Unitarian</hi>!! <add>?</add> his<lb/>
                disbelief in the Bible! On my election, people were taxed more highly to pay my
                salary, among<lb/> others himself. To get rid of this demand of the Synagogue, he
                applied to be admitted a<lb/> member of the Lutheran church; the<del>y</del>
                authorities consented to take his money, taxed him<lb/> $32 <add>?</add> allotted
                him a seat in church &amp;c, but the Govermt. told him he must<lb/> pay his
                    finta<add>?</add> to the Synagogue also, unless he became a Christian. Of course
                if <persName>Colenso</persName><lb/> unsettled his belief as a Jew, he did not
                predispose him to to take up xleavity<add>?</add><lb/> instead, so at the present
                moment he contributed to Shool and Church, and belongs<lb/> to neither. Another
                German <persName>Shofel</persName> likewise refused to pay the whole of his<lb/> tax
                and sent a letter to the representatives that if they did not reduce it to half<lb/>
                he would <hi rend="underline">apostatise</hi>. They sent him no answer, but recorded
                a strong resolution<lb/> on their minutes condemnatory of his conduct. He went to
                the Moravians, and applied<lb/> to become a member; but on being told that he must
                learn certain test books by<lb/> heart, and he examined on them in open assembly
                prior to being <sic>baptised</sic>, he withdrew in disgust. So<lb/> you see I do not
                repose on a bed of roses</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I <sic>inclose</sic> herewith the receipt of the Captn. of the
                Responsible<lb/> and your Invoice Amtg to $78.50 The books have not come to
                hand,<lb/> they must have been amongst that part of the cargo condemned and<lb/>
                sold at <placeName>Bermuda</placeName>. I want the small Bibles and Roads to
                Faith<lb/> badly, and Prayer Books too. I wrote all about them in the<lb/> letter I
                gave my brother, and which I suppose he has handed you.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Well the Great <persName>General Grant</persName> perhaps may not
                turn out<lb/> a <persName>Ulysses</persName> after all, and the
                    <placeName>south</placeName>
                <hi rend="underline">may yet conquer a peace</hi>. I<lb/> fervently hope and pray
                they may, and tho' I would be <sic>loth</sic> to see any<lb/> part of the Federal
                territory ravaged and despoiled as the Union soldiery<lb/> treated the Confederate
                territory, yet little commiseration would be felt<lb/> if northern soil were made to
                feel what it is to be trodden by the armed</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>heel of the invader. Down to date the southerners appear to have<lb/> the best of it.
                The deserve success, for they have sacrificed their<lb/> own lives to achieve it,
                and not hired mercenaries to fight their<lb/> battles. My brother has frightful
                northern proclivities. His opinion<lb/> of northern honor and political honesty is
                lofty and grand. We<lb/> are widely different in our Estimate of the result, and
                the<lb/> ability as well as inclination of the Federal states to pay the<lb/> public
                creditor. I hope he will not be one of the sufferers;<lb/> I have urged him till I
                am weary to sell out, and have<lb/> nothing to do with Greenbacks and 5/20s, and on
                the finely<lb/> engraved promises to pay of <persName>Mr. Chase</persName>, but all
                my entreaties<lb/> have been of no avail.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I will write you soon again. I delivered your<lb/> message to
                    <persName>Mr. Osorio</persName> about the £14. The <persName>Revd. Dr.
                    Myers</persName> of<lb/>
                <placeName>Kingston Ja</placeName> has received notice that his services will not
                be<lb/> required after his term of engagement expires, this time next year.<lb/>
                <persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> and her mother send their kind regards to you<lb/>
                and all old friends. <persName>Mayor Wolff's</persName> golden wedding will<lb/>
                take place on <date>31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> August</date>, Grand preparations are
                being made<lb/> for the event. I will write you all about it when it comes<lb/> off.
                    <persName>Chamacero</persName> is coming over for the occasion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">God bless and protect you prays</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">yours sincerely</p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName>
            </p>
            <p>The heat is dreadful. It is really a great effort to write<lb/> a long letter, and I
                am sure you will appreciate it.<lb/> Tell my brother, if with you, that I will write soon<lb/>
                <add>בברכה</add></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
