<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Stablin, J. P.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item78</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Stablin, J. P.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Alexandria, VA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1829-09" source="" attested="yes">11 September 1829</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item78_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item78_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item78_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item78_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Alexa</placeName> 9 mo. <date>&#40;Septr&#41; 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1829</date>.</p>
				<p>Respected Friend</p>
				<p><addressee>Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I hope my long silence after  the<lb/> reception of their <del>of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date></del> written on board of the S. Boat<lb/> Long Branch has not induced thee to believe I intend<lb/> to treat thy friendship with coldness.  No&#33;  I cannot<lb/> but love an <sic>afectionate</sic> heart let me meet with<lb/> it where I may.  As an apology&#44; let me state that the business in which I am interested with<lb/> my father required so much of my attention<lb/> that I had not time to bestow many thoughts upon<lb/> correspondence with my friends.  I am sorry it<lb/> was not convenient for them to call in <placeName>Alex<lb/>andria</placeName>.  <sic>Shouldst</sic> thou come this way again<lb/> when either myself or my father &#40;for I allowed<lb/> him the gratification of reading thy letters to my rela<lb/>tion <persName>Thos S. Pleasants</persName>&#41; is alive.  I hope thou wilt<lb/> call and spend a day or two with us.  As<lb/> well as I recollect now I knew nothing of thy<lb/> expectation of visiting <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> until my<lb/> cousin <persName>Theos S Pleasants</persName> informed me he had<lb/> requested thou to call upon me on thy way thither.  Such with<add>&#63;</add><lb/> intimacy and perfect confidence which subsist<lb/> between us that we do not hesitate to take this<lb/> liberty in regards to each other&#44; and it gives me<lb/> as much pleasure to entertain a friend who<lb/> comes thus recommended by him&#44; as one whom<lb/> I have invited myself.  I was lately in <placeName>Phila<lb/>delphia</placeName> and head I known where to call upon</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>this would have stolen an hour or two from my<lb/> engagements for the purpose of seeing thee.  Please<lb/> to inform me when thy residence is so that if<lb/> business or inclination should draw me to <placeName>Phila</placeName><lb/> again while thou art a resident of it I may<lb/> know where to find them.  Thou sayest I<lb/> know to a certain extent what are thy senti<lb/>ments.  In so far as they have been manifes<lb/>ted by thy correspondence with my friend <persName>T. S. P.</persName><lb/> and myself I am pleased with them.  It is not<lb/> necessary for me to inform them that I do not feel<lb/> bound as thou dost to observe rigorously the<lb/> Law as delivered through <persName>Moses</persName> to the children<lb/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; yet this being thy situation would not say any thing against<lb/> a strict obedience to it by all also feel this<lb/> obedience to be their duty.  I hope there is&#44; I<lb/> know there ought to be&#44; enough good feeling in<lb/> my heart to prevent me from regarding as un<lb/>fit for social and all other valuable inter<lb/>courses any person who honestly differs from<lb/> me in persuasion.  Our God will not I believe<lb/> require <del>from us</del> at our hands&#44; more than he has clearly<lb/> made known to us we ought to perform&#59; there<lb/>fore it is clear to my view that every man<lb/> must be allowed to judge for himself&#59; not<lb/> barely <hi rend="underline">suffered</hi> to enjoy this liberty without<lb/> <hi rend="underline">actual interference</hi> in his concerns&#44; but with<lb/> willingness on the part of every body else per<lb/>mitted to select the labour that best pleases him<lb/><del>self</del>.  I utter not these sentiments because</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>I think they are different from thine.  I think<lb/> it is no more than a fair inference from<lb/> thy letters that thy views are similar.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The information which I requested my friend<lb/> <persName>T. S. P.</persName> to obtain from thee in relation to the<lb/> customs of the early Christians would not have<lb/> been in time to subserve the end I then had<lb/> in view if thou couldst have furnished it&#44; for<lb/> the short essay I was writing had to make its ap<lb/>pearance on the <date>2d day of the 3d mo &#40;March&#41;</date>.  There<lb/> was one item in they communication which would<lb/> have been to the point if it had been supported<lb/> by <del>quotations</del> the authority of any <sic>jewish</sic> or other scribe<add>&#63;</add> of<lb/> early times viz that the pious <sic>jews</sic> have al<lb/>ways been in the habit of collecting together<lb/> every morning &#38; evening for the purpose of wor<lb/>ship.  It would have been evidence of some weight<lb/> to prove that the assembling of the Disciples of<lb/> <persName>Jesus</persName> on the first day of the week was not in con<lb/>sequence of its institution by him as a day of rest.<lb/>  If in the course of thy reading thou shouldst<lb/> print with any thing which will <sic>shew</sic> in what<lb/> light the early Christians viewed this day.  I will<lb/> thank thee if thou wilt make a note of it so<lb/> as to furnish me with an extract at some<lb/> future time if it shall be necessary.  I send<lb/> a no. of the newspaper contg my essay &#40;for the<lb/> matter of which I am principally indebted to other<lb/> witnesses&#41; without any expectation that it will ap<lb/>pear to be more than a very moderate perform&#61;</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>&#61;ance.  The side which I espoused and which I<lb/> believe is the liberal one triumphed in the e<lb/>lection of council&#45;men by a majority of three<lb/> to one.  Being so fairly beaten after unwear<lb/>ied efforts to obtain their object for seven or</p>
				<p rend="Text separated by lines written sideways in the middle of the page."></p>
				<p>eight years I do not think the other party will<lb/> have the hear to lift its hand again for a long<lb/> time.  With desires that it may be thy lot<lb/> to receive pleasant things at the hands of<lb/> the great Donor I subscribe myself thy<lb/> afft friend</p>
				<p><persName role="author">J P Stablin</persName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways in the center of the page."></p>
				<p><addressee>Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
				<p>care of <persName>David Judah</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Baltimore</placeName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways in the center of the page."><persName>David Judah</persName> will confer a favour on the<lb/> writer of this by forwarding it with the ac<lb/>companying Newspaper to <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName></p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">Abr <add><placeName>Alex&#39;r</placeName></add> 9 mo. <date>&#40;Sept.&#41; 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1829</date></p>
				<p>Respected Friend</p>
				<p><addressee>Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I hope my long silence after the reception of <sic>thein</sic> written on<lb/> board of the S. Boat Long Branch has not induced thee to believe I intend<lb/> to great thy friendship with coldness&#8212;<sic>sol</sic> I cannot but love an affect&#45;<lb/>ionate heart let me meet with it when I may&#8212;As an apology let me state<lb/> that business in which I am interested with my father required so much<lb/> of my attention that I had not time to bestow many thoughts upon corre&#45;<lb/>spondence with my friends&#8212;I am sorry it was not convenient for thee to<lb/> call in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>&#8212;Shouldst thou come this way again when either myself<lb/> or my father &#40;for I allowed him the gratification of reading thy letters<lb/> to my relation <persName>Thos. S. Pleasants</persName>&#41; is alive&#44; I hope thou wilt call and spend<lb/> a day or two with us&#8212;As well as I recollect now I knew nothing of thy<lb/> expectation of visiting <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> until my cousin <persName>Thos. S. Pleasants</persName> in&#45;<lb/>formed me he had requested thou to call upon me on thy way thither&#8212;Such<lb/> is the intimacy and perfect confidence which subsist between us that we do<lb/> not hesitate to take this liberty in regard to each other&#44; and it gives me<lb/> as much pleasure to entertain a friend who comes thus <sic>recommanded</sic> by him&#44;<lb/> as one whom I have invited myself.  I was lately in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> and had<lb/> I know where to call upon thou would have stolen an hour or two from my<lb/> engagements <sic>fro</sic> the purpose of seeing thou.  Please to inform me where thy<lb/> residence is so that if business or inclination should drive me to <placeName>Phila.</placeName><lb/> again while thou art a resident of it I may know where to find thee.<lb/>  Thou sayest I know to a certain extent what are thy sentiments&#8212;In so<lb/> far as they have been manifested by thy correspondence with my friend<lb/> <persName>T. S. P.</persName> and myself I am pleased with them.  It is not necessary for me to<lb/> inform thee that I do not feel bound as thou dost to observe rigorously the<lb/> Law as delivered through <persName>Moses</persName> to the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; yet this being<lb/> my situation I would not say anything against a strict obedience to it by<lb/> all who feel this obedience to be their duty.&#8212;I hope there is&#44; I know<lb/> there ought to be&#44; enough good&#45;feeling in my heart to prevent me from re&#45;<lb/>garding as unfit for social and all other valuable inter&#45;course any person<lb/> who honestly differs from me in persuasion.&#8212;Our God will not I believe<lb/> require at our hands&#44; more than he has clearly made known to us we ought<lb/> to perform&#59; therefore it is clear to my view that every man must be allowed<lb/> to judge for himself&#59; not barely <hi rend="underline">suffered</hi> to enjoy this liberty without<lb/> <hi rend="underline">actual interference</hi> in his concern&#44; but with willingness on the part of<lb/> every body else permitted to select the labour that best pleases him&#8212;<lb/> I utter not these sentiments because I think they are different from thine&#8212;<lb/> I think it is no more than a fair inference from thy letters that thy veins<lb/> are similar&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The information which I requested my friend <persName>T. S. P.</persName> to obtain from<lb/> thee in relation to the customs of the early Christians would not have been<lb/> in time to subserve the end I then had in view if thou couldst have furnished<lb/> it&#44; for the short essay I was writing had to make its appearance on the <date>2 <sic>of</sic><lb/> the 3 mo &#40;March&#41;</date>&#8212;There was one item in they communication which would have<lb/> been to the point if it had been supported by the authority of any <sic>jewish</sic> or<lb/> other writer of early times vis that the pious <sic>jews</sic> have always been in the<lb/> <sic>hab it</sic> of collecting together every morning and evening for the purpose of</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">2</p>
				<p>worship&#8212;It would have been evidence of some weight <sic>toknow</sic> that the<lb/> assembling of Disciples of Jews on the first day of the week was not<lb/> in consequence of its institution by him as a day of rest.  If in the<lb/> course of they reading thou <sic>shouldstmeet</sic> with anything which will show<lb/> in what light the early <sic>christians</sic> received this day I will thank thee<lb/> if thou wilt make a note of it so as to furnish me with an extract at some<lb/> future time if it shall be necessary&#8212;I send a no. of the newspaper<lb/> cont my essay &#40;for the matter of which I am principally indebted to<lb/> other writings&#41; without any expectation that it will appear to be more<lb/> than a very moderate performance.  The side which I espoused and which I<lb/> believe is the liberal one triumphed in the election of council&#8212;men by<lb/> a majority of thru to me&#8212;Being so fairly beaten after unwearied efforts<lb/> to obtain their object for seven or eight years I do not think the other<lb/> party will have the hear to lift its head again for a long time&#8212;With<lb/> desires that it may be thy lot to receive pleasant things at the hands of<lb/> the great Donor I subscribe myself thy</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)">Afft friend</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)">&#40;signed&#41;    <persName role="author">J. P. STABLIN</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
