<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item150</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Kingston, Jamaica</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1858-12" source="" attested="yes">20 December 1858</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>9 pages on 9 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Kingston Jam</placeName>&#58; <date>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Decr. 1858</date>.</p>
				<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
				<p rend="indent(1)">Dear Friend.</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">The Occidents for <date>October</date> have come<lb/> to hand&#44; but no letter from you.  By this time you will have<lb/> received my last p <persName>Abby Watson</persName> requesting you to obtain<lb/> 50 copies of my catechism from the Sunday School in your city.<lb/>  I have not a copy&#44; and none are to be had here.  I wish you<lb/> also to forward a couple dozen of <persName>Miss <sic>Peixottos</sic></persName> Book&#44; and about<lb/> 3 dozen <persName>Henry&#39;s</persName> Class Books&#44; of the Edition published in <placeName>America</placeName>.<lb/>  On consideration you need <hi rend="underline">not</hi> send <persName>Miss P&#39;s</persName> Books for <persName>Henry&#39;s</persName><lb/> will answer my purpose as well.  I require also about 1 dz<lb/> copies of <hi rend="underline"><persName>Cohen&#39;s</persName> Hebrew Grammar</hi> on the <hi rend="underline"><persName>Ellendorff<add>&#63;</add></persName> system</hi><lb/> which you will oblige me by procuring.  All these books I want<lb/> without delay&#44; and the money shall be remitted as soon as<lb/> they arrive.  On the <sic>inclosed</sic> tracing paper is the pattern of<lb/> the binding of a book&#44; side and back.  Send one of your daily<lb/> prayers &#40;<sic>portuguese</sic>&#41; similarly bound&#44; color red maroon approaching to<lb/> red morocco.  I had sold another copy of the Festival prayers<lb/> and if I get the money for them before an opportunity offers for forwarding<lb/> this&#44; the money <del>not</del> I have in hand &#40;&#36;60&#41; with that &#40;nearly &#36;20&#41;<lb/> will be sent by same via.  I have still on hand the 2 best bound<lb/> sets&#44; 91 Vol deft.&#41; and part of one set common sheep &#40;3 deft.&#41;.  If<lb/> your small Bibles were a dollar or &#36;1 &#189; each I could sell them<lb/> readily but 2 &#189; people decline to give.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Have you ever felt an Earthquake&#63;  For a quarter of a century</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>I have been familiar with them&#44; and their nature is such that&#44;<lb/> totally different from other dangers to which one gets accustomed<lb/> They excite and increase our fears the oftener their shock is felt.<lb/>  You become paralyzed&#44; your faculties are suspended&#44; the<lb/> will ceases to act on the voluntary parts of the body&#44; and tho&#39;<lb/> fully alive to the horrors of entombment&#44; whether in or out of<lb/> doors&#44; which threaten your life&#44; you are incapable of making<lb/> the effort to move from the spot.  To ejaculate a word or two<lb/> of prayer <del>and</del> in prospect of an immediate and awful death<lb/> which hundreds may share with you at the same moment is<lb/> all that your consciousness of the alarming extent of your peril<lb/> and the impossibility of escaping it&#44; permits you to do.  When<lb/> the earthquake is felt in the day time&#44; a rush from the house to<lb/> the street may be effected by some <del>one</del> whom fear does not render<lb/> incapable of moving.  At night however&#44; when enfolded in the bonds<lb/> of sleep&#44; you become suddenly awakened by the house shaking<lb/> and riding on its foundation&#44; the <sic>upheaved</sic> and undulating<lb/> earth on which it rests&#44; then can one realize in all its positive<lb/> meaning the <add>Hebrew</add> the Psalmist speaks of.  Not the bad dream<lb/> not the distressing night&#45;mare&#44; not the terrifying images which<lb/> a heated brain&#44; a sickly fancy&#44; or a superstitious mind<lb/> conjures up&#8212;but it is the awe of an instant dissolution&#44; a<lb/> stern summons to give up life in a few seconds which stops<lb/> the beating of the heart&#44; checks the current of the blood&#44; and<lb/> &#8220;<sic>distils</sic> you to jelly with the effect of fear.&#8221;</p>
				<p>On <date>Thursday at &#189; past 1 A M &#40;23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Decr.</date>&#41; the whole city was<lb/> on the verge of destruction from one of the severest earthquakes<lb/> I ever yet felt.  A few seconds longer&#44; say 3 or 4 and every</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>building would have fallen in and buried its inmates alive.<lb/>  Truly&#44; &#8220;God is merciful&#8221; or I would now not be writing.<lb/>  Imagine&#44; if you can&#44; the house <del>riding</del> being lifted and down&#44; rocking<lb/> from side to side&#44; the walls shaking&#44; beams&#44; joists&#44; rafters<lb/> roof&#44; cracking&#44; creaking as yielding to the irresistible force<lb/> of the subterranean movements&#44; one and all writhed and struggled<lb/> to disjoint itself from mortise and tenon&#44; to wrench itself from<lb/> the hold of girder&#44; screw&#44; and nail.  My wife and I were awake<lb/> when it began.  It must have lasted 15 seconds&#44; some say half a<lb/> minute.  Neither of us could move&#59; both were calm &#38; collected.  I<lb/> never&#44; during the agonizing interval&#44; indulged the slightest hope<lb/> of deliverance&#44; but momentarily expected to see the walls give way and<lb/> the roof fall in and crush us to death.  Short as was the<lb/> continuance of the horrid throes of our &#8220;mother and our grave<add>&#63;</add>&#8221;<lb/> they have left a never to be forgotten remembrance.  Thanks be to<lb/> the Almighty&#44; no life was lost&#44; no one injured.  But I fear that<lb/> every building has been so shaken that in case of a similar recur&#45;<lb/>rence there may be loss of life and destruction of property.<lb/>  Shortly after the occurrence&#44; several places of worship were opened<lb/> and thronged by <sic>worshippers</sic> scared and trembling with affright.  My<lb/> wife begged me not to leave her&#44; and therefore I did not go.  The<lb/> night was beautiful&#44; moon and stars shining brilliantly&#44; the<lb/> air cool and fresh.  The occultation of Saturn took place that<lb/> night.  There are many mining enterprises going forward on the<lb/> <placeName>Island</placeName>&#44; and as the work is carried on through the whole 24 <del>years</del> hours<lb/> fears were entertained for the safety of the miners&#44; but no accident<lb/> has been heard of&#44; altho&#39; the earthquake was severely felt in<lb/> the mining district.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Have you seen <persName>Dr. Kalisch&#39;s</persName> translation of Genesis.  From<lb/> a review of it in the &#8220;Westminster Review&#44;&#8221; whose tendencies<lb/> are rationalistic I have gleaned an extract or two.  He has<lb/> not been more fortunate in his rendering of <add>Hebrew</add> than his<lb/> predecessors.  I do not like <add>Hebrew</add> &#8220;tho&#39; many flock to <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>.&#8221;<lb/>  You may differ from me in opinion&#44; but I prefer the translation<lb/> given in the &#8220;Israelite&#44;&#8221; and <del>&#63;</del> the more I examine and<lb/> consider it with reference to history&#44; the more am I convinced<lb/> of its truth.  <persName>Onkelos</persName> and the masora have led the whole Jewish<lb/> and Christian world astray.  <add>Hebrew</add> occurs 3 times in the chapter<lb/> and why the first time it should be translated &#8220;<hi rend="underline">sceptre or</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">staff</hi> and the second &#38; 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> &#8220;<hi rend="underline">tribes</hi>&#8221; I cannot understand.  Again<lb/> why <add>Hebrew</add> should not apply to the &#8220;confederated Israelites&#8221; when<lb/> <persName>Judah</persName> is blessed&#44; and understood to allude to a portion of<lb/> that confederacy under the leadership of <persName>David</persName> and &#8220;<add>Hebrew</add>&#8221; is<lb/> also an enigma to me.  The passage is very simple&#44; if the legitim<lb/>ate rendering of <add>Hebrew</add> <del>be</del> as &#8220;tribe&#8221; be given.  Not shall depart<lb/> a tribe from <persName>Judah</persName>&#44; nor a commander from between his feet<lb/> from among his followers until he come to <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>&#44; and to him &#40;<persName>Judah</persName>&#41;<lb/> should be the gathering &#40;assembling&#44; marshalling&#44; in array&#41; of the<lb/> people  The armed confederacy as it existed from the Exodus<lb/> to the division of the land among the tribes&#44; was dissolved at<lb/> <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>&#44; by <persName>Joshua</persName>.  And the best proof that <persName>Judah</persName> was then<lb/> divested of the leadership is the divine permission to rescue<lb/> in Judges <add>&#63;</add> for a temporary purpose.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">So our friend <persName>Gutheim</persName> is going to be married.  I am<lb/> glad to hear of it&#44; and wish him all happiness.  Your<lb/> intended <del>periodically</del> weekly ought to succeed such an array of<lb/> talent taste and industry as <persName>Jacob</persName>&#44; <persName>Raphall</persName> &#38; yourself<lb/> is not often to be met with&#44; and in the ranks of <placeName>Israel</placeName> is<lb/> an anomaly considering that our utterances rarely combine<lb/> to advance the General Good.  I am glad the Pope still<lb/> refuses to give up the child of mortara&#59; his obstinacy will<lb/> the sooner bring on the crisis in which the Papacy and<lb/> its supporters &#40;<persName>Louis Napoleon</persName> &#38; <placeName>Austria</placeName>&#41; will be crushed.</p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways over the above text."></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The proceedings of the Habane Bushi<add>&#63;</add> at <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> are<lb/> very mischievous.  United <placeName>Israel</placeName> in <placeName>Europe</placeName> should by means of<lb/> its enlightened Rabbi&#39;s abolish the power of Cherem &#38; <add>&#63;</add><lb/> and the whole of this irresponsible power so insolently assumed by<lb/> such fellows as the Turkish Rabbis.  All this is the effect of the<lb/> dangerous precedents set by the Rabbinism<add>&#63;</add> of the dark middle<lb/> ages&#44; and its usurpation of a power which men like <persName>Akiba</persName> would<lb/> never have tolerated for an instant.  It will be unquestionably<lb/> beneficial to the Turkish Jews Generally that their Rabbis have<lb/> aimed so high as the <persName>Rothschilds</persName> and <persName>Albert Cohen</persName>&#44; who will now<lb/> keep them to break the gallery chain which ignorant zeal has bound<lb/> them.  What say you&#63;  Is this stupid orthodoxy less dangerous to <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> than cold rationalism&#63;  I say no.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> and her mother unite with me<lb/> in kind and friendly regards and trusting that you are<lb/> more cheerful and in higher spirits than when you last<lb/> wrote</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">I am</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">yours sincerely</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
