<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">M. R. M.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item74</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">M. R. M.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 8 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">The American Crisis. No. 4</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="underline">Concluding Reflections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Talmud gives us strong peculiar oriental<lb/> expressions
                touching the importance of civil<lb/> government and the obligation resting on
                every<lb/> man to support the government of the coun-<lb/>try, when it says, “Just
                as the fish which are<lb/> in the sea, every one greater than its companion<lb/>
                devours its comparison, so the sons of man, if there<lb/> were not the fear of the
                government, every one<lb/> greater than his companion would devour his<lb/>
                companion: and this is what <persName>R. Chanania</persName>, dep=<lb/>uty of
                priests, has taught, saying, Pray for the<lb/> peace of the government, because if
                there were not<lb/> the fear of the government, every man would<lb/> devour his
                neighbor alive.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If we would fairly examine how the<lb/> Federal Government of the
                    <placeName>U. S.</placeName> fulfills the<lb/> highest purposes of civil
                government, what are the<lb/> rights which it guaranties to all its citizens,
                how<lb/> much it deserves the support of all citizens and<lb/> how prayer ought to
                be made for it, we must<lb/> take the Declaration of Independence and the<lb/>
                Constitution together as two inseparable parts<lb/> of the one political structure.
                The Declaration is<lb/> the foundation, it clears the ground, and the<lb/>
                Constitution is the frame, the edifice, that has been<lb/> erected over this ground.
                These two documents<lb/> must be placed together, the Declaration below<lb/> and the
                Constitution close above it, to obtain</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>the true picture of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> government.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Here now is the <hi rend="underline">people's</hi> government.<lb/>
                This must be the first impression as we<lb/> survey the Declaration and
                Constitution, that<lb/> the Federal government has been called into ex<lb/>istence
                by the voice of the people. It was not<lb/> the State Legislatures that made this
                government,<lb/> but the people of all the States made it. Each<lb/> State
                government rests on the shoulders of the<lb/> people; and it is just as true that
                the Federal<lb/> government rests on the shoulders of the people<lb/> so that it can
                say to the most humble citizen,<lb/> I am your government, depending on your<lb/>
                vote just as much as your own State gov<lb/>ernment is yours. It has been asserted
                that<lb/> when the Americans cut themselves loose from<lb/> the British government
                they traveled back on<lb/> a path which had never been so trodden before in all the
                Christian Era;<lb/> they did not stop at the Colonial government<lb/> or the State
                government but they traveled back<lb/> to the people themselves as the original
                source<lb/> of all power in government. It was the act of<lb/> the people to
                dissolve the bonds which had con<lb/>nected them with the mother country. The
                princi<lb/>ples of the Declaration are that government is or<lb/>ganized for the
                people to secure them the rights<lb/> of life liberty and the pursuit of
                happiness;<lb/> that when it fails to serve the people they have<lb/> the right to
                dissolve it; that laws derive their<lb/> authority from the consent of the governed;
                and<lb/> that as the people make the government in their<lb/> own name and for their
                own rights they hold</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>it accountable to themselves. The Constitution<lb/> utters its first words in the
                name of the people<lb/> and in the first person: it does not begin,<lb/> We the
                States of <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>,
                    <placeName>Massachu<lb/>setts</placeName>, <placeName>Va.</placeName> but its
                beginning is “We, the<lb/> People of the <placeName>United States</placeName>”—for
                such and<lb/> such purposes—“do ordain and establish<lb/> this Constitution for the
                    <placeName>United States of<lb/> America</placeName>.” It leaves organized power
                to one<lb/> side and travels back to natural right: it leaves<lb/> State government
                to one side and travels back<lb/> to the people as the original source of all
                gov<lb/>ernment whether State or Federal.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">All this being true, still it is not the gov<lb/>ernment of a people
                who are atheists. The<lb/> people most distinctly acknowledge their own<lb/>
                responsibility to God. In the act of demolishing<lb/> their government they
                acknowledge themselves<lb/> responsible to God and not to man for this<lb/> act.
                They speak of those unalienable rights<lb/> with which their Creator has endowed
                them.<lb/> They place themselves on that platform of<lb/>
                <sic>of</sic> independence to which they say “the laws of<lb/> nature and of
                nature's God” give them a<lb/> title. When they declare themselves separated
                from<lb/> all the authority of the British King they appeal<lb/> to the Supreme
                Judge of the world for the<lb/> rectitude of their cause. The radical theory of<lb/>
                the American government is, <hi rend="underline">The government</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">responsible to the people</hi>, <hi rend="underline">and the
                    people</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">responsible to God</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is a government consisting of the three</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>essential departments, the legislative, the<lb/> executive and the judicial: each of
                these<lb/> departments has its own separate place, yet<lb/> like the prismatic
                colours of the rainbow they<lb/> flow together so that no line can perfectly<lb/>
                separate the edges. In the legislative department<lb/> the lower house is elected
                for two years, the upper<lb/> house or Senate for six years, the Executive<lb/> is
                elected for an intermediate period, four<lb/> years; the Judges are appointed for
                life. Each<lb/> department reaches over into the others. The Ju<lb/>diciary can
                declare laws of Congress unconstitu<lb/>tional and void, the legislature possesses
                and<lb/> occasionally exercises both judicial and executive<lb/> powers, and the
                Executive has at all times a<lb/> qualified negative upon legislation and a<lb/>
                judicial power of remission.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is a government which deserves to<lb/> be considered one of the
                grandest institutions<lb/> for the peace of the world. Here were thirty-<lb/>four
                States, and, if Secession is not ac<lb/>knowledged, here are still thirty-four
                States,<lb/> thirty-four Republics, each one delivering up<lb/> its sword to the one
                Federal central govern<lb/>ment, and this general government does not<lb/> spring
                from the States as such, but from<lb/> the people of the States. No one of
                these<lb/> States can make war with another or with<lb/> a foreign nation, or can
                enter into any treaty<lb/> among themselves or any treaty with foreigners,<lb/>
                without breaking the Federal constitution. What<lb/> a diminution of the chances of
                war! What a<lb/> security for the peace of <placeName>America</placeName>!</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is a government one of the elements<lb/> of the strength of which
                is the religious sacredness<lb/> of the oath. It is not without religion
                inas<lb/>much as it is not without the oath. The<lb/> Senators and Representations,
                and the members<lb/> of the several State Legislatures, and all execu<lb/>tive and
                judicial officers, both of the <placeName>United<lb/> States</placeName> and of the
                several States, must be<lb/> bound by oath or affirmation to support<lb/> the
                Federal Constitution. It binds the consci<lb/>ences of all these functionaries to
                loyalty. It<lb/> admits occasionally an affirmation in the place<lb/> of an oath, so
                that Quakers may not be<lb/> excluded. But while it thus religiously binds<lb/> by
                the oath, it allows no religious test ever<lb/> to be required as a qualification to
                any office<lb/> or public trust under the <placeName>United States</placeName>. It
                has no par<lb/>ticular favors for either Jew or Catholic or<lb/> Protestant or
                Deist. It gives to the professors<lb/> of different religions an equal chance
                to<lb/> spread spiritual blessings over the world.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The principles which underlie its<lb/> relation to slavery appear to
                be these; first,<lb/> that slavery is not a sin in itself, and, secondly,<lb/> that
                it is decidedly better that slavery be not<lb/> recognized in the Federal
                Constitution as a<lb/> beneficent institution. The treatment of slavery<lb/> in the
                Constitution embraces the following terms<add>?</add>;<lb/> first, in the slave
                States the population which<lb/> is the basis of representation in Congress
                must<lb/> embrace three fifths of the slaves; this slave ele</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>ment in the population has at times given as<lb/> many as twenty-five men their seats
                in Congress;<lb/> secondly, the importation of slaves into slave-<lb/>holding States
                was not to be prohibited prior<lb/> to the year <date>1808</date>; and, thirdly,
                slaves fleeing<lb/> from one State to another, are not in any<lb/> State free from
                the claim of their masters.<lb/> The Constitution thus favors the Slave States<lb/>
                and gives no countenance to the idea that to<lb/> hold a slave is essentially a sin,
                but at the<lb/> same time it is very careful to avoid every<lb/> mention of slavery
                or of slave. The framers<lb/> of the Constitution evidently felt that slavery<lb/>
                could not be a good word to have in the<lb/> Constitution. We must find slavery in
                one place<lb/> immediately after the mention of Indians, in the<lb/> language,
                “three fifths of all other persons;” or<lb/> we must find it in another place, in
                the<lb/> language, “The migration or importation of<lb/> such persons, as any of the
                States, now ex<lb/>isting, may think proper to admit;” or we<lb/> must find it in
                another place, in the language,<lb/> “No person held to service or labor in one
                State<lb/> under the laws thereof, escaping into another, shall,<lb/> in consequence
                of any law or regulation therein,<lb/> be discharged from such service or labor, but
                shall<lb/> be delivered up on claim of the party to whom<lb/> such service or labor
                may be due”, or we can<lb/> find it in any place in all the length and<lb/> breadth
                of the Constitution; and in each of these<lb/> places the Constitution uses the term
                    <hi rend="underline">persons</hi>, and<lb/> is most careful never to introduce
                the term slaves.</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The framers of the Constitution were most careful<lb/> that all the recognition of
                slavery in the Con<lb/>stitution should be a mere tacit recognition.<lb/> It is a
                Constitution which most quietly secures<lb/> slave States their rights, and most
                cordially<lb/> gives universal freedom every chance in other<lb/> States: it is the
                only Constitution for the union<lb/> and peaceful development of both slave and<lb/>
                free States. With one arm it checks the extreme<lb/> of Anti-slavery, with the other
                arm the extreme<lb/> of Pro-slavery, and it chooses its own ground<lb/> between.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">And now after all that has just been said<lb/> on the Federal
                Government as being the people's<lb/> government, called into existence by the
                people and<lb/> for the people and accountable to the people; as a<lb/> government
                acknowledging the immediate responsibility<lb/> of the people to God; <del>for their
                    governments</del> as a grand<lb/> adjustment of the three powers the legislative
                the<lb/> executive and the judicial; as a stupendous republican<lb/> wheel with
                thirty-four republics within it, each<lb/> of these republics being a wheel moving
                freely<lb/> within the great wheel; as one great rainbow of<lb/> peace spanning the
                heavens from ocean to ocean from<lb/> the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> to the
                    <placeName>Pacific</placeName>; as giving every man his<lb/> own vine and
                fig-tree where he with his neighbors may<lb/> worship God as conscience dictates and
                discuss their<lb/> rights with perfect liberty; and as a safe bond of<lb/> perpetual
                union between both slave and free States,<lb/> favoring on the one hand the right of
                all men to<lb/> life liberty and the pursuit of happiness and securing<lb/> to
                slavery on the other hand its right to life and</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>its representation in Congress as long as any<lb/> State wants it to live; we have
                only one thing<lb/> to say in addition. Let the hand that would destroy this union
                first give good evidence that it<lb/> is able to construct a better Union! Let the
                hand<lb/> that would dare to cut down the flag of the stars<lb/> and stripes, be
                sure that there is some better flag<lb/> ready to ascend!</p>
            <p rend="indent(12)">
                <persName role="author">M. R. M.</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
