<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">&#91;Morais, Sabato&#93;</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item209</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">&#91;Morais, Sabato&#93;</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1861" source="" attested="yes">[September 1861]</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0012.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0013.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0014.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0015.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0016.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>7 pages on 16 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">Reprinted in <hi rend="underline">Jewish Mess.</hi></p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>N. Y.</placeName> <date>Oct. 4&#44; 1861</date> pp 52&#45;3</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">For the <date>national fast&#45;day</date></p>
				<p><persName role="author">MORAIS&#44; SABATO</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Civil War Sermon</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">&#47;1498Lcb</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">Civil War</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">PATRIOTISM etc <add>&#63;</add> Cot 4 <persName role="author">Morais</persName></p>
			<p rend="align(right)">Sermon&#47;</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p>1</p>
				<p>Brethren&#33;  Were it my province to address an audience of non&#45;Israelites&#44;<lb/> I would&#44; on the present occasion&#44; select as my text a weighty sentence<lb/> which occurs in the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter of Exodus.  It is the following <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> <add>Hebrew</add> &#8220;The Eternal said to <persName>Moses</persName>&#44; wherefore criest<lb/> thou unto me&#44;&#63; Bid the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> go forward&#8221; When dearly bought<lb/> freedom is in jeopardy&#59; when the angry billows of a political sea im&#61;<lb/>&#61;pede the march of civilization&#44; and the adversaries of human brotherhood<lb/> are skillfully <sic>marshalled</sic> for the onslaught&#44; deeds of self&#45;denial more<lb/> than psalmody<add>&#63;</add> will sanctify the life of man.  The Lord of hosts will<lb/> be extolled by the efforts which tried to uphold truth&#44; more than by<lb/> the fervent utterance of the lips.  Let him therefore who values his<lb/> country&#39;s honor speed on&#44; let him trustingly follow the path which<lb/> leads to national deliverance&#44; and when the happy goal shall have<lb/> been attained&#44; raise the anthem which will be reverberated <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> from sea to sea&#44; even from the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> to the <placeName>Pacific Ocean</placeName>.<lb/>  Thus would I briefly speak this day&#44; and dismiss <del>a</del> the <hi rend="underline">greater</hi> assemblage.<lb/>  But as my lot was cast among those who are singled out in their<lb/> belief and their worship&#44; I deemed it expedient to adopt a different<lb/> course.  A non&#45;compliance of the Hebrew Community with the<lb/> counsel of the <persName>President</persName> of the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#44; might at this jun&#61;<lb/>&#61;cture&#44; have been open to animadversion.  It therefore became</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>2</p>
				<p>fit that we&#44; who in our devotional outpourings at this solemn<lb/> season&#44; <del>ever</del> tearfully remembered the sorrows of <placeName>America</placeName>&#44; that we&#44; who ceaselessly<lb/> pray for the welfare of the land of our adoption&#44; and testified the love<lb/> we bear it&#44; when at the first summons of the Executive we swelled the<lb/> ranks of her defenders&#44; it became imperative&#44; I say&#44; that we should<lb/> nevertheless your own voices&#44; this day also&#44; to that of our fellow&#45;citizens who<lb/> implore God for the restoration of peace.  And verily&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/>  Whatever opinion we may entertain touching the appositeness of the<lb/> request&#44; our acquiescence therein <del>will</del> can be but the prompting of our<lb/> responsive <del>sentiments</del> feelings.  This country&#44; which many of you<lb/> claim at that of their birth&#44; and some as that of them choice&#44; has<lb/> not&#44; like others that vaunt liberality&#44; doled out her benefits to<lb/> you&#44; O descendants of <persName>Jacob</persName>&#33; but she has generously invited you<lb/> to participate in all the exuberance of her goods&#59; hence&#44; you as you did glory<lb/> in her happiness&#44; <del>and</del> grieve over her distress.  And when the custodian<lb/> of her liberties&#44; descrying imminent danger&#44; exhorts to prayer that it may be<lb/> averted&#44; you who taught the world how to pray&#44; will even at this hour<lb/> exclaim as you are wont <add>Hebrew</add>.  &#8220;Save us O Lord&#44; answer<lb/> us O King on this day that we call upon thy name&#8221;.  But in<lb/> attuning our hearts to the national supplications&#44; we receive an addition<lb/>&#61;al incentive&#44; in the present instance&#44; by the remembrance that the<lb/> Chief Magistrate of our beloved Union&#44; did not transcend the proper <del>his</del> limits&#44; to</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p>3</p>
				<p>pander to the irregular wishes of a majority.  His proclamation is<lb/> the exponent of that excellent provision in the American Constitution&#44;<lb/> which forms its brightest ornament&#44; but of which zealots are now<lb/> striving to divert it.  Not they who tender divine adoration to the man<lb/> of <placeName>Nazareth</placeName> are exclusively recommended to beseech the living God for<lb/> the triumph of rightful authority over usurpation but the people at large&#44; so that<lb/> the entreats of a whole nation ascending the throne of grace may bring<lb/> down plentiful blessings upon our afflicted country.  Such&#44; or the like&#44;<lb/> are his words&#59; very dissimilar my Brethren&#33; from those of some high functionaries&#44;<lb/> whose narrow views debar them from discerning beyond the pale<lb/> of their religion&#44; an object worthy of any consideration.  In confor<lb/>mity therefore with so discreet a summons&#44; we will again pour<lb/> out our souls before the Omnipotent <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> &#8220;Peradventure will He think on us&#44; that we perish not&#8221; <del>Yet</del> But&#44; the<lb/> prayer of freedom&#45;loving Americans must be accompanied by deeds of<lb/> abnegation.  I will repeat it&#58; <del>That</del> Yonder sturdy man who in these<lb/> stirring times <hi rend="underline">inactively</hi> contemplates the perilous state of the <del>country</del> Republic&#44;<lb/> though he bow the head as a bulrush&#44; mistakes the aim of his exist<lb/>&#61;ence.  When around the noblest monument of human wisdom&#44;<lb/> fall destroyers have gathered&#44; let the vigorous&#44; like the ancient Hebrews<lb/> labour with one hand in the work of reconstruction&#44; and wield in the<lb/> other a repelling sword.  <add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>4</p>
				<p>the God of battles <del>of</del> will lead to victory.  But if the patriotic ardour<lb/> that seemed to burn in every breast&#44; when the national escutcheon was<lb/> first tarnished&#44; has been quenched by the Liuthean<add>&#63;</add> water of egotism&#59;<lb/> if the memory of the past achievements and past glory contrasted with<lb/> the present humiliation does not arouse <del>not</del> in our midst the <persName>Leonidas</persName>&#44; that<lb/> will struggle for the maintenance of this peerless Union&#59; if the<lb/> taunts of the ungenerous foreigner&#44; and the sardonic smile of despots&#44;<lb/> are incapable of inspiriting <hi rend="underline">all</hi> to energetic actions&#44; the entreaties<lb/> offered this day will fail to <sic>propitrate</sic> the assistance of the Most High.<lb/>  <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; is a wise aphorism of <placeName>Israel&#39;s</placeName> ancient Teachers.<lb/>  &#8220;We must not rely on miracles&#8221; Nothing is impossible to Him<lb/> who inspired a <persName>Gideon</persName>&#44; and by three hundred of the faithful&#44; put to flight<lb/> the redoubtable <del>best</del> army of <placeName>Midian</placeName>&#44; but while <del>we</del> it behooves us to beseech<lb/> Him and confide in his support for the ultimate success of a<lb/> righteous cause we must labour for our salvation. <sic>we</sic> must render ourselves deserving of it by prefer&#61;<lb/>&#61;ring to <hi rend="underline">individual</hi> promotion&#44; national honor&#44; national <del>greatness</del> Unity&#44;<lb/> national peace.  Shall I now point out&#44; how the pursuing of<lb/> the opposite course&#44; became the bane of <placeName>America</placeName>&#44;&#63; how personal<lb/> ambition becomes the vampire that fed on her life&#39;s blood&#63;  How self&#45;<lb/>interest gave birth to parasites who scampered with the rich spoil of<lb/> their unsuspecting host&#63;  Shall I say&#44; that even at this hour&#44; when</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p>5</p>
				<p>the tocsin resounds which tells the world that the pioneer of civil<lb/> and religious liberty is verging on a precipice&#44; men&#8212;<del>shall I call them<lb/> men</del>&#44; no&#44; heartless and soulless beings&#8212;are found&#44; who will turn<lb/> to profit the mighty struggles of the brave to escape the yawning gulf&#63;  No<del>y</del>&#44;<lb/> let others enumerate the sins which have exposed the country of<lb/> <placeName>Washington</placeName> to the contumely of the stranger and the horrors of war.<lb/>  I will rather deplore them and acknowledge the justice of the Divine<lb/> <del>&#63;</del> verdict <add>Hebrew</add><lb/>  &#8220;For the inequity of his covetousness was I wrath&#44; and smote him&#44; I hid<lb/> myself and was indignant&#44; for he went on forwardly in the way of<lb/> his heart&#8221;.  This sentence of <persName>Isaiah</persName> so applicable to your unhappy<lb/> condition&#44; O my hearers&#44; reveals the plague which has putrified the<lb/> channels whence have sprung these waters of <placeName>Meribah</placeName> &#40;contention&#41;.  Yet&#44; it lies<lb/> in your power to convert them again into refreshing streams of <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> brotherhood.  God showed you the tree that will sweeten those<lb/> bitter waters&#44; in the example of your immortal predecessors.<lb/>  Let the memory of their sterling virtues cluster around your minds&#44; and<lb/> awaken them to deeds of magnanimous valour&#44; let them counsel<lb/> the renunciation of all preconceived <del>thoughts</del> notions for the preservation of<lb/> this palladium of human rights&#44; the total subjugation of selfishness<lb/> for the <del>benefit</del> prosperity of the common country&#44; the repudiation of all</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
				<p>6</p>
				<p>doctrines subversive of the principles which they who framed the<lb/> Declaration of your independence unequivocally for the spread of civilization enunciated&#59; then will<lb/> you regain the attitude from whence you were ruthlessly &#38; unnaturally <del>cast</del> forced down&#44;<lb/> or&#44; to continue in the language of the prophet &#8220;God will see your ways and<lb/> heal you&#44; He will guide you securely&#44; and restore comforts to you and those<lb/> who mourn for your sorrows <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> And this day which a spirit of meekness has devoted to sacred communion&#44;<lb/> will be the opening of a new era&#44; glorious to <placeName>America</placeName>&#44; and fruitful<lb/> of joy to the whole <hi rend="underline">human race</hi>.</p>
				<p>Lord God&#33;  who didst bless this land with Thy favour&#44; restore her&#44; we<lb/> beseech Thee&#44; to Unity.  Cancel her inequities&#44; and let her be distinguished<lb/> anew for the virginal purity of her pristine years.  Grant that<lb/> charity and truth may weave the garland that shall adorn her children&#44;<lb/> for then will righteousness and peace be met in her midst clasped in each<lb/> <del>mutual&#44; others</del> others&#39; embrace.  Guide Thou the steps which are now wending toward<lb/> the conquest of national supremacy over faction&#44; that they may not<lb/> overreach the bounds justly prefixed.  Oh&#33; Eternal Being who didst<lb/> rekindle <del>the long suppressed</del> feelings of love in the bosom of the fierce<lb/> son of <persName>Isaac</persName>&#44; breathe into us words of brotherly reconciliation&#44; and let the hand<lb/> that wields the sword be <del>mutually&#44; grasped</del> fraternally seized with a mutual grasp <del>fraternal pressure</del>.  At this<lb/> hour&#44; when the heart of a whole nation is upheaved to Thee&#44; calm<lb/> O Omnipotent&#33; its inward perturbation.  Regard the prayer which</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
				<p>7</p>
				<p>in various strains but in consonance of thoughts is addressed to Thee&#59;<lb/> let the angels of mercy present it to the throne of grace&#44; and bring<lb/> down thy fatherly blessing upon thy suppliants&#44; even&#44; honor&#44; Union<lb/> and peace for evermore.  Amen.</p>
			<pb n="13"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">Specimen of <persName role="author">Morais</persName> writing</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">orig size of document</p>
				<p rend="Down arrow inserted&#44; pointing to copy of document."></p>
				<p>at a special meeting of the Faculty of Maimonides College held<lb/> in consequence of the sad<add>&#63;</add> bereavement recently sustained by<lb/> the house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; the following preamble and resolutions were<lb/> unanimously adopted</p>
				<p>Whereas the demise of the <persName>Revd Isaac Leeser</persName> is deemed by<lb/> each of us a national loss&#44; and whereas it is our conviction<lb/> that the establishing of this institution was principally due<lb/> to the unremitting exertions of our late colaborer&#44; and to his<lb/> constant advocacy of religious education&#44; therefore</p>
				<p>Resolved that we express our feelings of deep sorrow at the<lb/> loss of a man so zealous for the moral welfare of his people&#44;<lb/> so energetic in promoting the culture of human knowledge&#44; so<lb/> efficient as a professor&#44; so exemplary assiduous in the discharge<lb/> of all his duties.</p>
				<p>Resolved that we <del>gladly</del> descry bearing our testimony to the uniform kindness and<lb/> courtesy that marked his official relations with us&#44; and to<lb/> his timely and useful suggestions as <del>the</del> Provost of this College</p>
				<p>Resolved that we will ever cherish his memory as that of a friend&#44;<lb/> and teach <del>our</del> the students of this Institution to revere his <del>memory</del> name</p>
				<p>Resolved that these resolutions be published in one of our dailies &#38; in all Jewish<lb/> periodicals&#59; <del>and</del></p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><persName role="author">S. Morais</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">sect Pt.</p>
				<p><date>February 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1868</date></p>
			<pb n="16"/>
				<p rend="Note&#58;">Duplicate of page 13. The following is written in the left margin&#44; near the top of the page &#40;where <placeName>Israel</placeName> is underlined&#41;&#58; especially notable<lb/> comparison<lb/> line 4 page 1<lb/><date>Thanksgiving</date> discourse</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
