<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Testimony: An Address Delivered at the Schoolhouse of the Hebrew
					Education Society of Philadelphia</title>
				<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor/>
				<sponsor/>
				<funder/>
				<principal/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
				item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Published manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note/>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution/>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item227</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head/>
					<letHeading>
						<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
						<deliverer/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-04">6 April 1851</dateLet>
						<dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-04">4 Nissan 5611</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author/>
							<editor/>
							<respStmt>
								<resp/>
								<name/>
							</respStmt>
							<title/>
							<decoNote/>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl/>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation/>
							<textLang/>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0014.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0015.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0016.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0017.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0018.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_body0019.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_front0001.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item227_wk1_front0002.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
										>pamphlet</material>
								</support>
								<extent>19 pages on 21 sheets <dimensions/>
								</extent>
								<foliation/>
								<collation/>
								<condition fragment="false"/>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout/>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote/>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote/>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions/>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote/>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p/>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat/>
						<envDesc occ="false"/>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin/>
						<provenance/>
						<acquisition/>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source/>
								<change/>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent/>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates/>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl/>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p/>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p/>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p/>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p/>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p/>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p/>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p/>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p/>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition/>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc/>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc/>
					<label/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation/>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item/>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""/>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="Front Cover"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">THE TESTIMONY:</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">AN ADDRESS</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">DELIVERED BY THE <persName role="author">REV. ISAAC
					LEESER</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><date>NISSAN, 5611</date>.</p>
			<p><placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>,</p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><persName>C. SHERMAN</persName>, PRINTER.</p>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">THE TESTIMONY.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">AN ADDRESS, DELIVERED AT THE SCHOOLHOUSE OF THE HEBREW EDUCATION
				SOCIETY<lb/> OF <placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>, AT THE FIRST OPENING OF THEIR
				SCHOOL, ON <date>SUNDAY, THE<lb/> 4TH OF NISSAN, 5611, (APRIL 6TH, 1851,)</date></p>
			<p rend="align(center)">BY <persName role="author">ISAAC LEESER</persName>.</p>
			<p>MY FRIENDS,—</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Although we are not assembled this day in a house consecrated<lb/>
				to God, still we have met for the purpose of doing honour to our<lb/> Everlasting
				King, and to labour in His name. It has always<lb/> been the custom of
					<placeName>Israel</placeName>, on all occasions of public assembly,<lb/> not to
				let the words of prayer be wanting; it is <add>הקול קול יעקב</add><lb/> “The voice
				which is the voice of <persName>Jacob</persName>,” which is ever accep-<lb/>table on
				High; in this is our strength, in this our victory; herein<lb/> angels of mercy join
				us to do honour to the Creator; and of<lb/> this, in our deepest affliction, tyrants
				in all their power, nations<lb/> in all their tumultuous wrath, could not rob us.
				Let us, then,<lb/> not be unmindful of this our potent weapon, the two-edged
				sword<lb/> of God's praise, which is in our mouth, and let us reverentially<lb/> and
				with deep humility invoke the aid of our Father in heaven<lb/> on the work which we
				are about to begin, in order that He may<lb/> be with us at our first starting, and
				not withdraw from us His<lb/> grace and aid till our task be accomplished.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">1</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">2</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">O Lord Eternal! Thou has commanded us in thy law, that we<lb/>
				should propagate the doctrines Thou has bestowed on us; since Thou<lb/> has
				ordained, “And ye shall teach them to your children, to speak of<lb/> them when thou
				sittest in thy house, when thou walkest by the way,<lb/> when thou liest down and
				when thou risest up.” It is in obedience to<lb/> this behest that we, thy servants,
				have striven to establish a seminary<lb/> where the children born unto
					<placeName>Israel</placeName> might be taught of thy laws, and<lb/> acquire a
				knowledge of the sacred language of thy people, without<lb/> being exposed to the
				danger of contamination, by instruction which is<lb/> hostile to the faith which we
				derive from Thee. Long has our striving<lb/> been in vain, our words fell on ears
				deaf to admonition; but at length,<lb/> for which we bless thy Name, we are at the
				eve of commencing the<lb/> work which is so necessary to the well-being of all
				descendants of<lb/>
				<persName>Jacob</persName>. But, O! how feeble is this beginning—how small the
				number<lb/> of those who have inscribed their names unto Thee; but we entreat<lb/>
				Thee, do not despise the offering which we bring unworthy, though it<lb/> be, of thy
				acceptance; and cause it to prosper and flourish, since Thine<lb/> is the power to
				bless and perfect what man begins in doubt and sorrow.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Long has thy Name been profaned among the gentiles, when they<lb/>
				saw that they who were called thy people were untrue to their calling,<lb/> and
				faithless to the mission Thou has assigned them, to be a guide to<lb/> the nations.
				The knowledge of thy word and thy ways has fearfully<lb/> diminished, and many have
				fallen off, because they know not the prin-<lb/>ciples of thy faith, and the duties
				incident to its followers. Grant<lb/> then, O most merciful Father! that this school
				may become a shining<lb/> ledge the minds of many who otherwise would grope their
				way in dark-<lb/>ness; that its scholars may become quick in the spirit of
				salvation, and<lb/> stand forth as Israelites in whom Thou art well pleased; and
				that<lb/> through them many others may be drawn into the sacred influence, to<lb/>
				devote to Thee their life, their best exertions, and their whole soul.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Upon the teachers who are to engage in the holy work send, we<lb/>
				beseech Thee, thy gracious beneficence; inspire them with meekness,<lb/> to labour
				in the arduous task which they have assumed, and with per-<lb/>severance not to flag
				amidst discouraging trials to which they will be<lb/> exposed. Lend eloquence to
				their tongues, and deep persuasion to<lb/> their words, that they may be able to
				enchain the youthful hearts, and<lb/> bind them indissolubly to thy service, so that
				in after years they may<lb/> rejoice over the multitudes they have brought under the
				overshadowing<lb/> wings of thy Providence.</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">3</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">And upon us, and all the well-wishers of this institution, pour
				out<lb/> the spirit of liberality and devotedness, that we may not be weary in<lb/>
				our struggle, nor become faint-hearted, if immediate success crown not<lb/> our
				enterprise. Yea, teach us to wait for thy aid, in meekness and<lb/> submission, and
				not to expect too much from our own strength and<lb/> our own endeavours; so that,
				persisting to work in the cause of thy<lb/> religion, we may be strengthened with
				the hope that Thou wilt guide<lb/> us aright, and make everything eventuate for the
				best, to the extension<lb/> of thy kingdom, and the spread of thy glory, and the joy
				of the holy<lb/> ones on earth, in whom Thou feelest delight. Be it thus thy will
				to<lb/> establish the work of our hands, and to let thy beauty be revealed<lb/> over
				us. Amen.</p>
			<p>LADIES AND GENTLEMEN,—</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">When <persName>Joshua</persName>, the successor of
					<persName>Moses</persName>, was nigh the end of<lb/> his mortal career, he
				assembled the whole tribes of <placeName>Israel</placeName> at<lb/>
				<placeName>Shechem</placeName>, and addressed the elders, captains, judges, and
				officers<lb/> of justice, in a heart-stirring appeal, relative to their duties
				to<lb/> their God, in reminding them how mercifully He had brought<lb/> them and
				their fathers to be his servants. He left them, how-<lb/>ever, the choice of
				remaining faithful to the Lord, or to select<lb/> some of the various idolatries
				which were then in vogue, either<lb/> that of the Mesopotamians, or of the Emorites,
				near whom they<lb/> then dwelt; but whatever the people might resolve on, he
				de-<lb/>clared his firm determination that he and his household would<lb/> serve the
				Lord. The Israelites, however, who had been the<lb/> witnesses of the mercy and
				might which had been displayed<lb/> before them, had no doubt of the truth of their
				religion in their<lb/> heart; they therefore chose the same worship which their
				leader<lb/> had chosen, and they declared, “We also will serve the Lord,<lb/> for he
				is our God.” After again receiving an affirmation of this<lb/> pious and prudent
				resolution, <persName>Joshua</persName> wrote all that had trans-<lb/>pired in a
				book containing the law of God, and took a large<lb/> stone and erected it there,
				under the beech tree, which was near<lb/> the sanctuary of the Lord; and then we
				read</p>
			<p>
				<add>ויאמר יהושע הנה האבן הזאת תהיה בנו לעדה כי היא שמעה את כל אמרי ה' אשר דבר עמנו
					והיתה בכם לעדה פן תכחשון באלהיכם: יהושע כ"ד כ"ז</add>
			</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">“And <persName>Joshua</persName> said, Behold this stone shall be as
				a testimony against us,<lb/> for it hath heard all the sayings of the Lord which he
				hath spoken with us;”</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">4</p>
			<p>and therefore shall it be as a testimony against you, that ye may not prove<lb/>
				false to your God.”—<persName>JOSHUA</persName> xxiv. 27.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">These last words of the son of <persName>Nun</persName> may appear
				strange to<lb/> you, inasmuch as he ascribes hearing to an inanimate block of<lb/>
				stone, and says that it shall be a testimony against those with<lb/> whom he spoke.
				But it is not to be expected that <persName>Joshua</persName> meant<lb/> to convey,
				or that the people understood him as implying, any<lb/> such absurdity. It is only
				in a metaphorical sense that he<lb/> spoke. The people had been assembled near where
				the stone<lb/> lay on the ground, consequently all the words and promises<lb/> which
				they uttered could have been heard by the stone had it<lb/> been a living being;
				wherefore it might well be erected in that<lb/> place, and remind all future comers,
				on seeing it, that on that<lb/> very spot, and around it, their forefathers stood,
				when they<lb/> solemnly declared that they would remain Israelites, and
				obe-<lb/>dient to the words of God, though they had been offered the<lb/> free
				choice of rejecting Him if they preferred doing so; conse-<lb/>quently the stone, by
				its silent presence, would be a testimony<lb/> against the people, should they ever
				become untrue to their<lb/> Liege-Lord, who had done for them so many wondrous and
				mer-<lb/>ciful deeds. It is well known to you how powerfully mementos<lb/> of the
				departed affect us; how we can be made sad by recalling<lb/> to mind some simple lay
				which we in infancy heard our mother<lb/> sing; how we are constantly wrought upon
				by even trifling<lb/> matters, which bring back before our memory events that
				we<lb/> long since had deemed as faded and forgotten. It need not, there-<lb/>fore,
				surprise us that mankind, in all ages, have deemed monu-<lb/>mental columns of high
				importance, as fixing historical events in<lb/> the most energetic manner on the
				minds of the beholders; and<lb/> it is only in obedience to a positive injunction,
				that the ancient<lb/> Israelites did not invoke the aid of sculpture or the other
				cog-<lb/>nate branches of the plastic art, to commemorate their heroes<lb/> and
				their beneficent exertions. The more reason was there for<lb/> erecting simple, and
				if you will, rough stones, durable as they<lb/> are, and almost bidding defiance to
				the all-devouring tooth of<lb/> time, in order that they might serve to point out
				the spots con-<lb/>secrated by the occurrence of important events, which would</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">5</p>
			<p>then also call their attention to the fact that, because they were<lb/> servants of
				the Incorporeal One, who cannot be represented by<lb/> any outward figure, they had
				been interdicted to make any hewn<lb/> image, the simplest of which had, in the
				corrupt taste of those<lb/> times, been converted into objects of worship; wherefore
				the<lb/> mere product of nature, unadorned and undefiled by the artist's<lb/>
				chisel, must serve them, instead of the laboured monuments of<lb/>
				<placeName>Greece</placeName>, <placeName>Assyria</placeName>,
					<placeName>Babylon</placeName>, and <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. Some
				would-be-wise men<lb/> will, perhaps, esteem this prohibition of sculpture and
				carving as<lb/> narrow and illiberal; but if we view the depravity and hero<lb/>
				worship consequent on representing the human figure in relief,<lb/> as it was
					<sic>practised</sic> by the ancients—the necessary tendency of<lb/> rising in
				imagination from the mortal to the Immortal, and to<lb/> portray Him too with daring
				and impious hands—the means it<lb/> gives to represent criminal acts and indecencies
				of all sorts, as<lb/> we see but too often done among moderns:—we need not feel
				any<lb/> surprise that in our religion no opportunity was allowed to a<lb/> prurient
				fancy so to degrade the highest moral good as to make<lb/> it subservient to vice,
				or to elevate to an undue height frail mor-<lb/>tality, and to invest it with
				attributes to which it has no claims.<lb/> Besides all this, the emblematic pictures
				and sculptures of the<lb/> ancients have long since lost their significance; and
				however<lb/> some one highly endowed may yet be permitted to decipher their<lb/>
				secrets, and the history and lessons they convey, it is not to be<lb/> denied that,
				as guides to mankind, the stupendous works of anti-<lb/>quity are practically of no
				more use than the simple stone erected<lb/> by <persName>Joshua</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You may say, that so far as permanence is concerned, the<lb/>
				monument erected near the Sanctuary at <placeName>Shechem</placeName> is no
				longer<lb/> in existence; consequently to us, at this late day, it is of no
				more<lb/> use than the hieroglyphic-covered columns of <placeName>Luxor</placeName>
				and <placeName>Karnac</placeName>.<lb/> True, most true; but it is precisely this
				perishableness of all<lb/> structures, whether the rude or ornamental, which proves
				the<lb/> utter fatuity of man when he vaunts that he is building for<lb/> futurity.
				He may, indeed, pile up stone upon stone, wall on<lb/> wall, but he has not secured
				his edifice from decay; nay, the<lb/> very materials he employs, the hardest basalt
				and granite will</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">1*</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">6</p>
			<p>suffer from abrasion the moment after they are placed in rest.<lb/> So then let us no
				more know the site on which <persName>Joshua</persName> raised his<lb/> monument—it
				matters not; it spoke its instruction as long as it<lb/> was required, whilst the
				mind of the people needed to be re-<lb/>kindled whenever forgetfulness of God's word
				was threatened in<lb/> the corruption of the times; but, brethren, though the
				stone<lb/> itself has perished, and they have passed away, who, violating<lb/> their
				pledge, suffered for the covenant broken, and the law<lb/> violated: the object for
				which it was erected has not passed<lb/> away, and the religion of which it was a
				testimony is as potent<lb/> now as it was on that very day; and yet more, it is
				firmer esta-<lb/>blished in the hearts of all Israelites than at that early date
				of<lb/> our history, when so many wavered and went often astray after<lb/> strange
				gods who have no breath in their nostrils.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">And let me ask you, What brings us here together this day?<lb/> It
				is the very same idea which caused <persName>Joshua</persName> to set up his
				me-<lb/>morial stone,—it is to testify that we wish to erect an institution<lb/> in
				honour of the name of God. The sanctuary is indeed no<lb/> longer ours; we have only
				small places for meeting to pray and<lb/> to exhort; but we lack the glorious
				manifestation of the Divine<lb/> Presence which formerly animated and comforted us.
				But the<lb/> law itself which was to be glorified through means of the public<lb/>
				ministration of the priesthood is not yet extinct, and claims of<lb/> us, no less
				than in days of old, that we should spread it among all<lb/> classes, as we read:
				“Assemble together the people, the men and<lb/> the women and the children, and thy
				stranger who is within thy<lb/> gates, in order that they may hear, and in order
				that they may<lb/> learn, and fear the Lord your God, and observe to do all the<lb/>
				words of this law.” (Deut. xxxi. 12.) It was not only given for<lb/> the rich, the
				learned, the wise, the aged, the native born, the<lb/> noble, and the priest, but
				for all who bear God's soul in their<lb/> bosom, it was bestowed as the inheritance
				of all mankind, where-<lb/>fore all who were within reach of instruction were to be
				assembled<lb/> to take part in the septennial ceremony of its public
				proclamation<lb/> by the political chief of the people, in order that all might
				be<lb/> animated by one desire to learn how to obey the will of the<lb/> universal
				God, to whom all on earth bear the relation of children</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">7</p>
			<p>to their Father, of scholars to their Teacher. And we have<lb/> come hither to-day to
				commence a school of instruction, open<lb/> alike to the poor and the rich, the
				Israelite and the stranger,<lb/> where it shall be the principal business of the
				teachers to imbue<lb/> the mind early with true conceptions of the Godhead, and
				to<lb/> repeat the lesson so frequently, by a daily putting line upon line<lb/> and
				precept upon precept, that Judaism may become a part of<lb/> the very nature of our
				pupils, without which they could not exist,<lb/> even if they should at a future day
				be tempted to cast it off for<lb/> the glare and allurement of the hostile world
				beyond. It is not<lb/> an easy thing, through some of you, my hearers, may think
				other-<lb/>wise, to acquire this staunch love for religion; or else why do<lb/> we
				see so many violations of its precepts daily and hourly <sic>prac-<lb/>tised</sic>
				before our eyes? Had Israelites that devotion which they<lb/> ought to have, they
				could not so disregard their duties. It is<lb/> education only which can effect
				this, and a constant exhorting at<lb/> home and at school which can result in a
				God-fearing conduct<lb/> through life. You may ask me, “Are there not many
				highly<lb/> educated who are unfaithful? not many ignorant who are pious?”<lb/> I
				readily answer “Yes,” to both these questions. But though<lb/> you do find the
				ignorant pious after their fashion, as <hi rend="italics">far as they</hi><lb/>
				<hi rend="italics">know how</hi>, and the learned often desperately wicked, this
				does<lb/> not gainsay that true piety and an enlightened zeal are only<lb/> found in
				those who have been inly tinctured with divine wisdom.<lb/> For who were the great
				leaders of our race at all times? were<lb/> they the unlettered? who were the
				prophets? were they the un-<lb/>instructed? who were the most glorious martyrs? were
				they the<lb/> ignorant? No, fellow-Israelites, they were all, whether men or<lb/>
				women, those in whom the spirit of knowledge dwelt, and it was<lb/> in their
				footsteps that the multitudes followed, whether they<lb/> made their pilgrimage to
				the temple at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, whether they<lb/> ranged themselves
				under their country's banner on the day of<lb/> strife, although they knew that all
				efforts would be in vain, since<lb/> the enemy had penetrated within their walls, or
				whether they<lb/> hastened to a yet more glorious death when tyrants demanded<lb/>
				their blood as the price of maintaining their religion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We in our day require the same devoted zeal among our house-</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">8</p>
			<p>hold in order that we may maintain the proper influence over its<lb/> members. All
					<placeName>Israel</placeName> may in truth be viewed as one large family,<lb/>
				in which each one has assigned a part which he must achieve or<lb/> be recreant to
				his trust. But, alas! how many have proved so!<lb/> look at the records of the
				congregations in this country, and you<lb/> will seek in vain for the
				representatives of many families among<lb/> the professing Jews. Some have died out
				by the want of male<lb/> descendants to bear their names; but many others have left
				the<lb/> Synagogue, either by <sic>apostacy</sic> or the quiet intermingling
				with<lb/> the gentiles; and in addition to several families thus extinct<lb/>
				already, others are fast hastening to the same deplorable state.<lb/> Have you ever
				reflected on this fact? I have, many, many<lb/> times, with a heaviness of heart
				which I cannot describe to you.<lb/> To see the names once honourable among
					<placeName>Israel</placeName>, borne by those<lb/> who are in feeling the
				bitterest opponents of our race, and the<lb/> more so because they know themselves
				that they are ours by the<lb/> father's or mother's side, is indeed a cause of the
				deepest grief<lb/> to a sincere follower of the God of <persName>Jacob</persName>.
				And I ask you again,<lb/> have you never reflected on this fact? If you have, you
				must<lb/> have discovered that nearly all such connexions have resulted<lb/> from
				one cause, that is, that the offending parties did not con-<lb/>sider Jewish
				families good enough for them to associate with;<lb/> they regarded themselves a
				degree higher than all the Hebrews<lb/> they knew; and hence they sought for
				alliances where they<lb/> fancied their noble blood would suffer no contamination.
				You<lb/> may think that I speak harshly; but does the fact bear me out?<lb/> does
				your own experience confirm what I say? I appeal to<lb/> yourselves, and let me be
				condemned if in your innermost souls<lb/> you find not a response only too
				affirmative of my words. It is<lb/> nothing to the matter that persons of all grades
				of society have<lb/> so offended; for, alas! it requires neither wealth, nor
				intellect,<lb/> nor station, to puff up the human heart with pride, and no one<lb/>
				is so mean but he is in his own conceit higher than all the people<lb/> in
				self-importance. There have been others lost to us, because<lb/> they felt
				themselves neglected by other Israelites, they were not<lb/> appreciated as they
				deserved, so they thought, and they threw<lb/> themselves into the arms of those who
				are always anxious to</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">9</p>
			<p>receive the straying Jewish flock. But whence arose this self-<lb/>assumed
				superiority on the one side and the degradation on the<lb/> other? Do you know this?
				Only reflect a moment, and the<lb/> matter will become clear to you. Answer me,
				Where were our<lb/> religious schools in former times? where are they now? It
				has<lb/> always been to me a subject of profound astonishment and deep<lb/> regret,
				that there was not a single school all over the country,<lb/> until very lately,
				where a Jewish child could obtain any informa-<lb/>tion on his religion. The
				Synagogue was no place for instruc-<lb/>tion, because public lectures formed no part
				of the exercises.<lb/> Family worship, except in rare instances, was unknown,
				and<lb/> family religious reading was not though of, beyond a perusal of<lb/> the
				Bible in the common translation, which was first ordered to<lb/> be read in churches
				by authority of <persName>King James the First</persName>, of<lb/>
				<placeName>England</placeName>. The religious books accessible were limited to
				the<lb/> works of the late <persName>David Levi</persName>, who in his lifetime was
				but ill-<lb/>rewarded for the strenuous exertions he made in the cause of<lb/>
				Judaism. Our Jewish predecessors in this country had only one<lb/> place of meeting,
				and this was the Synagogue, where the worship<lb/> was uniformly the same every
					<date>Sabbath</date> in the year, the tunes<lb/> only varying to suit the
				various occasions for which they are<lb/> very happily adapted. Could such a system
				tend to make men<lb/> and women familiar with their faith? could it produce a
				fusion<lb/> of wills and a harmony of souls, not to speak among natives and<lb/>
				foreigners, but among the natives themselves? It is idle to ex-<lb/>pect it, for
				many knew not a word of Hebrew; the language of<lb/> their worship was an unknown
				tongue to them; consequently the<lb/> sounds, beyond the sweetness of the melody,
				fell like an unmean-<lb/>ing noise to their ears, and no improvement, no lifting up
				of the<lb/> heart, could be expected. And where a little Hebrew was acquired<lb/>
				from some casual <sic>travelling</sic> teacher, it served more to deepen the<lb/>
				shadow of the absence of information, than to remove it, just as<lb/> the taper
				reveals to us more grimly the desolation and darkness<lb/> of a subterranean prison,
				the outlines of which are not to be dis-<lb/>cerned by the flickering flame we carry
				in our hands.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It was indeed surprising that so many years should elapse<lb/>
				without due efforts being made to establish schools, and place the</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">10</p>
			<p>worship in the Synagogue on a better footing. But though the<lb/> evil was so
				apparent, it was allowed to continue unchecked, until<lb/> the eyes of many were
				painfully opened to the want of love and<lb/> harmony existing among us. People who
				had not in youth any<lb/> familiar intercourse, who had been exclusively reared
				among<lb/> gentiles, who had no friends among their own nation, could not<lb/>
				<sic>sympathise</sic> with the other Israelites, who moved in a different<lb/> or
				inferior station to themselves. The sequel was estrangement<lb/> from religion, and
				a constantly decreasing observance of the pre-<lb/>cepts of the Bible. I was told by
				an aged gentleman, now no<lb/> more, that about seventy years ago a Jewish woman,
				who kept a<lb/> boarding-house in <placeName>New York</placeName>, was remiss in
				some small observance<lb/> which I have forgotten. The trustees of the Synagogue, on
				learn-<lb/>ing this, at once proclaimed her house forbidden, and enjoined on<lb/>
				all to abstain from eating with her at her table; and only upon repa-<lb/>ration of
				the wrong was the interdict removed. You may say that<lb/> this was tyranny, an
				unwarranted interference in private family<lb/> matters; I cannot agree with you in
				such an opinion, as it was<lb/> a public affair in which the pious Synagogue elders
				thought<lb/> themselves authorized by custom and prescriptive right to
				inter-<lb/>fere. But be this as it may, it shows the high degree of con-<lb/>formity
				then prevailing in the oldest congregation in the country.<lb/> Now look at the
				contrast with the present state of affairs! See<lb/> how many violate the
					<date>Sabbath</date>; how many are married out of<lb/> the pale of Judaism; how
				many eat forbidden food; how many<lb/> disregard the <date>Passover</date>; how many
				neglect the precept of cir-<lb/>cumcision, and then say, that we have not changed
				for the worse.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I said the evil had become so apparent, and that something<lb/> was
				necessary to be done, that a friend of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, a friend
				of<lb/> mankind, thirteen years ago undertook, unsolicited and of her<lb/> own
				accord, to open a place of instruction for one day in the<lb/> week to all who might
				choose to avail themselves of its advan-<lb/>tages. The school was begun with hardly
				any books suitable<lb/> for the purpose; and now behold! we have a good though
				a<lb/> small series every way calculated to serve the end in view, as<lb/> the works
				embracing it convey a rational account of our religion,<lb/> both its theory and
				practice, and tend powerfully to make a</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">11</p>
			<p>lasting impression on the youthful mind. I cannot doubt that<lb/> much good has
				already resulted from it. Friendships have been<lb/> cemented which probably will
				last during life; children have<lb/> learned to know each other as Jews, and to
				admire each other's<lb/> character, who under other circumstances would never have
				come<lb/> in contact; and I have every reason for believing that evil and<lb/>
				anti-Jewish influences have been eradicated from the minds of<lb/> some who
				otherwise might have forsaken our communion. I do not<lb/> stand, however, here to
				flatter or to blame unduly; I have been<lb/> asked by my colleagues to urge the
				importance of our enterprise.<lb/> Therefore permit that I point out the defects of
				a mere Sunday<lb/> School, unaided by any other seminary. I will again
				acknow-<lb/>ledge, before I proceed further, that the example of the
				benevo-<lb/>lent lady whom we all esteem, and whom I am proud to be per-<lb/>mitted
				to call my friend, and that of her disinterested assistants,<lb/> has been imitated
				in various other parts of the country, until the<lb/> just charge of actual
				ignorance is no longer applicable to all places<lb/> where this has been done. But
				no one can say, that much has<lb/> been accomplished towards diffusing a knowledge
				of the language<lb/> of the Scriptures, without which no education of an Israelite
				can<lb/> be complete. The little that can be acquired in extra hours,<lb/> when the
				children have not to recite their usual lessons or to<lb/> study them, is not
				enough, and must necessarily be very ineffi-<lb/>cient. The child is wearied with
				conning over matters which are<lb/> in themselves of but questionable use, even when
				thoroughly ac-<lb/>quired; and when you demand of him now to repair to his<lb/>
				Hebrew teacher, he will find out a thousand reasons for desiring<lb/> to escape from
				this unwelcome additional task. And I tell you,<lb/> without in the least qualifying
				my assertion, that without an<lb/> adequate knowledge of the Hebrew, sufficient at
				least to <sic>under-<lb/>derstand</sic> the Scriptures and the ordinary prayers, no
				Jew can<lb/> allege that he has acquired that knowledge which is all in all to<lb/>
				him. A Hebrew not to be a Hebrew in language when this is<lb/> within his reach, is
				an absurd proposition, which requires no<lb/> argument to illustrate. And pray, why
				should we not teach to<lb/> all our children the holy tongue, that they may be able
				to speak<lb/> understandingly of God's word when they sit at home, and when</p>
			<pb n="12"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">12</p>
			<p>they walk together by the way? Few are acquainted with the<lb/> rich treasures of our
				literature; and now when modern investi-<lb/>gation is throwing so much light on
				this, no less than other sub-<lb/>jects, it sounds strangely that to English and
				American Jews the<lb/> whole is perfectly inaccessible.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Well may I ask you again, Shall this be always so? will you<lb/>
				always be satisfied with things as they are, when you see the<lb/> evil that has
				already resulted to our communities from this want<lb/> of education? Our Society,
				however, has made it its object to<lb/> become, if permitted by you, and if duly
				encouraged, under the<lb/> blessing of Heaven, to whose safe keeping we commit it,
				an<lb/> earnest agent to remove the reproach so far as our sphere of<lb/> action can
				extend. We purpose to combine elementary and<lb/> afterwards scientific education
				with a gradual and progressive<lb/> acquirement of Hebrew, Hebrew literature, and
				religion. It is<lb/> not to be as in other schools, a secondary matter whether
				the<lb/> children learn Hebrew and religion or not, but they are to acquire<lb/>
				these if nothing else even can be imparted. Still imagine not<lb/> that we are not
				fully alive to the importance of classical and<lb/> elegant literature; we know how
				to appreciate both, and we<lb/> trust that in a year hence our teachers will prove
				to you that<lb/> Jewish children can advance in all the necessary branches of<lb/>
				education under the superintendence of <sic>instructers</sic> of their own<lb/>
				people no less than of others. We mean, however, to let the<lb/> objects and
				concerns of eternal life not be merely the work of<lb/> spare time and a leisure
				day, but to see that daily, and in the<lb/> usual school hours, the language and
				religion of our fathers are<lb/> properly and full illustrated. Permit me to call
				your attention<lb/> to one fact: the members of the committee of school
				directors,<lb/> with a single exception, have no offspring of their own old
				enough<lb/> to be participants in the benefit which the school is to confer, it<lb/>
				is merely a sense of duty which impels them to be active in the<lb/> cause, and to
				incur, if need be, a considerable amount of labour<lb/> to carry out their views.
				But as this is the case, the greater<lb/> necessity rests upon those who have
				children, and who wish to<lb/> rear them in a religious and hopeful manner, to send
				them to us,<lb/> that we may <sic>fulfil</sic> in them the obligation which in
				obedience to<lb/> our religion we have assumed.</p>
			<pb n="13"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">13</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But, I hear some one say, What guarantee can you give us<lb/> that,
				when we remove our children from other schools, they will<lb/> be properly taught
				the branches of a good general education?<lb/> And it is, I apprehend, precisely
				this fear which has hitherto<lb/>
				<sic>withholden</sic> many of you from entering your children as scholars<lb/> on
				our books. But let me tell you that this is not wise, though<lb/> it may be prudent.
				Our efforts must fail, if we meet with no<lb/> encouragement; this I am willing to
				acknowledge; but on the<lb/> other hand I maintain that we shall do more than redeem
				our<lb/> promise, if the children are entrusted to our care. What is to<lb/> prevent
				us giving as good an education as is furnished in public<lb/> or private schools? do
				you believe that we cannot teach reading,<lb/> writing, arithmetic, history,
				geography and the higher branches,<lb/> if these be required? The very idea is
				absurd; whatever the<lb/> scholars show an aptness for can be taught as well, to say
				the<lb/> least, under Jewish supervision as any other. Only try us, if it<lb/> be
				only for one year; and if at its expiration you are dissatisfied<lb/> with the
				progress of your children, taking as the standard of<lb/> comparison what they have
				acquired before elsewhere, we shall<lb/> be willing to acknowledge that we have
				failed.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You must, however, reflect again, that we not merely charge<lb/>
				ourselves with simple education; we wish to return your children<lb/> to you at the
				end of each season improved in manners and morals.<lb/> We wish to subject their
				minds to a wholesome restraint, where<lb/> love shall govern and not force, where
				intellect is to lead, not<lb/> vain ambition. Look at the effects of the Sunday
				School, how<lb/> they have ennobled natures some thought incapable of
				improve-<lb/>ment, and then say that the effect will not be much greater if<lb/> the
				discipline be carried out through the whole period children<lb/> are at school. It
				will most assuredly take some time to get<lb/> everything in is proper train;
				perhaps several weeks must elapse<lb/> before we can fairly assert that we have made
				a proper begin-<lb/>ning; the thing is yet new, and circumstances, the surest
				indica-<lb/>tions of Providence, must show us how we are to proceed; only<lb/> have
				a little patience; the same you would demand if you all<lb/> were in our place, and
				we promise that we will faithfully strive<lb/> to do our whole duty. It is possible
				also, that we may commit</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">2</p>
			<pb n="14"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">14</p>
			<p>some mistakes at the very outset and during the subsequent ex-<lb/>istence of our
				enterprise; but shall this deprive us of your con-<lb/>fidence? we trust not; we are
				all working in one cause; parents<lb/> teachers, managers, children, have all one
				object, that is, the<lb/> diffusion of a knowledge of our religion; and hence we
				trust that<lb/> any error which may be discovered shall be pointed out to us
				with<lb/> candour and mildness, and we will endeavour to amend, so far<lb/> as this
				may be practicable with the means and materials at our<lb/> disposal. Only let me
				beg you, not to doubt hastily of a good<lb/> result; it has been well said that “our
				doubts are traitors;” and<lb/> it is certain that no great enterprise ever succeeded
				where the<lb/> actors themselves doubted of their final success. To insure a<lb/>
				happy issue we must have but one thing in view, namely, the <hi rend="italics"
					>end</hi><lb/> we are aiming at; we must not regard great or small
				obstacles<lb/> as things worth minding, but move straight onward, and let each<lb/>
				step taken in advance be the forerunner and guarantee of the<lb/> next succeeding
				one. Believe me, that the greatest results are<lb/> obtained by slow and contiguous
				minor advances; and they suc-<lb/>ceed the best who persevere the longest without
				despairing of<lb/> their chances of carrying out what they at first dimly
				conceived<lb/> to be within the range of their possibility. As little as wealth
				or<lb/> renown is suddenly acquired, except in rare instances, can any<lb/>
				enterprise, whatever it be, expect to prove itself at once among<lb/> the events
				which are established in the full tide of success.<lb/> Therefore I tell you, demand
				not of us that we shall accomplish<lb/> impossibilities all at once; that we are to
				gather in this institu-<lb/>tion children of various stages of intellect and
				progress in do-<lb/>mestic education, and <sic>mould</sic> them without delay into
				scholars of<lb/> a uniform conduct and progress. Without a miracle, this will
				be<lb/> impossible, and we are not vain nor foolish enough to claim the<lb/> ability
				to accomplish the impracticable. But let me beg of you<lb/> all, not to undervalue
				our and your capacity for succeeding with<lb/> this school because we are Jews. The
				remark is often made, that<lb/> we Israelites cannot do things like other people,
				and that we are<lb/> altogether too self-willed to succeed where others find no bar
				to<lb/> carry out their views. For my part I will never believe that we<lb/> are
				inferior to the best of mankind in whatever we devote our</p>
			<pb n="15"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">15</p>
			<p>attention to. Look at the great progress we have made in com-<lb/>merce and the
				mechanic arts wherever we had a fair field of<lb/> action: and I see no reason why
				the same result is not equally<lb/> certain in every pursuit to which we may
				seriously devote our<lb/> energies. It is and has been our misfortune for many
				centuries,<lb/> that small trading, and at best large commerce, has been our<lb/>
				main pursuit; still, with all the disadvantages of our position, we<lb/> have
				maintained a high character as an educated and intellectual<lb/> people, though at
				times our education systems have been highly<lb/> defective. But I ask you, What is
				to prevent us in this free<lb/> country, where all legal disqualifications are
				unknown, from ad-<lb/>vancing with the same or greater rapidity in intellectual
				pursuits<lb/> with our fellow-citizens of other persuasions? What a
				humi-<lb/>liating confession would it be were we to acknowledge that we<lb/> did not
				establish religious schools, because we lacked the capacity<lb/> and energy to
				undertake them, though we had ample means<lb/> and a fair opportunity to do so. Away
				with such croaking; let<lb/> us not hear the ominous sounds “We cannot;” we can, we
				must,<lb/> we will! say this all of you, induce others to say the same, and<lb/>
				then you will soon see whether Jews can succeed in disseminating<lb/> education and
				religious knowledge as successfully as the best and<lb/> most enlightened
				denomination, whatever this may be.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I use plain language, I deal in no flowers of oratory, and I<lb/>
				trust, therefore, that I shall be best understood. It is not so<lb/> much to the
				feelings I wish to appeal as to your good judgment,<lb/> and hence I hope that you
				will not get impatient when my ad-<lb/>dress detains you longer than you expected.
				The subject is one<lb/> of the highest importance, and concerns you all, my
				hearers,<lb/> whether you are rich or poor. Could I have the opportunity of<lb/>
				seeing you here frequently, I might indeed cut my remarks short<lb/> to resume them
				at another time; but as this may perhaps never<lb/> be in my power, I must crave
				your indulgence to some few other<lb/> considerations in connexion with the
				subject.—To Israelites their<lb/> religion is no <hi rend="italics">luxury</hi>,
				excuse me for using so strange an expres-<lb/>sion, but a matter of primary
				importance. An Episcopalian<lb/> need not be a high or low churchman in order to
				believe in his<lb/> system; for he has a wide range in which to move; and he can</p>
			<pb n="16"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">16</p>
			<p>be a Nazarene, and for all we know fully as good as in his sect,<lb/> though he turn
				Baptist or Quaker. But a Jew is no Jew if he<lb/> has not a firm hold on his
				peculiar opinions and distinguishing<lb/> practice. A theoretical Jew can exist; we
				have, unfortunately,<lb/> many such; but they are not the Israelites of the
				Scriptures,<lb/> because the material element of this character, <hi rend="italics"
					>religious confor-</hi><lb/><hi rend="italics">mity</hi>, is absent. We know,
				moreover, no exemption from duty;<lb/> we have no standard of indulgences or
				restrictions; no noble<lb/> classes who may transgress, no lower orders who may
				yield them-<lb/>selves to degrading vices in order to gratify the sensualities
				of<lb/> the lordlings, who look upon them with contempt even whilst they<lb/>
				minister to their pleasures. The Jew is a Jew, whether he is the<lb/> pedlar that
				bends double under the burden which his laborious<lb/> shoulders carry, or the baron
				of the <placeName>Austrian Empire</placeName> who idles<lb/> away his hours on the
				luxurious sofa. The hopes of the last are<lb/> not a whit higher and nobler than
				those of the first, and this one<lb/> has the same claims to immortality and a
				glorious hereafter, as<lb/> the most favoured child of luxury. Fortune's gifts may
				be, by<lb/> the will of Providence, very unequally distributed; but let not<lb/>
				their possessors deem themselves better men or more God-<lb/>favoured on this
				account. They have a tangible advantage in<lb/> their exemption from toil; they may
				lie down at night without<lb/> torturing their brain how to provide for their little
				ones by the<lb/> dawn of to-morrow. Is not this enough for them? must they also<lb/>
				wish to perpetuate for their families a rank which the now humble<lb/> and their
				offspring are never to attain? Weak! silly! wicked<lb/> idea! <hi rend="italics"
					>God</hi> has elevated you, I tell you, not <hi rend="italics">you</hi> have
				acquired<lb/> your position by your unaided skill and labour; and He can
				un-<lb/>make you, bring you down again to the dung-hill whence you<lb/> sprung, or
				your children, should you even be carried on a splen-<lb/>did bier to the grave, may
				have to claim the assistance of those<lb/> whom you despise as too inferior to
				associate with you and yours.<lb/> The world, and especially this country, presents
				so many instances<lb/> of changes of fortune, that it would be superfluous for me to
				hunt<lb/> for examples of which you, my hearers, know many in your own<lb/>
				experience. Let us hope, therefore, that no silly pride will pre-<lb/>vent parents
				of all standings in society from availing themselves</p>
			<pb n="17"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">17</p>
			<p>of the advantages which we hope to offer to you. “Ho! let all<lb/> you who are
				thirsty,” says the prophet, “come to the waters,<lb/> and he too who hath no money;
				come ye, buy and eat; yea,<lb/> come, buy wine and milk, without money and without
				price.”<lb/> The word of God is free to all, it is the water, the bread, the<lb/>
				wine and milk of life; it refreshes, it satisfies, it rejoices, it<lb/> nourishes.
				It is given to all, offered to all; and we summon all<lb/> within our reach, as did
				the ancient prophet, to partake of the<lb/> repast which we hope to spread for you
				in the name and by the<lb/> aid of God. We demand of those able to pay a small fee
				towards<lb/> defraying the expenses which we have to incur, and we trust that<lb/>
				this will be cheerfully given; but they who are not blessed with a<lb/>
				superabundance of means are invited, nevertheless, to entrust to<lb/> us their
				children, and we promise them that they shall not suffer<lb/> the least reproof for
				the inability of their parents. All we ask<lb/> of them is to send their children
				tidily dressed, and cleanly in<lb/> their persons, so that no stain will attach to
				them for their humble<lb/> state. And let me here remark at once, that nothing so
				promotes<lb/> good conduct and proficiency in study as scrupulous cleanliness;<lb/>
				in a dirty body a dirty soul too often dwells, and the exterior is<lb/> mostly a
				fair index of the inward man. Cleanliness, say our<lb/> wise men, is the first step
				to the acquisition of holiness, and it is<lb/> a necessary element of Jewish life,
				as our holy law amply proves.<lb/> It is not to be questioned, that if the children
				of the poor come<lb/> hither so that all can freely associate with them, it will be
				an<lb/> incentive for the rich to apply to us also to take theirs under<lb/> our
				charge; and only the non-observance of this rule can operate<lb/> as an excuse to
				withhold any one from taking advantage of the<lb/> institution we now commence.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Let no one thing that any injury can result to better trained<lb/>
				children, by associating with those not so fortunate as them-<lb/>selves; in
				after-life they will have to meet with persons of all<lb/> classes, and it is no
				detriment that they become early acquainted<lb/> with the fact that all are not
				prosperous alike. It will produce<lb/> in them kindliness of feeling, at finding
				that the same virtues<lb/> can dwell in a heart covered by a frieze coat, as that
				which<lb/> beats under a velvet mantle, and that the sorrows of the poor</p>
			<pb n="18"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">18</p>
			<p>are the same as those of the rich. This is <hi rend="italics"
					><sic>levelling</sic></hi>
				<hi rend="italics">upward</hi>;<lb/> you elevate the character of the humble, by
				bringing them in<lb/> contact with those of better manners and greater
				refinement;<lb/> and with children of good religious character, you need not
				fear<lb/> that they will corrupt yours, whilst they acquire from them<lb/>
				politeness and good breeding. This is well understood in the<lb/> country where I
				was born. Universal education has long since<lb/> been established there; and at the
				same colleges where the sons<lb/> of the nobles acquire their collegiate education,
				the children of<lb/> the day-labourers are freely admitted. The former have to
				pay<lb/> the annual stipend which the rules require, whilst the others<lb/> enjoy
				precisely the same advantages and privileges without any<lb/> charge whatever; and
				it is not rare that the poorest excel the<lb/> others in every requisite of
				intellect, industry, and aptness for<lb/> study. But what need is there to go over
				the ocean to seek for<lb/> examples of the kind? Look at your own great statesmen, your<lb/>
				<persName>Clay</persName>, your <persName>Webster</persName>, your
					<persName>Fillmore</persName>, and thousands of others, and<lb/> they were the
				children of poverty, of the unknown. And who<lb/> dares not to remind them of their
				origin? They have their<lb/> title of nobility from nature's God, and show me the
				worldling<lb/> who would dispute this claim, valid as it is above all others.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But much as I have yet to say, I find that it is time to close.<lb/>
				It has been my endeavour to exhibit to you, in as condensed a<lb/> manner as
				possible, the necessity of our school, its practicability,<lb/> and the happy
				effects it may produce, if it is rightly encouraged.<lb/> Its friends and projectors
				have laboured long to bring it so far<lb/> as to make a commencement; doubts and
				difficulties have sur-<lb/>rounded every step in advance we have taken, and much
				labour<lb/> and kindness will be required to keep it in operation. It is our<lb/>
				intention, should the demand make it necessary, and our funds<lb/> suffice, to open
				district schools at convenient distances, so as to<lb/> afford all children an
				opportunity to avail themselves of our<lb/> Hebrew education. For the present we
				have selected this place<lb/> as the most central, and we hope that no captious
				fault-finding<lb/> will prevent all our space to be soon claimed by attentive<lb/>
				scholars. The committee of school directors pledge themselves<lb/> to do all in
				their power to afford the utmost satisfaction, and to<lb/> act in all cases with
				strict impartiality.</p>
			<pb n="19"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">19</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In conclusion, permit me, like <persName>Joshua</persName> of old,
				to call your<lb/> attention to this stone, as it were in the great building of
				right-<lb/>eousness, on which all <placeName>Israel</placeName> should labour, which
				we have just<lb/> set up. It is a testimony against you, O Israelites of
					<placeName>Phila-<lb/>delphia</placeName>, whether or not you are true to the
				Lord your God.<lb/> Cherish it, cause it to expand, labour that it may become a
				chief<lb/> corner stone in an extended system of education, whence future<lb/>
				teachers and ministers of <placeName>Israel</placeName> may go forth, to propagate
				the<lb/> word of God: and you will have performed your duty, a duty<lb/> which is
				incumbent on you and all our brothers wherever they<lb/> are. Neglect it, and you
				will have perhaps to deplore <sic>apostacy</sic><lb/> in your own family, and a
				public desecration of the name of<lb/> God by some of your offspring, whom you would
				sooner follow<lb/> to the grave, than see them thus dishonour you and your
				faith.<lb/> It is for your own sakes that we call on you to aid us in our<lb/>
				effort; you will rejoice when you see those dear to you intelligent<lb/> servants of
				god, and familiar with his word, being thus faithful<lb/> from knowledge and not
				mere conformity by descent. You<lb/> never, we trust, will regret the exertions and
				outlay you have<lb/> made in this cause; and they who have laboured to bring
				the<lb/> Education Society into existence, under the blessing of Provi-<lb/>dence,
				will deem themselves amply compensated, when they see<lb/> that their striving has
				in part brought “peace in <placeName>Israel</placeName>.”</p>
			<p><date>Nissan 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, April 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 5611</date>.</p>
			<div>
				<p>
					<ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_9_2.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume
						9 No. 2 pages 61 through 78. Click here to view.</ref>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
