<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item134</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Barnard,
                            George</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1848-12">4 December 1848</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 10 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>My dear Sir,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When I wrote you last spring at <placeName>New<lb/>
                York</placeName>, I had asked <persName>Mrs. Green</persName> the Poetess to send
                an<lb/> article to the Occident, and I suggested to yourself,<lb/> if she did so,
                and you should wish for her farther con-<lb/>tributions, to return her a ten dollar
                bill. I dare say<lb/> neither of you thought proper to comply with my wishes,<lb/>
                because neither of you could see a prospect of advan<lb/>tage in so doing; but had
                you both complied without<lb/> such a prospect, I could have numbered two
                persons<lb/> who had once acted upon a principle of <hi rend="underline">Faith</hi>,
                that<lb/> is, seeing the right of a matter, had done it at their<lb/> own cost
                without a mercenary view, in perfect trust of<lb/> God that as the act was correct
                the result must be for<lb/> the best. Probably both <persName>Mrs. G.</persName>
                with her poetic talent, and<lb/> yourself and bank-note, may have been more fitly
                employed<lb/> though not in the exercise of greater faith, yet in the use<lb/> of
                better discretion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You asked me in your last letter, whether I was or am<lb/> still a
                prophet. I made no direct reply, because then a-<lb/>bout to send you the substance
                of my most signal im-<lb/>pressions as fast as I could get them published in<lb/> a
                newspaper, I did so. As soon as the most important<lb/> of these views had issued,
                the publication was discon-<lb/>tinued from the difficulty of getting them
                completely printed,<lb/> and other considerations regarding the newspaper
                office.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I will now endeavour to answer your question in full<lb/> by
                explaining for your satisfaction what it is to be a pro</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>phet—showing what constitutes the distinction between a<lb/> prophet and another man.
                You are enabled from your own<lb/> knowledge to form some conception of the labours
                and dif-<lb/>ficulties which I have encountered, owing to having my<lb/> mind
                occupied with these considerations. I have had no<lb/> new prophetic excitement or
                revelation since parting from<lb/> you in <placeName>New York</placeName>, nor do I
                expect ever to have any<lb/> of such overwhelming force as those experienced there
                    <del>in New</del><lb/>
                <del>York</del>, and wherein, seemingly, I was admonished of all<lb/> that is
                material for my future guidance. So far as<lb/> experience enables me to state, the
                grand result of a<lb/> prophet's intentions, is but to recognize the perfect<lb/>
                truth and correctness of the principle to do in all cases<lb/> whatever we can judge
                to be right before God, without<lb/> regard to consequences, trusting these entirely
                to His<lb/> disposal as immeasurably superior to our own limited<lb/> views. Thus
                    <persName>Mrs. G.</persName> the poetess, when she had promised<lb/> me some
                verses, would, if she had acted in accordance with<lb/> the suggestions of
                inspiration, have sent them to the Occident<lb/> at my request; merely because it
                was <hi rend="underline">right</hi> for her<lb/> to do so; and the Editor would have
                made her an ade<lb/>quate return in the manner pointed out, as an act of sim<lb/>ple
                justice. The principle of our duty to God is but Just<lb/>-ice: if we accept a
                benefit, we are bound to endeavour<lb/> to return it: if we would reap a good, we
                must sow<lb/> of the kind. This moral obligation so congenial to the<lb/> natural
                feelings, and the conformity to which is hailed<lb/> as a divine attribute of
                humanity, the prophet learns to be<lb/> but a just and pleasant indication of the
                course which is</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2.</p>
            <p>a necessary conformity to the requirements of natural laws.<lb/> The prophet, by
                glimpses of the future which he afterwards<lb/> sees verified, and whose connexion
                he can trace with volitions<lb/> of the past, ascertains <hi rend="underline">of his
                    own knowledge</hi> some outlines<lb/> of the retributive system wherein nature
                holds her courses<lb/> whereby God governs the universe, even down to its
                minu<lb/>test details. The fact of a person predicting a remark-<lb/>able event
                which comes to pass, is of little moment:<lb/> the <sic>surprize</sic> and reverence
                of others at the prophets' fore-<lb/>knowledge can be but humiliating to him, as it
                only evinces<lb/> the subject condition of his brethren upon the earth. When<lb/>
                one whose mind is enlightened by prophetic or inspired<lb/> knowledge, sees error
                reign in the mind of a person or<lb/> a people, it is as natural for him to foresee
                suffering<lb/> and trouble as a consequence, as it is for us to presume<lb/> that
                where weeds rankle among more delicate plants,<lb/> the coop will be unsatisfactory
                to the husbandman.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">How it is that I, so weak a man, so little given<lb/> heretofore to
                the adoption of peculiar or precise views upon<lb/> subjects in connexion with
                religion and government, should<lb/> be made the recipient of these revelations,
                revelations<lb/> so powerful that they seem clearly to involve author-<lb/>ization
                and commandment, that I, rather than any<lb/> other, should be the person to broach
                this might truth,<lb/> to subvert the false but fashionable creeds of the
                civil<lb/>ized world, is more than I can comprehend, and<lb/> therefore beyond my
                power or responsibility to account<lb/> for. I am commissioned by revelations whose
                truth and<lb/> imperative command I cannot doubt, to declare unto Is-</p>
            <p rend="The following word continues on the next page.">
                <placeName>Israel</placeName>
            </p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>rael that the time has come for its people to be res-<lb/>tored to their ancient
                inheritance, that little is wanting<lb/> besides their own earnest cooperation, that
                if any of them<lb/> will give me a hearty concurrence I am bound to labour<lb/> in
                the cause; if not, I have only to discharge the duty<lb/> appointed me to render
                them alone answerable for the<lb/> error. Strange as it may appear, it seems to me
                indi-<lb/>vidually, a matter of indifference whether or not this<lb/> undertaking be
                attended with success. If I am not<lb/> deluded, it must succeed, for such is my
                prophetic<lb/> impression; but notwithstanding the deepest sense of it,<lb/>
                importance to mankind, I feel personally indifferent to<lb/> events; for in these
                spiritual perceptions, I have been<lb/> taught so clearly they wearisome vanity of
                all earthly<lb/> considerations, that I am led to distrust more than de<lb/>sire the
                worldly exaltation which must be consequent<lb/> upon success.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am now living an idle life, yet labouring in<lb/> confusion and
                perplexity to prepare for this great<lb/> work. It is distinctly given me to expect
                that next<lb/> summer there will be a clearing away of difficulties,<lb/> and
                consequently until then I could not look for a<lb/> worthy reception were I sooner
                to undertake to make<lb/> known this mission. Still would I use every means to<lb/>
                prepare the way: therefore was the resort to newspaper<lb/> publication for some
                leading particulars, and there-<lb/>fore, being unable to visit <placeName>New
                    York</placeName> again this sea-<lb/>son, I may probably go to
                    <placeName>Montreal</placeName>, which is nearer<lb/> by, this winter,
                beseeching some individual Hebrews to</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">3</p>
            <p>hear me, though without the hope of producing any<lb/> important impression. Such is
                the only way which lies<lb/> open to a prophet: he hopes that by calling
                individual<lb/> attention to his views, they may be spoken of again, may<lb/> be
                reported abroad, until falling under the notice of some<lb/> true mind and heart,
                they will be made the subject of<lb/> a strict inquiry, and then their merits and
                importance<lb/> be discovered and appreciated. If after giving ample<lb/>
                opportunity to those who should be most immediately in-<lb/>terested in this cause,
                my views remain unaccepted<lb/> and my exertions unsupported, I can only suppose
                that<lb/> a too excitable imagination may have led me in some<lb/> respects to form
                erroneous conclusions, and willingly retire<lb/> to a private station, consoling
                myself for the shame of<lb/> failure with the consciousness of having
                faithfully<lb/> endeavoured to obey the mandate which I had con-<lb/>ceived to be
                entrusted to my execution. If such be the<lb/> will of God, (which I cannot
                believe,) you Jews must<lb/> wait another while for a Messiah and your
                restora-<lb/>tion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But that you may at least agree in opinion with<lb/> me so far as
                this, that the present time appears to be<lb/> a juncture most peculiarly fitted for
                the restoration<lb/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, I would ask you to turn your
                attention<lb/> to the present position of <placeName>Europe</placeName>. The nations
                are all<lb/> in a ferment from the opposition of artificial classes<lb/> grown out
                of false institutions. The masses of poor, be<lb/>sides being crushed by the
                powerful, have been quieted<lb/> with the cordial doctrine of tame submission for
                the sake</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of reward in another world, until they have so multiplied<lb/> as to crowd one
                another from all remunerating employment.<lb/> Starving and desperate they seek
                leaders to marshal them in<lb/> the terrible <del>desperate</del> struggle for
                bread! The call is answered by<lb/> too many of the abandoned, reckless and
                ambitious, proud to<lb/> extort submission from the old possessors of wealth,
                influence<lb/> and dominion. The massive weight of old established fashion<lb/> is
                evenly <sic>balance</sic> by new accumulated force. They who have<lb/> felt
                starvation will encounter it no more, and those who<lb/> hold inherited power and
                position cannot yield their birth<lb/> right:—“at weary bay each shatter'd band<lb/>
                Eyeing their foeman sternly stand;<lb/> And tumult wild and disarray<lb/> Mark the
                fell havoc of the day.”</p>
            <p>That the opposing parties are evenly balanced, only foreshows<add>?</add><lb/> a
                protracted contest. The victory in the end is certain to<lb/> the people so fear as
                relates to the humiliation of their ru-<lb/>lers, but not as regards an effectual
                and permanent<lb/> amelioration of their own condition; for a victory of the<lb/>
                government only reduces matters to their former false<lb/> position to result in a
                new and more violent outbreak<lb/> at the first occasion; while every signal
                advantage<lb/> gained by the masses is a stimulus to the popes and<lb/> energies of
                millions. The people then, sooner or later, must<lb/> triumph so far as to overturn
                their governments. What then?<lb/> Are these demoralized masses qualified to hold
                the<lb/> reins of power? Poverty, ignorance, prejudice and pas<lb/>sion all combine
                to render them corrupt and venal—<lb/> the sport and tools of ill-directed but
                ambitious minds.</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">4.</p>
            <p>Then what can come of all at last but a perpetual re-<lb/>iteration of tyrannies,
                conspiracies, rebellions and civil<lb/> wars? And is this <hi rend="underline"
                    >Progress</hi>? Is this in accordance<lb/> with the developments of nature which
                science and art<lb/> are so fast unfolding in our time? No. Then it<lb/> is not to
                be; for the works of the Lord proceed in uni-<lb/>son, by general laws. If progress
                betters man's outward con-<lb/>dition, it must also improve himself.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But whilst the governments of <placeName>Europe</placeName> are in a
                fer-<lb/>ment, where is the mighty influence of that hallowed pre<lb/>ventive and
                panacea of all earthly ills—the Christian Re-<lb/>ligion? Where shines the force of
                its holy precepts of mild<lb/>ness, affection, long-suffering and forgiveness? In
                the mouths<lb/> of men—not in their hearts. The excellent instructions<lb/> derived
                from or attributed to the meek and lowly<lb/>
                <persName>Jesus</persName> have been used as salt to season, to preserve<lb/> and
                render palatable a mass of fleshly lusts, a whole<lb/> code of impositions,
                falsehoods and absurdities, destined<lb/> to exist until an hour of search and
                trial, and no<lb/> longer. The people have found that however the injunc-<lb/>tion
                to submit to common sufferings in this world be-<lb/>cause their happiness hereafter
                is supposed to be<lb/> bought and paid for, may please their fancies, it<lb/> will
                not answer the requirements of appalling famine;<lb/> and they begin to suspect
                themselves imposed upon<lb/> when, amidst their sufferings, they perceive those
                    <del>very</del><lb/> enlightened superiors who inculcate this doctrine,
                very<lb/> carefully fortified against the contingency of having to<lb/>
                <sic>practise</sic> it. Religion then, as it exits among these peo</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>ple, is no imperishable bond of union, and no ultimate<lb/> resource for the
                reconstruction of their governments.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But how is all this trouble to end, how will the<lb/> nations of
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName> settle down in quietness, how can<lb/> oil be cast
                upon these agitated waters? With<lb/> man it is impossible; but with God, He
                    <del>speaks</del><lb/> wills, and it is done. While secret causes were
                operating<lb/> to set these nations all against themselves, the Lord<lb/> was
                rearing up an humble prophet who should call<lb/> upon <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                to come together and declare that He<lb/> is God, to manifest His truth in realizing
                the<lb/> promises of old, that all mankind might see and<lb/> know that “The Lord
                God Omnipotent Reigneth.”<lb/> Can <placeName>Europe</placeName> or
                    <placeName>Asia</placeName> behold the majesty of the most<lb/> High displayed
                in the restoration of His ancient people<lb/> as the prophets have foretold, and not
                learn to love, fear<lb/> and serve Him? Will they not verify the prediction
                “often<lb/> taking hold of the skirt of a Jew, saying let us go with<lb/> you for we
                have heard that God is with you?”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If this appear doubtful, allow the supposition of<lb/> its untruth,
                and observe the irresistible conclusion. The<lb/> nations of
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName> are impelled by absolute suffering to<lb/>
                overturn their existing governments: the scattered Jews,<lb/> properly neutral in
                regard to the issue, must, from<lb/> their wealth and ability become important
                allies for<lb/> either party: they are therefore surrounded with temptations<lb/> to
                throw the weight of their influence into either scale:<lb/> hence the most liberal
                enactments, emancipation, kindness.<lb/> Jews are but <del>flesh and blood</del>
                human beings like other</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">5</p>
            <p>men; and if a remnant have preserved their faith<lb/> and fashions through the
                severest persecutions it does not<lb/> follow that they will equally well resist the
                fascinating<lb/> influence of justice and generosity. A continuance of the<lb/>
                <del>the</del> action indicated by the motto “liberty, fraternity, equality,”<lb/>
                must soon entice the Israelite to make common cause,<lb/> and next to assimilate
                himself with the rational seek-<lb/>ers after good, in the midst of whom he lives.
                At the<lb/> siege of <placeName>Cressy</placeName>, <persName>Edward</persName>
                being conqueror, ordered six<lb/> of the principal inhabitants to the scaffold: his
                    <persName>queen<lb/> Philippa</persName> begged their lives: <persName>St.
                    Pierre</persName>, the leading patriot<lb/> of the city exclaimed “Ah my
                countrymen, it is now<lb/> that I fear for you; <persName>Edward</persName> only
                wins our cities,<lb/> but <persName>Philippa</persName> conquers hearts.” The
                influence of liber-<lb/>ality and kindness must be the same upon the Is-<lb/>raelite
                as another man; and if he is made a debt<lb/>-or for these benefits, he will acquit
                himself of the<lb/> obligation even at the cost of <sic>cancelling</sic> his
                birthright.<lb/> The Jew would be no more: tempted with alliance in<lb/> marriage,
                forced from his strict <date>sabbath</date> by custom and<lb/> the need of gain, or
                seduced from it by the repose and<lb/> pleasures of the succeeding day, flattened
                through the<lb/> influence of companions, from his cradle to esteem<lb/> himself and
                disregard his maker, he would vanish<lb/> in the surrounding throng—and created time
                stand<lb/> conqueror of eternal truth! It cannot be: the Jew<lb/> must still
                survive, and hold his indifferent course<lb/> amidst the wreck of nations. But to
                preserve his iden<lb/>tity, he must owe allegiance to another state, be bound</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to a government actually existing prompt and efficient<lb/> to protect his rights—a
                government ordained by God<lb/> Himself even as foretold in the cherished traditions
                of<lb/> his fathers.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In an old No. of the Occident, I saw an inquiry<lb/> for information
                as to the authenticity of the passage in<lb/>
                <persName>Josephus</persName> regarding <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.
                    <persName>Davis's</persName> Clairvoyant<lb/> Revelations, p. 578, says “the
                record is genuine altho'<lb/> not contained in some of the early versions of
                    <persName>Jo<lb/>sephus</persName>.” If you have not read <persName>Mr.
                    Davis's</persName> book,<lb/> there is in the store for you a fund of
                astonishment, if not<lb/> of entertainment and information, in whatever light<lb/>
                you may view it.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the letters with which you have been so kind as to<lb/> honour
                me, reference has once or twice been made to a passage<lb/> of scripture, for my
                special consideration. I find noth<lb/>ing more appropriate to the case than Deut:
                XIII.5<lb/> first verses; and by these do I desire to be judged.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When I wrote you last it was on the <date>sabbath</date>. Since<lb/>
                then I have had much reflection upon the observance of<lb/> the day; but my
                conclusions ought to be compared with the<lb/> convictions of others before being
                set down as mature.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Should you issue any thing regarding me in the Occident,<lb/> please
                forward the No. and if you think proper to honour<lb/> me with a reply to this,
                address <placeName>Sherbrooke C. E.</placeName>
                <hi rend="underline">vice</hi><lb/>
                <placeName>Derby Vt.</placeName> Postage must be paid to the line to insure<lb/>
                transmission. I remain my dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(6)">Most Respectfully &amp; faithfully yours</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">George Barnard</persName>.</p>
            <p><date>Decr. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1848</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd. I. Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
