<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Rex</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item133</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Rex</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when="1847?">1847?</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0014.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0015.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item133_wk1_body0016.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 16 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">having attended the late Advent Lectures<lb/> in the Great Tent, at
                    <persName>Niblo's</persName>, <placeName>Corner of Broadway<lb/> and Prince
                    Streets</placeName>, more or less during eight of the<lb/> ten days of their
                continuance, having given par-<lb/>ticular attention to the doctrines
                promulgated,<lb/> and being enabled without difficulty to detect the<lb/> material
                errors of those doctrines, I report for<lb/> publication, my views, stated in few
                    <del>words with</del><lb/>
                <del>sim</del> and plain words.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Adventists are a class of preachers,<lb/> who have undertaken to
                enlighten their fellow-men<lb/> upon Religion, substantially according to the
                opinions<lb/> of one <persName>William Miller</persName>, a worthy old farmer,
                who<lb/> possessing some good faculties for the investigation<lb/> and comprehension
                of the prophecies in the Bible af<lb/>ter diligent application to the subject, came
                to the ra-<lb/>tional conclusion that we are at the eve of a very<lb/> important
                chap in mundane affairs as under<lb/> the influence of Divine Government.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><del>And</del> Here let me promise that all observ-<lb/>ing and
                reflecting minds generally <del>are fast com-</del><lb/>
                <del>ing</del> which have been turned to the matter, are fast<lb/> coming to
                opinions consonant in some measure to that of the good<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Miller</persName>, whether their conclusions be drawn from<lb/>
                <del>Holy Traits, from</del> reflections upon Holy Writ, from behold<lb/>ing the
                recklessness of the age, or from contem-<lb/>plating the surprising developments of
                physical progress.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">What the Adventists preach, and uphold their<lb/> confidence in, as
                the forthcoming event of such mag-<lb/>nitude and importance, is the actual coming,
                ap-<lb/>pearance, presence and being in the body, of <persName>Jesus<lb/>
                    Christ</persName>, upon this earth, whose business, according<lb/> to their
                discourses, it will be to rule and govern<lb/> in money and justice, first making
                some mer-<lb/>ited disposal of all the wicked people, and<lb/> the presiding in
                wisdom and goodness over the<lb/> remainder, whom the Adventists denominate <hi
                    rend="underline">the</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">Saints</hi>, and <del>first and foremost</del> among whom
                are<lb/> to be the Adventists themselves.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Without undertaking here to declare any creed<lb/> or peculiar
                religious belief as especially my own,<lb/> I am ready to confute the Adventists
                upon their<lb/> own ground; and while my hand is in, I even<lb/> extend the offer of
                defiance to the advocates of<lb/> any and every set of opinions or fancies under the
                guise<lb/> of Religion, which recognize the benefit of preaching as<lb/> preferable
                to practice, of vain imagination before some<lb/> sense, of persuading or terrifying
                others rather than re-<lb/>forming one's own conduct, of investigating the future
                instead<lb/> of diligently using the present time, of indulging folly and<lb/> pride
                in lieu of disciplining the mind to reverence and humility,<lb/> of running after
                the <del>vanities of</del> pernicious vanities<lb/> of the world, and not attending
                with every faculty to<lb/> that one only good principle, which is called the
                sovereign<lb/> will of God.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If any would ask why I take upon myself to</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">3</p>
            <p>discuss these important matters, while censuring<lb/> in others the public advocacy
                of their peculiar<lb/> views, let all such <del>persons</del> inquirers distinctly
                un-<lb/>derstand that I object not to the promulgation of<lb/> any well-intended
                doctrine; I only endeavour to prevent<lb/> a false &amp; <del>foolish doctrine</del>
                absurd set of opinions from taking <sic>inspirious</sic> effect<lb/> upon the public
                mind.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Adventists, in their lectures, read us certain<lb/> passages of
                scripture, make their comments, which are<lb/> for the most part rational, declare
                their interpre-<lb/>tations, which are <del>clearly</del> in a great measure
                correct,<lb/> and draw their conclusions, which are mainly <hi rend="underline"
                    >wrong</hi>. They<lb/> profess to adhere closely to the letter or
                    <sic>naturel</sic> mean-<lb/>ing of the quoted words and phrases; and, so far
                as<lb/> they <hi rend="underline">do</hi> abide by the literal meaning, their
                inferences<lb/> appear to be correct; but the substituting of their own<lb/> false
                and imaginary notions for the evident and<lb/> perfectly simple and
                    <sic>indeniable</sic> meaning of the most<lb/> important words and expressions,
                is what leads them<lb/> into wildly ridiculous errors.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The primitive cause of the false conceptions with<lb/> which these
                gentlemen are so grievously misled, may like all other errors of the human
                intellect, be<lb/> found in their impurity of mind, vanity, prejudice,
                self-righteousness and<lb/> imcharitableness<add>?</add>. Of this I will give
                sufficient instances<lb/> before going farther, in citing the simple fact that,
                while<lb/> uttering their doctrines in all devotional sincerity, they<lb/>
                unhesitatingly allude to the Papal power as <hi rend="underline"
                >Antichrist</hi>,<lb/> and to the Jews, the lineal descendants of
                    <persName>Abraham</persName><lb/> who observe the laws of
                    <persName>Moses</persName>, as a God-forsaken</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">4</p>
            <p>people hardly worthy of human sympathy or comment.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">One of the late Advent sermons was preached from<lb/> the text
                        <persName><sic>Zechariah</sic></persName> VIII.23. <del>“Thus
                saith</del></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">“Thus saith the Lord of hosts, In those days <del>te</del><lb/> it
                shall come to pass that ten men shall take hold,<lb/> out of all languages of the
                nations, even shall take<lb/> hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew, saying,
                We<lb/> will go with you; for we have heard that God is<lb/> with you.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It would seem, to a person of plain common<lb/> sense, very easy to
                understand the meaning of this<lb/> text, just as it is written, allowing only for
                the figuration ex-<lb/>pression “take<del>ing</del> hold of the skirt,” after the
                preacher<lb/> had made it evident, (as he did tolerably well,)<lb/> that the
                expression “those days” was meant for<lb/> the present time, even on or close about
                the present<lb/> day and hour of the year <date>1847</date>. A plain man of<lb/>
                ordinary intelligence would then understand that,<lb/> at or about the present time,
                many <del>most</del> people would<lb/> get an idea that <hi rend="underline">the
                    Jews</hi> are in possession<lb/> of the true, original and vital doctrine of
                Religion;<lb/> but, under the declaration of these learned gentle-<lb/>men, the
                scripture is not held to mean what<lb/> it says: according to them the word <hi
                    rend="underline">Jew</hi> does<lb/> not mean <hi rend="underline">Jew</hi>, it
                means <hi rend="underline">Adventist</hi>! Yet these<lb/> learned gentlemen
                preachers loudly <del>sustain</del><lb/> oral advocate literal <del>meanings,
                    interpretation</del> readings, and <del>main-</del><lb/>
                <del>tain</del> proclaim that every passage of scripture is<lb/> best illustrated by
                its context. If, then, the word</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">5</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">Jew</hi> required any explanation as to its meaning,<lb/> such
                explanation should be sought in the rest of<lb/> the writings of the same author
                    <persName>Zechariah</persName>. Let<lb/> any one, then, search there, to see if
                there be any<lb/> reason to think that the prophet, when he said<lb/> “him that is a
                Jew”, meant any thing but such a person as one<lb/> should understand to the
                appellation <hi rend="underline">a perfect <sic>jew</sic></hi>,<lb/> that is an
                Israelite by birth, circumcised, and who strictly observes<lb/> &amp; always has
                observed the injunctions of his religion according to his best<lb/> ability. If the
                reader have not time to search<lb/> through the fourteen chapters of
                    <persName>Zechariah</persName>, he may<lb/>
                <del>even</del> satisfy his mind by reading the eighth chapter<lb/> alone, which
                ends with the above-quoted verse. The<lb/> whole scope and aim of the chapter is
                clearly to <sic>de-</sic><lb/> declare that God will allow his chosen people the
                Jews<lb/> to return and dwell happily in and about
                <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>.<lb/> The condition is simply that they properly
                reform them-<lb/>selves; and as to the time when, <del>the Adv</del> our
                friends<lb/> the Adventists very clearly make it out to be just<lb/> about the
                present day. <hi rend="underline">Amen</hi> say I, in full<lb/> confidence that
                every one who answers the prophets<lb/> character of “him that is a Jew,” will
                heartily join me.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Hear the prophet “These are the things that ye shall<lb/> do; Speak
                ye every man the truth to his neighbour; exe<lb/>cute the judgment of <hi
                    rend="underline">truth</hi> and <hi rend="underline">peace</hi> in your
                gates;<lb/> and let none of you imagine evil in your hearts a<lb/>gainst his
                neighbour; and love no false oath; for all<lb/> these things I hate, saith the
                Lord.”</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">6</p>
            <p>How will these simple precepts tally with the<lb/> supposition of the Adventists,
                that they them<lb/>selves are the subjects of this contemplated king-<lb/>dom? They
                who, professing entire confidence in<lb/> the immediate coming of their Saviour, as
                King<lb/> and Governor, manifest such deep and<lb/> hateful apprehension when they
                detail the<lb/> immense projects and arrangements of (their<lb/> imaginary
                Antichrist) the Roman Catholic Church, for<lb/> bringing all men under the influence
                of<lb/> the gospel. The Adventists admit that<lb/> the Jesuits are a people
                self-sacrificing in<lb/> order to do good, that they are endeavouring<lb/> to
                establish learning and discipline, to ame<lb/>liorate the condition of the poor, and
                to extend<lb/> the knowledge of Religion to the heathen.<lb/> Why, then, whatever
                may be their failings—<lb/> human failings such as <del>we are</del> all men are
                subject<lb/> to—may we not contemplate their efforts<lb/> with rejoicing in kindness
                and charity?<lb/> I, the humble writer, am accountable to the Giver of all good<lb/>
                for as clear <del>perfect</del> an understanding as is commonly<lb/> allotted to
                man, even after the exercises of<lb/> prayer, penitence and reformation—<del>not
                    to</del><lb/> and I for one know of no human influence compara<lb/>ble to that
                of kindness, no persuasive equal<lb/> to <del>good</del> behaviour, and no doctrine
                better<lb/> than that of <hi rend="underline">plain goodness</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When the Adventists come to the word <hi rend="underline"
                >Jeru</hi></p>
            <p rend="The following word continues on the next page.">
                <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>
            </p>
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">7</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">salem</hi>, they often represent its meaning to be an
                ima<lb/>ginary location wherein “<hi rend="underline">the saints</hi>” are forthwith
                to reign on earth.<lb/> These <hi rend="underline">saints</hi>, we understand from
                them, are to be the<lb/> Adventists themselves and such other persons as may<lb/> be
                found, at the time of the descent of the Saviour upon<lb/> earth, to be most
                zealously believing those portions<lb/> of the doctrine in vogue as of the New
                Testament,—<lb/> which are most difficult of comprehension, and<lb/> of least
                immediate practical adaptation to the every-day<lb/> business of ordinary life.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Adventists tell us that these saints<lb/> are to “<hi
                    rend="underline">reign</hi>”; but at the same time declare that they<lb/> are to
                be true Christians. Now it is perfectly<lb/> clear to every one who derives his
                religious prin<lb/>ciples from the New Testament, that the true<lb/> Christian is
                properly one who does not “<hi rend="underline">reign</hi>”<lb/> at all upon earth,
                save over himself, his own<lb/> passions and erroneous propensities, in the<lb/>
                humble endeavour to effect positive good,<lb/> he being thereto actuated by a
                perfect, tone, rever<lb/>ence and fear of the over riding Providence which<lb/>
                creates and controls all, such Christian necessarily<lb/> fully believing in the one
                only and vital Jewish doc<lb/>trine, that, for the wrong we do, we are
                inevitably<lb/> punished, save as Divine mercy may be extended<lb/> to us solely in
                case of thorough repentance and per<lb/>fect resolution and endeavour to always in
                future<lb/> learn and do that which is right in the view of God,<lb/> our Lord and
                maker.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But what I understand by the word <hi rend="underline"
                        ><placeName>Jerusalem</placeName></hi></p>
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">8</p>
            <p>is what every reasonable and unprejudiced mind<lb/> must understand namely what the
                prophet meant<lb/>—and that is <hi rend="underline"
                    ><placeName>Jerusalem</placeName></hi>, the ancient city of the<lb/> Jews, which
                is now in ruins, and which must be<lb/> rebuilt, in order to the verification of the term<lb/>
                <placeName><hi rend="underline">New</hi> Jerusalem</placeName>.<del><persName
                        role="author">Rex</persName></del>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This word <hi rend="underline"><placeName>New
                    Jerusalem</placeName></hi> is a favourite one of our<lb/> imaginative friends,
                the Adventists; but their mode of re-<lb/>building a destroyed city merely by
                preaching and praying and<lb/> singing, <del>to have</del> has never proved
                effectual. <hi rend="underline">We must put</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">our shoulder to the wheel</hi>, as, according to the fable,
                Hercules<lb/> commanded the <sic>waggoner</sic>. The Adventists, as well as
                most<lb/> other religious sects, have a great deal to say about <hi rend="underline"
                    >Faith</hi>;<lb/> the best faith is that which most usefully controls one's<lb/>
                actions, and the best evidence of faith is the shutting<lb/> up the mouth and taking
                hold to do with all our<lb/> might that which is evidently right and best to be<lb/>
                done.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">About these Jews, whom our friends the Adventists<lb/>
                <del>think</del> make so little of; possibly some of those unassuming<lb/> and
                discreet minds who think that perfect wisdom reigns<lb/> in the will
                    <del>councils</del> of the Deity, may conceive that the chosen<lb/> people have
                now sufficiently expiated their national sins,<lb/> and that they have but
                individually to turn unto the Lord<lb/> with all their hearts, to obtain the
                blessing recorded<lb/> throughout the scriptures as their inheritance, and to<lb/>
                stand a holy people, and a living monument, and<lb/> evidence of the truth of
                prophetic revelations. <hi rend="underline">Nous verrons.</hi></p>
            <p><persName role="author">Rex</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
