<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Kursheedt, Gershom</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item198</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Kursheedt,
                            Gershom</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser, Isaac
                            ?</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New Orleans, LA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-02">19 February 1854</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1854-02">19 February 5614</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item198_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item198_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item198_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item198_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">25</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>New Orls</placeName>
                <date>Feby 19. 5614</date>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)">Friday</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My dear friend</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">I have a few moments before<lb/> going home to prepare for the
                    <date>Sabbath</date> and devote<lb/> it to you. Your last letter dated in
                    <date>Decr.</date><lb/> needs no reply now, for everything is changed<lb/> by
                the death of our late friend <persName>Mr Touro</persName>.<lb/> Poor good old
                    <add>?</add>, he had noble impulses<lb/> but<add>?</add> his great misfortune
                was in his want<lb/> of education. Some of his notions were<lb/> good and to the
                extent that I can I<lb/> will carry them out, as I have done<lb/> thus far. I
                presume I may not be able<lb/> to leave here before <date>July</date> next, and<lb/>
                his positive and respected instructions<lb/> to different persons, were that after
                his<lb/> death everything relating to all the<lb/> last offices to be performed
                should<lb/> be directed and attended to by me<lb/> in person, I shall detain
                his<lb/> remains until I am read to start<lb/> from here, and until then I
                shall<lb/> make no final arrangements for<lb/> his burial in <placeName>New
                    Port</placeName>. In accordance<lb/> with his dislike to ostentatious
                funer<lb/>als, the interment here was attended<lb/> only by those who chose to come
                without<lb/> the slightest invitation. The children of<lb/> three Christian orphans
                asylums</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>26</p>
            <p>followed the hearse and the Firemens<lb/> Charitable Association, the veterans<lb/>
                of 14 &amp; 15 also attended. The hearse I ordered<lb/> to be perfectly plain—one
                horse. The<lb/> coffin—metal covered with black cloth. <persName>Genl.<lb/>
                    Plafrey</persName> desired to call out the military<lb/> but we
                    <sic>prefered</sic> to have no display<lb/> and particularly no music,
                nevertheless<lb/> the number of citizens was immense<lb/> and a general gloom was
                evident<lb/> The stores on the same square where<lb/> he resided were closed. Beyond
                the<lb/> spontaneous actions of the citizens, it<lb/> was an ordinary Jewish funeral
                with<lb/> the exception that I had those large<lb/> doors of the Synagogue opened
                while<lb/> the funeral passed.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">He had been unconscious for some<lb/> days before he died. When he
                died<lb/> (<persName>Gutheim</persName>) the minister the Doctor the Shamas<lb/> and
                myself were with him, and until<lb/> the last breath we repeated together the<lb/>
                usual verses. I closed his eyes—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Now <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> I have made up my mind<lb/> to
                one thing and that is to conduct the<lb/> affair at <placeName>New Port</placeName>,
                    <del>as</del> similarly to what<lb/> I did here—the only thing that may<lb/>
                induce me to <del>alt</del> deviate will be in<lb/> case the public civil
                authorities of that</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">27</p>
            <p>city or <placeName>Boston</placeName>, should wish to make<lb/> any demonstrations of
                respect, then<lb/> I shall feel it a duty to forego all<lb/> private considerations
                for the object<lb/> of bringing credit to <placeName>Israel</placeName> in the
                world.<lb/> Do not misunderstand me, I have no<lb/> idea of the remains leaving my
                or other<lb/> Jewish hands, it must be a Jewish funeral<lb/> and nothing else, but
                perhaps I might have<lb/> a service in the synagogue.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I shall see that you take some part in<lb/> the ceremonies, if any
                take place, but I<lb/> shall only study the general good effect<lb/> to be produced,
                in selecting ministers to<lb/> officiate on the occasion. Individual<lb/>
                preferences, nay the most friendly attach<lb/>ments must not be regarded, when
                an<lb/> opportunity offers to elevate the nation<lb/> in the eye of those who
                surround us—<lb/> you know we have always dispensed<lb/> with the Hakaforth here in
                    <placeName>New Orleans</placeName><lb/> and as it is only a minhag I should
                like<lb/> to omit it in <placeName>New Port</placeName> if possible. The<lb/> more
                quiet and the less <hi rend="underline">singing</hi> at a funeral<lb/> the more
                imposing it will ever be. Many<lb/> congregations &amp; societies have offered their
                services<lb/> in which those of the Hazans have been<lb/> included. On this occasion
                I shall not<lb/> study or regard official offers, to interfere</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>28</p>
            <p>with the great object in view. I know<lb/> some will claim preferences because
                they<lb/> are Portuguese or are in the Will or<lb/> any other special plea. Some
                may<lb/> say you are no longer a Minister. I shall<lb/> only strive to serve the
                common cause<lb/> and care little for the pleasure or displeasure<lb/> of any but
                such as can understand<lb/> my own feelings. I shall probably<lb/> inform the Jewish
                public through the<lb/> Occident, as to the time &amp;c of the interment.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You may depend I have no leisure<lb/> time. You can not imagine the
                disgusting<lb/> communications that come to shepherd<lb/> from some of our
                societies, giving recitals<lb/> of congregational differences jealousies &amp;c.
                I<lb/> have to blush frequently, and try to put<lb/> the best face on it. The main
                labor now<lb/> devolves on me, and I am Repl<add>?</add> hard<lb/> at work all
                day!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Oh my dear friend if you knew how I<lb/> had to work to get that
                Will made, and how<lb/> I strive to serve you, you would pity me. Alas<lb/> it was
                not altogether what I wanted yet I am<lb/> thankful to God that ever if I injured
                myself<lb/> I got the most of what I asked for
                <placeName>Israel</placeName>—<lb/>arguments, charges and counter-charges in<lb/>
                the sums of Institutions till my heart sickened<lb/> I appeared calm but indeed was
                almost crazy<lb/> ever dreading that nothing would be achieved in<lb/> the end. The
                list of Jewish Institutions I made up<lb/> as well as I could. I had dreadful hard
                work to raise<lb/> your Education Society from 10 to 20,000</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">yours truly</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">Gershom</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
