<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“One of them”</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSTCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item90</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“One of them”</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">R. I.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item90_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 6 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">1</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">To <del>the Editor</del>
                <addressee>R I</addressee> of the Asmonean.</p>
            <p>Sir</p>
            <p>an article which appeared in the Asmonean of the<lb/>
                <date>13<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> ins. under the head of “The Occident and the
                Asmonean”<lb/> challenges the animadonsion<add>?</add> not only of the friends
                of<lb/> the Revd Gentleman therein assailed, but also of all friends of<lb/>
                truth<lb/> justice &amp; the conventional decorum of society, all of which<lb/> in
                this article are violated.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This Sir, is a strong, and may seem<lb/> to you a harsh, &amp; rude
                assertion; but I assure you, that it is<lb/> not made in a wanton spirit of unkindly
                insult, nor with<lb/> a view to provoke in your bosom any angry or unpleasant
                feeling,<lb/> but is dictated solely by a sense of justice, to the object of
                your<lb/> unmerited abuse, and to that religious community of which you<lb/> assure
                to be a guide of shining light, whose dignity &amp; respectability<lb/> you have
                outraged by the contemptuous &amp; scornful language you have<lb/> held towards a
                man, who has <del>?</del> entitled himself to the<lb/> highest position in its
                regard, and whom is his delighted to honour with<lb/> its esteem &amp;
                reverence;</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I feel assured this if you, will review the<lb/> article in a calmer
                frame of mind than that <add>?</add> which it was<lb/> penned, you will yourself
                feel ashamed of the grossness of tone,<lb/> and unworthy jealousy, with which you
                there endeavor to cast<lb/> obloquy upon a man, whom your peevish susceptibilities
                have<lb/> conjured into an enemy, and your jealous fancies converted into a
                rival;</p>
            <p>What think you of the first sentence? “We (<persName>RI.</persName>) Do not usually
                bandy”<lb/> “words with a man of whom we have ceased to think except with
                commiseration”</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>2</p>
            <p>abstract yourself (if self love will allow) for a moment, from your own<lb/>
                individuality, be for an instant not (<persName>R I</persName>) but one of the
                    <del>mass</del> herd.<lb/> of the nameless—now consider who it is, who this
                ceased to be aught<lb/> but the object of commiseration to <persName>R I</persName>.
                Why truly it is he, who<lb/> selected by one of the most ancient &amp; respectable
                of the<lb/> American congregations as their religious guide &amp; instructor,<lb/>
                at an age, when others have scarcely ceased from the frivolities of<lb/> boyhood,
                gave instant proofs of piety &amp; ability, which not only seemed<lb/> for him the
                esteem of his flock but earned him an honored &amp; venerated<lb/> name throughout
                    <placeName>America</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Europe</placeName>;
                    <sic>It</sic> is he, who when others<lb/> were droning through their
                    hebdomadal<add>?</add> duties, in the lifeless and<lb/> monotonous forms of the
                synagogue, had the energy, zeal, and talent<lb/> to take the lead of all others in
                    <placeName>America</placeName>, in the introduction of sermons<lb/> as a regular
                portion of the service, for the purpose of imparting to his flock<lb/> religious
                instruction, and of infusing a living and breathing spirit of piety<lb/> into the
                religious torpor that <sic>prevaded</sic>, and his merits are not less in this,<lb/>
                that his sermons thus preached, <del>were</del> published at great cost &amp;
                pecuniary risk<lb/> by his own unaided exertions, and diffused to stimulate the
                slumbering piety<lb/> of distant congregations, furnished an example, slowly
                followed at first, and<lb/> at long &amp; wide intervals, until (to use the
                expressions of those who on a<lb/> late festival occasion, <sic>commemmorated</sic>
                in your pages, alluded to the practice,<lb/> tho oblivious of his claims of
                precedence.) it has become a “sine que non”<lb/> of synagogue requirement.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is he whose midnight labors, illuminated<lb/> by the pious zeal
                which urged him on the path of usefulness, in disregard<lb/> of personal pain or
                privation, prepared for his coreligionists, suitable and<lb/> correct translations,
                of the forms of prayer used by both minhags for the<lb/> service throughout the
                year, freed from the grammatical inaccuracies and</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3</p>
            <p>Barbarous and inelegant phraseology which disfigured those previously<lb/> in use.
                Furthermore sir it is he whose capacious intellect and untiring<lb/> enterprize,
                conceived <hi rend="underline">the</hi> idea of establishing a periodical
                devoted<lb/> to Jewish advancement social &amp; religious; &amp; unaided, achieved
                it.<lb/> It certainly does not argue favorably for the Jewish zeal, religious<lb/>
                sincerity, or intellectual qualifications of <del>the man</del> one, who can
                boast<lb/> “that he has had no opportunity properly to appreciate” such a man;<lb/>
                but let us as gently as we may, examine the pretensions of <persName>R.
                    I.</persName> who<lb/> “has ceased to think of such a man with any other feeling
                than commiseration,”<lb/>
                <persName>RI</persName> has but recently assumed a prominent position, as the Editor
                of a religious<lb/> print, ostensibly devoted to the diffusion of religious truth
                &amp; knowledge; and<lb/> under the banner of the <sic>maccabees</sic>, stands
                forth, the champion of Jewish<lb/> fame &amp; Jewish right. It would be hardly fair,
                from the short<lb/> experience the public have had of the ability with which he
                sustains<lb/> the character, to pass a definite opinion of his merits; I
                confess<lb/> that viewing his literary efforts as likely, if not of themselves,
                yet<lb/> by stimulating them, to promote Jewish progress, in faith &amp;
                knowledge;<lb/> I have been disposed to approve them; and have been willing to
                admire and<lb/> cheer the Banner of the Maccabees as it flaunted its folds in the
                air,<lb/> altho' I could not believe the staff upborne<add>?</add> by a
                    <persName>Sampson</persName>.<lb/> But it is quite fair to impugn, the acrimony,
                the insolence, the<lb/> jealousy (<hi rend="underline">all evil passions</hi>) which
                the editor of a professedly religious<lb/> paper exhibits in an attack against the
                personal character <del>&amp; public</del><lb/>
                <del>utility</del> of any individual; how much more, when against one whose<lb/>
                fame &amp; honor should be cherished by every Jew, and by those of<lb/>
                <placeName>America</placeName>, regarded as a subject of national pride!</p>
            <p><persName>R. I</persName> “derides arrogance, chastens insolence and rebuts
                falsehood”<lb/> did it not occur to him when framing his attack, that</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p
                rend="The bottom of the previous page is overlapping the top of the page in this scan, obscuring some words."/>
            <p><add>?</add> in his bosom? and that like<del>ly</del> an <sic>unskilful</sic>
                engineer<lb/> he might be crushed by the recoil of his own gun?<lb/> let him read
                the passage and ask himself, if he ever penned any<lb/> thing more arrogant,
                insolent &amp; false—<del>and when he shall have</del><lb/> than this contemptuous
                derogation &amp; denunciation of the merit<lb/> of a rival Editor, whose position is
                as eminent, as his own, has<lb/> hitherto been obscure,—</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I do not desire to pursue the subject<lb/> further, and in taking
                leave of <persName>Mr. I.</persName> I again repeat, that<lb/> it is no unkind or
                hostile feeling that I have written.<lb/> If from the nature of the subject and if
                necessitate <add>?</add>, I have<lb/> been forced to use harsh &amp; ungentle
                expressions <del>it has bee</del><lb/> my feelings have been those of the surgeon,
                who cuts but<lb/> to cure, and whose heart feels pain, while his patient bleeds.</p>
            <p>I am sir with the best wishes for Jewish progress</p>
            <p rend="indent(4)"><persName role="author">One of them</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
