<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">M. R. M.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item74</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk">M. R. M.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item74_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>8 pages on 8 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">The American Crisis.  No. 4</p>
				<p rend="align(center)"><hi rend="underline">Concluding Reflections.</hi></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Talmud gives us strong peculiar oriental<lb/> expressions touching the importance of civil<lb/> government and the obligation resting on every<lb/> man to support the government of the coun&#45;<lb/>try&#44; when it says&#44; &#8220;Just as the fish which are<lb/> in the sea&#44; every one greater than its companion<lb/> devours its comparison&#44; so the sons of man&#44; if there<lb/> were not the fear of the government&#44; every one<lb/> greater than his companion would devour his<lb/> companion&#58; and this is what <persName>R. Chanania</persName>&#44; dep&#61;<lb/>uty of priests&#44; has taught&#44; saying&#44; Pray for the<lb/> peace of the government&#44; because if there were not<lb/> the fear of the government&#44; every man would<lb/> devour his neighbor alive.&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">If we would fairly examine how the<lb/> Federal Government of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> fulfills the<lb/> highest purposes of civil government&#44; what are the<lb/> rights which it guaranties to all its citizens&#44; how<lb/> much it deserves the support of all citizens and<lb/> how prayer ought to be made for it&#44; we must<lb/> take the Declaration of Independence and the<lb/> Constitution together as two inseparable parts<lb/> of the one political structure.  The Declaration is<lb/> the foundation&#44; it clears the ground&#44; and the<lb/> Constitution is the frame&#44; the edifice&#44; that has been<lb/> erected over this ground.  These two documents<lb/> must be placed together&#44; the Declaration below<lb/> and the Constitution close above it&#44; to obtain</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>the true picture of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> government.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Here now is the <hi rend="underline">people&#39;s</hi> government.<lb/>  This must be the first impression as we<lb/> survey the Declaration and Constitution&#44; that<lb/> the Federal government has been called into ex<lb/>istence by the voice of the people.  It was not<lb/> the State Legislatures that made this government&#44;<lb/> but the people of all the States made it.  Each<lb/> State government rests on the shoulders of the<lb/> people&#59; and it is just as true that the Federal<lb/> government rests on the shoulders of the people<lb/> so that it can say to the most humble citizen&#44;<lb/> I am your government&#44; depending on your<lb/> vote just as much as your own State gov<lb/>ernment is yours.  It has been asserted that<lb/> when the Americans cut themselves loose from<lb/> the British government they traveled back on<lb/> a path which had never been so trodden before in all the Christian Era&#59;<lb/> they did not stop at the Colonial government<lb/> or the State government but they traveled back<lb/> to the people themselves as the original source<lb/> of all power in government.  It was the act of<lb/> the people to dissolve the bonds which had con<lb/>nected them with the mother country.  The princi<lb/>ples of the Declaration are that government is or<lb/>ganized for the people to secure them the rights<lb/> of life liberty and the pursuit of happiness&#59;<lb/> that when it fails to serve the people they have<lb/> the right to dissolve it&#59; that laws derive their<lb/> authority from the consent of the governed&#59; and<lb/> that as the people make the government in their<lb/> own name and for their own rights they hold</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>it accountable to themselves.  The Constitution<lb/> utters its first words in the name of the people<lb/> and in the first person&#58; it does not begin&#44;<lb/> We the States of <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>&#44; <placeName>Massachu<lb/>setts</placeName>&#44; <placeName>Va.</placeName> but its beginning is &#8220;We&#44; the<lb/> People of the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8221;&#8212;for such and<lb/> such purposes&#8212;&#8220;do ordain and establish<lb/> this Constitution for the <placeName>United States of<lb/> America</placeName>.&#8221;  It leaves organized power to one<lb/> side and travels back to natural right&#58; it leaves<lb/> State government to one side and travels back<lb/> to the people as the original source of all gov<lb/>ernment whether State or Federal.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">All this being true&#44; still it is not the gov<lb/>ernment of a people who are atheists.  The<lb/> people most distinctly acknowledge their own<lb/> responsibility to God.  In the act of demolishing<lb/> their government they acknowledge themselves<lb/> responsible to God and not to man for this<lb/> act.  They speak of those unalienable rights<lb/> with which their Creator has endowed them.<lb/>  They place themselves on that platform of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> independence to which they say &#8220;the laws of<lb/> nature and of nature&#39;s God&#8221; give them a<lb/> title.  When they declare themselves separated from<lb/> all the authority of the British King they appeal<lb/> to the Supreme Judge of the world for the<lb/> rectitude of their cause.  The radical theory of<lb/> the American government is&#44; <hi rend="underline">The government</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">responsible to the people</hi>&#44; <hi rend="underline">and the people</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">responsible to God</hi>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is a government consisting of the three</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>essential departments&#44; the legislative&#44; the<lb/> executive and the judicial&#58; each of these<lb/> departments has its own separate place&#44; yet<lb/> like the prismatic colours of the rainbow they<lb/> flow together so that no line can perfectly<lb/> separate the edges.  In the legislative department<lb/> the lower house is elected for two years&#44; the upper<lb/> house or Senate for six years&#44; the Executive<lb/> is elected for an intermediate period&#44; four<lb/> years&#59; the Judges are appointed for life.  Each<lb/> department reaches over into the others.  The Ju<lb/>diciary can declare laws of Congress unconstitu<lb/>tional and void&#44; the legislature possesses and<lb/> occasionally exercises both judicial and executive<lb/> powers&#44; and the Executive has at all times a<lb/> qualified negative upon legislation and a<lb/> judicial power of remission.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is a government which deserves to<lb/> be considered one of the grandest institutions<lb/> for the peace of the world.  Here were thirty&#45;<lb/>four States&#44; and&#44; if Secession is not ac<lb/>knowledged&#44; here are still thirty&#45;four States&#44;<lb/> thirty&#45;four Republics&#44; each one delivering up<lb/> its sword to the one Federal central govern<lb/>ment&#44; and this general government does not<lb/> spring from the States as such&#44; but from<lb/> the people of the States.  No one of these<lb/> States can make war with another or with<lb/> a foreign nation&#44; or can enter into any treaty<lb/> among themselves or any treaty with foreigners&#44;<lb/> without breaking the Federal constitution.  What<lb/> a diminution of the chances of war&#33;  What a<lb/> security for the peace of <placeName>America</placeName>&#33;</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is a government one of the elements<lb/> of the strength of which is the religious sacredness<lb/> of the oath.  It is not without religion inas<lb/>much as it is not without the oath.  The<lb/> Senators and Representations&#44; and the members<lb/> of the several State Legislatures&#44; and all execu<lb/>tive and judicial officers&#44; both of the <placeName>United<lb/> States</placeName> and of the several States&#44; must be<lb/> bound by oath or affirmation to support<lb/> the Federal Constitution.  It binds the consci<lb/>ences of all these functionaries to loyalty.  It<lb/> admits occasionally an affirmation in the place<lb/> of an oath&#44; so that Quakers may not be<lb/> excluded.  But while it thus religiously binds<lb/> by the oath&#44; it allows no religious test ever<lb/> to be required as a qualification to any office<lb/> or public trust under the <placeName>United States</placeName>.  It has no par<lb/>ticular favors for either Jew or Catholic or<lb/> Protestant or Deist.  It gives to the professors<lb/> of different religions an equal chance to<lb/> spread spiritual blessings over the world.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The principles which underlie its<lb/> relation to slavery appear to be these&#59; first&#44;<lb/> that slavery is not a sin in itself&#44; and&#44; secondly&#44;<lb/> that it is decidedly better that slavery be not<lb/> recognized in the Federal Constitution as a<lb/> beneficent institution.  The treatment of slavery<lb/> in the Constitution embraces the following terms<add>&#63;</add>&#59;<lb/> first&#44; in the slave States the population which<lb/> is the basis of representation in Congress must<lb/> embrace three fifths of the slaves&#59; this slave ele</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>ment in the population has at times given as<lb/> many as twenty&#45;five men their seats in Congress&#59;<lb/> secondly&#44; the importation of slaves into slave&#45;<lb/>holding States was not to be prohibited prior<lb/> to the year <date>1808</date>&#59; and&#44; thirdly&#44; slaves fleeing<lb/> from one State to another&#44; are not in any<lb/> State free from the claim of their masters.<lb/>  The Constitution thus favors the Slave States<lb/> and gives no countenance to the idea that to<lb/> hold a slave is essentially a sin&#44; but at the<lb/> same time it is very careful to avoid every<lb/> mention of slavery or of slave.  The framers<lb/> of the Constitution evidently felt that slavery<lb/> could not be a good word to have in the<lb/> Constitution.  We must find slavery in one place<lb/> immediately after the mention of Indians&#44; in the<lb/> language&#44; &#8220;three fifths of all other persons&#59;&#8221; or<lb/> we must find it in another place&#44; in the<lb/> language&#44; &#8220;The migration or importation of<lb/> such persons&#44; as any of the States&#44; now ex<lb/>isting&#44; may think proper to admit&#59;&#8221; or we<lb/> must find it in another place&#44; in the language&#44;<lb/> &#8220;No person held to service or labor in one State<lb/> under the laws thereof&#44; escaping into another&#44; shall&#44;<lb/> in consequence of any law or regulation therein&#44;<lb/> be discharged from such service or labor&#44; but shall<lb/> be delivered up on claim of the party to whom<lb/> such service or labor may be due&#8221;&#44; or we can<lb/> find it in any place in all the length and<lb/> breadth of the Constitution&#59; and in each of these<lb/> places the Constitution uses the term <hi rend="underline">persons</hi>&#44; and<lb/> is most careful never to introduce the term slaves.</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p>The framers of the Constitution were most careful<lb/> that all the recognition of slavery in the Con<lb/>stitution should be a mere tacit recognition.<lb/>  It is a Constitution which most quietly secures<lb/> slave States their rights&#44; and most cordially<lb/> gives universal freedom every chance in other<lb/> States&#58; it is the only Constitution for the union<lb/> and peaceful development of both slave and<lb/> free States.  With one arm it checks the extreme<lb/> of Anti&#45;slavery&#44; with the other arm the extreme<lb/> of Pro&#45;slavery&#44; and it chooses its own ground<lb/> between.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">And now after all that has just been said<lb/> on the Federal Government as being the people&#39;s<lb/> government&#44; called into existence by the people and<lb/> for the people and accountable to the people&#59; as a<lb/> government acknowledging the immediate responsibility<lb/> of the people to God&#59; <del>for their governments</del> as a grand<lb/> adjustment of the three powers the legislative the<lb/> executive and the judicial&#59; as a stupendous republican<lb/> wheel with thirty&#45;four republics within it&#44; each<lb/> of these republics being a wheel moving freely<lb/> within the great wheel&#59; as one great rainbow of<lb/> peace spanning the heavens from ocean to ocean from<lb/> the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> to the <placeName>Pacific</placeName>&#59; as giving every man his<lb/> own vine and fig&#45;tree where he with his neighbors may<lb/> worship God as conscience dictates and discuss their<lb/> rights with perfect liberty&#59; and as a safe bond of<lb/> perpetual union between both slave and free States&#44;<lb/> favoring on the one hand the right of all men to<lb/> life liberty and the pursuit of happiness and securing<lb/> to slavery on the other hand its right to life and</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>its representation in Congress as long as any<lb/> State wants it to live&#59; we have only one thing<lb/> to say in addition.  Let the hand that would destroy this union first give good evidence that it<lb/> is able to construct a better Union&#33;  Let the hand<lb/> that would dare to cut down the flag of the stars<lb/> and stripes&#44; be sure that there is some better flag<lb/> ready to ascend&#33;</p>
			<p rend="indent(12)"><persName role="author">M. R. M.</persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
