<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item201</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">De Sola, Abraham</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Joseph, J. H.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1851-02" source="" attested="yes">26 February 1851</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item201_wk1_body0012.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>11 pages on 12 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><addressee>J H Joseph Esqr.</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Dear Sir&#33;</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">Many thanks for <persName>Mr Leeser&#39;s</persName> letter which I read with every<lb/> feeling but of pleasure.  I shall make no apology to trouble you with a further communication&#8212;perhaps<lb/> a long one on this same subject&#44; as I desire you should know all particulars&#44; and I honestly tell you<lb/> that not only have I no objection that you should inform <persName>Mr L</persName> what I say in reply to his last to you<lb/> but I am quite content he should read every word following.  This letter may be seen by one or by a thousand<lb/> I care not&#44; for every one may know that I have&#44; and am again ready to aver in the most solemn manner&#44; yes&#44;<lb/> in the name of God who made me&#44; that I never sought to injure <persName>Mr L</persName> with his congregation&#8212;that to the best of my<lb/> judgment I never did or said anything to lessen his success &#38; promote my own&#8212;that I never had any desire to supplant<lb/> him in his situation whilst I thought he stood the least chance of retaining it&#8212;that it was only with others<lb/> I desired to contest it&#44; and that throughout I entertained for him none but sentiments of kindness &#38; sympathy&#8212;<lb/> how I would not &#38; could not write or say this much for a brother or a father did I trust know it was truth&#8212;I flatter<lb/> myself I need not assure you of this.  I do not say that a more <hi rend="underline">experienced</hi> person would not have acted differently<lb/> but I do not truthfully say that none could have acted with more honesty of purpose&#44; and under the former im&#45;<lb/>pressions that after the protracted &#38; serious dissensions between <persName>Mr L</persName> &#38; his congr. I could do him no injury to<lb/> act as I did.  These are protestations&#44; say&#44; but took at the facts.</p>
				<p>As you know I have been in correspondence with <persName>Mr L</persName> since my arrival in this country <date>Jany. &#39;47</date>.  I need not look<lb/> back to <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> earlier letters but it is now some 18 months since he told me he was not popular &#40;generally with<lb/> his flock &#38; that his re&#45;election was by no means sure.  The publication of his strictures on his cong. in the Oc. <date>October 49</date><lb/> the action taken by them thereupon certainly would not be calculated to Open the breach.  In a lengthy letter from<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> dated <date>Oct 49</date> I have the full history of his Ministry in <placeName>Phil.</placeName> To that date.  In this letter <persName>Mr L</persName> speaks of the unmerited<lb/> &#38; powerful persecution he had experienced from his opponents&#8212;of the impossibility of getting two thirds of the<lb/> votes necessary for the <hi rend="underline">repeal of the bond law</hi>&#8212;under which condition only&#44; <persName>Mr L</persName> writes as indeed he had publicly<lb/> printed in the Oc. he would take office.  &#8220;As I will not sign a contract such as was offered there is only the<lb/> alternative of <hi rend="underline">withdrawing fighting to the last</hi>.&#8221;  Again&#44; he says he cannot &#38; will not yield one point&#44; &#38; scorns<lb/> the <sic>adjunta&#39;s</sic> vote of censure.  It is unnecessary to quote other paragraphs from this letter expressive of the same<lb/> determination.  Thus already some 15 months ago <persName>Mr L</persName> spared me of his determining not to yield to the congre&#45;<lb/>gational terms&#44; and so long ago had Is<add>&#63;</add> all the world learnt through the Oc. That the congn. had determined not to<lb/> yield to <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> demands&#8212;witness the rejection by them of the new bye&#45;law for Hazan&#44; offered by <persName>Mr S Solis</persName>&#44; and<lb/> the motion to do away with the bond&#44; which latter motion they had uniformly rejected on all other occasions<lb/> &#38; by large majorities&#44; as I learn from <persName>Mr C&#39;s</persName> letters.  On <date>16 Octr.</date>&#44; my earliest leisure&#44; in reply to <persName>Mr I.</persName> I took the liberty<lb/> to censure the article in the <date>Octr</date> Occident&#44; plainly telling him that I thought he had done exceedingly wrong to hold all<lb/> his cong. to the severe<add>&#63;</add> ridicule of the world&#8212;that he had thereby laid himself under the imputation of attempting<lb/> to gain by threats what he could not by persuasion &#38; argument or influence &#40;This was not the language of one desiring him Evil&#41;<lb/> And with respect to the bond I said that all with whom I had discussed the matter agreed that in <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> case he being<lb/> known to them 20 years&#44; that it was uncalled for &#38; wrong though in the case of a stranger &#40;or newcomer&#41; the cong would<lb/> be justified to ask it&#44; though even there the candidates simply subscribing a declaration of willingness to be governed<lb/> by existing by&#45;laws would be preferable.  I have referred to this circumstance at length because when in <placeName>Phil.</placeName> I was<lb/> told I believe &#40;but am not sure&#41; by <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> but it matters not <hi rend="underline">by</hi> whom that he had heard &#40;from whom he did not say&#41; that I had written <persName>Mr L</persName> advising him not to sign the<lb/> bond it being beneath the dignity of a minister so to do &#40;so as to get him out of the way I suppose&#33;&#41; but when I had sense<add>&#63;</add> of <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> absence from candidateship hereby I<lb/> turned round and was willing to do it myself.  A very pretty charge to do me injury&#44; but false as Christianity.  A concoction<lb/> worthy the most rascally Jesuit around us.  I am glad to know however that it did not&#59; or could not&#44; injure me<lb/> with so right&#45;minded a person as <persName>Mr Solis</persName> to whom I know I explained the matter though cannot be sure whether<lb/> I broached it to him.  The truth is as above.  But a little more about this <add>&#63;</add>.  I never said I would sign the<lb/> bond.  If elected I would ask to be excused as I do not admire it&#8212;but would not refuse signing if the retention<lb/> of the place depended upon it &#40;<del>mind</del> I speak of myself as a new comer&#41; for I would not have the power of it<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> <hi rend="underline">now</hi> has.  If I signed it I should be doing nothing worse than <persName>Mr L</persName> had himself done on several occasions.<lb/>  The bond I maintain degrades the congregation not the minister.  There are many abuses in one synagogue government<lb/> which a Hazan must at present submit to.  What if a Parnass <hi rend="underline">orders</hi> a Hazan to call up to read to the Sepher a<lb/> man notoriously <add>&#63;</add>.  Could <persName>Mr L</persName> or any other Hazan refuse&#8212;he might get off doing so by his influence over<lb/> the Parnass.  I could point out to you many cases wherein <persName>Mr L</persName> according to the present system must<lb/> submit to his <hi rend="underline">rulers</hi> in matters of much greater importance than signing the bond and I could show you</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>that he has done so.  This does not say that we should not agitate by mouth &#38; pen to destroy these abuses.  I believe<lb/> from my little experience that a Minister would by affectionate remonstrance&#44; &#38; reasoning would soon &#40;had he even a<lb/> little more influence than a stick&#41; induce his flock to do away with so useless to say the least of it&#44; a by&#45;law<lb/> And I say further that it appears to me many would in <placeName>Phil</placeName> be willing to do away with the law but not<lb/> for <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>.  Perhaps the new incumbent might get them not to ask him.  <persName>Mr L</persName> was not asked I believe for the first<lb/> few years&#8212;he says because his enemies wished to serve their own purpose.  But to continue with my letter<lb/> In conclusion I advise <persName>Mr L</persName> to take special care what he did &#38; above all not to write anything in his Oc. about<lb/> his cong. something as absurd the idea that he should put with them because of this bond business when in &#39;41 &#40;I believe&#41;<lb/> the same thing occurred as you are perhaps aware and <persName>Mr L</persName> <del>signed</del> contrived by a <hi rend="underline">ruse</hi> which he afterwards regretted&#44; to satisfy<lb/> them.  In this letter I also offered to confer with you on the matter for <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> benefit&#44; not doubting you would do all you<lb/> could in his behalf &#38; asked him permission to do so.  On <date>3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Dec</date> <persName>Mr L</persName> sends me copy of intended by law tells me your interference<lb/> would be useless&#44; &#38; that any would be unpalatable to him.  On <date>March 27&#44; 1850</date>&#44; <persName>Mr L</persName> writes me &#8220;the die is at length<lb/> cast &#38; the congregation have resolved to advertise for a successor&#44; after having endorsed the vote of censure of the Adjunta<lb/> &#38; refusing to repeal the bond law&#8212;appointing salary &#38; term of office for the successor.  &#40;<persName>Mr L</persName> does not write me he wanted<lb/> a life term of office&#41; on hearing of this fatal &#38; decisive step I wrote <persName>Mr L</persName> &#40;<date>9 April 1850</date>&#41; expressing my surprise<lb/> &#38; regret at this intelligence&#44; stating candidly however that I did not think this determination was come to by<lb/> the congregation because of the bond &#38;c but because &#8220;their spirit was not with him&#8221; i. e. that they did not care for him<lb/> and I as candidly intimated &#40;also by a Hebrew <add>&#63;</add>&#41; that the breach was past healing&#44; but to prove my esteem<lb/> I would&#44; <hi rend="underline">did he concur</hi>&#44; get up a memorial &#40;with <persName>Rev S M Isaacs</persName>&#41; to be signed by the Jewish ministry generally<lb/> in his favor&#44; I also asked him to point out to me how I could be of use to him.  This letter brings up our corres&#45;<lb/>pondence on this subject to about 2 months before the day appointed for election &#40;viz <date>16. June</date>&#41; And here let me ask you<lb/> whether it is strange I should begin to think that <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> chance of reconciliation or reelection was becoming<lb/> more &#38; more desperate &#40;If I mistake not you were of opinion that <persName>Mr L</persName> would not have the least chance after his<lb/> article in <date>October</date> Occident&#41; when in almost every letter for about 2 years he had told me so himself&#33;  Is it strange<lb/> I should entertain this idea when he more than once had told me the power of his enemies was too great to allow<lb/> him to suppose he would ever gain the 2&#47;3rds he required to carry his measures&#44; when he had informed the public that<lb/> he would not take the place but on his own terms&#44; &#38; when they had also assured the public through the press<lb/> that he should not have it but on theirs &#38; by asking for others to fill the office &#40;in their advertisement&#41; showed that they cared not for<lb/> him to remain&#8212;when I knew he must either disgrace himself by giving the lie to his public &#38; private protestations<lb/> or stoop to the congregation &#40;&#38; I had too high an opinion of his honesty to suppose he would do either&#41; and when<lb/> I could not but know that the cong would not yield to him&#44; as they had always &#38; uniformly upheld the bond<lb/> and when I viewed in conjunction with all this the continually increasing bad feeling between <persName>Mr L</persName> &#38; his flock<lb/> his strictures&#44; their votes of censure &#38; determined opposition the former not trifles to a man of spirit&#44; was I<lb/> so wrong in thinking <persName>Mr L</persName> stood little or no chance of again occupying his old position.  And could I desire his<lb/> injury let me also ask when I strongly advised him not to make the press the vehicle for his complaints<lb/> to be careful that he gave his enemies no farther advantage over him by losing temper &#38;c.  Thus far I think even<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit that I have acted aright &#38; that my conclusions were by no means unnatural.  To return On<lb/> <date>22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> April</date> I received <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> reply dated <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date>.  He would permit my combining with <persName>Isaacs</persName> &#38;c for the memorial &#8220;but<lb/> he knew it would be of no avail the influence on the other side being too great.&#8221;  On the <date>23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi></date> the day I received <persName>Mr<lb/> L&#39;s</persName> letter I addressed <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> stating the case &#38; my conviction that &#8220;a respectfully worded memorial&#8221; I quote from my<lb/> letter to <persName>Mr I.</persName> &#8220;to be written by you &#38; signed by all of us&#8221; would do good&#44; inviting him to take the initiative thinking<lb/> that both from age character &#38; influence he and not I was the man&#44; &#38; because he was <del>more</del> intimate with more<lb/> ministers than I.  I received <persName>Mr I&#39;s</persName> reply dated <date>26 April</date>.  I omitted to state that <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> in his letter of <date>10</date> <add>&#63;</add> me<lb/> that <add>&#63;</add> I had already offered his services as mediator which he declined as useless but made no objection to a<lb/> combined action.  <persName>Mr I</persName> however in this letter stated that it would now be perfectly useless.  He writes<lb/> &#8220;I would gladly co&#45;operate could <del>I</del> we achieve any good but knowing that none can be effected our time is<lb/> too valuable &#38;c&#8221; Does this answer <persName>Mr Leeser&#39;s</persName> charge that instead of attempting to make peace I was getting<lb/> up certificates&#8221; I have asked for no certificates up to this date.  After such dampers from <persName>Messrs Leeser</persName> &#38; <persName>Isaacs</persName><lb/> I thought it useless to persevere&#44; and am of opinion now that I thought rightly.  The same post that brought<lb/> me <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> letter brought me several communication from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#44; informing me among other things<lb/> that <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> had publicly stated I was the only person competent to succeed him &#40;In my ignorance I thought&#44;<lb/> that <persName>Mr L</persName> not being willing longer to remain&#44; was believed the curtain <del>doing all he</del> recommending me&#41;&#8212;again<lb/> that a large portion of the members desired me to apply&#8212;that certain parties had declared themselves my suppor&#45;<lb/>ters&#44; and though there would be other candidates &#40;one was already however even if he had not applied viz <persName>Ellis Lyon</persName>&#41;<lb/> still &#8220;there was none on the continent of <placeName>America</placeName> to oppose me.&#8221;  <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> laughs at the idea of <persName>Mr Lyons</persName><lb/> standing any chance of success.  But I who have seen much  more important congregations than <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> choose a <add>&#63;</add> because he had a fine voice did not think <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> so laughable an opponent especially<lb/> as I heard he had family influence in <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#44; which my ignorance then exaggerated&#44; and I also know that his</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>brother whose influence through his congregation I thought might be great would also canvass for him.  A member of my<lb/> congregation also had received a letter from his friends in <placeName>Phil</placeName> stating the same things.  He showed me the letter I saw I<lb/> must apply without loss of time.  I communicated with all my friends here &#40;you &#38; <persName>Mrs Joseph</persName> were then<lb/> absent from <placeName>Montreal</placeName>&#44; and one &#38; all advised me as he had done&#8212;ridiculing any objections.  They said &#8220;<persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> <sic>cant</sic> be so unreasonable as to find fault with you &#40; I did not say that he would&#44; at me remark <hi rend="underline">en parenthese</hi>&#41;<lb/> for seeking for a situation he cannot &#38; will not longer hold.  To suppose that the congregation will yield to him<lb/> he not being generally liked and not being altogether in the <del>wrong</del> right&#44; is absurd.  <hi rend="underline">If the place had not been advertised</hi><lb/> &#38; you solicited to apply&#44; you might then hesitate.  But now&#44; hesitate&#44; &#38; others will not.&#8221;  Such was the language<lb/> of my friends both here &#38; elsewhere.  I confess it was not without its effect on me.  But what had greater effect on me was<lb/> <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> letter of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date> already referred to as that wherein he gives me leave to combine with <persName>Isaacs</persName> for the memorial.  He &#40;<persName>Mr L</persName>&#41;<lb/> commences by telling me that all my efforts would be useless in his behalf as far as his ministry is concerned&#44; he could<lb/> not <hi rend="underline">imagine the possibility of his being elected on terms agreeable to himself</hi> &#40;and yet&#44; let me here remark in his last<lb/> letter to you he says as much that I am the other candidates <del>were</del> the cause of his not being elected.  What had I staid<lb/> away&#8212;another would have come forward.  To suppose that none would &#40;who perhaps did not care one <add>&#63;</add> for <add>&#63;</add>&#41; is<lb/> childish &#38; absurd But before any one had any idea of coming forward <persName>Mr L</persName> plainly says he cannot imagine the possibility of his reelection on his terms.  This being the case <persName>Mr L</persName> waited he owed it to his character both as a man &#38; a Jew <hi rend="underline">to retire to</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">private life</hi>.  Again says <persName>Mr L.</persName> &#8220;<hi rend="underline">My engagement is precluded by the wording of the advertisement</hi>.&#8221;  Now my firm impression<lb/> from the forgoing was &#40;as it would have been I think of every <sic>imprejudiced</sic> person that <persName>Mr. L</persName> seeing he stood no<lb/> chance of success gave up the contest&#44; and that with the great encouragement held out to me&#44; and the persuasions of<lb/> my friends&#8212;honest thinking men too&#44; I was now fully justified in doing what I heard <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> &#38; others had already<lb/> done or was caring to do&#8212;and apply for the office&#8212;informing <persName>Mr L.</persName> thereof at the same time.  But I will tell you<lb/> what I did presently.  If I had any doubts as to the hopelessness of <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> cause the anonymous pamphlet which<lb/> <persName>Dr David</persName> and I received &#40;on <date>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date>&#41; would have dispelled them.  I would most assuredly&#44; not at all refer to this pamphlet but that<lb/> it contains extracts of the minutes of the Cong. the truthfulness of which none has challenged.  From these minutes I<lb/> learned what <persName>Mr L</persName> had never informed me&#8212;that in addition to the insurmountable obstacle of the bond&#44; there<lb/> were other difficulties equally insurmountable &#40;as the votes showed&#41;.  <persName>Mr L</persName> had declared at the meeting of <date>24 March&#47;50</date><lb/> through <persName>Mr A Hart</persName> that unless the tenure of office was during good behaviour &#40;for life&#41; <hi rend="underline">he would not be a candidate</hi>&#44; but<lb/> would remain 6 months after expiration of his present term to afford the cong. an opportunity to get a successor not<lb/> withstanding which <hi rend="underline">the cong settled the term at 10 years</hi>.  Now would I be wrong in concluding from this circumstance<lb/> what <persName>Mr L</persName> himself wrote me &#8220;It was evident to me&#44;&#8221; he says with reference to this meeting not this particular vote&#44;<lb/> that my dismissal from office was resolved on.  So I thought.  The particulars of the term of office discussion<lb/> I did not learn from <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>.  Now I could not think so ill of <persName>Mr L</persName> as to suppose that he would act contrary<lb/> to his declaration at the meeting &#38; accept 10 years&#44; nor did I think&#44; knowing that a large majority &#40;including some who did<lb/> not ever to insist upon the bond as I afterwards heard&#41; had determined <hi rend="underline">not to grant</hi> the life tenure&#44; such having<lb/> been the policy of the Kahal&#44; as I learn from the extracts of the minutes&#59; ever since they first had a regular Hazan<lb/> because as they assert &#40;<date>Nov&#47;42</date>&#41; &#8220;a frequent occurrence to the election of their officers is the best check upon them.&#8221;  I do<lb/> not desire to bear me the apologist of this assertion&#44; but that such is the opinion of the majority of the <placeName>Phil.</placeName> Cong. I <sic>dont</sic><lb/> this moment sincerely believe.  And in the very first letter received from <persName>Mr A Hart</persName> he informs me that in the event<lb/> of our <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> not being a candidate &#40;Let <persName>Mr L</persName> know that others besides me could use this expression&#41; on <date>16 June</date> they would<lb/> reduce the term of office probably to 3 years.  From all this I become convinced that <persName>Mr L</persName> stood not the least chance<lb/> of election &#40;especially as the cong would not&#44; as he wrote me&#44; &#8220;even hear him in his defence&#8221;&#41; I also thought I had a<lb/> chance of being chosen&#8212;and that if I did not apply other persons&#8212;whitewashed Germans&#8212;would&#44; leaving <persName>Lyons</persName><lb/> out of the question.  Events prove my conjecture right.  <persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> no doubt a learned &#38; estimable man&#8212;but still<lb/> as much a Portuguese Hazan as I am a German&#8212;has read as candidate in the synagogue Mikveh Israel &#40;so I hear.&#41; In his<lb/> letter of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date> I must not omit to state <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> told me he was then going &#40;in the course of the week&#41; to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and that it was &#8220;likely<lb/> enough that before my answer could reach him he would have left <placeName>Phila.</placeName>&#8221;  He said moreover he could not call at<lb/> <placeName>Montreal</placeName> as he had intended but would hasten to be back by the day of election.  On <date>23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> April</date> immediately on<lb/> receipt of <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> of <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> I addressed <persName>Mr L</persName> directing one letter to <placeName>Savannah</placeName> &#38; <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> &#40;he had supplied me on <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> with<lb/> these addresses&#41; <del>in care<persName> J I</persName> <add>&#63;</add> </del> as <persName>Mr L</persName> might have left <placeName>Phil</placeName> before he could receive my letter.  If you recollect<lb/> you sent me a slip of paper it came with the Oc. Whereon <persName>Mr L</persName> tells you he was not going yet&#44; <del>&#63;</del> for a few days.  I believe<lb/> then it was a couple of days&#8212;perhaps one&#8212;after I had written <persName>Mr L</persName> to <placeName>N. O.</placeName>&#8212;where you sent me the slip.  <del>&#63;</del> I then<lb/> wrote another letter to <placeName>Phil</placeName> thinking it might reach him before he left.  I don&#39;t know the date of this<lb/> as it contained pretty much what I wrote in the one to <placeName>N. O.</placeName>  I did not keep a copy of it.  Both letters were<lb/> written in the desire not to do anything without <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> knowledge&#44; &#38; so&#44; afterwards&#44; I would not have moved<lb/> a single step without his knowledge &#38; he might have guided me for his advantage&#44; but that&#8212;he would not.<lb/>  In these letters I told <persName>Mr L</persName> that I was convinced now that his connection with his congregation would be<lb/> at last severed.  In this case I had determined I told <persName>Mr L</persName> to <del>take</del> adopt the advice of my friends &#38; to write &#40;which<lb/> I did by the same post which took <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> letter&#41; to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> acquainting him with my desire to be<lb/> considered a candidate for the office <hi rend="underline">in case <persName>Mr L</persName> was not &#38; only in such case</hi>.  <persName>Mr L</persName> says in his last letter</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>to you that had I truly desired to <del>&#63;</del> consult him I should have written to no one &#40;not to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> <persName>Mr L</persName> means I<lb/> suppose&#41; before applying to him.  I never <del>&#63;</del> wished to consult <persName>Mr L</persName> as to the propriety of making a qualified application<lb/> The propriety of this step under the circumstances appeared to me to be too evident.  I had no doubt of its propriety<lb/> &#38; therefore did not ask <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; I only asked him to guide me aright <hi rend="underline">for his advantage</hi>&#44; not to tell me what<lb/> seems<add>&#63;</add> right honorable or religious to do.  Thank God&#44; I know my duty&#44; my eyes were opened not jaundiced.<lb/>  None of my friends had any doubts of the propriety of my conduct&#44; nor had any of the Jewish Ministry with<lb/> whom I correspond&#8212;<hi rend="underline">nay none has been expressed to me even by <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> himself either by pen or mouth</hi><lb/> This I shall now show.  The gentlemen I addressed for certificates a few days after I had written <persName>Mr L</persName> I was going <add>&#63;</add>&#44;<lb/> were <persName>Messrs Lyons</persName> <persName>Raphall</persName> &#38; <persName>Wise</persName>.  <persName>Isaacs</persName> I did not ask for any I believe&#44; through some inadvertence.  <persName>Mr Lyons</persName>&#44;<lb/> &#40;who in <add>&#63;</add> to <persName>Mr Isaacs</persName> I forgot to say I wrote to advise about <persName>Mr L</persName> &#38; his cong.&#41; wrote me that he desired<lb/> I would excuse his interest as he must devote it to his mother who had already bespoken it.  Now if he thought it<lb/> right in his brother to apply he could not think it wrong in me&#8212;and I have good reason else&#44; to know he did not.<lb/>  <persName>Dr Wise</persName> writes me a very complimentary letter &#38; would recommend me at <placeName>Phil</placeName> but says that his recommendation<lb/> would do <del>him</del> me more inquiry than good desired as he was as a heretic but adds <persName>Dr W.</persName> go to <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#44; let them<lb/> hear your intentions show them your abilities &#38; you will be elected&#8212;the best recommendation is your<lb/> own self.&#8221;  Subsequently <persName>Rev D. A De Sola</persName> &#40;as just and good a man as any of us&#41; approves highly my design<lb/> and bids me God speed.  <persName>Rev Ansel</persName> <add>&#63;</add> of <placeName>New York</placeName> most heartily wished me &#40;when in <placeName>N. Y</placeName>&#41; success.  <persName>Rev S M<lb/> Isaacs</persName> after waiting <add>&#63;</add> that &#8220;all we could &#38; might have done &#40;when we corresponded about the memorial&#41;.<lb/>  had been destroyed by the congregation pamphlet&#8221; adds &#8220;your intention to become a candidate <hi rend="underline">is <add>&#63;</add>dedly</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">correct</hi>&#8221; and after some characteristic kind remarks adds &#8220;let me at once assure you of my readiness to<lb/> serve you.  Your competition is I suppose <persName>Ellis Lyon</persName> &#38;c &#38;c.  <persName>Rev David Meldola</persName> chief Rabbi of the Portuguese<lb/> congregation&#44; <placeName>London</placeName> before and often he had written <persName>Mr L</persName> offering his services to make peace between him and<lb/> the congregation most earnestly wishes my success and earnestly &#38; affectionately advises me to do all<lb/> I can for myself.  I don&#39;t know whether <persName>Mr L</persName> may consider this quote compatible with the letters <persName>Mr Meldola</persName><lb/> wrote him.  I think it is.  He would like to see <persName>Mr L</persName> remain if possible &#38; so would I.  He does not think I<lb/> am wrong&#44; however&#44; in doing what I have done.  Nor do I.  His last letter to me on this subject was written <date>22nd<lb/> Novr.</date> last&#44; about the same time he addressed <persName>Mr L.</persName>  I should also state <persName>Mr Meldola</persName> has heard all particulars from <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/>  Here there were some of our most prominent &#38; respectable ministers opposing my application.  Surely <persName>Mr L</persName> will<lb/> not say they are all <persName>Baals</persName> prophets&#8212;he the only true one.  How they thought it would have injured <persName>Mr L</persName> they would<lb/> not have advised as they did.  They were quite aware of all attending circumstances.  <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> writes me<lb/> &#40;<date>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> May</date>&#41; he <sic>enclose</sic> a testimonial which he hopes&#44; will meet my views&#44; but can only offer one his influence in <placeName>Phil</placeName><lb/> in case <persName>Mr L</persName> declares his intention not to accept the place even if elected.  &#40;<persName>Dr R</persName> apparently was not then aware<lb/> that <persName>Mr L</persName> <hi rend="underline">had refused</hi> accepting office except under conditions frequently &#38; <add>&#63;</add> absolutely <add>&#63;</add>&#41; how declining<lb/> to use his influence in my behalf but under certain conditions&#8212;to which only the latter amounts.  &#40;The letter<lb/> I have&#44; &#38; is at <persName>Mr L</persName> service should he ever wish to see it&#8212;during this is not tantamount to &#8220;writing me<lb/> not to apply for <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> place&#8221; as <persName>Mr L</persName> says the Dr told him he did.  This letter is the only one I have heard of the<lb/> Dr since &#38; I will leave it to any one to decide whether it contains one word recommending me not to apply.<lb/>  Besides <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> could not have written to advise me not to do a thing he knew I &#40;perhaps others&#41; had already<lb/> done&#44; nor would he have supplied me with a testimonial the design of which as he well knew was to <add>&#63;</add> my views<lb/> in <placeName>Phil</placeName> as I wrote him in asking for it.  I did not see <persName>Dr A</persName> nor any one but a <add>&#63;</add> on arriving in <placeName>New York</placeName> from<lb/> <placeName>Montreal</placeName> since I went almost immediately from the boat to the cars&#44; but on my return to <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> I <add>&#63;</add> with the Dr<lb/> who said you know I would do much to serve you but you must not apply for <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> place &#40;This was after<lb/> I had been in <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#44; recollect&#44; &#38; had corresponded with <persName>Mr Hart</persName>&#41; I said I most assuredly did not desire to take <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> place<lb/> from him&#8212;and after stating to him <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> true position&#44; I added I have not the same scruple to take it from other<lb/> candidates.  What are there other candidates asked the Dr&#44; there are&#44; I said&#44; and I knew this when I applied<lb/> or I would not have moved at all in the matter.  Ok then&#44; said <persName>Dr R</persName> that is a very different thing&#8212;that alters the case<lb/> and we will say nothing more about it&#8221;  No doubt <persName>Dr. R</persName> will also remember this conversation if recalled to him. <del>&#63;</del><lb/> Enough of this matter.  I am at least guiltless of acting in opposition to any recommendation of the Dr for he gave<lb/> me none.  There was another reason why I did not delay writing <persName>Mr Hart</persName> till I heard again from <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> after telling him I had made qualified application.  It was this.  I was by no means <add>&#63;</add>&#59; my letter would<lb/> reach <persName>Mr L</persName> in <placeName>Phila.</placeName>  He was not himself&#44; as he wrote me on <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> Now before I could have got a reply from<lb/> the <placeName>South</placeName> supposing <persName>Mr <add>&#63;</add></persName> to have answered immediately some 6 or 8 weeks must have elapsed which would<lb/> have prevented my qualifying myself as candidate by visiting <placeName>Phil</placeName> &#38; reading one <date>Sabbath before 16 June</date>.<lb/> &#40;<hi rend="underline">En passant</hi>&#8212;This is the custom in most synagogues&#8212;I had hoped &#38; intimated as much by letter to <persName>Hart</persName>.&#41; that<lb/> it would have been departed from me my case but all <persName>H</persName> wrote I also must submit.  Hence my visit to <placeName>Phil</placeName><lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> writes you in his last My disclaimer in case he should apply was no disclaimer at all as he had written<lb/> me he would not accept the terms proposed.  Then if <persName>Mr L</persName> refused the terms proposed it was stating he would<lb/> not be a candidate&#44; and that others might be <add>&#63;</add> would accept the terms&#44; and I would in such case<lb/> &#40;as I had determined&#41; have acted on my first communication to the cong&#44; &#38; accepted if elected what <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> refused.  But see what I wrote to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> &#38; the cong. and judge better or not I disclaimed my<lb/> desire to oppose <persName>Mr L.</persName> In my first letter to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> sent with that to <add>&#63;</add> informed <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> thereof</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">2.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I write&#44; &#8220;Should <persName>Mr L</persName> solicit for himself once more their suffrages I should consider it my duty not to contest them<lb/> with him but at once retire before one whose attainments &#38; prior connection with you doubtless entitle him to your support<lb/> not only before me but before all who may apply &#38;c &#42;&#42;I cannot but express my sincere hope that you &#38; your present talented<lb/> Hazan may yet for many years be peaceably &#38; profitably connected together &#38;c&#8221; And on the <date>10 June</date> I addressed a letter to the<lb/> <placeName>Phila.</placeName> congregation through <persName>Mr A Hart</persName> which that gentleman acknowledged on the <date>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> and writes me should be recd on the meeting<lb/> of <date>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> as I had requested it should to the congregation.  In this I write the cong that as I heard when in <placeName>Phil</placeName> <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> would probably be a candidate&#44; I called their attention to the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> letter written <persName>Mr Hart</persName> and add &#8220;should this prove true<lb/> I must beg to request that I be not put in nomination against him &#38;c.  Now if the terms just quoted from my letters did<lb/> not amount to a disclaimer of candidateship were <persName>Mr L.</persName> on the field then I don&#39;t know what would.  <persName>Mr L</persName> may doubt my having<lb/> attached my credence to the report of his intention to accept office after what has passed&#44; but I did nevertheless&#44; knowing and<lb/> I say this not disrespectfully of <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; knowing that he had before signed the bond under circumstance certain modifications<lb/> &#40;and I presume the minutes of the cong more especially of <date>16 May 1841</date> &#38; <persName>Mr L&#39;</persName> letters to me are sufficient proof of this&#41; although<lb/> he had at first <hi rend="underline">determined not to do so</hi>.  But it is evident <persName>Mr L</persName> did not &#38; does not give me credit for any honesty of purpose<lb/> he views my reservation as a mere plead and does not believe that had his friends been able to do what some told<lb/> me when in <placeName>Phil</placeName> and  <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> after I had left also&#44; they desired to do&#44; viz so notify the terms that <persName>Mr I</persName> could become<lb/> a candidate.  <persName>M. L</persName> cannot believe that&#44; under these circumstances I would have retired in his favor what I most<lb/> assuredly would.  The extracts from my letters to the <placeName>Phil</placeName> cong. may be sufficient answer to <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> question<lb/> How could I have injured my cause by advocating him&#44; Will not any dispassionate person at once see<lb/> that by sending in on the day of election <date>16 June</date> &#40;&#38; before&#44; also an intimation that I would retire did <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> stand for election&#8212;that I might hereby <hi rend="underline">cool</hi> my supporters&#8212;that I might be considered as hinting that the cong<lb/> had not behaved as generously as they should to <persName>Mr L.</persName> &#38; that consequently I might have disgusted those who<lb/> would not grant <persName>Mr L</persName> what he wanted.  This risk I would have been an idiot not to force&#44; but I wrote<lb/> so nevertheless&#44; though I knew many might tell me that it was for <persName>Mr L</persName> to move in the matter&#8212;that I had no<lb/> right to refer to him at all.  I do not mean to say that it was by these means &#38; on this occasionally that<lb/> I advocated <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> cause&#8212;there were other occasions when I probably did myself no good to speak as I<lb/> did of <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>&#8212;but I am not a <persName>Jack Brag</persName> nor is it necessary at all I should refer further to this subject<lb/> at present.  <persName>Mr L</persName> however probably thinks I spoke ill of him whenever I could.  That he thinks me<lb/> capable of hating him in my heart &#38; doing him all the mischief I can I infer from his gratuitous remarks<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Perhaps if <persName>Mr De S.</persName> had written that anonymous pamphlet &#38;c</hi>&#8221; <del>I ask</del> &#8220;he would have gained the influence<lb/> of <persName>Mr Phillips</persName>.  Let me say in justice to the <persName>Messrs Phillips</persName> that not one of them spoke to me disrespectfully<lb/> or angrily of <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>&#44; or entered into any details as to what had passed between him &#38; his congregation.  They<lb/> said nothing more severe of <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; &#38; I think not so much as his best friends did.  But to return&#44; <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName><lb/> friends <hi rend="underline">were not able</hi> to carry for <persName>Mr L</persName> on <date>16 June</date> what he wanted.  This he ought&#44; perhaps&#44; <add>&#63;</add> know.  True<lb/> there was a small majority &#40;as <persName>Mr L</persName> writes&#41; willing to elect him Hazan still this very majority would not<lb/> give him all he asked.  So now he would have voted for the repeal of the bond law would not be willing<lb/> to grant a life term of office.  Some voted thinking <persName>Mr L.</persName> observed at least the compliment of being<lb/> elected&#44; since he declared he would not submit to the conditions&#8212;in short this majority were much divided<lb/> in opinion &#38; had they elected <persName>Mr L</persName> it would have amounted to nothing.  Had they all been content to give<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> all he asked what prevented them electing him &#38; then altering the terms to suit.  But instead of<lb/> postponing because of the threats of certain members withdrawing&#44; they subscribed because it was impossible<lb/> to obtain two thirds of the votes for repeal of the bond which first of all <persName>Mr L</persName> required.  I am warranted in this<lb/> assertion by the assurance of many and by communications received from some of <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> staunchest supporters<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> has therefore deceived himself as to the true cause of his want of success on <date>16 June</date>.<del>probably</del>  In his<lb/> last letter to you he says the reason of his new success was that &#8220;as others applied&#44; the congregation<lb/> thought his remarks were founded in mere caprice and hence would not grant them.&#8221;  <persName>Mr L</persName> does not<lb/> say much here for the strength of mind &#38; penetration of the meeting of <date>12 June</date> thus to be influenced.<hi rend="underline">  And</hi> I<lb/> <hi rend="underline">cannot at all reconcile</hi> this assertion of <persName>Mr L</persName> with his former assertions to me that he knew his dismissal<lb/> from office was resolved upon&#44; &#38; that he could not imagine the possibility of being re elected on terms<lb/> agreeable to himself <hi rend="underline">as he wrote me long before I or anyone elected applied</hi>.  Nor can I quite reconcile it with<lb/> his former assertion in this his last letter to you that it was &#8220;<hi rend="underline">in consequence of the threats</hi> &#38; false<lb/> representations of &#8220;certain parties that he failed.  Now today that <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> friends sacrificed him because<lb/> of the threats of withdrawal is to say that they acted with gross stupidity for they must have known<lb/> they would have to sacrifice him for the same reason in <date>April</date> when too those of <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> opponents<lb/> who could not be present in <date>June</date> would probably then attend.  Therefore it seems improbably they should<lb/> have voted with the others on this account.  <persName>Mr L</persName> can rest no proof of the truth of his suspicion than the<lb/> reason for postponing is what he says because this statement in the <date>Nov.</date> Oc. remains <sic>uncontradicted</sic><lb/> who should contradict it&#63;  And is the Occident the vehicle to give such discussions to the world&#63;<lb/>  And if <persName>Mr L</persName> be correct in his idea that certain parties &#40;when I had those <add>&#63;</add> his <add>&#63;</add> friends&#41;<lb/> really did not desire his success because of young <persName>Allan&#39;s</persName> sake&#44; then the more <add>&#63;</add> I proved<lb/> to be in the remarks made above.  And in this connexion<add>&#63;</add> let me also state that the adoption of the<lb/> pamphlet by the congregation containing some reference to a man &#40;<hi rend="underline">purporting to be from the minutes of the Congrg</hi></p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>and which almost looks as if the the principles of <persName>Lyola</persName> or <persName>Liguori</persName> had been <del>&#63;</del> brought into practice<lb/> when I <sic>learnt</sic> that this had been fathered by the cong &#40;I believe on the <date>28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April</date>&#41; I again saw how<lb/> little chance <persName>Mr L</persName> had of re&#45;election.  And because I saw this and because when <persName>Mr L</persName> told me<lb/> constantly himself that he stood no chance and should as in duty bound retire&#44; he now I may almost<lb/> say hates me because I believed &#38; read in earnest what he told me&#44; and in this belief tried that I should<lb/> have a chance as he had none.  <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> would not &#38; could not have the place himself nor did he<lb/> desire I should.  Hence his silence to me&#44; as I conclude.  But was this friendly magnanimous or<lb/> kind or candid.  What would I and <hi rend="underline">many others</hi> have said had <persName>Mr L</persName> after assuring me so constantly<lb/> that he had no hopes for himself&#44; as had he added&#44; therefore as I have so often professed the great<lb/> desire I have to bring you <sic>promnently</sic> before the public I will <del>tell</del> ask my friends if they cannot<lb/> modify the existing conditions of office&#44; to do all they can to forward my friend.  And in the<lb/> mean time I advise you to do so &#38; so.  <sic>Dont</sic> go to <placeName>Phil.</placeName>  <sic>Dont</sic> correspond &#38;c.  <persName>Mr L</persName> says he would<lb/> not advise me&#8221; why not.  Why not do as much to me if he were my true friend as he did<lb/> for <persName>Mr Morais</persName> after the latter had applied for <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> situation&#44; and tell me through a<lb/> as he <del>told</del> wrote a friend of <persName>Morais</persName> he would not advise him to come out here.  This was written<lb/> no doubt in friendly feeling&#44; but he did not show the same friendly feeling to me.  Both had equally<lb/> applied.  I have good cause then &#40;and not only in this particular instance&#41; to say as I<lb/> wrote <persName>Mr Solis</persName> in very bitterness of feeling that had <persName>Mr L</persName> acted with the same candour<lb/> as he <persName>Mr S</persName> had &#40;<persName>Mr S</persName> had acquainted me a short time before the election what the<lb/> intentions of <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> friends were for that day&#41; that I would have then been in a<lb/> very different position with respect to their congregation.  And so&#44; I solemnly assert&#44; I <add>&#63;</add><lb/> For had <persName>Mr L</persName> said do this I would have done it&#8212;do that&#44; &#38; it should have been executed.<lb/>  Even supposing for a moment that I was the first candidate in the field <hi rend="underline">which I was not</hi><lb/> is it possible <persName>Mr L</persName> could believe that <persName role="author">Abraham De Sola</persName> had not applied&#44; <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> <persName>Lyons</persName><lb/> <persName>Morais</persName> or others would not have done so.  And he himself admits that there was or is a party<lb/> desiring <persName>Mr Allan</persName>.  As <persName>Mr L</persName> says so say I&#44; They <del>did not</del> opposed &#40;covertly perhaps I may add&#41; <persName>Mr<lb/> Leeser</persName>&#44; so that <persName>Mick Allan</persName> ought ultimately be appointed.  &#40;<hi rend="underline"><add>&#63;</add> a son <add>&#63;</add></hi>&#41;  Hence had<lb/> <persName>A. D. S.</persName> not been there <persName>M. Allan</persName> would.  <persName>Mr L</persName> also states to you he knew beforehand that<lb/> I should not succeed would be the result of my application.  It would have been more candid in <persName>Mr L</persName> had he told <del>me</del> this before I went<lb/> to <placeName>Phila.</placeName>  And if <persName>Mr L</persName> knew this before hand he cannot with any justice say that I had <add>&#63;</add> not<lb/> come forward he would have conquered&#8212;for a fact favor the fact that others were in the field before me<lb/> &#38; therefore left me no choice unless I would see some one besides <persName>Mr L</persName> or myself in the office&#8212;<lb/> &#8212;if the cong had determined what the issue should be&#44; why I nor any other candidate could<lb/> control it.  That my friends in <placeName>England</placeName> should ask <persName>Mr A Franklin</persName> to support my claims will not<lb/> seem unnatural to many&#8212;but they were not so like led<add>&#63;</add> or advised to do so by me.  And this leads<lb/> me to say how deeply indignant I felt at <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> insinuations &#40;since <sic>learnt</sic>&#41; that I supplied<lb/> the Jewish papers with the various paragraphs headed <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.  I solemnly assert<lb/> and defy contradiction that to the Jewish Chronicle I never sent a line since the election&#44;<lb/> was first talked of&#44; nor to the Asmonean either.  I challenge either editor to say I have<lb/> But let <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> claim what his false friend so unjustly aspersed<add>&#63;</add> really did do&#44; though<lb/> he never boasted of any well intentioned act performed by him for <persName>Mr L.</persName>  I should not have mentioned<lb/> this but for the charge against me.  <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> wrote me when starting his paper&#44; asking me more<lb/> than once to support it and write for it.  Attached to the Occident however I would not write for<lb/> it&#44; and so wrote <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; I have since altered my determination because young <persName>Mr Allan</persName> who is as<lb/> one of the agents for the Asmonean in <placeName>Phil</placeName> told me <persName>Mr L</persName> had mentioned to him &#40;what I wrote in<lb/> confidence to <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> respecting my intention not to write for the Asmonean <del>the Asmonean</del>.  Moreover&#44; <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> has behaved with such extreme<lb/> politeness&#44; both in respect to sending me the paper <add>&#63;</add>lously&#44; that I may wait for it<lb/> and on several occasions that I feel bound to make some return to him.  But without<lb/> further digression&#44; the very day after I received the anonymous pamphlet <date>21 April</date> I wrote <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> that I<lb/> had received it&#8212;that no doubt a paper war would now cause but I entreated him for the<lb/> sake of all parties to close his columns to any &#38; every communication on the subject of the election<lb/> as it would be a disgrace &#40;<add>Hebrew</add>&#41; that his <add>&#63;</add> readers should become acquainted with<lb/> these internal dissensions.  I said he would not regret granting my request but that hereafter he<lb/> would see cause to congratulate himself upon his moderation when he saw what anarchy<lb/> had been thereby avoided.  In reply <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> writes me &#8220;Your letter requesting me to <sic>withold</sic><lb/> from publishing any remarks upon the emente<add>&#63;</add> between the <placeName>Phil</placeName> Cong &#38; <persName>Mr L</persName> did not reach me except the short<lb/> notice of the pamphlet alluded to was in <add>&#63;</add>&#44; but it was so guardedly worded that not<lb/> the slightest inference could be drawn by parties not knowing of the publication of the <add>&#63;</add><lb/> as to what the Asmonean alluded.  <persName>Mr L</persName> adds that altho&#39; he owed nothing to <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> for courtesy<lb/> in ushering the Asmonean before the Jewish public&#44; <hi rend="underline">still he would not suffer private</hi></p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p><hi rend="underline"><add>&#63;</add>ique to interfere</hi> &#38;c&#8221;  But <persName>Mr L</persName> published a Review of a Review &#40;from kind &#38; honorable motives there can<lb/> be no doubt&#44; yet I have reason to believe that that production did <persName>Mr L</persName> considerable harm.  This<lb/> was not writing scraps for the Jewish papers against <persName>Mr L.</persName>  I must not omit to state in this connection<lb/> that in writing <persName>Mr Lyon</persName> about some business matter connected with the Asmonean &#40;I believe among other<lb/> things I gave him <persName>Mr Aschers</persName> name as subscriber at that year&#39;s request &#40;I told <persName>Mr L</persName> just as I told all<lb/> the world at the time that I was applying for the office of <placeName>Phila.</placeName>&#8212;this was the extent of my information<lb/> to him.  <persName>Mr Lyon</persName> very kindly however added some complimentary &#38; recommendatory remarks&#8212;of the <add>&#63;</add><lb/> was written by <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> not by me&#44; but a single <del>&#63;</del> communication did I send to the Jewish papers on this subject nor <persName>Mr L</persName> cant be surprised that I should acquaint <persName>Mr Lyons</persName> what he would have heard from <placeName>Phil.</placeName> and apart<lb/> from my letter to <persName>Mr Hart</persName> I no secret of my intentions &#38; wishes&#8212;Had I deemed them dishonorable<lb/> I might have done so.  I therefore wrote <persName>Mr S. Solis</persName> &#40;before I went to <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#41; with whom I was slightly acquain<lb/>ted in <placeName>England</placeName>&#8212;the only one I knew ever so slightly in <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#8212;and whom I knew to be a zealous &#38; able<lb/> supporter of <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; both in the meeting room &#38; in the Occident  I <del>told</del> wrote <persName>Mr S</persName> &#40;<date>1 May</date> I think&#41; that <hi rend="underline">should</hi><lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> persist in his intention to retire from office&#44;&#8221; I hoped that he &#40;<persName>Mr Solis</persName>&#41; would consider my<lb/> next worthy his support.  I have made this communication so very long that I feel I<lb/> am trespassing on your kindness &#38; should conclude.  Still I must ask leave to touch briefly upon a<lb/> few more subjects requiring notice.  When in <placeName>Phila</placeName> I sought not to do&#44; what is usual for candidates to<lb/> do under the present wrong system&#8212;to canvass the Cong.  I went these avowedly to qualify myself as a candidate<lb/> by reading <hi rend="underline">once</hi> &#38; preaching in the Syng again.  To <add>&#63;</add> I would not defend&#44; hence apart from suffering<lb/> from slight indisposition I read with less gusto than I would on an ordinary <date>Sabbath</date> here.  I did not conceal<lb/> why I went&#8212;hence I plainly told them in Synagogue what my intents of the office were &#38; how I would<lb/> discharge them should I ever be their Minister.  Some comprehensive minded individuals and being<lb/> of course very unprejudiced thought I reflect on <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> because I said it was the duty of a Minister<lb/> to visit his flock&#44; which <persName>Mr L.</persName> usually did not&#44; and which I knew at the time I was speaking<lb/> as the dog who now sits at my feet does.  Haugh<add>&#63;</add>&#33;  Fortunately people are not all equally thin skinned<lb/> But having read once I resisted all importunities &#40;which were not a few&#41; both of my new found friends<lb/> and <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> supporters also &#40;<persName>Mr S Solis</persName> also advised my reading again&#41; and to the disappointment of<lb/> many I would not read or preach again&#44; but left <placeName>Phil</placeName> just in time to go to <persName><sic>Lyn</sic></persName> in <placeName>N. York</placeName> on<lb/> <date>Friday</date> Evening&#8212;That I did not do myself justice hereby I know just as my friends told me&#44; for the<lb/> times are so very different form the <placeName>London</placeName> Minhag which we here follow for other reasons&#8212;but<lb/> enough&#44; I paid <add>&#63;</add> to those hospitable friends who made my stay in <placeName>Phil</placeName> so pleasant&#8212;went<lb/> to see Girard College.  Fine arts exhibition&#44; &#38; some of the lions of the Quaker&#45;city&#44; and left to make a few<lb/> days stay in <placeName>N. York</placeName> where I had not yet been able to stay to see my many friends there.  Even from <placeName>N. Y</placeName><lb/> I hurriedly departed.  I wanted to get back to my charge &#38; my books.  As far as my interests were concerned I made<lb/> a careless stay in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.  But no matter let me conclude my notice of <persName>Mr <sic>Leesers</sic></persName> letter.  I made no<lb/> assertion to <persName>Mr S Solis</persName> that the above or what else I could say <del>what</del> would I justify.  <persName>Mr L</persName> writes he was Hazan<lb/> till <date>27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Septr</date> and it would been time enough &#40;for me&#41; to apply when he had withdrawn.  But did <persName>Mr L.</persName> consider when he<lb/> wrote this.  The election was fixed for <date>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date>&#44; 3 months before <persName>Mr. L</persName> time expired.  An application in <date>September</date> I might<lb/> naturally conclude would meet with the answer.  Sir you are three months too late.  We have appointed one who applied at the<lb/> time we advertised.  &#8220;then&#8221; writes <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; my influence would have been at his disposal.  Would it have been too much in <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> <add>&#63;</add> was&#44; till my application&#44; my true friend writing to me&#44; &#40;after stating as he had that he had no hope of election&#41;  Do you apply<lb/> when my term is expired&#44; &#38; my influence shall be at your &#39;disposal.&#8221;  I of course&#44; felt the absence of so friendly an act.  <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> writes I was &#8220;desirous&#39; to get his place &#40;<del>&#63;</del> &#38; at the same time <add>&#63;</add> to retain his good opinion.  &#8220;but adds <persName>ML</persName>&#8221;<lb/> this was impossible&#8221;  Why so&#44; I ask&#44; I did not make or in my way promote the state of ill feeling between <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> &#38; his congregation.  It was not through my influence that the  Cong. outvoted <persName>Mr L</persName> &#40;for he says their conduct<lb/> amounted to depriving him of his office&#41;  Why should <persName>Mr L</persName> have formed a bad opinion of me because I was desirous<lb/> of having what he would not.  <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> does not say I have same against him past forgiveness&#44; I solemnly<lb/> assert that I never sinned against him at a &#8220;<del>with</del> in thought&#44; and if I did in deed&#44; it is unknown to me.<lb/>  This will be my unchangeable conviction&#8221; till my last hour&#44; I do not say I may not have unintentionally<lb/> erred in one or two trivial matters&#44; but for the life of me I cannot see&#44; after <add>&#63;</add> all I have done<lb/> not now only but a <add>&#63;</add> times&#44; I cannot at all see that I did him any serious harm.  I am<lb/> convinced that had I never lived <persName>Mr L</persName> would not in consequence have been restored.  This has been my<lb/> conviction since <date>October 1849</date>&#8212;a sorrowful one it was&#44; and truly sorry am I even now to know it.<lb/>  I can in all truth say I had rather see <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> retain his situation&#44; than that I should be elected<lb/> or any other divine man chosen.  &#8220;But I must acknowledge&#44;&#8221; continues <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; &#8220;that I have been greatly disappointed<lb/> in <del>him</del> <persName>Mr. R. S.</persName>&#8221;  But have I had no cause to be disappointed in <persName>Mr L.</persName>  I am sure I have.  Let me read one<lb/> most trifling circumstance only&#44; and I am strongly of opinion&#44; unless I am even to a greater extent mistaken&#44;<lb/> that <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit&#44; he would not have so acted in a cool moment.  In his notice of the<lb/> meeting of <date>16 June</date> &#40;see Occident of <date>July 50</date>&#41; <persName>Mr L</persName> in an article worthy the <add>&#63;</add> of <placeName>New York</placeName></p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>and not <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>&#44; is guilty of a most gross &#38; <sic>petulent</sic> attack upon me.  Well do I recollect now<lb/> the feelings of surprise pain &#38; indignation with which I read it but now I regard it only as a proof of<lb/> <persName>Mr Leesers</persName> impetuosity which leads him to say &#38; write what he must afterwards regret.  But let me <del>&#63;</del><lb/> refer briefly to this article.  <persName>Mr L</persName> says &#8220;<persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> we understand only applied in case the present<lb/>  minister was not a candidate.&#8221;  Is it possible <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> informant did not tell him that on the<lb/> <date><hi rend="underline">16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of June</hi></date> the day appointed for the election I also sent in a letter to the Congregation stating that<lb/> I desired not to be put in nomination <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Mr L</persName> a candidate&#33;  This letter of mine <persName>Mr Hart</persName> assured<lb/> me on its receipt&#44; should be read to the Cong.  I was therefore a matter of sufficient notoriety.  Why then say<lb/> for <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> more than he said for me.  Overlook both&#44; but don&#39;t do an injustice to one.  That <persName>Rosenfeld</persName><lb/> behaved better on <date>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June</date> than I&#44; it is impossible for <persName>Mr L</persName> to prove for to use <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> own words &#8220;He<lb/> knew &#40;that is <persName>Mr Rosenfeld</persName> knew&#41; that his reservation or disclaimer was no disclaimer&#44; since he<lb/> also knew that I <add>i. e. <persName>Mr Leeser</persName></add> would not apply under the conditions &#8220;as all the world did.  Why then favor<lb/> <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> more than <persName>De Sola</persName> by recording to the credit of the <del>&#63;</del> former what the other also should have<lb/> received credit for and would had <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> when he then wrote been the <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> of other cooler<lb/> moments.  Hereby <persName>Mr L</persName> caused me to think what others have also thought&#44; that in his anger he<lb/> desired to injure me.  For <add>&#63;</add> acct the election had not then been held&#44;but postponed&#44; consequently<lb/>  this implied charge of a want of consideration for <persName>Mr L</persName> &#38; some other <sic>inuendos</sic> equally unfounded<lb/> &#38; uncalled for notice presently were calculated to do me harm with some in <placeName>Phila.</placeName>  <persName>Mr De S.</persName> <add>&#63;</add> <persName>Mr L</persName> in<lb/> the Occident was the only one of the candidates who had been to <placeName>Phil</placeName> &#38;c during the late absence of <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> I was not the only one who thought that had <persName>Mr L</persName> left out the words during the late absence of <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> it would have been more fair &#38; dignified on his part since some not acquainted with the true state of<lb/> affairs might have imagined that I went to <placeName>Phil</placeName>&#44; knowing it was not correct to go there&#44; &#38; not desiring<lb/> to meet <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; went behind his back&#44; covertly slyly like a thief.  Those who know me <add>&#63;</add> well<lb/> imagine how my heart beat&#44; &#38; ears tingled where I thus read &#38; thought.  Instead of avoiding <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> I did all I could to see him.  I delayed going to <placeName>Phil.</placeName> as long as possible&#44; though you know certain parties<lb/> not members of the congregation telegraphed me that it was important I should go at such a such<lb/> a time&#8212;again that I should go for <date>Pentecost</date>&#44; which I nevertheless did not mind but waited<lb/> as long as I could consistently with <persName>Mr Hart&#39;s</persName> recommendation so that I might see <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; who&#44; I thought<lb/> would by that time be returned.  And indeed the answer to my particular inquiries&#59; at <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> residence<lb/> also I was told he was daily expected.  As I before told you I would not to please friends&#44; or <sic>teaze</sic><lb/> enemies stay to read another <date>Sabbath</date> in <placeName>Phil</placeName> though strongly recommended so to do but I wrote a few lines<lb/> and if I forget not also told the lady I saw at <persName>Mr l&#39;</persName> house&#44; to inform <persName>Mr L</persName> I should stay a few days<lb/> in <placeName>New York</placeName> so that I might see him&#44; I think I said how long I should stay &#38; I asked him to<lb/> telegraph me as soon as he arrived as I desired much to see him.  I do not know whether <persName>Mr L</persName> did arrive<lb/> while I was in <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> but had we met&#44;  I think we should not have been so many months alienated to come<lb/> twice.  The Oc says and his &#40;my&#41; testimonials which were extensively circulated &#40;among the voters only<lb/> I believe&#41; in a hand bill &#40;Either I did not yet know the meaning of hand bill or I was right in supposing&#41; <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> intended it as a sneer on my circulars&#44; which in <placeName>Europe</placeName> or say <placeName>England</placeName> it is always the custom to send e. g. <persName>Dr<lb/> Raphall</persName> sent them when he applied for the lectureship at the <placeName>Dukes Place</placeName> Synagogue in <placeName>London</placeName>.  All the candidates<lb/> did when applying for the office of Hazan in <placeName>London</placeName>.  It was an inadvertence for which I afterwards blamed myself<lb/> much that I did not send one to <persName>Mr L</persName> &#40;he says in the Oc a copy reached him through the kindness of a friend&#41;<lb/> for I should with my then feelings certainly have done so just as I sent then the gist of my letter to <persName>Mr Hart</persName><lb/> but I sent the parcel on to <placeName>Phil</placeName>  I could not afterwards procure one.  <persName>Mr L</persName> says <persName>Mr De S&#39;s</persName> testimonials<lb/> were highly creditable to <add>&#63;</add> But I &#38; others too thought this no praise&#8212;no kind words&#44; for none<lb/> could say otherwise.  And if all our doubt&#44; if we had any were removed by <persName>Mr L</persName> himself who labored<lb/> hard to show&#44; altho&#39; he did not plainly say that these testimonials were only given me as a matter of favor<lb/>  Thus <persName>Mr L.</persName> says they were signed by the <persName>Rev D. Meldola</persName> &#40;This name would be sufficient&#44; as every<lb/> reader of the Occident knew who <persName>Mr Meldola</persName> was&#44; since a few numbers back there was a <add>&#63;</add><lb/> of a Catechism he published or if this readers must know who <persName>Mr M</persName> his say he is 6<add>&#63;</add><lb/> Rabbi of the Portuguese Jews in <placeName>London</placeName> but no <persName>Mr L</persName> gives his title the maternal uncle of<lb/> <persName>Mr De S.</persName>  The inference from this must be obvious.  Again next &#8220;by <persName>Dr Lowe</persName> his preceptor<lb/> &#40;of course a preceptor would cry up his pupils&#41; next &#8220;by <persName>Dr A Benisch</persName>&#44; says <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; &#8220;once Editor<lb/> of the voice of Jacob &#40;why not style him what my &#8220;handbill more properly calls him&#44; Professor<lb/> of Hebrew at the Jews Institution at <add>&#63;</add> Hall author of &#38;c &#38;c but no&#44; he was author of<lb/> the voice of J. &#38; <persName>Mr D S</persName> &#8220;assisted him in his labours says <persName>Mr L.</persName>  The influence is that in return<lb/> for my kindness the Dr gave me a testimonial at all events he was particularly intimate with<lb/> me &#38; would not refuse&#44; next writes <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; but <persName>Dr Raphall</persName>.  Now it might be naturally<lb/> thought that it would be quite unnecessary to say who the eminent <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> was&#8212;however<lb/> as he was to the American Jewish community among whom he had but lately been elected Minister<lb/> with much <add>&#63;</add> as well as <persName>Mr L.</persName> but <persName>Mr L</persName> thought otherwise.  He therefore writes<lb/> <persName>Dr Raphall</persName> who was associated in various literary labours with <persName>Rev David De Sola</persName></p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">3.</p>
				<p><add>&#63;</add> of <persName>Mr A D. S.</persName> of course the Dr in his good feeling for the father&#8212;his old friend<lb/> would favor the son with a testimonial.  Thus then might one not unnaturally infer that all<lb/> my testimonials were given me because all the donors were friends or relatives.  The testimonial of the<lb/> late venerable &#38; talented <persName>Michael Josephs</persName>&#8212;one of the greatest Hebrew scholars &#38; writers among the Jews of<lb/> <placeName>England</placeName>&#44; <persName>Mr L</persName> did not comment upon or take any notice of at all.  I could not but think that <persName>Mr L</persName> thereby<lb/> rendered himself open to a charge of want of <sic>candour</sic>&#44; since one might naturally conclude that as he did<lb/> not know in what relations <persName>Mr Josephs</persName> &#38; myself were since he could not say <persName>Mr J</persName> was my preceptor<lb/> or co&#45;laborer&#44; or a co&#45;laborer of my father&#44; or even a particular friend he ignored the testimonial lest his<lb/> readers should think that at least one man gave me a good character who had no motive for doing so enough<lb/>&#8212;couple this with what I have already written &#38; say whether I too have not cause to be disappointed in <persName>Mr L.</persName><lb/>  Say openly in your magazine or where you will that I have done you an injury.  I can then defend myself&#8212;<lb/> but do not stab me like an Italian bravo&#8212;do not blast my reputation &#38; character unnecessarily <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> may say I have fancied all this but the facts are too stubborn.  Believe me&#44; dear sir&#44; before I had said or<lb/> hinted anything about it more than one expressed themselves indignant at such treatment &#38; strongly advised<lb/> me to reply to it either in the Asmonean or by circular&#44; but altho&#39; I felt myself injured &#38; knew if I<lb/> replied all would give me right in my strictures on this article&#8212;still I had too much self pride so to do.<lb/>  And this is the reason&#44; let me tell you <hi rend="underline">en passant</hi> that I have determined not to write more for the Occident<lb/> and was sorry that an article of mine appeared after the publication of the above notice so that people might<lb/> suppose I was still a correspondent&#8212;but which in truth I cannot be until something more shall have<lb/> passed in explanation between the writer of that injurious article &#38; myself.  That it has done me no good<lb/> I am sure.  Let <persName>Mr Solis</persName>&#8212;the friend to whom <persName>Mr L</persName> thinks I have maligned him&#8212;a just &#38; candid friend himself<lb/> a correspondent of the Occident&#8212;let him decide&#8212;&#38; I am sure he will not say I am altogether wrong.  Your opinion<lb/> you need not give for I flatter myself I know it.  My efforts such as they are for the Jewish cause shall not<lb/> be wanting when I can make them.  Hence I will write &#40;being forced&#41; for the Asmonean &#38; for any paper not<lb/> under the control of an Editor who could thus unjustly &#38; unmercifully attack me.  I am fully as sensitive as <persName>Mr Leeser</persName>.<lb/>  In his last letter to you <persName>Mr L</persName> writes &#8220;I would not have reacted so had <persName>Mr De S.</persName> been in my position &#38; I in his.&#8221;  I think<lb/> he would &#38; he ought not to forget the recommendation of our sages &#8220;Judge not thy fellow&#44; until thou hast been<lb/> in his position.  <persName>Mr L.</persName> would rather do anything &#8220;than undermine a friend.&#8221;  If <persName>Mr L</persName> wishes to convey that I have<lb/> done or attempted to do so&#44; I repel the accusation with indignation&#44; and deny its truth by all that is sacred.  <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> also says &#8220;to be in league with them whom he knew to be my enemies is no test of friendship&#8221; I&#44; as solemnly<lb/> deny the truth of this allegation.  I never have been in league with any one to injure <persName>Mr L</persName>&#44; nor has any one even<lb/> proposed so dishonorable a thing.  I am not so easily made a cats paw.  No one else would charge me with acting<lb/> so irreligiously.  It is an unjust change founded on illiberal irreligious suspicions.  Let <persName>Mr L</persName> prove to you<lb/> or any one that I have leagued with his enemies if he can.  He surely cannot charge me with this because I<lb/> did not refuse the civilities &#38; support of the <persName>Messrs Phillips</persName> whom he told me were his enemies for the first<lb/> time just before he went to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#8212;a few weeks before the election.  Previously he had never mentioned<lb/> their names to me.  But I will not say more about this unworthy charge.  <persName>Mr L</persName> says <persName>Mr D. S.</persName> would do himself<lb/> real honor by acknowledging his unintentional error as I am willing to regard it as such&#44; my feelings<lb/> were  greatly outraged by the manner in which he ought to carry his plan.  <persName>Mr L</persName> exhibits&#44; it appears<lb/> to me some inconsistency in this statement &#38; it is what I cannot easily reconcile.  If I undermined<lb/> him or attempted to do so&#8212;if I leagued with his enemies to his detriment &#38; if I sought to carry<lb/> my plan in so dishonorable a manner as to wound his feelings&#8212;all of which <persName>Mr L</persName> says I did&#8212;how can<lb/> he say at the same time I erred unintentionally.  I could not undermine or league or plan unintentionally.  No<lb/> if I did this then I acted not unintentionally&#44; but rascally&#44; &#38; with malice <sic>propense</sic>.  This is the English of it<lb/> <sic>And</sic> therefore I &#38; you &#38; any man of common sense cannot admit that <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> believes I have only erred<lb/> unintentionally&#44; while he brings forward &#40;in the same paragraph&#41; such serious charges against me.  If <persName>Mr Leeser</persName><lb/> would do himself real honor &#38; act with the justice he is fully capable to do&#44; he will admit how incon<lb/>gruous his statements are&#44; &#38; plainly say that he does not think I leagued undermined flamed &#38;<lb/> plotted against him&#44; but that I &#8220;<hi rend="underline">erred unintentionally</hi>&#8221; only.  I on my part am willing to make<lb/> any acknowledgment consistent with my convictions of my innocence of desiring by thought or deed<lb/> to hurt him.  No false pride or obstinacy&#44; or desire to show that I am better than my neighbour<lb/> shall <sic>withold</sic> me.  And I do not scruple to say&#44; and <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> may know it that I am<lb/> truly sorry we are not on the same terms we were this time last year.  Anything that</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
				<p>night cause<add>&#63;</add> angry feeling I have endeavored to avoid in this letter&#44; for it is not I who make<lb/> charges&#44; but defend myself I must.  I am quite sure that I never spoke injuriously or disrespectfully<lb/> &#40;as I could not&#41; of <persName>Mr L</persName> to any.  If I have written something in haste&#44; likely in <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> estimation<lb/> to do him an injury which I am not conscious however of having done I am quite ready to make<lb/> all the reparation <persName>Mr L</persName> may require.  <persName>Mr L</persName> should recollect that being no more than human it is<lb/> quite natural that I should err&#44; and that he himself wrote a review of my testimonials which<lb/> is quite open to the construction I &#38; others put upon it&#8212;that he has erred&#44; &#38; that I have<lb/> forgiven it&#44; for <persName>Mr L</persName> may be assured that after its first perusal I never had another angry<lb/> feeling on the matter&#8212;further than thinking I was injured&#44; which did not anger me much as I know<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> wrote it in misconception of all circumstances<add>&#63;</add> &#38; in heat&#8212;and that from the first day I wrote him.  Even before<lb/> I worried in <placeName>America</placeName> until the present moment I have always entertained for him feelings of great<lb/> respect regard &#38; kindness and <sic>thugh</sic> I may no longer address him as a friend&#44; still I am his friend yet<lb/> Even if wrong&#44; which to the extent <persName>Mr L</persName> has intimated&#44; I never can admit I have been&#8212;and I do<lb/> sincerely hope that after a dispassionate reading of what I have written &#38; which I desire he should see<lb/> <persName>Mr L</persName> will admit he has been deceived and ignorant of all the motives &#38; circumstances under which<lb/> I acted and that he consequently has been somewhat mistaken in what he has written to you<lb/> I could not say as much as I have&#44; knowing what <persName>Mr L</persName> has written already to yourself and my<lb/> uncle &#40;with whom it is impossible to injure me&#41; I could not in all candour &#38; sincerity admit<lb/> that I value <persName>Mr L&#39;s</persName> good opinion&#44; and desire he should think better of me&#8212;as well as he did of old<lb/> did I not <hi rend="underline">sincerely</hi> so desire&#44; since I lay myself open to the charge that having <add>&#63;</add>fully offended <persName>Mr L</persName><lb/> I know desire to conciliate him.  Heaven knows I never <sic>wilfully</sic> offended him as I never <sic>wilfully</sic><lb/> injured him.</p>
				<p><persName>Mr Leeser</persName> says in his letter to you &#8220;<persName>Mr De Sola</persName> himself cannot regret as much as I do that<lb/> an estrangement has taken place between us&#8221; but <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> has entirely mistaken my feelings<lb/> towards him.  He appears to have regarded me as false I therefore incapable of entertaining any<lb/> kind feeling towards him.  Not so.  My communication with him during some four years was<lb/> not without its pleasures.  But it was our intimacy as Israelites&#44; having the same religious<lb/> convictions&#8212;belonging to the same school working in the same glorious cause&#8212;having<lb/> kindred tastes &#38; sentiments&#8212;it was this intimacy that I valued&#8212;always conscious &#40;no<lb/> false pride deters me from saying it&#41; that I profited by it&#8212;as I wrote <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> in I<lb/> think the very first letter I was addressed him <add>Hebrew</add>&#8212;it was the sudden<lb/> unexpected severance of this intimacy that I have since regretted&#8212;the more so that I am<lb/> conscious of never having been guilty of doing that which should cause it.  Is <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> willing<lb/> to retract his serious charges that I have attempted <sic>wilfully</sic> to undermine him&#8212;that I have<lb/> leagued myself with his enemies&#8212;that I have made false protestations and acted falsely to him<lb/> and instead of these charges admit after reading the above that he now attaches I only unintentionally<lb/> erred against him and bore him no malice &#40;as how should I&#41; then I on my part am quite<lb/> willing beforehand candidly to admit that in many things I may have acted foolishly both for<lb/> his &#38; my interest and that it is quite possible I hurt his feelings as he says&#44; and even slightly<lb/> injured him by anything I may unintentionally have done.  Any further admission compatible with<lb/> the declarations I have already made&#44; I am quite willing further to make and questions to<lb/> answer&#44; since it is not a matter of indifference whether <persName>Mr L</persName> or any other man thinks<lb/>  well or ill of me.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Having made this communication so long I must <sic>apologise</sic> for stating up so much<lb/> of your time&#44; but it will be the last time I shall ever trouble you with so long &#38; tiresome<lb/> a letter on this subject.  Indeed it will be quite useless and impossible for me to do so since<lb/> should <persName>Mr Leeser</persName> not be willing to admit what I think he in common justice &#38; truth<lb/> should I have not one word more to say in the matter as it would be a waste of<lb/> time that could be better employed.  I am now writing into another day and last night<lb/> it was the same for I have been unable to put aside other things go claiming my<lb/> attention just now.  I would not mind my convenience and I think any good<lb/> could come of it&#44; but as <persName>Mr Leeser&#39;s</persName> retraction of his unfounded charges can be the only good</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
				<p>that can satisfy me&#44; I think under the circumstances I would not be right even to devote<lb/> a leisure hour further to this subject of which by this time you are of course heartily tired<lb/> so I subscribe myself at once</p> 
			<p rend="indent(2)">Yours truly</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><persName role="author">Abraham de Sola</persName></p>
				<p><date>26 Feby&#47;51</date></p>
			
			<div>
				<p><ref target="Occident_PDFs/Occ_7_7.pdf">The above text refers to Occident Volume 7 No. 7 pages 376 through 378. Click here to view.</ref></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
