<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item207</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Hirschel, Solomon</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1836-11" source="" attested="yes">4 November 1836</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1836-11" source="" attested="yes">12 Heshvar 5596</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item207_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>8 pages on 8 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Philadelphia &#40;Pennsylvania</placeName>&#41; <date>Thursday Heshvan 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#40;Nov. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>&#41; 5596</date>.</p>
				<p>To the Rt. <addressee>Rev. Dr Solomon Hirschel</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Grand Rabbi of the Polish &#38; German Jews in <placeName>London</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Honoured Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">The eminent station which you occupy has made your name<lb/> familiarly known among us&#44; and the fame which attaches to you as<lb/> an able expounder of the holy law with which we are blessed naturally<lb/> makes you conspicuous to us even who are separated from your residence<lb/> by the distance which the great sea interposes.  In this country there is none<lb/> who is authorized to give an opinion in contested or uncertain points of<lb/> law&#44; and we are therefore compelled upon any emergency which arises to<lb/> decide for ourselves as best we can&#44; or to ask an opinion of one another&#44;<lb/> and as our books for reference are but few&#44; and our knowledge in these<lb/> matters not being as extensive as it should be&#59; I have on mature reflec&#45;<lb/>tion&#44; and upon the advice of friends&#44; amongst whom I may mention <persName>Dr. Mr. Ema<lb/>nuel</persName>&#44; whom you well know&#44; resolved to place before you several questions for<lb/> your decision&#44; and to beg you most earnestly to favour me with your<lb/> reply by the earliest possible opportunity&#44; that we may have a certain and<lb/> an authentic opinion to go upon in the cases hereafter to be enumerated.<lb/>  I myself am a native of <placeName>Westphalia in Germany</placeName>&#44; whence I emigrated<lb/> to this country in the winter of the year <date>5584</date> when I was seventeen years old&#59;<lb/> I had then a slight acquaintance with <add>&#63;</add> having gone through <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> and a part of <add>Hebrew</add> and <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; with the <add>Hebrew</add> I had as yet not meddled&#44; as<lb/> of course I was yet too young at that time for so important a study&#44;<lb/> and after I reached <placeName>America</placeName> I was engaged in business&#44; and had besides<lb/> neither books nor teachers to help myself further.  It is now about six<lb/> years and a quarter since I was elected to serve as <add>Hebrew</add> to the Portuguese<lb/> congregation <add>Hebrew</add> in this place&#44; altho&#39; I can hardly say that I was suffi&#45;<lb/>ciently qualified&#44; but owing to there being but few in this country capable at all<lb/> for this station the partiality of the people here called me away from <placeName>Richmond<lb/> in Virginia</placeName> where I had lived five years and a quarter with my uncle&#44; an old gentleman</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>who had been settled for many years in <placeName>America</placeName>.  Knowing my own want of<lb/> proper qualification I would never have consented to serve&#44; if others more<lb/> fitting in point of standing&#44; information or other qualities had been here&#59; but<lb/> this not being the case&#44; as is proved by there being yet two congregations at<lb/> least in this country without a regular <add>Hebrew</add> I consented to serve.  During the<lb/> whole time of my being in office constantly occurrences have taken place<lb/> which demanded decisions more complicated than my own information was<lb/> able to afford.  But having in the neighbouring city of <placeName>New York</placeName> a man of<lb/> sterling information and a connection of my family by name of <persName>Israel B.<lb/> Kursheedt</persName>&#44; no doubt also known to you by reputation&#44; I occasionally<lb/> referred to him.  But as he is not authorized in the regular way to give<lb/> decisions&#44; and as therefore his opinions are liable to be objected to&#44; I now<lb/> address you&#44; as already stated to ask of you&#44; which will without doubt be<lb/> a pleasure to you&#44; to assist your brethren in <placeName>America</placeName> with your advice and<lb/> counsel in their endeavours to worship the God of their fathers in truth.<lb/>  Perhaps all said hitherto might have been as well omitted&#44; but yet I thought it<lb/> best to inform you at once why you are troubled with a letter by one who<lb/> is in all <sic>likelyhood</sic> a perfect stranger to you&#44; for I doubt whether even my<lb/> name has ever reached your ears before.  In the first place then allow<lb/> me to levy a case before you which has recently occurred here&#44; and which<lb/> has carried a considerable degree of excitement.  You must know that<lb/> from a cause or the other things occur here for which it is difficult to<lb/> find a parallel elsewhere&#44; and so it happened that a man by name of<lb/> <persName>Reuben Etting</persName> living in <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>&#44; where there was no <add>Hebrew</add> had a son<lb/> born to him about 35 years ago.  He sent for a <add>Hebrew</add> from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName><lb/> if I am not mistaken&#44; and they <sic>alledge</sic> that some accident happened<lb/> to the child in consequence of the <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; which however the family of the<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; who has been dead long before I came to <placeName>America</placeName>&#44; as strenuously<lb/> deny.  Be this as it may&#44; three sons born to <persName>Etting</persName> after that time were<lb/> left uncircumcised&#44; the youngest of whom was however circumcised here after<lb/> he was old enough to judge for himself.  The elder two however are <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>one of them&#44; named <persName>Benjamin</persName> was married some years back to the daughter of a<lb/> gentleman of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> by name of <persName>Joseph Marx</persName>&#44; highly respected for his wealth<lb/> and standing as a merchant.  I lately saw in this place the gentleman that<lb/> gave them <add>Hebrew</add> and he assured me that he did not know that the man<lb/> he married was an <add>Hebrew</add>.  Of this however I can not speak with certain&#45;<lb/>ty&#44; and I only state it that you may have all the circumstances of the<lb/> case as far as known to myself.  <persName>Benj. Etting</persName> had born him two<lb/> sons&#44; whom he <hi rend="underline">contrary</hi> to the advice of his family&#44; &#40;who are now all<lb/> residents in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#44;&#41; left <add>Hebrew</add>.  In the beginning of the summer<lb/> he himself went out on a voyage to <placeName>Canton in China</placeName>&#44; and in the mean<lb/> time his youngest son sickened and died on the last <date>Sunday in<lb/> Elul</date>.<lb/>  Our congregation was applied to&#44; to permit the child to be buried in our<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and by my advice the Parnass permitted it to be done&#59; I conten<lb/>ded that the child was <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and not worse than <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> of whom it is said <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; from which I inferred that<lb/> a <add>Hebrew</add> he may have&#44; not being able to find any thing in relation to <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> mentioned in the <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; at the same time I decided that the child should be<lb/> looked upon as a <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and that they should give it <add>Hebrew</add> and call<lb/> it a name as it mentioned in reference to a child that dies before it is<lb/> eight days old.  <persName>Dr. Emanuel</persName> made the <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; but because the parents had<lb/> been <add>Hebrew</add> and having been warned&#44; I refused to attend the <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; not being<lb/> willing to read the <add>Hebrew</add> over such a child.  Understand me well&#44; venerable<lb/> Rabbi&#44; that on no account would I have presumed to <del>have</del> given an opinion&#44;<lb/> if there were any body else here to whom I could have applied for advice&#44; and<lb/> thus therefore I was compelled to act&#44; as I have done&#44; altho by so doing I<lb/> gave <sic>offence</sic> to those that said the child ought not to have been buried<lb/> at all&#44; and others again&#44; and among them the large family connection<lb/> of the child&#44; who said I should and ought to have attended the <add>Hebrew</add>.  I<lb/> therefore ask now your opinion&#44; upon the following points arising out of this case</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>a&#41; Is a <add>Hebrew</add> allowed to marry a <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;</p>
				<p>b&#41; Is a &#8220; allowed to have a <add>Hebrew</add> or to be <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;</p>
				<p>c&#41; Is he allowed to come to <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and if he is&#44; what is to be done in case<lb/> he is full grown and had had an opportunity to take the <add>Hebrew</add> on himself&#63;</p>
				<p>d&#41; Is he entitled to be buried in the regular row or should he be laid <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;</p>
				<p>e&#41; Should the <add>Hebrew</add> say <add>Hebrew</add> over a child like the one spoken of&#44; or had he<lb/> better not be at the burial&#63;</p>
				<p>f&#41; Should <add>Hebrew</add> and the other <add>Hebrew</add> be at all said over such a <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;</p>
				<p>g&#41; Are the <hi rend="underline">daughters</hi> of such a man&#44; born to him by a <add>Hebrew</add> regular<lb/> and <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;</p>
				<p>On some of these points I have no draft myself&#44; but to satisfy every one<lb/> both who agreed with and those who differed from me of what is really the law I<lb/> have asked perhaps more questions than were necessary.  In case you answer<lb/> this be kind enough also to quote the authorities&#44; if there are any to which<lb/> we may refer for future decisions&#44; that we may not be compelled to encroach<lb/> again upon your valuable time.  I forgot to mention that <persName>Mr. Reuben Etting</persName><lb/> has besides the four sons already mentioned a fifth to whom he gave regularly<lb/> the <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; and so it would appear that he may have been prevented in the other<lb/> instances by a fear&#44; however idle&#44; of accidents&#44; which he believed to have<lb/> occurred to his eldest son.  The whole family was very much distressed at my<lb/> absence from the burial&#44; and were of course in a corresponding degree angry&#44;<lb/> at what they thought a wanton insult offered at them. However it must<lb/> be borne in mind that there are four or five more families here who are<lb/> situated in the same way&#44; and as there are at least <hi rend="underline">two</hi> grown persons&#44; it<lb/> is absolutely necessary that we should have some fixed opinion to go by&#44; that<lb/> we may in future avoid giving just <sic>offence</sic> to anyone&#44; for I believe sin&#45;<lb/>cerely if once an opinion has been obtained from you or some other great<lb/> teacher in <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; but especially you&#44; since you are the only one now<lb/> in the countries where English is spoken&#44; it will settle the matter for&#45;<lb/>ever&#59; since despite of this professed indifference men may feel for religion in<lb/> this country still they have sense enough left and virtue enough too to<lb/> submit to a <del>&#63;</del> righteous decision once given&#44; for <add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p>And having ventured thus far permit me to ask you a few other questions.<lb/>  In this country there are unfortunately many who have married <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> and there are many children descended either by the father or mother&#39;s<lb/> side from <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; you know well what is said <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; still<lb/> a great multitude is lost to our people by the great mixture which<lb/> has unfortunately subsisted for so many years.  I should like therefore<lb/> to have a distinct answer to the following question&#44; only premising that<lb/> we are in this country permitted to make as many <add>Hebrew</add> as we please.<lb/>  I know also that <add>Hebrew</add> are not likely to be the best <add>Hebrew</add> still the confu<lb/>sion arising from the number of females particularly who are partly Jews<lb/> causes me to lay this question before you for your candid decision and<lb/> sincere reflection&#58;</p>
				<p>First.  Would it be lawful in case a <add>Hebrew</add> has married a <add>Hebrew</add> to<lb/> receive her as a <add>Hebrew</add> that the children born from such a union<lb/> may be <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; or would it be better to leave them go altogether<lb/> to destruction&#44; and to refuse them every opportunity of coming again<lb/> among us.</p>
				<p>You will easily perceive that this matter is of great importance&#44; and<lb/> if it would be legalized might prevent much evil.  Further&#44; since there<lb/> are in this country very often <add>Hebrew</add> who are willing to marry <add>Hebrew</add> and<lb/> become <add>Hebrew</add> before hand&#44; whether under the circumstances of the country<lb/> it would be right to take them&#44; knowing what their object is in<lb/> joining us.  Instances indeed have occurred where gentile women<lb/> would have been willing to <del>have</del> become Jewesses&#44; and being refused<lb/> they still married and they and their children were afterwards<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add>&#44; since their daughters afterwards married <add>Hebrew</add> and so carried<lb/> the sin from generation to generation.</p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Second</hi>.  In what light are children to be regarded whose father was a Jew and<lb/> whose mother a <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;</p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Third</hi>.  What must be done to children whose mother was a <add>Hebrew</add> and whose<lb/> father a <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;  are they to be considered as <add>Hebrew</add> without <add>Hebrew</add> or must they too</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>have <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;</p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Fourth</hi>.  Suppose a <add>Hebrew</add> marries a <add>Hebrew</add> and they have children&#44; and afterwards the mother<lb/> become a <add>Hebrew</add> are the children both before her <add>Hebrew</add> to be considered as <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;<lb/>  I myself have decided that they are also <add>Hebrew</add> and of course not <add>Hebrew</add>&#59; but<lb/> I should like to know whether I was right or wrong&#63;</p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Fifth</hi>. Suppose a <add>Hebrew</add> should have children or rather daughters by a <add>Hebrew</add> are<lb/> they <add>Hebrew</add> or not&#63;</p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">Sixth</hi>. Would it be right <add>Hebrew</add> to accept as <add>Hebrew</add> grown persons whose father<lb/> was a <add>Hebrew</add> and whose mother a <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;</p>
				<p>At the present moment I cannot think of more cases concerning<lb/> this point&#44; but be kind enough to write out if you can do it without<lb/> too much trouble all the laws relating to this important consideration&#44;<lb/> and you will I hope undertake to satisfy us in this country&#44; when I assure<lb/> you that there are at least a third of all the American families interested<lb/> in it&#44; I refer especially to those that live in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.  There are<lb/> also a number in <placeName>New York</placeName> and elsewhere similarly situated&#44; but of<lb/> those I cannot speak with as much certainty.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Sometime ago several families from various causes wished<lb/> the marriage of their daughters to take place in the morning instead<lb/> of the afternoon as usual.  The congregation very properly refused<lb/> granting their consent to such an innovation.  But yet it would give<lb/> us much satisfaction to have your decision on this subject also&#44; and<lb/> whether a marriage may take place in the morning or not&#63;&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Would a marble basin&#44; hewn out of a solid block&#44; holding a<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add> filled with water coming by means of fixed machinery from a<lb/> river&#44; which water is originally forced up in a reservoir by means<lb/> of machine pump be <add>Hebrew</add> for a <add>Hebrew</add>&#63; or would it be considered a <add>Hebrew</add> and <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;<lb/>  bay water brought into a bath built of <hi rend="underline">stone</hi> or <del>single</del> bricks cemented by<lb/> mortar from a river as above be used for a <add>Hebrew</add> or are they considered as <add>Hebrew</add>&#63;</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I should like to ask your opinion upon many other points from time to<lb/> time&#44; if you would permit me&#44; to address you occasionally&#59; which I trust<lb/> you will grant me&#44; and I assure you&#44; that you still never need blame<lb/> yourself for the favour granted.  If you can conveniently do it&#44;<lb/> please to make your reply in English&#44; that it may be extensively<lb/> circulated.  Answer this if you can by the earliest packet&#44; since<lb/> not I alone but many other persons are anxious for your opinion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I have seen with pleasure that <add>Hebrew</add> <persName>De Sola</persName> has undertaken<lb/> a new edition of the Portuguese service&#44; since the books formerly issued<lb/> by <persName>David Levy</persName> <add>&#63;</add> are not now to be had any more though often inquired<lb/> after.  Two years ago I wanted to undertake the same labour myself&#44;<lb/> but a <sic>sever</sic> illness&#44; the small&#45;pox&#44; kept me confined for several months&#44;<lb/> and my health has ever since continued too bad to permit me to<lb/> undertake so heavy a task.  Having been thus myself prevented by<lb/> the hand of God from accomplishing my design&#44; I am glad to see it under&#45;<lb/>taken by one who I hope is fully capable to do justice to the work.  If it is<lb/> well done&#44; I shall rejoice that it has been accomplished&#44; and shall use<lb/> my endeavours&#44; feeble as they are&#44; to forward the author&#39;s design.  If you<lb/> think proper you may communicate this to him&#44; altho&#39; I have never<lb/> had the pleasure of hearing any thing about him&#44; till I heard of his<lb/> prospectus some weeks since from a bookseller of eminence who belongs<lb/> to our congregation&#44; and not till this morning was the prospectus itself<lb/> placed in my hands.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am afraid I have detained you too long&#44; particularly by matters<lb/> not <sic>relevent</sic> to my inquiries&#44; if so I beg you to excuse me&#59; and to<lb/> forgive the errors of a stranger&#44; who speaks to a father and teacher<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#59; whom he would gladly personally see &#38; know.  May our<lb/> God preserve you many years in health and prosperity&#44; and may there<lb/> never be wanting one in your family to sit on the seat of judgment in <placeName>Israel</placeName>.</p>
				<p><add>Hebrew</add></p>
				<p><add>Hebrew</add> <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>My address is <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName> <placeName>Philadelphia Pennsylvania</placeName>.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
