<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Review of the Review of the Late Controversies between the Rev. Isaac
                    Leeser and the Philadelphia Congregation Mikveh Israel</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“An Israelite”</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Published at the office of the Asmonean</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item231</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“An
                            Israelite”</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1850">1850</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_back0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_back0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item231_wk1_front0001.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >pamphlet</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 14 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">OF</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">“THE REVIEW”</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">OF</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">THE LATE CONTROVERSY</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">BETWEEN THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <persName>REV. ISAAC LEESER</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)">AND THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> Congregation, “Mickve
                Israel;”</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">BY</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName role="author">AN ISRAELITE</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>NEW YORK</placeName>:</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">PUBLISHED AT THE <placeName>OFFICE OF THE
                ASMONEAN</placeName>,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>140 Nassau Street</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><date>1850</date>.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW OF “THE REVIEW”</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">OF THE LATE CONTROVERSY BETWEEN</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">THE <persName>REV. ISAAC LEESER</persName></p>
            <p rend="align(center)">AND THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="italics">CONGREGATION “MICKVE ISRAEL.”</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When men throw their private quarrels before the public,<lb/> they
                cease to be private, and that public to whom the appeal is<lb/> manifestly made, has
                the right to approve or disapprove, as facts<lb/> may demand. It is this feeling
                which prompts me to examine<lb/> the controversy, and through the Press, to proclaim
                the opinion<lb/> of an humble, but disinterested Israelite.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">There are but few occurrences in life which may not be
                pro-<lb/>ductive of good, and I can but trust that, though a good man may<lb/> be
                sacrificed to the malice of his enemies, yet that this controver<lb/>sy between
                    <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>, and the <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                congregation<lb/> Mickve Israel, will be productive of the happiest results, by
                im-<lb/>pressing the minds of the Jews of <placeName>America</placeName> with the
                necessity<lb/> of elevating the Priesthood, of making them Teachers of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>,<lb/> not the mere hirelings of a moment, the
                pliant tools of a Parnas<lb/> and Adjunta, who may, or may not be fit to rule. The
                paths of<lb/> duty of the two are entirely distinct. The Parnas and Adjunta<lb/>
                should manage the temporal concerns of the congregation, whilst<lb/> the Priest, or
                Hazan should teach, guide, control, and direct the<lb/> congregation. How can he be
                a Teacher unless he have power<lb/> in <hi rend="italics">all things</hi> pertaining
                to his office? How can he rebuke sin in<lb/> high places, perhaps the very sins of
                his petty tyrants, when he<lb/> is powerless, the mere servant of these very men?
                The idea,<lb/> then of making a Hazan a bonded officer, and of forcing him<lb/> to
                obtain leave of the Parnas before he may deliver a moral dis-<lb/>course, or perform
                the marriage or burial service, is altogether<lb/> repugnant to a just conception of
                his proper position, and whilst<lb/> such an idea obtains, he is no Teacher, no head
                of the flock, but a</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>4</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>mere tool and an underling. Any rule therefore which requires<lb/> a Teacher in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> to give a bond for the performance of his
                du-<lb/>ties—a bond, forsooth, that he shall be “<hi rend="italics"
                >devout”!!!</hi>—is a dis-<lb/>grace to the congregation, and at war with the spirit
                of the age.<lb/> Our Priests should “be clothed with righteousness,” men of<lb/>
                character, and able to teach and control their flock. The Hazan<lb/> should be
                elected as <persName>Mr. Carvallo</persName> was elected in <date>1815</date>— “<hi
                    rend="italics">noth-</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="italics">ing being said about the term of office.</hi>”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">These remarks bring me directly to the pamphlet under
                con-<lb/>sideration.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As regards “the regular <hi rend="italics">Hazanim</hi> who preceded
                    <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>,”<lb/> I have nothing to say—comparisons are
                odious—they may have<lb/> been intellectual “giants.” I take it for granted, that
                they were<lb/> undoubtedly men of worth—perhaps the superiors of <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName>.<lb/> I repeat I will institute no comparisons, but this much
                I will say,<lb/> that in our day and generation, <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>
                stands in<lb/> the general good that he has done in <placeName>America</placeName>,
                and those very<lb/> “English discourses” so <sic>delightingly</sic> spoken of in the
                pamphlet<lb/> under review, have done more to exalt the Jewish name in<lb/>
                <placeName>America</placeName>, to awaken a spirit of piety among our people,
                to<lb/> breathe life, and spiritually into our religion, than the ritual could<lb/>
                do in a thousand years, however dignified, and impressively it<lb/> may have been
                said. And here, too, I may remark, it is strange<lb/> that if <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName> has for years, hurried through our beautiful<lb/> ritual in
                “an undignified, and unimpressive manner,” that he<lb/> should have been retained as
                Hazan for more than twenty years,<lb/> have been <hi rend="italics">five</hi> times
                elected, and “that a majority of the mem-<lb/>bers would have been willing to have
                elected him for ten years<lb/> longer.” Alas! I fear the writer spoke from his
                prejudices,<lb/> rather than his judgment.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">At Page 6 of the pamphlet, we are told that “the Committee<lb/> on
                the subject of certain complaints against the <hi rend="italics">Shochet</hi> made
                a<lb/> report in which they recommended that the tenure of his office,<lb/> which
                before that time, was during the pleasure of the congre-<lb/>gation, should be
                turned into an annual term”—and again—“it<lb/> has always been the policy of the
                congregation to elect the Ha-<lb/>zan for a stipulated period, and the principle is
                the same as to the</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">5</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>Shochet.” What! are the Shochet and the Hazan to be compar-<lb/>ed? Are there no
                distinctions in society? no grades in the va-<lb/>rious callings of life? Do the
                butcher and the Minister of God—<lb/> the baker, and the lawyer—the blacksmith, and
                the physician<lb/> stand on the same platform? Politically they are equal, but
                no<lb/> farther. My minister, my spiritual guide and teacher, must be<lb/> my equal
                socially and otherwise, or he can not have a proper and<lb/> controlling influence
                over me. My butcher, or Shochet, may be<lb/> an honest man—I may respect him as
                such, but he can not be a<lb/> companion for me, or my family. And I am sure I
                hazard<lb/> nothing in saying that the Hazan, and Shochet of the congrega-<lb/>tion,
                do, and will ever, occupy very different stations in the minds<lb/> of all right
                thinking people in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, and every where else.<lb/>
                The comparison therefore, does not hold good—there is no analogy<lb/> in the duties
                of Hazan and Shochet, and the rules governing the<lb/> one, would be inapplicable to
                the other. The one is the highest<lb/> and holiest calling to which man can devote
                the energies of his<lb/> mind, the other a mere physical duty, which any one may
                per-<lb/>form; requiring neither mind nor morals, beyond that morality<lb/> which
                impels my barber, or tailor to do his work faithfully.—<lb/> When therefore, a
                candidate for the office of Hazan is a strang-<lb/>er to a congregation, it is
                perhaps well to take him for a limited<lb/> period on trial, and afterwards he
                should be elected, and have<lb/> nothing “<hi rend="italics">said about the term of
                    service.</hi>”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Judge's tenure, <hi rend="italics">dum bene se gesserint</hi>,
                may, or may not<lb/> be proper—but again, there is no analogy between these
                offices.<lb/> The life tenure of the Judge was created as a protection to the<lb/>
                liberties of the people. If he held his office at the will of a ty-<lb/>rant, he
                would pander to the tyrants pleasures—but again I see<lb/> no analogy between these
                offices. If the writer really desired<lb/> an analogous case, he should have
                referred to the Christian<lb/> Preacher, or the Jewish Priests of former days. Are,
                or were,<lb/> these elected from year to year? Do, or did they give bonds,<lb/> with
                money penalties for their good behaviour, for their “devout<lb/> manner?”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This idea of annual, or decennial elections, and of making the<lb/>
                Hazan a bonded officer, finds no sanction in the habits of the</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">1*</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>6</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>Jews in the palmy days of their nationality—none in the present<lb/> practice of the
                Christian world. For our sins we are dispersed<lb/> over the whole world. We have no
                temple—no regularly God-<lb/>appointed Priesthood, but if we desire our Hazanim,
                teachers in<lb/>
                <placeName>Israel</placeName>, men of worth, and piety, and really spiritual guides,
                we<lb/> must elevate the Ministry; we must draw a distinction between<lb/> things
                sacred and profane, we must raise our Hazan above our<lb/> Shochet.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But let us pass on to Page 8, where we are told that <persName>Mr.
                    Lee-<lb/>ser</persName> “was willing to hold himself out to the world as elected
                for<lb/> life, and yet take the office under a secret written engagement<lb/> with
                the congregation, converting its tenure into a <sic>tenantcy</sic> at<lb/> will,
                subject to be determined at any time by a bare majority<lb/> vote; which was the
                more degrading position, an open honorable<lb/> engagement for ten years, or a false
                representation to the world,<lb/> of an engagement for life, with the reality of a
                secret under-<lb/>standing that it was but a tenure at will? The congregation
                re-<lb/>fused to become a party to such a hypocritical proceeding.”—<lb/>Now I
                appeal to any candid man, and ask if such language is<lb/> proper, if the writer (as
                he states on his first page) really de-<lb/>sired to diffuse the light of truth,”
                and “to give a brief review<lb/> of the late controversies between <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName> and the congre-<lb/>gation?” Is this language supported by the
                    <hi rend="italics">facts</hi> of the case,<lb/> or rather, is it not,
                manifestly, the outpourings of bitterness, and<lb/> prejudice? <hi rend="italics"
                    >Let the pamphlet itself, answer these questions.</hi> At<lb/> Page 6, we find
                “that <persName>Abraham Hart, Esq.</persName>, Parnas, announced<lb/> from the
                Chair, that he was authorized by <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> to state to<lb/>
                the congregation, that if they adopted any other tenure of office,<lb/> than during
                good behavior, he would not be a candidate for re-<lb/>election, but adding in
                substance, that if he were elected during<lb/> good behavior, he was willing to hand
                in a written resignation of<lb/> his office, to take effect whenever called for by
                the congregation.”<lb/> Was this any thing like “a secret written engagement?”
                Was<lb/> this a false representation to the world? Did not <persName>Mr.
                    Hart</persName><lb/> proclaim it aloud, before the assembly, over which he
                presided?<lb/> Was it not known to the writer of the pamphlet, who is
                mani-<lb/>festly no friend of <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>; and can any one
                justly call this</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">7</p>
            <p>A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>a “secret engagement,” “a false representation,” “a hypocriti-<lb/>cal proceeding?”
                The truth is, <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> assumed the true<lb/> ground. The
                ground on which <persName>Mr. Carvalho's</persName> election was<lb/> placed. The
                ground taken by <persName>Mr. Lazarus</persName> in <date>1824</date>, and the<lb/>
                ground which I trust, will hereafter be taken by every Hazan<lb/> in
                    <placeName>America</placeName>. The tenure of the office of Hazan should be
                at<lb/> will. He should be bound to his congregation, and they to him,<lb/> by the
                bonds of love, and not of money penalties; and he should<lb/> serve no longer than
                was mutually agreeable, for no longer could<lb/> he be useful.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Let us <hi rend="italics">test this idea</hi> of making the Hazan a
                bonded officer,<lb/> for limited periods, say five, or ten years, and to do this,
                let us<lb/> examine the terms and character of the articles of agreement,<lb/> which
                may be found at Page 10, of the pamphlet. The Hazan<lb/> agrees to serve and
                officiate for ten years, during which time, he<lb/> is to perform the duties of the
                station—these duties are subse-<lb/>quently defined, viz: on <date>Sabbaths</date>
                and Holy days, to read the<lb/> prayers in devout manner in the original Hebrew. To
                attend<lb/> funerals &amp;c: to support and abide by, and obey the Charter<lb/> and
                Bye-Laws, and obey the legal orders of the Parnas. In<lb/> consideration of said
                services, the congregation agrees to pay<lb/> $1200 per ann. during the ten years in
                quarterly payments. And<lb/> for the due performance of the covenants, each party
                (Hazan<lb/> and congregation) binds himself in the penal sum of one thou-<lb/>sand
                dollars. Now as the covenant has <hi rend="italics">expressed precisely</hi>,
                what<lb/> each party is to do, no more could be claimed in law, or morals,<lb/> than
                what is therein expressed. It is therefore manifest that a<lb/> Hazan under that
                covenant would be entitled to recover his<lb/> salary, if he read the prayers in
                Hebrew, on <date>Sabbaths</date> and Holy<lb/> days, attended funerals, &amp;c.
                &amp;c., even though he lived in open vi-<lb/>olation of the moral law, and should
                ascend the <hi rend="italics">tebah</hi> dressed in<lb/> the most fantastic attire.
                I do not press this point of my argu-<lb/>ment too far. When men enter into written
                contracts, the con-<lb/>tract becomes to them, the law, and they can not go beyond it.<lb/>
                <hi rend="italics">Expressio unius, est exclusio alterius</hi>. Could the
                congregation<lb/> sue the bond, and <sic>alledge</sic> as a breach the bad moral
                character of<lb/> the Hazan, or if the Hazan were compelled to sue, would his</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>8</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>character be allowed in evidence? Certainly not. All this re-<lb/>minds me of an
                anecdote, of which I was personally cognizant.<lb/> A man presented himself as a
                candidate for Hazan—it was re-<lb/>marked that he was flippant in his manners,
                foppish in his<lb/> dress, and above all, of doubtful moral character. But said
                one<lb/> of his advocates, “have you heard him read—he has a magnifi-<lb/>cent
                voice,” and I suppose he might have added, “he would<lb/> read our beautiful Hebrew
                ritual in a dignified and impressive<lb/> manner.” Let me not be misunderstood—I am
                no reformer—I<lb/> love and venerate our beautiful Hebrew ritual. It is a noble
                lan-<lb/>guage—it is the mother of languages, and above all, it is sancti-<lb/>fied,
                by time, and the glorious recollection that it was the lan-<lb/>guage of our
                Prophets, and our Poet King, and that in it, God<lb/> spoke to his people amid the
                thunders of <placeName>Sinai</placeName>. Let it then be<lb/> read in a sonorous
                voice, and in a dignified, and impressive man-<lb/>ner; but let all this be
                secondary to the pure character, and moral<lb/> teachings of the Hazan.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But let us return to the pamphlet. At page 17 we find that a<lb/>
                vote of censure by the Adjunta was passed upon the Hazan,<lb/> (<persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName>) for an article which he published in the <hi rend="italics"
                    >Occident</hi><lb/> of <date>October</date> last. Now, if anything were wanting
                to show the<lb/> bitter persecution, and relentless hostility of <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser's</persName> ene-<lb/>mies, it will be found in this whole affair. It is
                marked by a ty-<lb/>ranny and oppression, that, thank God, finds no parallel in
                our<lb/> country, blessed as it is by free institutions, guaranteeing to every<lb/>
                one liberty of conscience, and protecting <hi rend="italics">the Liberty of the
                    Press.</hi><lb/> But this <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> Adjunta, riding
                above the spirit of the age,<lb/> would trammel the press, and entrenching
                themselves behind<lb/> the dignity of office, would punish by votes of censure any
                one<lb/> who would differ from them, or animadvert upon their conduct.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>, as Hazan, had certain duties to perform,
                specifical-<lb/>ly set forth in the Bond, and I cannot find among these duties
                any<lb/> that requires him to consult the Adjunta, as to what articles he<lb/> might
                write, or that inhibits him from scanning their votes on<lb/> any subject. But the
                whole affair seems to me extra-judicial—<lb/>an assumption of power, and strongly
                savoring of all the ingre-<lb/>dients of a libel. The Bond does not make him
                amenable to the</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">9</p>
            <p>A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>Adjunta, except as to marriage and funeral rites, and as he is<lb/> elected by the
                congregation, it alone should have the power of<lb/> censure. It is true that in
                political and national organizations,<lb/> there are tribunals created to try and
                punish officers and others<lb/> for misdemeanors, but surely a Hazan should be only
                responsi-<lb/>ble to the congregation—as the creating power. It will not avail<lb/>
                to reply that the congregation approved the action of the Board,<lb/> for no
                subsequent act can legalize an usurpation, the more espe-<lb/>cially when the rights
                of a third party are affected. And besides<lb/> this, it is manifest that though the
                Adjunta had attempted to<lb/> control and direct public opinion, still the
                congregation would<lb/> have allowed the resolutions to pass unnoticed, thereby
                tacitly ap-<lb/>proving the contemptuous silence of <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>,
                who properly<lb/> disdained to offer “any explanation, palliation or
                apology,”—“but<lb/> for an onslaught on the Board made by one or two of the
                Ha-<lb/>zan's indiscreet friends.” It was the conduct of the “friends”<lb/> then,
                that the congregation animadverted upon, and not the con-<lb/>duct of <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName>. Such being the true version of the affair, the<lb/>
                congregation committed the injustice of punishing <persName>Mr.
                Leeser</persName><lb/> for the indiscretion of his friends.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is right and proper that we return again to this idea of
                mak-<lb/>ing the Priest who ministers at the altar of God a bonded officer<lb/> for
                a specified period of time. I am no advocate for a <hi rend="italics">life
                    tenure</hi><lb/> for the same reasons that I object to any engagement for a <hi
                    rend="italics">limit-</hi><lb/><hi rend="italics">ed time.</hi> Suppose you
                engage a man for life, or for five or ten<lb/> years, how are you to get rid of him
                until the expiration of the<lb/> time of the agreement? He may perform his duties
                and yet be<lb/> obnoxious to the congregation, or they to him. You are bound<lb/>
                hand and foot together by the harsh chains of a stern agreement,<lb/> and not united
                by the silken cords of <sic>love.</sic> and the interchange<lb/> of mutual benefits
                and blessings. Nor does your Bond with a<lb/> money penalty mend the matter—it
                circumscribes the power of<lb/> the Hazan and congregation, and limits their rights
                to the terms<lb/> of the bond. Let then our Hazanim (except perhaps when<lb/>
                strangers to the congregation) be elected without any thing being<lb/> “said about
                the term of service,” and then the majority of the<lb/> congregation may dismiss, or
                the Hazan retire at pleasure. It</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>10</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>cannot be urged that this may leave a congregation without a<lb/> Hazan, for it
                cannot, in fairness, be supposed that the connection<lb/> would be dissolved without
                timely notice. But even supposing<lb/> the probability of this contingency, or that
                the Hazan may be<lb/> thrown penniless on the world, still it is far better for both
                par-<lb/>ties to have the congregation thus arranged, than to have Hazan<lb/> and
                congregation tied to each other, even after love, respect, and<lb/> power of
                usefulness were all departed. And again, this tenure<lb/> at will is a guarantee,
                worth all the bonds in the world, for mu-<lb/>tual forbearance, respect, and
                devotion to their respective duties.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">One word in conclusion, and that in relation to the pamphlet
                it-<lb/>self. To the <hi rend="italics">casual</hi> and careless observers (and
                these form a<lb/> large majority of readers), it would seem that this was an
                official<lb/> expose, a manifesto from the Adjunta. This impression is fairly<lb/>
                <sic>inferrible</sic> from the three first paragraphs of the pamphlet, and the<lb/>
                internal evidence that the books, papers, and minutes of the Ad-<lb/>junta must have
                been under the free control of the writer. And<lb/> yet I for <sic>oneam</sic> sure
                that it is not an <hi rend="italics">official production</hi>, firstly,
                be-<lb/>cause it is not declared to be so; and secondly, because it is
                anon-<lb/>ymous, and even the very office from which it is issued is
                con-<lb/>cealed. The writer of the pamphlet is evidently a man of talent<lb/> and of
                education, and his sense of justice should have induced<lb/> him to have declared
                    <hi rend="italics">in express terms</hi>, that he wrote on his own<lb/>
                individual responsibility, and not to have left so important a fact<lb/> in doubt.
                But there are other objections to the pamphlet, of a<lb/> more serious character. It
                charges a man, who for the fifth part<lb/> of a century has been the Hazan of one of
                the most respectable<lb/> congregations in <placeName>America</placeName>, with
                false representations, hypocrisy,<lb/> violation of duty, and a childish vanity that
                induced him to sacri-<lb/>fice his holy official duties to “one engrossing fancy.”
                And does<lb/> the “light of truth” thus daguerreotype the character of
                    <persName>Isaac<lb/> Leeser</persName>? No, no, no, and such would be the echo
                and response<lb/> of ninety-nine hundredths of the Jews of
                    <placeName>England</placeName> and <placeName>America</placeName>.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> is “neither more nor less than a man,” he has
                the<lb/> faults and the frailties of humanity. His quick sensibility, his<lb/>
                ardent temperament, may, and perhaps do, rob him of that suavi-<lb/>ty of manner,
                which, like the tinsel glitter of false ornaments, too</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">11</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A REVIEW.</p>
            <p>often deceives and deludes. But he is honest, capable, intelligent,<lb/> stands high
                in public estimation, and should be the pride, as he is<lb/> an ornament, of our
                nation.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">For myself, I have no personal object to attain. My desire was<lb/>
                to protect and vindicate the private character and public useful-<lb/>ness of one
                who is “a great man in <placeName>Israel</placeName>,” and whose writings<lb/> will
                cause him to be remembered when his detractors shall be<lb/> forgotten.</p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><persName role="author">AN ISRAELITE</persName>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
