<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item64</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item64_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item64_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item64_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item64_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item64_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 5 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>
                <placeName>
                    <hi rend="underline">Albany</hi>
                </placeName>
            </p>
            <p>During <date>Passover</date> as we learn from our present<add>?</add>
                correspon<lb/>dent the first semi annual public examination of the children
                attached<lb/> to the school lately organized by the <persName>Reverend Dr.
                    Wise</persName> took place. The<lb/> examination was conducted under the
                presidency of the President of the Beth-el con-<lb/>gregation, assited by the School
                committee and the Reader, the <persName>Rev. Mr. Traub</persName>.<lb/> A very
                interesting introductory address was delivered by a male scholar of the<lb/> first
                class, after which that <del>first</del> class was examined by <persName>Dr.
                    Wise</persName> on Catechism<lb/> &amp; lessons in religion. The female teacher,
                    <persName>Miss Chaplin</persName> to whose execution<add>?</add><lb/> the
                greatest credit is due, and who is a teacher any school may be proud of,<lb/>
                examined in Spelling, Reading, Arithmetic &amp; Geography. <persName>Dr.
                    Wise</persName> also exami<lb/>ned in reading the Prayer Book &amp; Pentateuch,
                and much praise is due<lb/> to the Rabbi for his labours in teaching the scholars
                the true way of becoming<lb/> what they ought to be. The specimens of writing also
                afforded proof of<lb/> astonishing progress <del>for</del> during the first six
                months of the existence of the school.<lb/> The sight the examination presented, is
                said to have been a pleasant one, and it<lb/> was delightful to witness parents
                watching with great anxiety, to observe<lb/> whether their wishes would <del>be
                        <add>?</add>
                </del> be gratified, and their children would indeed<lb/> become learned; but the
                progress then exhibited inspired them with the<lb/> confident hope, that they would
                not be disappointed with the blessing of Hea-<lb/>ven. The examination over, prizes
                were distributed to the deserving<lb/> scholars, and the whole was concluded by an
                address from a female<lb/>
                <del>scholar</del> pupil of the first class. <del>We could use</del></p>
            <p><placeName><hi rend="underline">St. Thomas</hi></placeName>.</p>
            <p><persName>Mr. A. Wolff</persName> the lately appointed president of the
                congrega<lb/>tion of <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName>, held a fair at his house on
                the <date>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi></date> &amp; <date>3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> of
                    March</date> for the benefit of the Sunday school<lb/> of that place, and we are
                happy to state that it realized the handsome sum<lb/> of five hundred Dollars.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline"><placeName>Russia</placeName> &amp; the Jews</hi>.</p>
            <p>We see it stated in the papers that the <persName>Emperor<lb/> Nicholas</persName>
                has lately issued a new edict which orders that Jews in<lb/> the military service
                shall not be held to do <add>?</add> duties on <date>Sabbath</date>,<lb/> &amp; holy
                days, but be left at leisure to attend <add>?</add> worship. Also that<lb/> Hebrew
                may advance to the rank of lieutenant. Both these<lb/> regulations are certainly a
                great concession and an improvement<lb/> upon the <add>?</add> policy of the
                Russians, especially the former, which<lb/> gives Israelites opportunities to attend
                to this religions requirements. We<lb/> trust therefore that the report which has
                reached us may be true, &amp;<lb/> we can only believe it to be so, without assuming
                a cordial change of<lb/> policy in the Czar toward the Jews, as he acts often
                    <sic>acts</sic> from the caprice<lb/> of the moment, as many of his <add>?</add>
                too will demonstrate.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>My address is <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
                <placeName>Philadelphia Pennsylvania</placeName>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I should like to ask your opinion upon many other points from time to<lb/> time, if
                you would permit me, to address you occasionally; what I trust<lb/> you will grant
                me, and I assure you, that you still never need blame<lb/> yourself for the favour
                granted. If you can conveniently do it,<lb/> please to make your reply in English,
                that it may be extensively<lb/> circulated. Answer this if you can by the earliest
                packet, since<lb/> not I alone but many other persons are anxious for your
                opinion.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have seen with pleasure that <persName>Mr De Sola</persName> has
                undertaken<lb/> a new edition of the Portuguese service, since the books formerly
                issued<lb/> by <persName>David Levy</persName>
                <add>?</add> are not now to be had any more though often inquired<lb/> after. Two
                years ago I wanted to undertake the same labour myself,<lb/> but a <sic>sever</sic>
                illness, the small-pox, kept me confined for several months,<lb/> and my health has
                ever since continued too bad to permit me to<lb/> undertake so heavy a task. Having
                been thus myself prevented by<lb/> the hand of God from accomplishing my desires, I
                am glad to see it under-<lb/>taken by one who I hope is fully capable to do justice
                to the work. If it is<lb/> well done, I shall rejoice that it has been accomplished,
                and shall use<lb/> my endeavours, feeble as they are, to forward the author's
                design. If you<lb/> think proper you may communicate this to him, altho' I have
                never<lb/> had the pleasure of hearing any thing about him, till I heard of his<lb/>
                prospectus some weeks since from a bookseller of eminence, who belongs<lb/> to our
                congregation, and not till this morning was the prospectus itself<lb/> placed in my
                hands.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I am afraid I have detained you too long, particularly by
                matters<lb/> not relevant to my <sic>enquiries</sic>, if so I beg you to excuse me;
                and to<lb/> forgive the errors of a stranger, who speaks to a father and
                teacher<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>; whom he would gladly personally see
                &amp; know. May our<lb/> God preserve you many years in health and prosperity, and
                may there<lb/> never be wanting one in your family to sit on the seat of judgment in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>.</p>
            <p>
                <add>I have seen with pleasure that חזן</add>
            </p>
            <p><add>כ"ד עב אדוני המונו לשרתו ה"ק יצחק אילן כל כ"ה אורי ליפמן אליעזר</add>
                <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
            <p>Specimen of <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser's</persName><lb/> Handwriting</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>week, and after he has got a house his father and mother are to<lb/> follow. As he
                has now an office it is possible that the congregation<lb/> may restore my salary;
                but I doubt it much. From <placeName>Charleston</placeName> I<lb/> hear that it is
                likely that <persName>Mr. Poznanski</persName> will be elected for life<lb/> at the
                expiration of his present term; his salary now is 1500,<lb/> from orphan society for
                6 boys 144; house say 150; perquisites<lb/> &amp; other scholars at least 250, which
                is an aggregate exceeding<lb/> 2000; against which I have been elected four times
                and all<lb/> I got from teaching, marrying and salary may amount to 875 and<lb/> not
                a farthing more. Of course <persName>Mr. Poznansky</persName> is popular; but<lb/>
                who more than myself nobody can tell. <persName>Mr Hart</persName> had a rest<lb/>
                <add>?</add> raising my salary; but there being no quorum a <add>?</add><lb/> the
                last meeting the whole must lay over till <date>September</date>, near<lb/> five
                months longer. My salary due <date>March 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> has not
                been paid<lb/> yet. But enough of this, all talking does not alter the whole<lb/>
                affair one cent; and only irritates me when I think of it.<lb/> Have my books I left
                gone to <placeName>Washington</placeName>?<lb/> Give my love to aunt &amp; all the
                family &amp; believe me</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">yours respectfully</p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">
                <persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
