<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item150</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Kingston, Jamaica</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1858-12">20 December 1858</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item150_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 9 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Kingston Jam</placeName>: <date>20<hi rend="sup"
                        >th</hi>. Decr. 1858</date>.</p>
            <p>
                <addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Dear Friend.</p>
            <p rend="indent(2)">The Occidents for <date>October</date> have come<lb/> to hand, but
                no letter from you. By this time you will have<lb/> received my last p
                    <persName>Abby Watson</persName> requesting you to obtain<lb/> 50 copies of my
                catechism from the Sunday School in your city.<lb/> I have not a copy, and none are
                to be had here. I wish you<lb/> also to forward a couple dozen of <persName>Miss
                        <sic>Peixottos</sic></persName> Book, and about<lb/> 3 dozen
                    <persName>Henry's</persName> Class Books, of the Edition published in
                    <placeName>America</placeName>.<lb/> On consideration you need <hi
                    rend="underline">not</hi> send <persName>Miss P's</persName> Books for
                    <persName>Henry's</persName><lb/> will answer my purpose as well. I require also
                about 1 dz<lb/> copies of <hi rend="underline"><persName>Cohen's</persName> Hebrew
                    Grammar</hi> on the <hi rend="underline"
                        ><persName>Ellendorff<add>?</add></persName> system</hi><lb/> which you will
                oblige me by procuring. All these books I want<lb/> without delay, and the money
                shall be remitted as soon as<lb/> they arrive. On the <sic>inclosed</sic> tracing
                paper is the pattern of<lb/> the binding of a book, side and back. Send one of your
                daily<lb/> prayers (<sic>portuguese</sic>) similarly bound, color red maroon
                approaching to<lb/> red morocco. I had sold another copy of the Festival
                prayers<lb/> and if I get the money for them before an opportunity offers for
                forwarding<lb/> this, the money <del>not</del> I have in hand ($60) with that
                (nearly $20)<lb/> will be sent by same via. I have still on hand the 2 best
                bound<lb/> sets, 91 Vol deft.) and part of one set common sheep (3 deft.). If<lb/>
                your small Bibles were a dollar or $1 ½ each I could sell them<lb/> readily but 2 ½
                people decline to give.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Have you ever felt an Earthquake? For a quarter of a century</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>I have been familiar with them, and their nature is such that,<lb/> totally different
                from other dangers to which one gets accustomed<lb/> They excite and increase our
                fears the oftener their shock is felt.<lb/> You become paralyzed, your faculties are
                suspended, the<lb/> will ceases to act on the voluntary parts of the body, and
                tho'<lb/> fully alive to the horrors of entombment, whether in or out of<lb/> doors,
                which threaten your life, you are incapable of making<lb/> the effort to move from
                the spot. To ejaculate a word or two<lb/> of prayer <del>and</del> in prospect of an
                immediate and awful death<lb/> which hundreds may share with you at the same moment
                is<lb/> all that your consciousness of the alarming extent of your peril<lb/> and
                the impossibility of escaping it, permits you to do. When<lb/> the earthquake is
                felt in the day time, a rush from the house to<lb/> the street may be effected by
                some <del>one</del> whom fear does not render<lb/> incapable of moving. At night
                however, when enfolded in the bonds<lb/> of sleep, you become suddenly awakened by
                the house shaking<lb/> and riding on its foundation, the <sic>upheaved</sic> and
                undulating<lb/> earth on which it rests, then can one realize in all its
                positive<lb/> meaning the <add>פחד לילה</add> the Psalmist speaks of. Not the bad
                dream<lb/> not the distressing night-mare, not the terrifying images which<lb/> a
                heated brain, a sickly fancy, or a superstitious mind<lb/> conjures up—but it is the
                awe of an instant dissolution, a<lb/> stern summons to give up life in a few seconds
                which stops<lb/> the beating of the heart, checks the current of the blood, and<lb/>
                    “<sic>distils</sic> you to jelly with the effect of fear.”</p>
            <p>On <date>Thursday at ½ past 1 A M (23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Decr.</date>) the whole
                city was<lb/> on the verge of destruction from one of the severest earthquakes<lb/>
                I ever yet felt. A few seconds longer, say 3 or 4 and every</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>building would have fallen in and buried its inmates alive.<lb/> Truly, “God is
                merciful” or I would now not be writing.<lb/> Imagine, if you can, the house
                    <del>riding</del> being lifted and down, rocking<lb/> from side to side, the
                walls shaking, beams, joists, rafters<lb/> roof, cracking, creaking as yielding to
                the irresistible force<lb/> of the subterranean movements, one and all writhed and
                struggled<lb/> to disjoint itself from mortise and tenon, to wrench itself from<lb/>
                the hold of girder, screw, and nail. My wife and I were awake<lb/> when it began. It
                must have lasted 15 seconds, some say half a<lb/> minute. Neither of us could move;
                both were calm &amp; collected. I<lb/> never, during the agonizing interval,
                indulged the slightest hope<lb/> of deliverance, but momentarily expected to see the
                walls give way and<lb/> the roof fall in and crush us to death. Short as was
                the<lb/> continuance of the horrid throes of our “mother and our
                grave<add>?</add>”<lb/> they have left a never to be forgotten remembrance. Thanks
                be to<lb/> the Almighty, no life was lost, no one injured. But I fear that<lb/>
                every building has been so shaken that in case of a similar recur-<lb/>rence there
                may be loss of life and destruction of property.<lb/> Shortly after the occurrence,
                several places of worship were opened<lb/> and thronged by <sic>worshippers</sic>
                scared and trembling with affright. My<lb/> wife begged me not to leave her, and
                therefore I did not go. The<lb/> night was beautiful, moon and stars shining
                brilliantly, the<lb/> air cool and fresh. The occultation of Saturn took place
                that<lb/> night. There are many mining enterprises going forward on the<lb/>
                <placeName>Island</placeName>, and as the work is carried on through the whole 24
                    <del>years</del> hours<lb/> fears were entertained for the safety of the miners,
                but no accident<lb/> has been heard of, altho' the earthquake was severely felt
                in<lb/> the mining district.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Have you seen <persName>Dr. Kalisch's</persName> translation of
                Genesis. From<lb/> a review of it in the “Westminster Review,” whose tendencies<lb/>
                are rationalistic I have gleaned an extract or two. He has<lb/> not been more
                fortunate in his rendering of <add>לא יסור שבט</add> than his<lb/> predecessors. I
                do not like <add>עד כי יבא שילה</add> “tho' many flock to
                    <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>.”<lb/> You may differ from me in opinion, but I
                prefer the translation<lb/> given in the “Israelite,” and <del>?</del> the more I
                examine and<lb/> consider it with reference to history, the more am I convinced<lb/>
                of its truth. <persName>Onkelos</persName> and the masora have led the whole
                Jewish<lb/> and Christian world astray. <add>שבט</add> occurs 3 times in the
                chapter<lb/> and why the first time it should be translated “<hi rend="underline"
                    >sceptre or</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">staff</hi> and the second &amp; 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> “<hi
                    rend="underline">tribes</hi>” I cannot understand. Again<lb/> why
                    <add>עמרם</add> should not apply to the “confederated Israelites” when<lb/>
                <persName>Judah</persName> is blessed, and understood to allude to a portion of<lb/>
                that confederacy under the leadership of <persName>David</persName> and “<add>דן
                    ידין עמו</add>” is<lb/> also an enigma to me. The passage is very simple, if the
                legitim<lb/>ate rendering of <add>שבט</add>
                <del>be</del> as “tribe” be given. Not shall depart<lb/> a tribe from
                    <persName>Judah</persName>, nor a commander from between his feet<lb/> from
                among his followers until he come to <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>, and to him
                    (<persName>Judah</persName>)<lb/> should be the gathering (assembling,
                marshalling, in array) of the<lb/> people The armed confederacy as it existed from
                the Exodus<lb/> to the division of the land among the tribes, was dissolved at<lb/>
                <placeName>Shiloh</placeName>, by <persName>Joshua</persName>. And the best proof
                that <persName>Judah</persName> was then<lb/> divested of the leadership is the
                divine permission to rescue<lb/> in Judges <add>?</add> for a temporary purpose.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">So our friend <persName>Gutheim</persName> is going to be married. I
                am<lb/> glad to hear of it, and wish him all happiness. Your<lb/> intended
                    <del>periodically</del> weekly ought to succeed such an array of<lb/> talent
                taste and industry as <persName>Jacob</persName>, <persName>Raphall</persName> &amp;
                yourself<lb/> is not often to be met with, and in the ranks of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> is<lb/> an anomaly considering that our utterances
                rarely combine<lb/> to advance the General Good. I am glad the Pope still<lb/>
                refuses to give up the child of mortara; his obstinacy will<lb/> the sooner bring on
                the crisis in which the Papacy and<lb/> its supporters (<persName>Louis
                    Napoleon</persName> &amp; <placeName>Austria</placeName>) will be crushed.</p>
            <p rend="The following is written sideways over the above text."/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The proceedings of the Habane Bushi<add>?</add> at
                    <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> are<lb/> very mischievous. United
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> in <placeName>Europe</placeName> should by means
                of<lb/> its enlightened Rabbi's abolish the power of Cherem &amp; <add>?</add><lb/>
                and the whole of this irresponsible power so insolently assumed by<lb/> such fellows
                as the Turkish Rabbis. All this is the effect of the<lb/> dangerous precedents set
                by the Rabbinism<add>?</add> of the dark middle<lb/> ages, and its usurpation of a
                power which men like <persName>Akiba</persName> would<lb/> never have tolerated for
                an instant. It will be unquestionably<lb/> beneficial to the Turkish Jews Generally
                that their Rabbis have<lb/> aimed so high as the <persName>Rothschilds</persName>
                and <persName>Albert Cohen</persName>, who will now<lb/> keep them to break the
                gallery chain which ignorant zeal has bound<lb/> them. What say you? Is this stupid
                orthodoxy less dangerous to <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> than cold
                rationalism? I say no.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> and her mother unite with me<lb/>
                in kind and friendly regards and trusting that you are<lb/> more cheerful and in
                higher spirits than when you last<lb/> wrote</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">I am</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">yours sincerely</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)">
                <persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
