<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item89</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Barnard,
                            George</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Sherbrooke, Canada East</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1849-02">12 February 1849</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="">12 February 5609</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 8 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>My dear Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your kindness in forwarding the <date>Feby</date> No. of the
                Oc-<lb/>cident claims my grateful thanks. Its contents at once show the<lb/>
                lamentable state of disunion upon matters in connection with<lb/> religion amongst
                Israelites in <placeName>America</placeName>, and sufficiently<lb/> exhibit the
                    <sic>impracticability</sic> of your inserting my commu<lb/>nication, up to this
                time. There may be other reasons<lb/> wherefore you think it improper. In the
                absence of a spe<lb/>cial explanation, I can only, and but imperfectly, infer
                your<lb/> views from the course of proceedings. Had the Occident contained<lb/> an
                indication of liberty to proceed in addressing your readers,<lb/> this letter would,
                agreeably to intimation, have <sic>inclosed</sic> a<lb/> year's subscription, as I
                would not remain under obligation<lb/> for worldly favour, when it is avoidable. But
                since the seeking<lb/> of your assistance is, or ought to be, solely in obedience
                to<lb/> spiritual mandates which I dare not disregard, I must learn<lb/> in some
                way, if possible, to what extent your good will or good<lb/> opinion towards my
                business may be counted upon. To purchase<lb/> and pay for the Occident while
                containing nothing in this regard,<lb/> would make me no wiser in that respect. If
                you insert<lb/> or discuss my letters, I can then learn your views on them;<lb/> if
                you are so liberal as to continued the transmission of the Oc-<lb/>cident without
                expectation of payment, it must be from some spe<lb/>cial consideration; and if you
                withdraw it, while aware how ne<lb/>cessary it is to me to learn by its medium the
                prospect of the pro<lb/>posed assembly. I shall be nonetheless enabled to appreciate
                your<lb/> estimation in my behalf. I am the more anxious to learn, from<lb/>
                practical demonstration, your judgment concerning me be<lb/>cause the very
                extraordinary situation in which I am placed<lb/> overwhelms my weak and unsettled
                mind with the dread of<lb/> misconceiving my duty. By carefully comparing ideas
                with<lb/> the differently affected yet interested and able to discover the<lb/>
                truth, I may test the soundness of conceptions, which, without</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>some corroboration, must incur distrust. The <sic>inclosed</sic> $1.00 I beg you
                to<lb/> accept on act. Of some No's of the O. formerly sent me at <placeName>New
                    York</placeName>; or if you<lb/> would decline it on that ground, let it be to
                defray postage which may occur.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">One would think that, while so desirous of bringing my views<lb/>
                before some authority in <placeName>Israel</placeName>, I should greatly rejoice in
                the pros<lb/>pect of an Assembly and their doings, as now before us; but
                reflec<lb/>tion upon the issue of my formal application to the Beth Din in<lb/>
                <placeName>New York</placeName> as I reported it to you, teaches me to expect little
                from<lb/> any body of men who may be actuated by a dread of compromi<lb/>sing their
                character for wisdom. Yet as our excellent friend <persName>Mr.<lb/>
                Noot</persName>, <persName>Dr. Salomon</persName> and another passed a resolution
                that my repre<lb/>sentations were worthy of attention and ought to be investigated
                &amp;<lb/> reported on by two or more persons of the first distinction for
                learning<lb/> devotion, character and understanding, I must not fail, if the
                venerable<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName> come together, to apply for the
                relection of a suitable<lb/> committee, who after free and full communication, shall
                formally de<lb/>clare their views of the matter submitted to their
                consideration.<lb/> If you would do me the greatest kindness, if you would
                become<lb/> nobly instrumental in relieving the deepest anxieties of a mind<lb/>
                that seeks to ascertain its duties in order to their discharge, you<lb/> have but to
                forward by every means in your power my honest<lb/> aim to bring the teachings of
                this extraordinary state of mind<lb/> fairly and fully before the Jewish public for
                their consideration<lb/> To my private desires, it would seem to be of little
                importance how<lb/> men should entertain these disclosures provided the decision
                could<lb/> be final. What makes me anxious is that whilst my thoughts<lb/> are
                absorbed as they are and must be for the present, my<lb/> wife and children are
                suffering for the want of attention<lb/> which is their due, and which I cannot give
                them, as my<lb/> faculties are insufficient under such a distraction. It
                appears<lb/> that I must either become an active, however humble, servant<lb/> of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, or, obtaining some conscientious satisfaction
                that will</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>authorize the withdrawal of my attention from the subject, devote<lb/> the more
                energy to pursuits of a private nature. Could I but learn<lb/> by a reasonable
                decision of the judgments of others upon these un<lb/>common views, that they must
                pass for either erroneous or im<lb/>practicable, gladly would I hail the liberty to
                apply to the cares<lb/> labours and pleasures of my family and farm; gladly
                would<lb/> I strive to join in the common and selfish pursuits of life:<lb/> but
                while the best and soundest with whom I am enabled to con<lb/>verse, approve and
                even reverence my views, while those who<lb/> censure are evidently inconsiderate in
                their examinations, while<lb/> it is not only what has been manifested to an excited
                percep<lb/>tion; but a calm examination of all current events of every sort<lb/>
                leads to a like conclusion,—and while, to my utter amazement,<lb/> the whole seems
                indicated in the prophecies of old, how can<lb/> I doubt the evidence that presents
                itself to one purpose in<lb/> so many different ways, when that purpose is but the
                es<lb/>tablishment of a government recognizing, what sound sense re<lb/>quires, as a
                leading principle, the accountability of man to his<lb/> maker?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I do not appeal to you for the sake of
                <placeName>Israel</placeName>, for you<lb/> are sufficiently bound already to that
                consideration. I plead<lb/> not for the good of mankind in general, for you
                comprehend<lb/> as well as I the connection between the Restoration and the
                spread<lb/> of intelligence, uprightness and peace. But as the Lord so<lb/> orders
                that even in our highest aims we are influenced more<lb/> or less by private
                regards; as He kindly grants the grateful<lb/> stimulus of selfish satisfaction in
                our most sacred aspira<lb/>tions; and as we are humble men, of limited capacities,
                yet<lb/> generous and sympathetic feelings; I will endeavour to elicit<lb/> your
                sensibilities in my favour by appealing to your knowledge<lb/> as a spiritual
                teacher and your heart as my brother man, in<lb/> regard to my private position as a
                religious individual. I have</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>two children, sweet little girls, the eldest but two years of age, whom<lb/> I would
                bring up in the knowledge and fear of the Lord. I am<lb/> an Israelite in faith, if
                I know what it is to be an Israelite—<lb/> namely, to live under a perfect sense of
                accountability to God,<lb/> aiming in all things to do that which is right in His
                view; there<lb/>fore necessarily adopting the high wisdom of inspiration in the<lb/>
                formation of rules of conduct, and devoutly seeking self-improvement<lb/> and the
                general good in associating with others disposed to wor<lb/>ship and serve God in
                purity and truth. I would say with pi<lb/>ous <persName>Joshua</persName> “as for me
                and my house, we will serve the Lord.”—<lb/> but how? Shall I take my family to a
                Christian Church to hear<lb/> that belief in absurdity is the vital condition of
                happiness hereafter.<lb/> Shall we cultivate ignorance, and avoid participating in
                any estab<lb/>lished form of worship—to the effect that <add>?</add> be heaped
                upon<lb/> my innocents as being trained to error and infidelity? Or shall<lb/> I
                crave admission from a Jewish congregation, to join in prayer<lb/> for the advent of
                a Messiah, instead of returning thanks for<lb/> the appointment of a special and
                most distinguished service—<lb/> shall I enter such a congregation on condition of
                allegiance<lb/> to all the existing Laws and customs, when I do not intend<lb/> to
                obey them, and the very perception which makes me desire<lb/> religious association,
                also assures me that many of those u<lb/>sages and institutions are now needless,
                some of them wrong,<lb/> and that it is my especial calling to be humbly
                instru<lb/>mental in their reform? Which shall I adopt, of these er<lb/>roneous
                courses? Or rather what <hi rend="underline">can</hi> I do but prayerfully<lb/>
                trust in the Divine Goodness to relieve my perplexities<lb/> in due time, and strive
                by every means to bring my views<lb/> to be compared with those of others whose
                superior attainments<lb/> entitle them to respect and confidence, while their vital
                wants, the<lb/> proper longing of their souls, must stimulate them to discover
                and<lb/> approve and establish the truth if truth it be, which I have to
                disclose</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">2</p>
            <p>I can see no other course to be right; and therefore do I thus beseech
                assistance.<lb/> For some half year more, according to a remarkable impression, must
                I<lb/> remain in this uncertainty and trouble: if by that time there be not a<lb/>
                clearing up of difficulties I shall have cause to respect a radi<lb/>cal error in
                these sublime perceptions.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You once wrote me the story of <persName>Shaman</persName> and
                    <persName>Hillel</persName> and one who<lb/> would become a Jew with the
                condition of being made High Priest.<lb/> The case is no parallel to mine; I desire
                no distinction—far less the<lb/> accountability of power. I have lived forty years
                without at any time<lb/> being led by political ambition or religious zeal. True
                heroes, in my<lb/> view, are those who, keeping within their means, devoutly apply
                themselves<lb/> to the common duties of life. What devotion I have exercised may
                have<lb/> been far surpassed in the experience of many religious minds amongst<lb/>
                us. It is prophecy a startling glimpse of the natural course of events,<lb/> and
                their causes, showing the unfailing means established for the pro<lb/>duction of
                good, which it only devolves upon men to observe and employ,<lb/> that this impels
                me to so strange a course. What should I care<lb/> for worldly appearances? What is
                it to me if my conduct seem<lb/> unaccountable and absurd to those who know not its
                motives?<lb/> I must only hasten to bring matters to a crisis, to attain
                facil<lb/>ities for efficient action, or freedom to forbear from futile
                endeavours.<lb/> Will you not help me? Do I ask more than naturally pertains
                between<lb/> man and man? You admit that the developments of the day indicate<lb/>
                the present as a fit time for rising in behalf of <placeName>Israel</placeName>. Let
                it then<lb/> be decided whether I may lawfully and properly undertake to act<lb/> in
                this good cause in conjunction with the chosen servants of the<lb/> most High. If
                you say that I am not a Jew, let me ask, was<lb/>
                <persName>Abraham</persName> other, in that respect, than I am? Or did
                    <persName>Moses</persName><lb/> submit to a string of rabbinical exactions?
                Supposing he had,<lb/> it would be no rule for me. The useless part of these
                observances<lb/> must be done away. The general forms of Jewish worship are as<lb/>
                grand in effect as venerable from antiquity. But many spe<lb/>cial institutions
                which were founded in good reason from the ex<lb/>igency of circumstances, have now
                no effect but a detrimental in</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>fluence. Long have the people groaned under these absurd incum<lb/>brances; and what
                is worse, forsaken the faith of their fathers,<lb/> to escape form such annoying
                accomplishments. In assisting to re<lb/>tain these evils, you become answerable for
                their natural conse<lb/>quences. It needs but to prune away such exhausting,
                useless<lb/> and unsightly branches—it needs but to exhibit the pure princi<lb/>ples
                of religious faith under a rational and modest form,<lb/> and the tree of
                righteousness will flourish, take root in the earth,<lb/> unfold its blossoms to the
                world, give fragrance to the airs<lb/> of heaven, and yield reproductive fruit
                spreading abroad<lb/> for the delight and shade and comfort of regenerate man.<lb/>
                The pure Jewish faith, the simple belief in omnipresent Deity, to whom<lb/> we are
                strictly accountable, must become the religion of the world,<lb/> not because it is
                written that the Lord declared so by His prophet<lb/> not because it bears a
                fascinating show to the imagination<lb/> for it does not, but because it is <hi
                    rend="underline">the truth</hi>, and men are becom<lb/>ing sufficiently
                enlightened and considerate to distinguish sim<lb/>ple truth from seductive
                falsehood. Let the Jew once stand<lb/> a free man in his own country, and the
                brawling nations will<lb/> let fall their weapons in astonishment, acknowledge in
                their heart<lb/> the truth of revelation, and incline to turn from the errors of
                their<lb/> ways. Then may peace and reason and kindness prevail; for<lb/> men,
                become more reflective, will see it for their interests to<lb/> cultivate good
                dispositions. The best minds among gentiles will<lb/> associate themselves with the
                already established Jews. Dif<lb/>ferent races will thus intermingle without
                violence to law<lb/> or custom. By this means a large portion of subsequent
                generations<lb/> will be born under the ameliorating influence of those natural<lb/>
                laws hereby increase of vigor is given to cross breeds.<lb/> The ancient blood of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> serving as a basis, a foreign admix<lb/>ture to a
                certain extent, will benefit the race, promoting the<lb/> development of its
                energies, and marking the Jews, as a people,</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>with such physical and mental superiority, as must inevitably<lb/> render them
                masters amongst mankind. The use they will make<lb/> of power, must depend, in a
                great measure, upon the purity of<lb/> their religious principles: and it therefore
                devolves the more<lb/> fearfully upon us, if it please God to employ our weak
                hands<lb/> in this His good work, to aim at the highest perfection in<lb/> whatever
                rules and practices we may <add>?</add> to establish.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It is observable from the records of history, as well as
                re<lb/>searches into nature, that the chief means whereby a race ar<lb/>rives at a
                high standard of perfection is the copulation of pa<lb/>rentage bringing together
                somewhat dissimilar constitutions:<lb/> yet, when one of the parties is highly
                cultivated, extreme oppo<lb/>sition does not answer the purpose: thus the refined
                white<lb/> and the barbarous negro or Indian cannot be intermixture<lb/> bring
                improvement to the superior; and the effect is ques<lb/>tionable even upon the
                inferior race. In a mind of much<lb/> refinement is established a deep repugnance to
                the coarse<lb/>ness of ignorance and vulgarity; for it is decreed that<lb/> when
                such excellence is once attained, it ought not to be<lb/> thrown away: yet the two
                sexes are established, that, by<lb/> continental intermixture of different
                constitutions, offspring<lb/> may arise inheriting the general characteristics,
                which<lb/> it is our business to establish in ourselves, of both<lb/> parents; and
                not the particular defects which may be<lb/> beyond our control, of either.
                Intermarriages therefore are<lb/> predicated upon a positive, though not extreme,
                dissimilar<lb/>ity of constitution in the parties, while they are as
                necessarily<lb/> influence by similarity of sentiments, habits and pursuits.<lb/> It
                is then plain that the restored Jews, together with those no<lb/>ble</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>-ble-minded from other nations, who will dare to cast off the<lb/> fetters of error
                and prejudice, must operate under every<lb/> beneficial influence to produce the
                most powerful and highly<lb/> gifted race of which we can conceive, precisely in
                accord-<lb/>ance with undeviating and well known laws of nature. There<lb/> is no
                record of a people becoming, either on the whole or at any<lb/> particular time,
                great and powerful in all respects, whose<lb/> physical excellence is not to be
                traced directly to the inter-<lb/>mingling of different races or dissimilar tribes.
                Thus, under<lb/> ordinary circumstances, a conquest<add>?</add> however lamentable
                to the<lb/> humbled people becomes the means, under God, of health<lb/> and blessing
                to posterity. If a nation could but comprehend<lb/> their duty, if a government
                would only provide, by ade-<lb/>quate and strictly natural means; for the
                development<lb/> of every inherent energy of man, and for preserving the<lb/>
                excellence of the race when once attained, that people could<lb/> never be subdued;
                for, granting by way of argument, the<lb/> existence of abler nations, their ability
                would abundantly<lb/> supply their wants by easier and more profitable measures<lb/>
                than war against the unoffending, who would be supported<lb/> by a sense of justice,
                and ruled by a regard for the most<lb/> High, that would require conquest and
                extermination to be<lb/> made <sic>synonimous</sic> terms. Even the corrupted Jews
                of old were<lb/> but beaten and dispersed, and not subdued like other nations,<lb/>
                to resign their peculiar laws and coalesce with the victors. They<lb/> were
                conquered as men—not as Jews. Persecution, in its ut-<lb/>most violence could only
                cripple, but never tame their true<lb/> spirit of adoration. It has still angered
                upon earth and<lb/> groaned in agony unto the Lord of hosts,—and lo! he
                com-<lb/>-eth to relieve. Most faithfully yours—</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">George Barnard</persName>
            </p>
            <p><placeName>Sherbrooke C. E.</placeName>
                <date>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 5609</date>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
