<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Panegyric on the Life, Character and Services of the Rev. Isaac
                    Leeser</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Dropsie, Moses A.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jones and Company, printers</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item230</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Dropsie, Moses
                            A.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1868-02">19 February 1868</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1868-02">5628</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_back0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_front0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_front0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_front0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item230_wk1_front0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >pamphlet</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>16 pages on 18 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">PANEGYRIC</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">ON THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">LIFE, CHARACTER AND SERVICES</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">OF THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName>Rev. Isaac Leeser</persName>,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">PRONOUNCED BY</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName role="author">MOSES A. DROPSIE</persName>,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">BEFORE THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">HEBREW EDUCATION SOCIETY OF
                <placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>,</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="italics">On <date>February 19, 1868, (5628.)</date></hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>:</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><persName>JONES &amp; CO.</persName>, PRINTERS, <placeName>104
                    HUDSON STREET</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)"><date>1868</date>.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">PANEGYRIC</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">ON THE</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">LIFE AND CHARACTER OF <persName>REV. ISAAC
                LEESER</persName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">IF the life of a good man were the only source of benefit to
                man-<lb/>kind—if the sphere of his usefulness was limited only to his
                contem-<lb/>poraries or to the age in which he lived, or if perishable, like
                the<lb/> transitory things of life, his death would be an irreparable loss, and<lb/>
                our grief would be inconsolable. But fortunately, the good man lives<lb/> forever.
                The muse of history, in gathering the fragments which she<lb/> records, blots out
                the interval of time, and makes the past and the<lb/> present but one. The great and
                the good of the many centuries<lb/> that have rolled on in their course, live now
                fresh in our recollections.<lb/> We share their hopes and fears, we rejoice in their
                gladness, and<lb/> grieve in their sorrow, and the wisdom that fell from their lips
                has<lb/> all its original freshness and vigor. It would be deplorable, indeed,<lb/>
                if man's usefulness were circumscribed by the short span of life; for it<lb/> is not
                till the tongues of those envious of his fame have been silenced,<lb/> the passions
                of his antagonists have been stilled, and the ambition of<lb/> his rivals has been
                gratified or lost its zest by his death, that the<lb/> clouds that obscured his name
                are dispelled, and his worth and his<lb/> merits shine out in all their brilliancy.
                For we do not properly<lb/> appreciate him whom we meet in the daily walks of life,
                “famili-<lb/>arity breeds contempt,” we see the petty faults and foibles
                com-<lb/>mon to humanity, specks on the character that our weakness oft<lb/>
                magnifies to colossal proportions, but when the career of a good</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">4</p>
            <p>man has been impressed with the seal of death, the recollections of<lb/> his virtues
                throng the memory, and we discover, oft too late, our<lb/> great loss.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My friends, we have met to pay a tribute to the memory of
                    <persName>Isaac<lb/> Leeser</persName>. But a few brief hours have passed since
                his death, and our<lb/> people, by their manifestations of grief, show that they
                have <sic>sup-<lb/>denly</sic> risen, as if from a stupor, to a consciousness of
                their loss.<lb/> Death has been active in our ranks; within a brief period, he
                has<lb/> cut down some of our brightest men; men whose career has con-<lb/>ferred
                honor and renown on our race, but he has taken none brighter<lb/> or more devoted to
                Judaism than he.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> was born in the village of
                    <placeName>Neuenkirchen</placeName>, in the pro-<lb/>vince of
                    <placeName>Westphalia</placeName>, on <date>December 12, 1806</date>. At the
                early age of<lb/> eight years he was bereft of his mother, when his grandmother
                as-<lb/>sumed the care of him. At the age of fourteen he lost his father.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> recently, in speaking of his grandmother, said:
                “We<lb/> honor her memory and she deserves it, as she watched over us from<lb/> our
                eighth year, when our own mother was early called, till our four-<lb/>teenth, when
                both she and her son, our father, were borne to the<lb/> grave in the course of
                three weeks, and left us thus orphaned in a<lb/> double degree, in the wide world.
                Her instructions and admonitions<lb/> have never left us, and we trust that we shall
                be preserved faithful<lb/> to the end.” After some preliminary education in a
                preparatory<lb/> school, he entered the gymnasium of <placeName>Münster</placeName>,
                where he remained<lb/> until the year <date>1824</date>. We have often heard
                    <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName>, in speaking<lb/> of his early education,
                express his praise for the Catholic priests who<lb/> instructed him. In
                    <date>February, 1824</date>, he came to the <placeName>United States</placeName>
                at<lb/> the instance of his uncle, <persName>Zalma Rehiné</persName>, who resided in
                    <placeName>Richmond,<lb/> Va.</placeName> His uncle being engaged in the
                mercantile business, employed<lb/> young <persName>Leeser</persName> in his store,
                when it soon became apparent that he<lb/> was not adapted to such a pursuit; though
                frequently in after life,<lb/> he expressed a different opinion. In <date>July,
                    1828</date>, there appeared<lb/> an article in the <hi rend="italics"
                        ><placeName>London</placeName> Quarterly Review</hi>, attacking Judaism.<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> being then a young man, a foreigner, and a
                resident<lb/> of this country but four years, single-handed and alone entered</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">5</p>
            <p>the lists with his unknown and powerful adversary, and defended<lb/> our cause with
                such ability as to attract great attention. This de-<lb/>fence introduced
                    <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> to the notice of the congregation<lb/> Mikveh
                Israel, of this city. The readership having become vacant<lb/> by the death of
                    <persName>Mr. Keys</persName>, <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> was chosen, in
                the year <date>1829</date>,<lb/> to fill that position, which he retained till the
                year <date>1850</date>. Some time<lb/> subsequently, the new congregation Beth El
                Emeth was formed, ex-<lb/>pressly for him, by a number of his friends. He was chosen
                the<lb/> minister of it. The congregation's pecuniary resources being very<lb/>
                limited, the compensation for his services was trifling indeed; but<lb/> as
                usefulness was his object, not money, he accepted this position,<lb/> which he
                retained till his death.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1839</date>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> again appeared before the public, in<lb/> a series
                of articles addressed to the editor of the <hi rend="italics"
                        ><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> Gazette</hi>,<lb/> in reply to
                unfounded and illiberal strictures on our religion in the<lb/>
                <hi rend="italics"><placeName>London</placeName> Quarterly Review </hi>of
                    <date>1839</date>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Leeser's</persName> literary labors, for their
                variety, number, character,<lb/> and extent, are surprising; in this, few men of our
                age have sur-<lb/>passed him. In the year <date>1830</date> he published a work
                entitled “In-<lb/>structions in the Mosaic Religion,” translated from the German of<lb/>
                <persName>Johlson</persName>, of <placeName>Frankfort on the Main</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1833</date> he published an original work entitled
                “The<lb/> Jews and the Mosaic Law,” in the preface of which he stated that<lb/>
                “This book, now for the first time published, was composed more<lb/> than four years
                ago, whilst I was engaged in pursuits quite uncon-<lb/>genial to literature. Many a
                time, after a day of active application<lb/> to business, have I spent the hours of
                night in writing. Books for<lb/> reference I had but few, and the reader will
                therefore excuse the<lb/> brevity with which many of the points are treated, which
                no doubt<lb/> would have received more attention could I have had authorities
                to<lb/> refer to.” In the years <date>1836</date> to <date>1838</date> he published
                a collection of<lb/> sermons in two volumes.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1837</date> he published the Portuguese Form of
                Prayers<lb/> in Hebrew, with his English translation; and in the same year, he<lb/>
                published a Hebrew spelling and reading book.</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">1*</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">6</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Hebrew Sunday School of this city having been formed, in a<lb/>
                great measure through his exertions, there was no book for imparting<lb/>
                instruction in our religion to the young children, which he deemed<lb/> adapted to
                that purpose. To supply this want, he published his<lb/> Catechism in the year
                    <date>1839</date>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In <date>1841</date> he published another volume of his sermons, to
                which he<lb/> appended a series of his articles which had appeared in the <hi
                    rend="italics"><placeName>Phila-<lb/>delphia</placeName> Gazette.</hi></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1842</date> he edited <persName>Grace
                    Aguilar's</persName> Spirit of Judaism.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1845</date> he published the Pentateuch in Hebrew
                with<lb/> his English translation, in five volumes. A short time subsequently,<lb/>
                he published the Daily Prayers in Hebrew and English, for the use<lb/> of the German
                Jews; and in the year <date>1853</date> he published, in quarto<lb/> form, his
                translation of the Bible. Of this <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> said, “That
                it<lb/> is not a new notion by which he was seized of late years, which<lb/>
                impelled him to the task, but a desire entertained for more than a<lb/> quarter of a
                century, since the day he <sic>quitted</sic> school in his native<lb/> land to come
                to this country, to present to his fellow-Israelites an<lb/> English version, made
                by one of themselves, of the Holy word of<lb/> God.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">If <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> had done naught else, this work
                alone would entitle<lb/> him to the gratitude of every English reader. Prior to this
                edition, the<lb/> only English versions of the Bible were that of <persName>King
                    James</persName> and the<lb/>
                <placeName>Douay</placeName>, the imperfections of which were deplored by biblical scholars<lb/>
                <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> availed himself of the great ancient commentators,
                    <persName>Rashi</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>Redak</persName>, <persName>Aben Ezra</persName>,
                    <persName>Rashbam</persName> and others; and of the labors of
                    <persName>Men-<lb/>delssohn</persName>, <persName>Wessely</persName>,
                    <persName>Zunz</persName>, <persName>Herxheimer</persName>,
                    <persName>Philippsohn</persName>, and of that host<lb/> of illustrious modern
                commentators, who, devoting their erudition to<lb/> the proper interpretation of the
                Holy Scriptures, have shed a flood<lb/> of light over them. To these <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName> added his own critical<lb/> knowledge, in which he at that
                time, perhaps, had no superior in<lb/>
                <placeName>America</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1857</date> he published this Bible in an 18mo
                form.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the year <date>1864</date> he published <persName>Miss Grace
                    Aguilar's</persName> religious<lb/> works and poems, and at the time of his
                death, he was engaged in</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">7</p>
            <p>publishing his sermons in ten volumes, eight of which had appeared<lb/> previous to
                his decease, and the remaining two of which will shortly<lb/> be published. In the
                year <date>1843</date> he began the publication of the<lb/>
                <hi rend="italics">Occident</hi> magazine, which he continued till his death.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In addition to these literary labors, <persName>Mr.
                    Leeser</persName> translated and pub-<lb/>lished a number of other works, such
                as <persName>Mendelssohn's</persName>
                <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>,<lb/> catechisms, and primary educational books,
                and when it is remem-<lb/>bered that he faithfully attended to his labors as minster
                of his con-<lb/>gregation; that in his literary, as well as all other labors, he
                was<lb/> unaided by an amanuensis or other assistant; that he was his own<lb/>
                proof-reader, that he had to teach printers to compose in Hebrew;<lb/> that
                frequently he was compelled to set up Hebrew type, we can<lb/> have some conception
                of the immensity of his labors and the inde-<lb/>fatigability of his industry.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">When <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> arrived in the
                    <placeName>United States</placeName>, the number of<lb/> Jews was small, and
                they were scattered over our broad expanse of<lb/> territory. The little learning
                they possessed was confined to a few<lb/> persons. Most of our people, having fled
                from the oppression <sic>prac-<lb/>tised</sic> on our race by
                    <placeName>Europe's</placeName> political tyrants or religious bigots,<lb/> came
                here with but few of the world's goods, and in their struggles<lb/> against the
                pinchings of poverty, could give but little time or at-<lb/>tention to their
                religious culture, and many, who possessed both<lb/> knowledge and pecuniary
                resources, were indifferent to their religious<lb/> duties.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The means for instruction in the Hebrew were very limited and
                in-<lb/>efficient. The knowledge of those who were born here did not greatly<lb/>
                exceed the rudiments of the language in which our prayers were<lb/> printed, and
                some elementary principles. <persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> soon saw the<lb/>
                deplorable state of affairs, and his first efforts were directed to our<lb/>
                improvement; and with his characteristic ardor, by his writings<lb/> and addresses,
                he infused vitality into the inert Jewish body. His<lb/> earnestness, devotion and
                purity attracted around him the true Jews,<lb/> who lamented their destitution;
                though but a youth, they hailed<lb/> him as a leader; his agitations extended over
                our entire land, and<lb/> were felt even in <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">8</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">His labors accomplished a two-fold purpose. They not only
                in-<lb/>structed us, but they contributed in an eminent degree to eradicate<lb/>
                those prejudices respecting our people, which ignorance and bigotry<lb/> had
                engendered. Immediately on accepting the ministerial office,<lb/> he commenced to
                teach and exhort by public addresses. He may<lb/> be said to be the originator in
                this country of the delivery of sermons<lb/> among our people. His fame soon became
                extended; he received<lb/> numerous invitations for his services from various parts
                of the Union,<lb/> which he always cheerfully accepted, and in many places his
                ad-<lb/>dresses and sermons were the first delivered in English by a Jewish<lb/>
                divine. In the accomplishment of his purpose to elevate Judaism,<lb/> his magazine,
                the <hi rend="italics">Occident</hi>, was an important aid; in its pages, as<lb/>
                well as by his other literary labors, there was unfolded to the new<lb/> world, some
                account of the names and writings of those illustrious<lb/> men, who by their
                learning contributed to preserve and protect our<lb/> existence, religion, and name,
                through that long period of suffering<lb/> and tribulation, which stained the
                historic page with the bloody<lb/> record of man's inhumanity.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Leeser's</persName> learning was not profound; that
                is, he had not de-<lb/>voted himself to some especial subjects, and exhausted or
                attained<lb/> the highest degree of knowledge by them, but he possessed a great<lb/>
                fund and variety of learning. There were but few subjects on which<lb/> he had not
                some information; his mind was perspicuous; he saw at<lb/> a glance, and from all
                sources, absorbed knowledge which became<lb/> indelibly fixed in his wonderful
                memory. He knew Hebrew, Chal-<lb/>dee, Greek, Latin, French, German and English. He
                had a natural<lb/> adaptation for philology, and thoroughly understood the
                philosophy<lb/> of the structure and grammar of languages; it was this
                knowledge<lb/> which enabled him to translate with great fidelity, without
                losing<lb/> the spirit of the original.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">His traits of character were strongly marked; his idiosyncrasy<lb/>
                unmistakably distinguished him from his fellows; with an indomi-<lb/>table will, he
                had but few negative qualities. His industry was<lb/>
                <sic>marvellous</sic>. After transacting the multifarious duties of the day,<lb/> he
                curtailed the hours allotted for rest, by his incessant toil.</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">9</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">His perseverance was untiring, his energy was inexhaustible,
                his<lb/> determination was unfaltering. By the combination of these qualities<lb/>
                he accomplished those great results which will render his name<lb/> immortal.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The practices of his life strictly accorded with his professions;
                of<lb/> the highest purity, he neither said nor did that which could produce<lb/> a
                blush on the cheek of chastity.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">His charity was as broad and expansive as that of the religion<lb/>
                which he taught; he was neither avaricious nor sordid; with many<lb/> opportunities
                for the accumulation of pecuniary wealth, he rejected<lb/> them with disdain; he had
                higher and holier aspirations, and at<lb/> his death left but few worldly goods.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">He regarded life as a period of obligations and duties;
                impressed<lb/> by its stern realities, he rarely indulged in those amusements
                or<lb/> enjoyments which lighten our burdens and invigorate mind and<lb/> body.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But in this recital of the traits of this truly noble man, it
                must<lb/> not be forgotten that justice requires “<hi rend="italics">De mortuis nil
                    nisi verum.</hi>”<lb/> He was human. In his ardor for the accomplishment of some
                good<lb/> purpose (he had none other), he sometimes forgot that all were not<lb/>
                gifted with his quick perceptions, and, in urging them on, was impa-<lb/>tient and
                impetuous, and at times he would wound tender sensibili-<lb/>ties by his frank and
                outspoken manner; for he had never learned<lb/> the art of disguising his thoughts.
                If these be frailties, they are<lb/> too infinitesimal to dim his name.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> was connected with the various
                Jewish charitable in-<lb/>stitutions of this city; in these he exhibited his
                customary restless<lb/> activity; he strove to make them permanent, and not
                dependent on<lb/> spasmodic efforts for their existence.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">He was the founder of the Hebrew Education Society of this<lb/>
                city, the Society that I am now honored in addressing. For years<lb/> he endeavoured
                to establish schools wherein Hebrew should form one<lb/> of the leading branches of
                education. The result of those endeavours,<lb/> was the establishment of this
                Society and its school, which was the</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">10</p>
            <p>precursor in this country of all schools of a similar character. Sub-<lb/>sequently,
                he directed his efforts to its permanence, and at his in-<lb/>stance, the late
                    <persName>Judah Touro</persName> endowed it with a liberal bequest. To<lb/> the
                school he devoted much time and attention; it was his favorite<lb/> scheme. He
                regarded it as a powerful instrument in the advance-<lb/>ment and elevation of
                Judaism, but his ambition did not rest here.<lb/> In the draft of the Act for the
                incorporation of this Society, he<lb/> inserted a provision authorizing a higher
                institution of learning, and<lb/> Maimonides College sprang into being but a short
                period previous<lb/> to his death, an appropriate closing act of his life.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In recognition of his services, he was chosen the Provost, and
                in<lb/> the distribution of the duties among the faculty, he had no ambition<lb/>
                beyond that of serving in a capacity in which he could be most<lb/> useful. He
                entered on his duties, but death had already marked<lb/> him for his victim. The
                sands of life had nigh run out, and ere he<lb/> could witness the fruition of his
                hopes, death closed his earthly<lb/> career.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><persName>Mr. Leeser</persName> dedicated his life to Judaism, of
                which he was the<lb/> embodiment and type; it was the subject of his reveries by
                day,<lb/> and the theme of his dreams by night. He sympathized with its<lb/> sorrows
                and rejoiced in its gladness. Not having the cares of a<lb/> wife or family, he
                watched over it with the fond solicitude of a hus-<lb/>band and parent. He was a
                vigilant sentinel; when descrying danger<lb/> threatening it, he became its valiant
                champion, and, clad with the<lb/> panoply of truth, defended it with his power and
                strength. No<lb/> soldier rushing against the blazing cannon's mouth, in his country's<lb/>
                <sic>defence</sic>, or martyr writhing under the tortures of the Auto-da-fé for<lb/>
                conscience' sake, exhibited greater devotion than he. It was the<lb/> object of his
                creation, the purpose of his life.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Within a brief period, <placeName>Israel</placeName> has mourned for
                the loss of illus-<lb/>trious children, but none greater than he. What a void
                his<lb/> death creates! Upon whom shall his mantle fall? Let not our<lb/> grief be
                heartless lip-service. Let our actions attest our truthful-<lb/>ness and
                earnestness. Let us build up as an imperishable monu-</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">11</p>
            <p>ment to his fame, an edifice on the deep and broad foundations which<lb/> he planted.
                    <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName> is dead, but the memory of his public<lb/>
                services and private worth, will live through the ravages of time,<lb/> and his name
                will be enrolled among those who have conferred<lb/> honor and renown on our race,
                and who recognized no earthly dis-<lb/>tinction equal to that conferred on us by the
                great Creator.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
