<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item225</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Wise, Dr.</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>5 pages on 8 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(center)"><hi rend="underline">a card</hi></p>
				<p>To the <addressee>Rd Dr. Wise</addressee> Edt Israelite</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The following Art. appeared in your Paper on <date>Tudy<lb/> 1. April</date> &#8220;<persName>Mr. Bruel</persName> on Talmud Yelodim <sic>institute</sic>&#41; <del>speaks thus</del><lb/> <persName>Mr. B</persName> in a lengthy <sic>Letter</sic> to the Oc<hi rend="underline">cid</hi>ent notices the T Y I. thus<lb/> &#8220;The school under <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> is similarly circumstanced its annual<lb/> report show a <sic>dificiency</sic> of 7. to 800<add>&#63;</add> but the members of his congregation<lb/> are very proud of their school.  They attach to it a greater degree of<lb/> consequence than some might think it deserves hence they endeavor<lb/> to preserve its <sic>existance</sic> by private contributions and other sources&#44;&#8221;&#8220;<lb/> would I have <sic>preferd</sic> answering your remarks to the above in<lb/> your own <sic>Paper</sic> but as you have denied me a hearing on 3 <sic>seperate</sic> occasions<lb/> though you profess to admit Articles of all kinds of persons in the<lb/> Israelite.  I am reluctantly <sic>compelld</sic> to seek a hearing elsewhere&#44;<lb/> <hi rend="underline">reluctantly</hi>&#44; because the public can have little interest in such<lb/> affairs&#8222;  The constant readers of yr. paper have satisfied themselves<lb/> that it invariably provokes <sic>dissention</sic> and when <sic>legitimatily</sic><lb/> opposed&#44; one is sure to be met with a torrent of abuse or a total deni<lb/>al is given the things it has provoked. these facts can be verified by the<lb/> <sic>Paper</sic> itself.  You Sir&#44; are not alone callous to <add>&#63;</add> the feelings of others&#44; but<lb/> are also indifferent to your own standing as a journalist&#44; it should be<lb/> your duty in accordance with your profession on the forthcoming of<lb/> the Israelite&#44; to place both sides of public questions before the world<lb/> particularly matters pertaining to <del>religion</del> theology since justice<lb/> toward individual members of society&#44; will reward the press&#44; in the form<lb/> of increased confidence and respect in conclusion I may remark that<lb/> no public man should object to have his official conduct <sic>criticised</sic><lb/> when the criticism manifests a desire to reveal truth and useful<lb/> information.  I cannot conceive that the article now before<lb/> the public is in <sic>itsself</sic> of so flagrant a character as to cause such a<lb/> torrent of bitter recrimination&#44; as you have bestowed on it&#44; partic<lb/>ularly as you are aware I have only stated facts&#44;&#44; you commence<lb/> thus &#8220;One would scarcely think that fanaticism could thus mislead<lb/> an old man&#44; as to speak slightly of an institute in which his own</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">2</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">x <sic>complaind</sic></p>
				<p>Grand children receive their education and are counted among<lb/> the best of their age&#8221; In reply I have reason to say&#44; that my<lb/> Grand children are as intelligent for their age as most children are&#44;<lb/>  It is because they can show so little for their prompt attendance<lb/> of nearly 3 years in a school that boasts&#44; having preeminent adean<lb/>taps<add>&#63;</add> that cannot be had in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> or <placeName>England</placeName> nor elsewhere&#44; it is<lb/> because they make no progress in things most essential at their<lb/> age&#44; that I have repeatedly x to their parents&#44; and if they are <sic>faithfull</sic><lb/> to their children&#44; and to themselves I trust they will soon perceive<lb/> that I have not <sic>complaned</sic> in vain&#44; but sir in what I have said<lb/> I have not injured the reputation of the school&#44; unless you consider<lb/> it <sic>Treason</sic> to speak the truth.  I am not the only <del>insidid</del> individual<lb/> who think <del>so</del> its members attach <del>more</del> a greater degree of consequence<lb/> to their school than some might think it deserves.  I can name<lb/> several if required&#44; that will say the same&#44; but sir <sic>their</sic> must be <sic>othr</sic><lb/> causes which has so sorely displeased you&#44; a <sic>side</sic> from the Article<lb/> in question.  May it not be that you being aware of the members<lb/> mistaken attachment to their school&#44; and as the Editor of an Hireling Press<lb/> have again prostituted your Ephemeral sheet to please your<lb/> supporters&#44; you know you did in the like manner in the fall<lb/> Edition which greatly facili<del>ated</del>tated to crush the cause you then<lb/> espoused.  I spoke of the financial affairs of the school from its<lb/> annual report without co<hi rend="underline">m</hi>ent.  You continue that &#8220;The ortho<lb/>dox are <sic>enimies</sic> to instruction.  They are therefore opposed to schools&#8221;<lb/> you boast&#44; &#8220;That the school sends forth American Jews no Poles&#44; no<lb/> Germans&#44; no English&#44; and no Irish&#44; but <sic>Genuine</sic> self reflecting <sic>indipendant</sic><lb/> American Jews&#44; whom you <sic>cant</sic> <del>trample whom you cannot</del><lb/> trample under the feet of <sic>Preists</sic>.  This is all true and we can <sic>imma<lb/>gine</sic> your grief&#44; your burning pain&#44; your sacred woe&#44; you should respect<lb/> this sacred plae<add>&#63;</add> but your boundless fanaticism your unholy Zeal as<lb/> a partisan would not allow you to do justice to a place which is more<lb/> sacred than your Synagogue together with all your singing chanting<lb/> crying and jumping.  Well <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> you <sic>certanly</sic> x must have</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">3</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">to their school</p>
				<p><sic>labord</sic> under some spiritual illusion&#44; when you composed the foregoing<lb/> sentences&#44; but can it be believed that the man who profess to defend<lb/> the Jew&#44; and Judaism against every outside attack&#44; will himself<lb/> address his coreligionists so wickedly <sic>spitefull</sic>&#44; and for no other reason than<lb/> their misfortune to differ with him&#44; and because an individual hath<lb/> said&#44; &#8220;They attach a greater degree of consequence &#8220;Than some might think<lb/> it deserves&#8222; Great man how <sic>contemptily</sic> have you fallen how differ<lb/>ently did <persName>Moses</persName> our faithful preceptor act&#44; on a similar occasion.</p>
				<p>&#8220;Because one man hath <sic>sind</sic>&#44; wilt thou O Lord be indignant with an entire<lb/> community.&#8221; witness the language of a reformed Rabbi a teacher of <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> the head and soul of a school&#44; when the <del>sacred</del> pupils are trained to a<lb/> moral and religious course of education&#44; that such a sacred place<lb/> under such a leader is more sacred than your <sic>Synagoge</sic> <sic>to gether</sic> with your<lb/> singing chanting crying and jumping&#8222; <hi rend="underline">shame</hi> <persName>Dr. <hi rend="underline">Wise</hi></persName> a person of your<lb/> cloth&#44; to speak so insultingly to a god serving people&#44; now can any<lb/> thing be more Priest trodden than this.&#8222; let me tell you <persName>Dr. Wise</persName><lb/> there is not a <sic>jewish</sic> congregation on this or the old continent&#44; that<lb/> is so Priestly imposed under fair <sic>pretences</sic>&#44; as your congregation are<lb/> witness their reception of your new Minag &#40;liturgy&#41; which they<lb/> accepted by acclamation in its printed form&#44; they having full<lb/> confidence in all things you write or preach while it is rejected<lb/> by every congregation in the union excepting a miserable few.<lb/>  Thus you revised a prayer Book&#44; and have stricken out passages<lb/> &#38; prayers&#44; the best to fortify Israelites in a belief in god&#44; as a benevolent<lb/> rewarder of the good&#44; and the strict judge of sin&#44; the belief in the life of<lb/> the spirit after death&#44; and the eternal permanence of <placeName>Israel</placeName> as<lb/> gods people&#44; as also in the restoration of the Temple of the Lord now<lb/> in ruins and of our state&#44; which is now no more&#44; yes in order to<lb/> deprive your congregation of this belief&#44; were all those prayer<lb/> which refer to it <hi rend="underline">Banished</hi> and the remainder so mutilated&#44; and<lb/> discoverable only to the initiated&#44; and to make room for such a <del>po</del><lb/> patch work&#8222; you have caused them to reject a prayer book com<lb/>posed by <placeName>Israels</placeName> heroes&#44; by the most famed teachers&#44; whose spirit<lb/> <del>so</del></p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">4</p>
				<p>survives to this day among us&#44; as the ornament and glory of <placeName>Israel</placeName> whose<lb/> names will never be blotted out b y time&#44; but which one age hands down to<lb/> the other by men who did not degrade science into an instrument for the<lb/>ir own advancement or employed as a mere means of getting bread.  I will<lb/> spare you the pain of naming your associate authors&#44; in the work of yr.<lb/> new liturgy enough to say they are all worthy of each other.  You conclude that<lb/> &#8220;<persName>Mr Bruel</persName> boasts that his orthodox congregation are free of debt&#33;&#33;&#33;<lb/> &#8220;This is because they do not pay their Hazonam &#40;Readers&#41; <sic>enoug</sic> to make<lb/> a living&#44; because they have no synagogue of their own&#44; because they care<lb/> not for the poor&#44; they pay not a cent for education excepting a few only<lb/> they pay not a cent to our Hospital nor to our relief society nor to<lb/> any charitable <del>institute ton</del> purpose&#44; therefore <sic>there</sic> Synagogue are<lb/> free of debt.  Open your ears <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> and I will tell you truths&#44; things<lb/> indeed out of your line.  Know then that our small congregation<lb/> pay our chazan &#40;reader&#41; an amt of salary fully equal to that which your<lb/> <sic>synagog</sic> or any other in this city are paying&#44; we have a Synagogue &#38;<lb/> furniture of our own on a lease&#44; a <sic>Cemetry</sic> for our dead real estate<lb/> paid for&#44; our <del>congregation</del> synagogue pay as much to the Hospital<lb/> and relief fund as yours do.  The Hospital originated with the orthodox while<lb/> the <sic>releif</sic> society grew out of a benevolent Institution&#44; in a word&#44; you have placed a<lb/> false constriction on the whole&#44; because all the charitable institutions you have<lb/> enumerated are supported entirely by voluntary subscription&#44; and all of them were in <sic>existance</sic><lb/> before you came here&#44; nor do any of the synagogues here pay one cent to them from their<lb/> respective treasury&#44; therefore we pay as much as you do every family obtain private<lb/> Hebrew teachers for their children&#44; they need not support your schools if they disa<lb/>prove of its chief head.  They avail themselves of our districts schools believing they<lb/> are better than yours.  What <sic>benifit</sic> have for taunting a religious institution<lb/> for being cold and indifferent to the wants of their needy correligionists when you<lb/> know to the contrary.  If I have said any thing <sic>offencively</sic> concerning their school<lb/> I can assure its leaders that none was intended&#44; and none but a persons having the<lb/> principles of <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> <hi rend="underline">principles</hi>&#44; who constantly is striving to sow the seed of contention<lb/> would have made so much from so small an affair <hi rend="underline"><persName>S Bruel</persName></hi> ND &#8222;The Occident is<lb/> now a weekly paper every Israelite should read that old established sheet&#44; whose uniform course have<lb/> obtained for itself a reputation for ability&#44; truthfulness&#44; and <sic>consistancy</sic>&#44; it is a faithful and reliable<lb/> <sic>Jurnal</sic> whose views and principles remain unchanged by reading the weekly Occidn.<lb/> persons will have the opportunity of <sic>examing</sic> both sides of disputed public<lb/> <add>&#63;</add> the camp of <placeName>Israel</placeName></p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p><persName><hi rend="underline">S Bruel</hi></persName></p>
				<p>at. <persName>D. Wolf</persName> 50.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><persName><add>&#63;</add> <hi rend="underline">S. Wert</hi></persName></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
