<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“A Native of Germany”</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item213</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">“A Native of
                            Germany”</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Editor of the
                            Whig</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Richmond, VA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1829-01">25 January 1829</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item213_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 8 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">5</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You will say, however, true the Old Testament contains the doctrines
                I<lb/> have advanced, but the Jews did not understand them so; in fact you partly
                have<lb/> said so already,—you have asserted it, without proving it further than by
                referring<lb/> to the general history of the Jews. You know it is easy to make
                    <del>asser</del> assertions,<lb/> but they will not stand without substantial
                proof. I will therefore first<lb/> deny your assertion and then bring proof of the
                truth of what I advance<del>d</del></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We all know, that the temple, which <persName>Solomon</persName>
                built, was finished in the<lb/> four hundred and eighty seventh year after the
                promulgation of the law on<lb/>
                <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName>, and of course <hi rend="underline">we all
                    must</hi> admit, that the opinion then<lb/> prevailing concerning the meaning of
                    <hi rend="underline">any part of the law</hi>, must be considered as<lb/> a
                pretty correct standard to ascertain the meaning the Israelites attached<lb/> to the
                law, which was then, as it is now, our guide through life. It is<lb/> a lamentable
                fact, that the Old Testament, particularly the historical books,<lb/> are but little
                read by the <sic>christians</sic>, and therefore do we find men of<lb/> learning,
                nay preachers, ignorant of the writings I speak of I shall<lb/> therefore transcribe
                a portion of <persName>Solomon's</persName> prayer in the Temple at<lb/> its
                dedication as contained in the VIII chapter of the first book of Kings.</p>
            <p>v. 37-43</p>
            <quote>“If there be in the land famine, if there be pestilence, blasting, mildew,
                    <del>locut</del> locust<lb/> “or if there be caterpillar; if their enemy besiege
                them in the land of their<lb/> “cities, whatsoever plague, whatsoever richness there
                be; whatsoever prayer<lb/> “and supplication be made by any man, or by all they
                people <placeName>Israel</placeName>, which<lb/> “shall know every man the plague of
                his own heart, and spread forth his<lb/> “hands unto this house; then hear thou in
                heaven thy dwelling-place,<lb/> “and Lo, and give every man according to his ways,
                whose hear thou knowest;<lb/> “(for thou, even thou only, knowest the hearts of all
                the children of men)<lb/> “that they may fear thee all the days that they live in
                    the<del>y</del> land which thou<lb/> “gavest unto our fathers.</quote>
            <quote>“Moreover, concerning a <del>the</del> stranger, that is not of they people
                    <placeName>Israël</placeName>, but cometh<lb/> “out of a far <del>of</del>
                country for they names sake; (for they shall hear of they great<lb/> “name, and of
                thy strong hand, and of thy stretched out arm,) when he shall come<lb/> “and pray
                towards this house; hear thou in heaven thy dwelling-place,<lb/> “and do according
                to all that the stranger calleth to thee for; that all<lb/> “the people of the earth
                may know thy name, to fear thee, as do thy people<lb/>
                    “<placeName>Israël</placeName>; and that they may know that this house which I
                have <sic>builded</sic><lb/> “is called by thy name.” (English version.)</quote>
            <p>I know very well, that the last part would have been enough for my<lb/> purpose, but
                I extracted the first one also, to show, to those, <hi rend="underline">who may
                    not</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">be as well acquainted with the Bible</hi>, in what manner the
                wisest of men<lb/> prayed for the nations, who <hi rend="underline">do not belong to
                        <placeName>Israël</placeName></hi>; he first prays that</p>
            <p rend="The text is cut off at the bottom of the page."/>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>6</p>
            <p>received, and have granted to him, that, for which he petitioned the throne of<lb/>
                Grace.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">We find in the second book of Kings <persName>Elisha</persName>
                healing the leper <persName>Naaman</persName>,<lb/> though it is well known that the
                nation, to whom he belonged was frequently<lb/> at war with
                    <placeName>Israël</placeName>, thus we find him, not alone assisting a gentile,
                but<lb/> an enemy also; what then becomes of your assertion, that the Jews did<lb/>
                not <sic>practise</sic> acts of universal <del>acts act</del> benevolence? Let me
                advise you,<lb/> my dear friend, to read the books of the Old Testament well, before
                you<lb/> venture on such dangerous ground again as asserting things about us
                Jews,<lb/> which you may not <hi rend="underline">be able to sustain with
                    incontestable</hi> proof, when called upon.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In support of your assertion concerning the beauty of the gospel
                you<lb/> introduce a few verses from the <hi rend="underline">sermon on the
                    mount</hi> in the fifth chapter<lb/> of <persName>Matthew</persName>. By <hi
                    rend="underline">so doing you have imposed upon me an</hi> invidious task,<lb/>
                namely of attacking the <sic>christian</sic> religion in some manner, when I should
                have<lb/> been very glad, to have let the gospels <del>at</del> rest. But I am now
                called upon to<lb/> defend the tenets of my faith, and dare not therefore shrink
                from the<lb/> responsibility thus thrown upon me, although this happens without
                my<lb/> desiring it.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Let me premise that the religion which we profess, is divided<lb/>
                into three parts: first, duties towards God, secondly, duties towards our fellow
                men,<lb/> and lastly duties towards ourselves. The duties towards God impose upon
                us<lb/> the belief in the Creator, confidence in His protection, hope in His
                salvation and<lb/> the observance of His statutes. The duties towards our fellow men
                consist in acts<lb/> of charity and benevolence and in abstaining from injuring
                them, in their person<lb/> property and honour. Duties towards ourselves are: self
                preservation &amp;<lb/> self-<sic>defence</sic>; by which I mean that first we shall
                not depend upon others for our <sic>livelyhood</sic>,<lb/> if we are ourselves
                capable of making a living, as it is beautifully said<lb/> in the Proverbs of the
                Fathers: “Sweet is the learning of the law, combined<lb/> with labour, for to be
                engaged in both makes us abstain from sin;” and<lb/> secondly to be careful for the
                preservation of our health. Self <sic>defence</sic><lb/> demands of us to conduct
                ourselves so that we shall not be exposed to<lb/> the hatred or violence of others;
                but if in spite of all our endeavours we<lb/> are molested and violently attacked,
                it is lawful to prevent our adversary<lb/> from injuring us; and if he attempts to
                kill us, it is even permitted to<lb/> slay him, if we can in no other manner prevent
                him; in support<lb/> of this position, I refer you to Exo. Chapter 22 verse 2.—</p>
            <p rend="The text is cut off at the end of this page."/>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">7</p>
            <p>repealed, except in the same manner as it has been promulgated, that is<lb/> before
                the whole nation of <placeName>Israël</placeName> in the same manner as the law was
                given on <placeName>Sinai</placeName>.<lb/> These preliminaries area <hi
                    rend="underline">sine qua non</hi>, without which no argument,<lb/> however
                ingenious, can stand the test of Jewish criticism. Let us now apply<lb/> this rule
                to the chapter of <persName>Matthew</persName> in question, to test its correctness.
                In<lb/> the outset, he, whom the <sic>chirstians</sic> call the Messiah
                    (<persName>Christ</persName>) says him<lb/>self; “think not that I am come to
                destroy the law of the prophets: I am not<lb/> come to destroy, but to
                    <sic>fulfil</sic> &amp;c &amp;c. Here, my dear Prof. of
                    <persName>Christ</persName>, you have<lb/> it <hi rend="underline">from what you
                    must think the highest authority</hi> that <hi rend="underline">the gospels
                    must</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">in every particular</hi> conform to the <hi rend="underline"
                    >Mosaic</hi> writings which let me repeat were<lb/> given by the Author of All
                for the government of <placeName>Israël</placeName>, and as you believe in<lb/>
                Revelation, you must acknowledge, that these writings contain the best code<lb/> of
                laws that can be devised. Well then, when <persName>Matthew</persName> says, “swear
                not at all,”<lb/> the <sic>christian</sic> writers are puzzled how to explain it,
                and the learned <persName>Dr. James<lb/> Beattie</persName> explains it so as to
                mean any unnecessary oath, which however can<lb/> hardly be the meaning of this
                passage. What <persName>Matthew</persName> says in the same chapter<lb/> from the v.
                38 to the 41, I am bold to assert has never been fulfilled by fifty<lb/> men from
                all <sic>christendom</sic> ever since <sic>christianity</sic> was established, and
                if<lb/> these doctrines were adopted as the general rule of society, every wicked
                person<lb/> could <hi rend="underline">with impunity despoil his unoffending
                    neighbour</hi>; and let me ask you<lb/> can this be the will of God? For what
                did he command the election of<lb/> judges if it were not to see the innocent
                righted? And have the Society of Friends,<lb/> who more than any other Christian
                sect, try to obey the <del>above</del> commandments<lb/> in question, ever acted up
                to the letter of them?</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In the 43 v. of the same chapter <persName>Matthew</persName> says:
                Ye have heard that it<lb/> has been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbour and hate <hi
                    rend="underline">thine</hi> enemy; &amp;c<lb/> Now pardon me, my friend, when I
                beg of you to tell me in what part of the Old Testa<lb/>ment or any Jewish writing
                the foregoing sentiment is found? Hate our<lb/> enemies? Heavenly father!
                    <sic>has</sic> it come to this, that thy children<lb/> who have suffered for
                ages persecutions without number for the SANC-<lb/>TIFICATION OF THY HOLY NAME, who
                have been<lb/> slaughtered like sheep that are dumb before their shearers, without
                mur-<lb/>muring, without repining—shall thy children Oh our Father above be<lb/>
                accused of hating their enemies! Do they not pray to thee daily:<lb/> “To prepare
                the world for Thy kingdom, Almighty God, to cause all flesh to<lb/> “call Thy name,
                and to bring to Thee all sinners of the Earth, that all<lb/> “may receive the yoke
                of Thy kingdom, and that Thou mayest speedily<lb/> “reign over all for ever, for
                Thine is the kingdom, and for ever and ever Thou<lb/> “wilt reign in glory?”</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>8</p>
            <p>Again we find it commanded in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ch. 18<hi rend="sup"
                    >th</hi> v. of Lev. that we shall not<lb/> avenge ourselves, nor even, as we
                Rabbinical Jews understand the word<lb/> “<persName>Thitore</persName>” (transl. in
                the Eng. version nor bear any grudge) to tell those that<lb/> have offended us,
                “look here though you would not do me the favour I asked<lb/> of you, yet will I not
                do like you have done, here is what you ask for.”<lb/> In the 28<hi rend="sup"
                    >th</hi> ch. <add>?</add> 5 v. of Exodus we are positively enjoined <hi
                    rend="underline">to assist our</hi><lb/> enemy when we see him in need of our
                assistance. In the 24 ch. 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> v. and<lb/> 25 ch. 12 v of the
                Proverbs <persName>Solomon</persName> tells us: “Rejoice not when they enemy
                falleth<lb/> and when he <sic>stumbleth</sic> let not thy heart be glad; lest the
                Eternal see it, and it<lb/> displease him, and he turn his wrath from him. If thine
                enemy be hungry,<lb/> give him bread to <del>it</del> eat; and if he be thirsty,
                give him water to drink &amp;c Thus<lb/> we clearly see that the Old Testament
                enjoins those <hi rend="underline">exalted doctrines</hi>, for which<lb/> you give
                the gospel the sole credit.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">But you will say, <persName>Christ</persName> lived in the time of
                the Pharisees and<lb/> Scribes, who did not act so, who were hypocrites, and
                deviated from the letter<lb/> of the law? Indeed! but even here you would be
                mistaken; for in the<lb/> Talmud we find the following: “A stranger came to <hi
                    rend="underline"><persName>Shamai</persName></hi> and told him<lb/> Rabbi I wish
                to become a <sic>proselite</sic>, but you must teach me the law, while<lb/> I can
                stand on one leg; but <persName>Shamai</persName> turned him off, not thinking it
                possible<lb/> to teach him the law in so short a time. The stranger went next to
                    <persName>Hilled,<lb/> surnamed the Elder</persName>, and repeated the same
                request, “my son,” answered<lb/> the Rabbi, “what is disagreeable to thee, do not to
                thy neighbour, (or companion),<lb/> for thus it is written thou shalt love thy
                neighbour like thyself, this is the princi-<lb/>ple commandment, and if you observe
                this strictly you will easily observe<lb/> the other precepts of the law.”—What
                    <persName>Matthew</persName> says concerning the punish-<lb/>ment to him, who
                makes his antagonist ashamed in public, is also found in<lb/> the Proverbs of the
                Fathers, which declare: “He, who <del>that</del> makes the face of his<lb/>
                neighbour turn pale in public, though he has knowledge of the law and has<lb/>
                otherwise acted well, will not <del>have</del> share in the happiness of the
                future<lb/> life.” What then I ask you again has the gospel taught new to the
                Jews?<lb/> Since the Old Testament <sic>containes</sic> all the moral doctrines, and
                the Rabbins<lb/> (Pharisees &amp; Scribes) of the time of
                    <persName>Christ</persName> did invariably preach up in<lb/> the Synagogues
                &amp; Temple doctrines conformable to their Text-Book,<lb/> namely the
                    <del>two</del> twenty four books of the Jewish Canon.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have thus I hope made my assertions good, that our law is a<lb/>
                perfect model of a moral and religious code, that there is nothing too much<lb/> and
                nothing too little in it, and in fact, if any man will but examine the<lb/>
                wonderful effect it has had of keeping a <hi rend="underline">dispersed people
                    united in</hi></p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">9</p>
            <p>every sense of the word he must acknowledge: “That no nation though<lb/> ever so
                great has such just statutes and commandments as those, which<lb/> the Eternal our
                God has given us.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">You, my friend, call upon me, to do the <sic>christians</sic> that
                justice which<lb/> I demand at <del>of</del> their hands; I am willing to concede
                all that <sic>christians</sic><lb/> deserve, and I have already acknowledged, and
                shall always do so, that I<lb/> have been treated very <add>?</add> by them, and
                shall always, till my dying hour,<lb/> remember the benefits conferred upon me, by
                some of them. But while<lb/> I do this I must repeat and reassert it, that the
                prejudice existing against<lb/> us is highly unjust and even condemned by
                    <del>against</del> that law which you as <sic>christians</sic> are<lb/> bound to
                respect. This was the reason why I in the first instance undertook<lb/> the
                    <sic>defence</sic> of our people from the vile and insidious attacks of the
                Quarterly<lb/> Review, and this now impels me again to answer you, though even
                here<lb/> I am very willing to admit again the difference which exists between
                your<lb/> mode of warfare and that of the above mentioned magazine. Pardon<lb/> me
                one remark, before I dismiss you altogether; do you know that<lb/> what you profess
                about universal salvation is no <sic>christian</sic> doctrine? Do you know<lb/> that
                it was taught only by the Jewish Rabbins? And do you know that<lb/> if you believe
                in the gospel, you must renounce this doctrine as <hi rend="underline">not
                    ortho</hi><lb/>dox? How<del>ever</del> this may be, I leave you to settle with
                the <sic>christian</sic><lb/> divines; but only enter my protest against what you
                say about the voice<lb/> of conscience; for revelation was given to assist us in <hi
                    rend="underline">forming a correct</hi><lb/> course of life, and if conscience
                could affect that, to what purpose was the<lb/> law then given? But our opinion is
                this, our law was given as the standard,<lb/> to which all nations were ultimately
                to resort <del>to</del> as a rallying point, till<lb/> when, every man <del>was to
                    be saved</del>
                <hi rend="underline">who is no Israelites</hi>, was to be saved if he<lb/> acted
                according to the light given him, if <del>they</del> he only observed the
                precepts<lb/> of general revelation given to <persName>Noah</persName>, which are to
                be found in the ninth<lb/> chapter of genesis, and it was therefore the practice of
                the Jews, when ever<lb/> they conquered, to make the subdued nation conform to the
                “seven command<lb/>ments of the children of <persName>Noah</persName>” as they are
                called in the Talmud. Each<lb/> son of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, on the
                contrary is bound to observe all that lies in his power<lb/> to do, as otherwise he
                is to be punished for good deeds omitted and sins committed.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It would be a great satisfaction to me, to be assured, that I had
                effec-<lb/>tually removed the ill-will so many feel towards us, that I had
                contri-<lb/>buted a little to make <placeName>Israël</placeName> more respected in
                this country, and particular-<lb/>ly in this city. Let me at the same time call upon
                my brethren, those<lb/> who with me believe in the <hi rend="underline">same
                    immortal unchangeable God</hi>, who</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>10</p>
            <p>with me are bound by the same faith; who with me live in the land of strangers<lb/>
                far, far, from the sweet hills of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, far, far, from the
                sacred banks of<lb/> the <placeName>Jordan</placeName>, far, far, from the holy
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, the city, where God's glory<lb/> used to
                dwell; who with me hope to reach a glorious immortality, when<lb/> God will open the
                graves of his people as promised by <persName>Ezekiel</persName>. Let<lb/> me call
                upon them to arouse from their lethargy, to break those<lb/> chains of listlessness
                by which they are bound. Let them draw the<lb/> bond of <add>?</add> closer, let
                them forget the offenses committed to <add>let each man forget the injuries done by
                    his neighbor</add><lb/> one another, and then show the world what
                    <placeName>Israël</placeName> can <del>do</del> be even in captivity.<lb/> Let
                them show their attachment to that beautiful religion, which<lb/> has ever been the
                admiration of the world and <del>show</del> prove themselves, by<lb/> conforming
                strictly to the spirit and letter of the divine law, worthy<lb/> of that glorious
                    <del>hereafter</del>
                <sic>furturity</sic> for which they are destined by the God of<lb/> nature by the
                ever kind Father of <placeName>Israël</placeName>!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In conclusion I think it necessary to make an apology<lb/> why I, a
                young man, who has scarcely reached the age of manhood,<lb/> who moreover
                    <del>is</del> am a foreigner, should step forward, to do that which<lb/> older
                and wiser men than <del>himself</del> myself have omitted to do. But I hope,
                that<lb/> my justification is contained in the following from the 32 ch. of
                    <persName>Job</persName>, which with little alteration<lb/> is well applicable
                to the present case:</p>
            <quote>“And <persName>Elihu</persName> the son of <persName>Barachel the
                    Buzite</persName> answered and said, I am young and Ye are<lb/> “very old;
                wherefore I was afraid, and dunt<add>?</add> not shew you my opinion. I<lb/> “said,
                Days should speak, and multitude of days should teach wisdom,<lb/> “But there is a
                spirit in man: and the inspiration of the Almighty gives them<lb/> “understanding.
                Great men are not always wise; neither do the aged<lb/> “understand judgment.
                Therefore I said, Hearken unto me; I will also show<lb/> “mine opinion. Behold I
                waited for your words; I gave ear to your reasons,<lb/> “while ye searched out what
                to say. Yea, I <sic>attendd</sic> unto you, and behold, there<lb/> “was none of you
                that convinced <persName>Job</persName>, or that answered his words; lest ye<lb/>
                “should say<del>s</del> We have found out wisdom; God thrusteth him down not<lb/>
                “man. Now he has not directed his words against me; neither will Answer<lb/> “him
                with your speeches. They were amazed, they answered no more; they<lb/> “left off
                speaking. When I had waited, (for they spake not, but stood still and<lb/> “answered
                no more;) I said, I will answer also my part I <del>will</del> also will<lb/> “show
                my opinion. For I am full of matter the spirit within me constrai-<lb/> “neth
                me.</quote>
            <p>Like <persName>Elihu</persName> I have considered it my duty to speak, because
                    <del>the</del> older<lb/> men did not speak, and was thus in a manner compelled
                to assume the<lb/> fearful responsibility to accept the challenge which others
                neglected to do.</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">11</p>
            <p>I have, like the holy writer, endeavoured to abuse no man, <del>but</del>
                neither<lb/> to flatter anyone; but have given as far, as I believe, things their
                right<lb/> names, without intending to give <sic>offence</sic> to any one; I have
                tried:</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Nothing to extenuate nor <del>to put</del> set down aught in malice;
                how<lb/> far I have succeeded I leave of hers to judge, but only beg of
                    <del>them</del> all to listen<lb/> to my <sic>defence</sic> with patience, and
                to read my remarks to the end. I dare<lb/> not hope, that what I have written could
                pass the age <add>shall stand the test</add> of severe criticism,<lb/> but I
                    <add>request</add> expect, that every fault may be ascribed <hi rend="underline"
                    >to the head but not the heart</hi> of</p>
            <p rend="indent(9)"><hi rend="underline"><persName role="author">A Native of
                            <placeName>Germany</placeName></persName></hi>.</p>
            <p>
                <placeName>Richmond Va.</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)"><date>Sunday Morning Janu. 25<hi rend="sup">Th</hi> 1829</date>.</p>
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>To the <addressee>Editor of the Whig</addressee></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
