<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckmann, J.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item93</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckmann, J.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-08">20 August 1851</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-08">20 August 5611</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item93_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item93_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item93_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item93_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="he">Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="The following paragraph is written in small handwriting above the main letter."/>
            <p>I cannot enter particulars but I had reason to think so as that Dictator is known to
                me to belong as much to our unprejudiced<lb/> school as any. “We speak and write
                mostly according to the different passions &amp; emotions which agitate us. And
                those objects<lb/> which strike us most forcibly represent themselves in a lively
                manner to our imagination, and thus determine us to that<lb/> side„ <persName>Dr Pin
                        Stru<add>?</add></persName> with the supposed wrong I broke forth with my
                expressions. They were more a censure against the<lb/> dissension <del>created
                    in</del> widened—then <add>?</add> approbation, of the dissension which by earth
                acts<lb/> was caused. The whole if expressed would have been “what all this tunnels,
                this <sic>anathemising</sic>, why not<lb/> rather<add>?</add> conciliate. The
                opinions of preaching about or against messiah, is a censure<lb/> against
                    <persName>P.</persName> (I wish to know whether have they original you know my
                hand writing<lb/> and can identify it, before doing so, it is not fair to send it
                forth as I have no means to ascertain, and<lb/> every reason to question their
                honesty.</p>
            <p>
                <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <date>Aug 20. 5611</date>
            </p>
            <p>To the <addressee>Revd I Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p>
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Your enclosed letter, I found but last night taking out the
                proof<lb/> in haste the letter must have dropped. I thank for proof, for letter and
                your kind<lb/> advice. My letter to <persName>P.</persName> is written in such a
                careless manner as even you<lb/> must have some proofs, a copy of it I have not. The
                word aerial<lb/> does not seem to be original after ideal seems to be an
                insertion<lb/> for my letter ideal stands opposed to practical. Could not you
                claim<lb/> the original? The contents of his own petition cards denies a
                    <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The letter was written under the impression, that the Congr are
                considered<lb/> as no more being Jews for their Synag: reformer &amp; for the
                abrogation<lb/> of <add>יט שנה</add>
                <add>see top</add> and so in my haste, I placed<add>?</add> myself as champion
                when<lb/> I ought to have heard first. It now serves me right. But this<lb/> is
                    <sic>incontestible</sic> and in due time will be stated that I in presence<lb/>
                of the Trustees, &amp; at the House of <persName>Mr Moise</persName>, and with
                God<lb/> for <add>?</add> 3 hour warmly protested against 2d day <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>מנהג עוקר הלכה</add> and this is meant in my letter in <date>July</date>
                occid<lb/> “admissible on the letter of the law, but not so on the score<lb/> of
                charity &amp; piety. I have not admitted it as right, though it may be legend<lb/>
                With regard to <persName>Nusser</persName> the case is the same <persName>Mr Ab.
                    Moise</persName>, with<lb/> also appear when required. Let the volcano first
                destroy itself.<lb/> Strange that there are men who can condone that of opposed Drs
                views,<lb/> and none is more that will say he heard me in private or in pulpit<lb/>
                preach any thing that is not quite called on.</p>
            <p>To his creed I never gave consent, I knew nothing of his changes<lb/> as little as
                any body else, I only read about the word <add>אמת</add></p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>I allow all to be as it is. And supposing I had changed my<lb/> views, or had been
                inconsistent <persName>Poznanski's</persName> Gents ought<lb/> to idolize me, had
                not their Prophet done such tricks and thereby<lb/> gained their attachment of
                respect. The best is told them<lb/>
                <add>ולא תדקדק מלות נאמרו בשכל בזה הפרק וזולתו, כי הכוונה הישרה אל העניין המכוון
                    מורה א פ ל"ב</add> prove that his words ought not be so much attended to as the
                    <add>?</add> expected<lb/>
                <add>שום חשש איסור</add> go on. The letter contains nothing of moment facts fr:
                first day<lb/>
                <add>מחלוקת</add><lb/>
                <add>המון עם</add> What induces you to advise me to go to
                    <placeName>Engl.</placeName> I am justified<lb/>
                <add>חוצפה</add><lb/>
                <add>זדון</add> and qualified to take any orthodox congreg. This reform Synag is<lb/>
                <add>שני י"ט</add>
                <sic>a</sic> Orthodox as any other. Reform has nothing to do with orthodoxy<lb/>
                never did I preach any but orthodox principles, and the<lb/> congreg wanted such, on
                this ground even <persName>Mr Wise</persName> was<lb/> elected. This was held forth
                in a speech on the occasion of<lb/> his election by <persName>Mr Moise</persName>.
                Though it displeased <persName>P.</persName> the congreg<lb/> want such.
                    <persName>P</persName> and his disciples are of no weight at all when<lb/> the
                question is Judaism.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">What Ideal is, see traff. In what sense I applied it<lb/> is proved
                by my controversy 2d day after my arrival.<lb/> I reiterate my thanks for your
                valuable services<lb/> you will oblige me with<lb/> 20 copies again, if not
                    <sic>to</sic> late I remain <sic>gratefuly</sic></p>
            <p rend="indent(10)">your</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">J Eckman</persName>
            </p>
            <p><persName>Dr Fränkel</persName> Rabbi at <placeName>Dresden</placeName> is famous for
                Learning, Character</p>
            <p>&amp; Piety. He is true orthodox Rabbi though he introduced<lb/> organ, choir &amp;
                    <sic>german</sic> prayers. It is he who some few weeks ago was mentioned in<lb/>
                the <sic>asmonean</sic> to have stayed at <persName>Dr Adlers</persName> House in
                    <placeName>London</placeName>. <persName>Dr F</persName> is one of the most<lb/>
                famed men in <placeName><sic>germany</sic></placeName>.
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName> wished to elect him as Rabbi, this failed in the
                despo<lb/>tism of <placeName>Prussia</placeName>, he wanted some restriction under
                which the clergy labor re..<lb/>moved, government would not do so. Through the
                tyrant would have been glad<lb/> to have such a man at the head of the <add>Jews of
                    his</add> Capital, see Fost Histo<add>?</add> Torme 12</p>
            <p><persName>Dr Jacks</persName> was co <add>?</add> at
                    <placeName><sic>Prag</sic></placeName>, in his ancient Synag exists an organ for
                several<lb/> centuries as early as <date>1176</date> a new one was built. How old
                must the<lb/> old one have been? See <persName>Shuldt A Herthumer</persName> Theil
                4. Zunz<add>?</add> Gottesdienst<lb/> bihe<add>?</add> Vorträge <sic>pag</sic>
                476</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p><persName>Dr Sacko</persName> assented to a great temple that was to be built with
                organ, choir, <sic>german</sic> prayers</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The king would not allow a spot where they waited. The revolution
                broke<lb/> out and so the affair is dropped. <persName>Dr J.</persName> is a strict
                orthodox man.<lb/> There is no <add>מדברי סופרים</add> at all. I could here address
                authorities that would more<lb/> than satisfy you. When you wrote so harshly against
                me some time ago<lb/> I could have easily come out and shown you <hi
                    rend="underline">that nothing</hi> that has<lb/> been done in the Synag is
                against our Relig. or against any <hi rend="underline">din</hi>, but I would<lb/>
                have been obliged to show it to the world. And <sic>If</sic> I can do no better
                than<lb/> fear<add>?</add> how <add>עלנו עלינו</add> might be produced? For if the
                    <add>אדון עולם</add> various<lb/> it they will soon here and <sic>and</sic>
                there from a desire of innovation etc<lb/> roughly attack all that is holy, as was
                done here. Men who know<lb/> no 2<add>?</add> who neither know nor practice any
                Relig at all became<lb/> reformer, green girls scold the Rabbis at vote for or
                against creeds<lb/> and so I will rather be thought to <hi rend="underline">be</hi>
                wrong than to <hi rend="underline">do</hi> wrong</p>
            <p>The great wickedness is not the deformed Synag: but it is.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <head/>
                <item n="1"> That neither Bibl nor Rabb Law are observed</item>
                <item n="2"> The whole treasures heaped by our nation marked<lb/> and
                    ridiculed</item>
                <item n="3"> It was not Relig: at all in <persName>P.</persName></item>
                <item n="4"> his <add>שאלה ותשובה</add>, &amp; <add>רבנו חכם שם טוב</add></item>
                <item n="5"> To drive these pious men out of their<lb/> property</item>
                <item n="6"> To hurt the feelings of so many people<lb/> and in the abrogation of
                        <add>אב"ד דקק לאוברנא "כלל העולה מכל הכתוב ומפורש לעיל דמות לשורר ולנגן בכל
                        כלי שיר בבהכנ לכבוד ה'</add> legally<lb/> it is but <add>ותורתו, דל דבר מצוה
                        לא גזרו חז"ל כלל כמ"ש ועמל ותו טעמא אחרינא איכא בהא מלתא דעי"כ באים לבה"כ
                        האנשים והנשים לשמע אוזן אשר ישמעו כלי השיר הערב הנל וכבר אמרו חזל מתוך שלא
                        לשמה בא לשמה, ואין להאריך בדברי' פשוטים</add>; but the feelings of<lb/>
                    <sic>of</sic> all who hear of it.</item>
                <item n="7"> The <sic>unparalelled</sic> Hypocrisy</item>
                <item n="8"> His plan to subvert every thing</item>
            </list>
            <p>Here was neither reform, we have all the<lb/> prayers in <sic>hebrew</sic> except
                    <date>friday</date> evening<lb/> | prayer | Hymn &amp; <add>והגלילות במדינת
                    אנגארן</add> is read Heb &amp; then Engl<lb/>
                <date>Sabbat</date>
                <add>?</add>, 1 confessor <add>?</add><lb/> the <add>ושוב עוד מזה שיאמרו פסוקי דזמרה
                    שירי יגדל ואדון עולם ויתר התפלות הנשגבות בשבת ובי"ט בהלוית כנור וקול זמרה להרחיב
                    ו לבב המתפללים לתגברות רוח השכל, וכבר כתב הרמ"א בא"ח ס. הק"ס סג של צורך מצוה
                    מותר לנגן בכל שיר וכל מיני וחס</add>, &amp; Prayer to government in Engl</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in a column to the right of the list above."/>
            <p> It is the relig life that I have to reform<lb/> but in the Syng, nothing amiss
                has<lb/> been done<lb/> Had a Pious &amp; good man been here<lb/> of course nothing
                of the kind would<lb/> have happened, as it could not be<lb/> done without a
                rupture. Yet<lb/> had a pious teacher been here and<lb/> a party was desirous of
                    <add>?</add> and were<lb/> not to be dissuaded from it. He<lb/> would have
                proved his piety by<lb/> his “life &amp; protested against <add>?</add><lb/>
                <add>?</add> &amp; tried by instruction<lb/> to prepare the mind to
                <add>?</add><lb/> changes. But here all was<lb/> preposterous. No respect of<lb/>
                persons, no reverence for what<lb/> is sacred. Like a robber he came<lb/> against
                our wise men with</p>
            <p rend="The following is written in the left margin near the top of the page.">I
                would<lb/> rather leave<lb/> teaching</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a battle arc and clubs. And like a thief in the dark to steal their faith<lb/> a good
                man would never propose changes, he would wait till asked<lb/> if a congreg feels no
                want to curtail prayer, prayer cannot be too<lb/> long. I cannot write so much.</p>
            <p>What <persName>P</persName> &amp; his men wanted at all in a Jewish Synag I do no
                know. But<lb/> my adherent intended no harm</p>
            <p><persName>Mayer Lazarus</persName> several times assured me “That they intended
                nothing but<lb/> to introduce order &amp; decorum into the service to render it
                more<lb/> attractive. As to a creed “They never<add>?</add> intended to change or
                alter, it was<lb/> but by chance that it was fined up there it was only to have<lb/>
                a “p<add>?</add>dent to the Decalogue.</p>
            <p>Should I <add>?</add> to reform the Congreg I shall not complain at<lb/> all
                    <del>?</del> about the Syngag. And I am by no means to be blamed<lb/> so fill up
                the place I will transcribe part of <add>אחי אל תפנו אל בלע עם ואל ... למדו לשונם
                    דבר שקר העוה לא נלאו עשו ברית עם חזה שוא וקסם קסם, מרעה אל רעה צאן, ואת הטוב לא
                    ידעו. בסוד עמי לא יהיו ועם צדיקים אל יכתבו. חקקו חקקי און, ומכתבים עמל כתבו – לא
                    אענה את דבתם, כי גם נודע רעתם, וגם נפלו ברשעתם</add><lb/>
                <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> I wrote so fast is this the contents?</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
