<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item151</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Leeser, Isaac</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item151_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item151_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>1</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">The American Society M. C. I.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">By invitation of <persName>Rev. Mr. Bokum</persName> one of the Vice
                Presidents and trav-<lb/>elling agent of this society, we attended on the even. of
                the <date>27<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date> ult. a <add>?</add><lb/> of a meeting held
                for the purpose of organizing an auxiliary society in<lb/> this city. From his
                speech based upon the XXXVII of <persName>Ezekiel</persName> from 1-15<lb/> verses
                (which is strangely enough as our readers know is one of He<add>?</add> of<lb/> the
                    <date>Passover</date>) we learned that the society has in view to heal the
                “dry<lb/> bones”, the remnants of the house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, who
                are scattered “in the valley”<lb/> meaning the whole earth, in such a manner that
                the spirit of the gospel<lb/> may reach and animate them. But this favor to our race
                is not to be<lb/> forced upon us as of old by the fire &amp; the sword, nor as in
                modern<lb/> times by abuse &amp; exclusion from public employment, which
                procee<lb/>dings be characterized as anti-christians &amp; barbarous (yest how
                many<lb/> anti-christians and barbarians do exist according to this view, not
                omitting<lb/> the <persName>king</persName> of <placeName>Prussia</placeName> and
                the <persName>queen</persName> of <placeName>England</placeName> in whose countries
                the Jews are<lb/> not equals with their Christian neighbours); but by acts of
                kindness,<lb/> charity and benevolence; he urged it at the gospel should not be
                forced upon our notice<lb/> by words of the preacher but to teach us its practical
                effects by itself<lb/>
                <del>kindness</del>
                <add>?</add> as should prove to the Jews that its spirit is one of real<lb/>
                goodness &amp; virtue. He stated that with this view the society had through<lb/>
                its agent in <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> given away a great deal of money to the
                poor from<lb/> $5 and up to one hundred Dollars to one individual; but that in<lb/>
                <add>?</add> instance had the charity been improperly applied by the recipients.<lb/>
                <add>?</add> last is high praise in favour of the <add>?</add> of the poor Jews in
                the<lb/> city many of whom are in abject want of even the necessities of life<lb/>
                <add>?</add> the <add>?</add> of <persName>Mr. Finestro</persName>. <persName>Mr.
                    Bokum</persName> farther gave an account</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>2</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">AS. MC.I.</p>
            <p>of his progress thus far in human <add>?</add>, and spoke of a public meeting<lb/>
                with <persName>Mr. Lawrence Blumenthal</persName> at
                    <placeName>Chambersburg</placeName>, who by the<lb/> courtesy of <persName>Mr.
                    Bokum</persName> obtained the permission of making an exposition<lb/> of the
                tenets of Judaism before a crowded church in that town.<lb/> (We may probably have
                to say something more of this address of our<lb/> friend in a future number.)—He
                also advocated to the establish-<lb/>ment of a <add>?</add>prick at
                    <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> in the person of a known<lb/> of state under
                the patronage of the <persName>Queen</persName> of <placeName>Britain</placeName>
                and the<lb/>
                <persName>King</persName> of <placeName>Prussia</placeName>. He spoke of the alleged
                infidelity of which we<lb/> have lately heard a good deal as existing among our
                people,<lb/> and he ascribed it, as also the same phenomenon among<lb/> the
                catholics, to our acceptance of tradition for us as contained in the Talmud<lb/> and
                    <del>for them as embraced in</del> the so called superstitious practices
                ari-<lb/>sing therefrom; and he alludes to the new congregation established<lb/> in
                    <placeName>London</placeName> in opposition to rabbinical authority, as a
                legitimate<lb/> consequence of the missionary labours of the
                    <placeName>London</placeName> Society<lb/> for evangelizing the Jews, who he
                averred had opened by their<lb/> publication &amp;c the eyes of our brethren in
                    <placeName>England</placeName> to the errors<lb/> of their <add>?</add> to the
                Talmud.* (*How will our friends of<lb/> the new congregation of
                        <placeName>B<add>?</add> Street</placeName> relish the allegation<lb/> that
                their reform is the legitimate result of a society<lb/> the object of which is the
                destruction of the Jewish religion?<lb/> For our part we should be sorry indeed were
                any one to ascribe<lb/> any act of ours to the result of such unfriendly advice; and
                we<lb/> hope that they will boldly deny the assumptions of the missionary.<lb/> We
                will <add>?</add>say, that this is not the first time that the opponents<lb/> of
                Judaism have gloried over the secession (and have feigned to</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>3</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">AS.M.C.I.</p>
            <p>discover therein a gradual approach to Christianity. We<lb/> think that, much as we
                differ from the gentlemen who have<lb/> too hastily adopted a new form of worship,
                that they will be<lb/> grieved as much as we were mortified to hear such
                notices<lb/> ascribed to them; and if they feel inclined we offer them our<lb/>
                magazine to reply to these unfounded charges, they may<lb/> please to entrust us
                with a temperate <del>reply</del> exposition calculated<lb/> for our paper.]—<add>He
                    stated also that is the object of <persName>Mr. <add>?</add></persName><lb/> to
                    employ missionaries to the Jews in all large<lb/>
                    <add>?</add>, and to station one of them in
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</add> He referred likewise to our labours,
                and<lb/> stated something about a controversy which we might probably wage<lb/>
                against each other, for the sake of ministerial conviction; and in demanding<lb/>
                public support for the Jewish Chronicle he stated that the managers will<lb/>
                carefully exclude everything calculated to offend; and nothing should<lb/> be said
                which could wound the feelings of an Israelite.</p>
            <p>The above is a meager <sic>synnopsis</sic> of the Rev. gentleman's<lb/> remarks,
                which appeared to be contemporaneous; we were not in a favourable<lb/> position to
                take note, if even we had been inclined to do so, yet we<lb/> think that we have
                reported him fairly and for our purpose fully.<lb/> Our readers will see from the
                above that the weapons are changed,<lb/> but that our religion is nevertheless to be
                attacked. Flattery &amp; money are<lb/> to do what violence in <del>the first
                    instance</del> old and coarse rudeness in<lb/> more modern times failed to
                accomplish. We trust that there<lb/> is not much danger to be apprehended from such
                means,<lb/> nevertheless there may be a few “whose heart is turning<add>?</add>
                this<lb/> day from the Lord their God;” and it <sic>behoves</sic> us then to
                omit<lb/> no means in our power to counteract such deeds of our oppo-<lb/>nents. Of
                one thing our Jewish friends may rest assured, that if money<lb/> can purchase <hi
                    rend="underline">souls</hi>, they will be ready paid for; because we see</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>4</p>
            <p>that there is a false species of philanthropy spreading<lb/> over the land which is
                anxious to catch every straggler and to<lb/> take away any wandering sleep that has
                missed our fold. As<lb/> for us we are concerned we regard an inimical everyone who
                comes<lb/> to deprive us of our religion, be the means or the <add>?</add> what they
                may; and though we are personally friendly<lb/> to <persName>Mr. Bokum</persName>,
                both as a gentleman and a preacher, we certainly<lb/> must look upon the efforts he
                is making as by no means an evidence<lb/> of good will towards our belief. We
                cheerfully accord to him the praise<lb/> of moderation and candour; but it would be
                much better were all<lb/> this moderation &amp; candour exerted to allay prejudices
                instead of<lb/> drawing away perhaps some <hi rend="underline">unworthy</hi> members
                from our church.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Respecting the charge of infidelity, we fear that there is some<lb/>
                truth in it; we do not believe that modern Jews are skeptics, but<lb/> that a
                practical infidelity regarding religious duties has obtained<lb/> alas! too much
                currency cannot be denied. We mean not to enter into the discussion<lb/> this month;
                but only to call the attention of our brethren to the fact<lb/> that others besides
                Jews watch their conduct and that their<lb/> neglect of religion brings them to
                honour, and even causes<lb/> them to be suspected of unbelief in that blessed faith
                for which<lb/> many would shed their last drop of blood, altho their<lb/> conduct
                    bet<add>?</add> so much indifference.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Lastly with regard to our own self we have never promised<lb/> to
                wage a controversy with any man. We probably shall<lb/> admit controversial articles
                if we think proper; but nothing<lb/> shall induce us to be always tilting like some
                anxious knight errant<lb/> against all comers. Indeed no one shall provoke us, if we
                can</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>5</p>
            <p>keep our temper; and we will use our discretion in this<lb/> as in every thing else,
                and act independently <del>from</del> of all parties.<lb/> The Occident was
                commenced to diffuse knowledge in our<lb/> religion; and this we mean to do whilst
                we continue its editor;<lb/> avoid mere controversy which is only a trial of
                skill—is therefore evidently not <del>fit</del> suited to our<lb/> object. We
                nevertheless assure our friends that we neither fear<lb/> nor want religious
                arguments; all we meant to say, we will not<lb/> be provoked for any special object;
                which would evidently be<lb/> the case were we to enter the lists regularly once a
                month<lb/> against the Jewish Chronicle or its reverend editor.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Nonetheless we thank <persName>Mr Bokum</persName> for his
                conciliatory<lb/> manner, and we hope always to meet him with equal<lb/> courtesy
                both personally and if occasion demands it before<lb/> the public. With these
                remarks we take our leave for<lb/> the present from the AS.M.C.I. but likely not
                longer than<lb/> next month.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
