<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item7</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Mikveh Israel</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1840-05" source="" attested="yes">15 May 1840</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1840-05" source="" attested="yes">12 Iyar 5600</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item7_wk1_body0012.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>12 pages on 12 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>To the Parnass and members</p>
				<p rend="indent(1)">of the congregation Mikveh Israel</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Gentlemen</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">At one of your meetings in the early part<lb/> of this year&#44; I asked for permission to be present at the<lb/> meeting and to address you personally in relation to and in ex&#45;<lb/>planation <del>to</del> of matters which are&#44; as I conceive&#44; of great in&#45;<lb/>terest to the congregation on the one side and to me&#44; as your minister&#44;<lb/> on the other.  For circumstances had occurred&#44; <del>and</del> over which<lb/> I had myself not the least control&#44; which had excited feelings<lb/> that ought not to exist between us&#44; and I fondly hoped that<lb/> a mutual interchange of opinions might tend to enable us<lb/> to come to a better understanding&#44; and to proceed in future with<lb/> perfect harmony and mutual good will.  But a construction of the<lb/> by&#45;law&#44; which specifies that none but members &#38; their sons over the<lb/> age of thirteen years should be present at any meeting of the congregation&#44;<lb/> that the congregation could on no account permit any other than these<lb/> persons to be present at their deliberations&#44; deprived me of this pleasure&#44;<lb/> and at the same time was the cause&#44; as I truly believe&#44; that the<lb/> unimportant difference of opinion between us has not been long<lb/> since satisfactorily settled&#59; for I honestly think that a few hours<lb/> free &#38; candid conversation would have exhibited things in a light<lb/> very different from what some now view it&#44; or at least formerly did view<lb/> it.  Understanding therefore&#44; that a meeting has been called in<lb/> relation to the <sic>reengagement</sic> or reelection of the Hazan&#44; I take the<lb/> liberty of sending you my own views in writing&#44; and I shall endea&#45;<lb/>vour to condense as much as possible&#44; not wishing to fatigue<lb/> you with listening to a long harangue&#44; or to introduce matters<lb/> not relevant to the subject.  Let me premise the ardent hope&#44;<lb/> that every member of the congregation in proceeding to delibe<lb/>rate upon the matter before the meeting will discard every<lb/> thing like prejudice and partiality&#44; &#40;and <hi rend="underline">endeavour for</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">once to throw personal dislike</hi> or <hi rend="underline">friendship</hi> aside&#41; and vote<lb/> in a manner which he can conscientiously hereafter look<lb/> upon as the best conducive to the welfare of the congregation<lb/> and to the promotion of the spread among us of that heavenly<lb/> religion which we have received&#59; and lastly act&#44; not as opponents<lb/> or supporters of the present incumbent of the office&#44; but as men<lb/> and Israelites anxious for the general welfare of their faith.</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>2.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">To come to a proper understanding of my connection with the congre<lb/>gation I will briefly give a short account of my stay in this city&#44; since<lb/> it is highly probable that some of the facts may have escaped the recollec<lb/>tion of the members.  It is now nearly eleven years ago that through<lb/> the partiality of several residents of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> I was applied to to become<lb/> a candidate for the office of Hazan then recently vacant through the<lb/> death of the <persName>Revd. A. I. Keys</persName>.  I at that time lived with my uncle at <placeName>Rich&#45;<lb/>mond</placeName> in capacity of a mercantile clerk&#59; I had the confidence of many<lb/> persons in the state of <placeName>Virginia</placeName> and the city of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44; and if I had en&#45;<lb/>tered in business for myself my chances of success would have been as<lb/> good&#44; to say the least&#44; as that of many young men&#44; who since then <del>that time</del><lb/> have earned an honourable independence and respectable standing.<lb/>  I had at that time just passed my twenty&#45;second year&#44; my health&#44; though<lb/> never very robust&#44; was better than it is now and has been for many years<lb/> past&#59; and though young and inexperienced I was not dazzled with the<lb/> prospect of obtaining a high &#38; responsible office.  On the contrary&#44; I not<lb/> only expressed&#44; but truly felt a want of confidence in my abilities to<lb/> discharge properly the new duties to be expected from the situation of a minister<lb/> <del>properly</del>&#59; and for a long while I absolutely refused to permit my name<lb/> to be used.  My friends were not satisfied&#44; they urged&#44; that the education<lb/> I had received&#44; and the talents which their partiality ascribed to me&#44;<lb/> pointed out to me a different calling from that of a merchant&#59; they<lb/> appealed to my feelings as an Israelite who ought to labour in the propa<lb/>gation of true religion among his brethren&#59; and to my want of <del>a</del> riper years<lb/> <del>age</del> which I opposed to my fitness for the office&#44; the averred that<lb/> that would correct itself every day&#44; as daily my increase of age would entitle<lb/> me to more respect.  Without being satisfied that my happiness<lb/> would be increased by a change of pursuits&#44; I left&#44; being over&#45;persua&#45;<lb/>ded by the arguments of those who were older&#44; wiser and more expe&#45;<lb/>rienced than myself&#44; <del>I left</del> the paternal roof of my uncle about<lb/> the middle of <date>August 1829</date> to go away persons entirely strangers to<lb/> me&#44; and upon whom I had no farther claims than the community<lb/> of faith given to the humblest of <placeName>Israel&#39;s</placeName> sons upon the most exalted<lb/> I had fondly hoped&#44; that if the <sic>sufferages</sic> of the members would call<lb/> me to preside over their worship and to appeal in their behalf<lb/> to the throne of Grace&#44; every thing like disunion<add>&#63;</add>&#44; want of confidence&#44;<lb/> or the wising up with worldly matters&#44; <hi rend="underline">such as regards salary&#44; emolu&#45;</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">ments &#38;c would have been banished</hi>.  But I regret that such was<lb/> not the case.  In the letter sent to me by the committee of corres&#45;<lb/>pondence&#44; consisting I believe of <persName>Messrs R. De Cordova</persName>&#44; <persName>L. M. Goldsmidt</persName> and</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">3</p>
				<p><persName>Isaiah Nathans</persName> it was distinctly stated&#44; that the salary attached to the office<lb/> was &#36;1000 Dollars&#44; and in fact <persName>Messrs Carvalho</persName> &#38; <persName>Keys</persName> both received this<lb/> amount&#44; and I hear moreover that it was understood&#44; that the latter gen&#45;<lb/>tleman found that amount entirely insufficient for his support.  Yet after<lb/> I had been here a few days I was waited upon by several gentlemen&#44;<lb/> one of whom your respected Treasurer&#44; who represented to me that the funds<lb/> of the congregation were then too low to allow the payment of the above<lb/> sum.  I therefore authorized an election for <hi rend="underline">one</hi> year with a <hi rend="underline">voluntary</hi><lb/> surrender of two hundred Dollars&#59; but when the report was afterwards<lb/> brought to me that I had been elected by a vote of 27 to 7 for two<lb/> years at &#36;800 per annum&#44; I also consented though against my original<lb/> intention&#44; thus proving that I was not unwilling to make a pecuniary<lb/> sacrifice where I thought it was requisite.  During the first year&#44; how&#45;<lb/>ever&#44; of my residence here&#44; various unpleasant things took place&#44;<lb/> which it is needless to call to mind again&#59; and altho&#39; matters were<lb/> smoothed over again&#44; <hi rend="underline">still the report reached a distant congregation</hi>&#44;<lb/> that my situation was not very pleasant here.  Therefore overtures<lb/> were made to me by several influential members from that place<lb/> to take the office of Hazan vacant there.  About the same time a meeting<lb/> of this congregation was held&#44; at which it was understood that it had been<lb/> left to a committee to reengage me at &#36;800 per annum for five years.<lb/>  As this amount was evidently less than I had a right to expect&#44; I did<lb/> not think myself at liberty altogether to decline a proposal made<lb/> to me from abroad&#59; yet <hi rend="underline">I made such exorbitant demands as almost</hi><lb/> to preclude any idea of their being agreed to&#59; one was <hi rend="underline">an election with&#45;</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">out being a candidate</hi> or going on to be heard beforehand&#59; second&#44; one election<lb/> for life&#59; third&#44; an absence of three months every year&#44; and lastly to be<lb/> permitted to stay in this congregation three months after the expiration<lb/> of my time of service&#44; to enable them to provide a suitable successor.<lb/>  Strange enough&#44; all but the two first demands &#40;and they in a modified<lb/> degree to correspond with the laws of the above Kahal&#41; would have been accep&#45;<lb/>ted&#44; if I may put any confidence in the assertions of the heads of the con&#45;<lb/>gregation&#44; if in case I had consented to accept office there&#59; but as<lb/> their election was to be held in <date>July</date>&#44; and as the meeting of this congre<lb/>gation would not take place till <date>September</date>&#44; I declined soon all farther<lb/> correspondence&#44; as I could not conscientiously leave this place before I<lb/> had made every effort at reconciliation.  It will therefore appear&#44;<lb/> that whether I could or could not have been elected elsewhere&#44; which<lb/> must remain a <hi rend="underline">matter</hi> of <hi rend="underline">doubt</hi>&#44; I at all events declined leaving</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>4</p>
				<p>hastily&#44; though I was <hi rend="underline">offered</hi> more advantageous terms elsewhere were I <hi rend="underline">asked</hi><lb/> here&#44; and it was very doubtful whether your body would recede from their<lb/> vote which had been adopted after mature deliberation.  If then I put<lb/> the congregation in danger of being unprovided with a minister&#44; I put<lb/> myself equally in jeopardy of losing a situation&#44; as there was no vacancy<lb/> at that precise period in any city in this country&#44; and it is not so easy&#44;<lb/> as some may imagine&#44; to change one&#39;s occupation&#44; and that at a moment&#39;s<lb/> warning.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The congregation however found my reasons&#44; addressed to them<lb/> correct &#38; cogent&#44; and they so altered their vote as to elect me for<lb/> five years at one thousand Dollars.  So matters remained for the<lb/> whole period&#44; till a reelection became necessary&#44; when although<lb/> there was no opposing candidate&#44; still I was only reelected&#44; as I heard<lb/> a year afterwards&#44; by a bare majority&#44; despite that there was<lb/> no charge of misconduct or incompetence against me.  Nay more<lb/> than this&#44; after a resolution had been amended to read &#8220;for three years<lb/> at &#36;1000 per annum&#44;&#8221; the resolution as amended was rejected&#44; and<lb/> consequently there was properly speaking no <hi rend="underline">minister elected</hi> to <hi rend="underline">offici</hi>&#45;<lb/><hi rend="underline">ate during the latter part of the holydays</hi>&#44; a circumstance which<lb/> evidently must be <hi rend="underline">mortifying to one who had</hi> for seven <hi rend="underline">years</hi> faith&#45;<lb/>fully done his duty&#44; and highly prejudicial to the interest of the<lb/> congregation&#44; as it was thus in my power&#44; <hi rend="underline">if I had chosen to display</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">a revengeful feeling&#44; to leave the congregation absolutely unpro</hi>&#45;<lb/><hi rend="underline">vided at the very season of the holy festivals.</hi>  After the holydays<lb/> I understand a meeting was held&#44; and an election made for one<lb/> year&#59; but by some oversight I was never officially notified of this<lb/> fact&#44; and I continued to act under the request made to me by the<lb/> Parnass that I might not till a meeting could be held.  I com&#45;<lb/>menced at that time the publication of the Discourses I had delivered<lb/> at the synagogues in this place and <placeName>New York</placeName>&#44; which was followed by the<lb/> printing of the entire prayer book according to our <hi rend="underline">Minhag</hi>.  These<lb/> labours required a space of about seventeen months for their comple<lb/>tion&#44; and I am happy to mention <sic>incidently</sic> that so far the usefulness of<lb/> the one work and the necessity of the other have been amply proved by<lb/> the support which as been extended from different parts of this &#38; other<lb/> countries.  But during their progress another election for Hazan became<lb/> necessary&#44; and now for the first time since my first election an active<lb/> opposition was exhibited&#44; and votes were openly and privately solicited for a</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">5</p>
				<p>gentleman who had lately arrived from a foreign country.  If any influ<lb/>ence was used by my friends to induce any one to vote for me&#44; it was<lb/> done without my knowledge&#44; and I may here remark that I<lb/> never asked for any man&#39;s vote since the first day of my being<lb/> called to come here&#44; thinking that in elections&#44; particularly to religious<lb/> offices the candidate ought to be removed as far as possible from the<lb/> humiliation of receiving a vote as a personal favour which might<lb/> otherwise be denied to his merits or qualifications.  After a very ani&#45;<lb/>mated contest the congregation honoured me for the fourth time with<lb/> their suffrage&#44; but now by a decided majority of all the members<lb/> of the congregation.  But I regret that I am compelled to notice that this<lb/> renewed mark of confidence was accompanied by a redirection of<lb/> my salary&#44; when I had every right to expect&#44; that you would<lb/> have taken the opportunity when voting me in again to <hi rend="underline">increase</hi><lb/> my income&#44; as since my first coming here your finances had<lb/> so much improved and the member of <sic>worshippers</sic> so greatly<lb/> increased.  Why this reduction was made every member knows as<lb/> well as I can tell him&#44; and I do not wish to revive unpleasant feelings<lb/> by expressing my own sentiments of a proceeding which operated so inju&#45;<lb/>riously upon my interests.  Enough the congregation thought fit to fix the election<lb/> for <hi rend="underline">three</hi> years at 800 Dollars per annum&#59; but when a committee consisting<lb/> of two members notified me of the result I answered&#44; that I would accept<lb/> the office but leave the salary to be farther adjusted at a future meeting.<lb/>  A special meeting was called for general purposes&#44; but no quorum was pre<lb/>sent&#59; of course the committee were not able to report my answer<lb/> as their doing so would have answered no purpose whatever.  Before<lb/> now the regular meeting of the congregation came round&#44; a bond was<lb/> offered to me for signature &#40;the first that ever had been drawn up<lb/> since my holding office&#41; which stipulated that I would serve three<lb/> years at &#36;800 pr annum.  As I thought that the reduction<lb/> ought not to have been made&#44; and that the congregation at a later<lb/> meeting would&#44; as I conceived&#44; see ample reason to amend their<lb/> vote&#44; I unhesitatingly refused signing except conditionally for one<lb/> year&#44; and the other two to be left for future adjustment.  I accordingly<lb/> wrote the letter to the Parnass which I believe has been read to you&#44; and<lb/> also sent such a bond for his approval&#44; as accorded with my own views.</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>6.</p>
				<p>You will please to bear in mind&#44; that I was engaged in a work of great<lb/> magnitude and importance&#44; and which involved an outlay of several<lb/> thousand Dollars&#44; which would assuredly have detained me in the<lb/> city for a while year&#44; whether I had been in office or not.  I stated<lb/> this both in words and in writing to the Parnass&#44; but he conceived it<lb/> as his duty to refuse the bond I offered&#44; and to insist upon the<lb/> one which had been tendered to me.  It was in fact&#44; that I should<lb/> resign&#44; or sign a bond which I never could conscientiously assent to.<lb/>  I therefore refused positively for about four weeks.  But then reports<lb/> were spread&#44; in fact the Parnass told me so himself&#44; that a meeting<lb/> would be called&#44; and that my want of confidence in the congregation<lb/> would doubtfully so much operate against me&#44; as to prevent any vote<lb/> in my favour being obtained.  This however had no <hi rend="underline">influence upon</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">me</hi>&#44; believing myself in the right&#59; and there was then the gentleman who&#44;<lb/> had been the opposing candidate yet in the city&#44; and consequently my<lb/> not serving would have left the congregation the <hi rend="underline">choice of a person who</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">has since been elevated</hi> to the ministry of two respectable congregations.<lb/>  But appeals were made to my <hi rend="underline">feelings</hi> <add>&#63;</add>&#44; whether I could consent to have<lb/> those I had served so long&#44; and that besides <del>that</del> there was enter<lb/>tained such a prejudice against the above gentleman by many mem<lb/>bers&#44; that they would not vote for him&#59; and thus the congregation would<lb/> be placed by my <hi rend="underline">obstinacy</hi>&#44; as it was termed&#44; to be without a minister<lb/> and that <hi rend="underline">disunion</hi> would be the inevitable consequence.  Besides this<lb/> I ought to trust to the <hi rend="underline">honour</hi> and good will of the congregation and<lb/> that doubtlessly at the next meeting ample justice would be done to me.<lb/>  It may have been a <hi rend="underline">weakness</hi> in me to recede from my first purpose&#44;<lb/> yet if I have erred&#44; I erred for the sake of peace.  However this may be&#44;<lb/> I referred the whole matter to the judgment of my honoured uncle&#44; whom you<lb/> nearly all know and respect&#44; and I told him that I would abide by his<lb/> advice.  So I did&#59; in a few days I got a letter from him advising me to<lb/> accede to the demand made upon my forbearance&#59; I did press my<lb/> purpose&#44; I signed the bond&#44; and I believe that no one can say that<lb/> either since then or before I did otherwise than faithfully discharge<lb/> my duty&#59; not because I had signed a bond&#44; but because I wish to<lb/> do what is incumbent on me without faltering or evasion.  I had<lb/> however good reasons for believing that the congregation would have recon&#45;<lb/>sidered their vote&#44; and not regarded the bond in any other light than that<lb/> of a peace&#45;offering&#59; but I <hi rend="underline">deceived myself&#44; a bargain it was considered</hi>&#44;<lb/> and so it has remained to this day.  I did not tell you&#44; how galling</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">7</p>
				<p>such a proceeding has been to my feeling&#44; not for the sake of the amount<lb/> involved but because it makes by implication the service in the house of God<lb/> one of mere trade&#44; &#8220;who shall serve the cheapest.&#8221;  If I might be allowed<lb/> to judge&#44; the congregation ought to choose the most competent&#44; and allow<lb/> him a sum commensurate with their ability to give&#44; and not according<lb/> to what he might be willing to take.  I therefore last autumn wrote<lb/> to the congregation stating what I expected of them&#59; and I leave it to<lb/> their nonsense of propriety whether my views are right or wrong.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">For the future I have to state the following.  Experience<lb/> has proved that the salary originally promised me is not enough<lb/> for a moderate support of a genteel decent appearance.  Other<lb/> congregations not more numerous or at least not greatly so&#44; and<lb/> not having much more extensive means&#44; give their Hazan<lb/> a house and from &#36;1200 to 1800 salary per annum&#44; besides perqui<lb/>sites which are larger or smaller according to circumstances.  More&#45;<lb/>over in every instance elections have been made during good<lb/> behaviour.  We have all learned from observation&#44; that a small minority can<lb/> at any election render the result very uncertain&#44; and besides<lb/> constant reelections for short periods weakens the attachment of<lb/> the minister to the congregation.  He knows not whether all his<lb/> honest services will render him sufficiently popular to insure<lb/> him in his situation and every days longer continuance in office<lb/> disqualifies him more for other pursuits if he should have<lb/> to resort to them if in case he should be discarded.  It is no argument<lb/> to say&#44; that such a result is unlikely&#44; as it is within the range<lb/> of probability&#59; and the constant <sic>harrassing</sic> of the mind does not pro&#45;<lb/>mote either contentment or good will to others.  Some may say&#44; a<lb/> minister of religion ought to be above such thoughts&#44; his mind should<lb/> seek for heavenly support&#59; it is true that there is some sinfulness<lb/> mixed up with all feelings of discontent&#59; still your minister<lb/> is a man like yourselves&#44; he has feelings like yourselves&#44; and<lb/> if he is injured and his mind is distorted he must necessarily feel<lb/> discontent even if he tries to overcome it.  The very thing that<lb/> he has something to forget and to forgive destroys his usefulness<lb/> in part&#44; and greatly militates against his inward peace.  This<lb/> can be avoided&#44; and it therefore ought to be done.  An amiable arrange<lb/>ment between us can easily be arrived at&#44; if you only endeavour to</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>8</p>
				<p>convince yourselves&#44; that the Hazan as an individual has some rights<lb/> and consequently some little to say about the disposal of his services&#44; no less<lb/> than the congregation <del>have</del> as a body <del>and as much as they</del> are empowered<lb/> to select one to serve them&#44; in whom they can place confidence</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In consideration of all this I now notify the congregation&#44;<lb/> that I am willing to continue in their services if they allow me<lb/> the yearly salary of <hi rend="underline">twelve hundred and fifty dollars</hi>.  This amount<lb/> never to be reduced whilst I continue in office.  And if the congre<lb/>gation are at any time willing to increase this amount&#44; that they never&#45;<lb/>theless shall not be empowered to demand any other duties than those<lb/> hitherto rendered unless by mutual consent.  On this condition I must and do absolutely insist.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">With regard to the continuance of office I make the following<lb/> proposition&#58; The election to be&#44; if the congregation think proper for an inde&#45;<lb/>finite period&#59; I not to be allowed to resign without giving <hi rend="underline">six</hi> months<lb/> previous notice&#44; and the congregation to be at liberty to discharge me<lb/> at any time if <del>an entire</del> a clear majority of all the members either in or<lb/> out of meeting shall send a written recognition to that effect either<lb/> to the Parnass and board or to myself&#44; as I never wish to hold office<lb/> unless it be by the consent of the majority.  I know that I subject myself<lb/> more to the control of the congregation than by the mode of electing for<lb/> a stated period&#59; but still it will then be out of the power of a non&#45;resident<lb/> office&#45;seeker to disturb the harmony of the congregation periodically<lb/> at the recurrence of every reelection&#44; by not having any incentive or excuse<lb/> to offer himself as a candidate&#44; for though I may succeed in being elected<lb/> over such an opponent&#44; it is nevertheless highly unpleasant to be under<lb/> the necessity of succeeding to the disappointment of another worthy man&#44;<lb/> and such alone it is evident will offer himself to your suffrage.<lb/>  Besides this&#44; if the election stands till annulled by the congregation&#44;<lb/> &#38; as it is barely possible that a removal will be made except for good<lb/> cause&#58; the incumbent will and must feel himself more at home&#44;<lb/> and his mind more disposed to devote himself to his duties&#44; than<lb/> under the arrangement hitherto pursued&#44; where he is liable to<lb/> be sent adrift with or without reason whenever his stated period<lb/> elapsed.  According to my view of the case therefore&#44; I can see many<lb/> cogent reasons in favour of the proposal I now make to the congregation&#44;<lb/> &#38; none of any force against it.  For it differs in this from an election<lb/> during good behaviour&#44; that in the latter case the incumbent can hardly<lb/> be removed except with great difficulty&#44; unless at his own option&#44; and in<lb/> accordance with my proposition&#44; whenever the majority changes against him.</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">9</p>
				<p>If therefore a more worthy man should be within your reach&#44; you can ap&#45;<lb/>point him to <sic>supercede</sic> me&#44; no matter when this opportunity may<lb/> offer itself.  And my giving six months notice before resignation will<lb/> leave you ample time to get a fit successor&#44; as in a late instance in<lb/> a neighboring city a new Hazan was elected in thirty days after<lb/> the burial of his predecessor.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Another consideration is that up to this period I have been four<lb/> times elected&#44; twice when there were opposing candidates&#59; in all I have been<lb/> nearly eleven years in your service&#59; of the degree of my fitness all of you have had am&#45;<lb/>ple opportunity of judging&#44; and whatever imperfections of character&#44;<lb/> qualifications&#44; temper&#44; or behaviour I may be accused of&#44; you have long since<lb/> known.  No doubt I have given <sic>offence</sic> very often&#59; but I may freely say&#44;<lb/> that knowingly and <sic>wilfully</sic> I never offended any one.  But even if I had<lb/> done so&#44; and that you had collectively and individually much to<lb/> forgive&#58; still you ought to reflect that during so long a period<lb/> many unpleasant occurrences must have fallen to my lot&#59; and if I have<lb/> been found wanting in the hour of trial&#44; I can be accused of no<lb/> greater fault than any other of my fellow&#45;creatures.  At all<lb/> wants you know me thoroughly just as I am&#59; and surely it is high<lb/> time that I be assured whether <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> is to be my permanent<lb/> home or not.  I am now past thirty three years old&#44; and I ought to<lb/> be no longer <sic>harrassed</sic> about my future prospects&#59; I am content<lb/> with humble means&#44; but I should like to hold them not subject<lb/> to the constant caprice or change of dispositions to which all public<lb/> assemblies are liable&#44; and none more so than religious corporations.<lb/>  I will not appeal to your good feelings on account of past services&#59;<lb/> as I <del>did</del> have done no more than my duty&#44; although I assumed many more<lb/> details than my predecessors did.  All I claim merit for is an<lb/> honesty of intentions&#44; and a fearlessness in the discharge of my duties&#44;<lb/> without regarding my own personal interests.  This being the case&#44;<lb/> I will leave it to yourselves to determine whether if I am re&#45;<lb/>elected&#44; the engagement should not be for an indefinite period&#44;<lb/> subject to the limitations specified above.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Other matters&#44; to which I should like to call your attention<lb/> I will leave till the regular meeting of the congregation&#44; not wishing<lb/> to mix up my own situation with matters not strictly relevant to<lb/> the present subject.  In conclusion let me again earnestly exhort</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
				<p>10</p>
				<p>you all to judge kindly of my faults&#44; and not to expect perfection from<lb/> one so frail as myself.  One thing you may believe me&#44; that I have had<lb/> a great deal to forgive&#44; and hardly any one can judge of the bitterness<lb/> which has often been mingled in my cup since I have lived<lb/> among you.  It is in your power&#44; gentlemen&#44; to sweeten a little the<lb/> course of life of one to whom sorrow is no stranger.  If you<lb/> resolve to reelect me in accordance with my just wishes&#44; I<lb/> shall as formerly endeavour to devote whatever abilities I have<lb/> received from the Creator to the faithful discharge of the duties<lb/> incident to my station.  But if you decline to reelect me&#44; I shall<lb/> have the consolation that I have staid among you as long as it<lb/> was in my power to do so&#44; and that I did not leave my post whilst<lb/> I could hold it with honour to myself and usefulness to others.<lb/>  I certainly am ambitious&#59; but my ambition will be amply satisfied&#44;<lb/> if with a moderate income suitable to my calling&#44; I am permitted&#44;<lb/> without fear of a malign influence from abroad or at home to sign<lb/> myself&#44; and to be the Hazan of the congregation of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">Yours respectfully</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)"><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName>.</p>
				<p><placeName>Philaa.</placeName> <date>Friday May 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Iyar 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 5600</date></p>
			<pb n="12"/>
				<p>Not to be opened unless there be a quorum present&#59; if no meeting is held&#44; it is to be returned.</p>
				<p>To the Parnass &#38; Members</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">of the Congregation Mikveh Israel</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">of</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
				<p rend="The following is written sideways at the right hand side of the page."></p>
				<p>Address to congregation by</p>
				<p><persName role="author">Revd. Isaac Leeser</persName></p>
				<p><date>May 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Iyar 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 5600</date></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">&#40;<date>1840</date>&#41;</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
