<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item66</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 12 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">For the “Occident”</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">the Burying Ground lease</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">at <placeName>Richmond Va</placeName></p>
            <p>Mr Editor,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As perplexing as it may seem for Jewish Congregations<lb/> for to be
                compelled to assert their rights by appealing to the courts<lb/> of Justice relative
                to matters that could and ought to be settled by<lb/> their own bodies, or by the
                arbitrament of others that are disinter<lb/>ested, It is to be regretted that the
                Portuguese Congregation “Beth<lb/> Shalome” and the German Congregation “Beth Ahaba”
                have now<lb/> pending a suit in the Chancery court of the City of
                    <placeName>Richmond</placeName>,<lb/> depositions are now being taken in
                evidence for the same, before<lb/> the commissioner of that court, relative to the
                rights of the respective cong<lb/>regations to the “Beth Haim” that was vested in
                the former congregation<lb/> in the year <date>1816</date> by the Common<add>?</add>
                Hall of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>, by<lb/> virtue of the following
                ordinance</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">An ordinance</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">concerning the Hebrew Society of
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName></p>
            <p rend="align(center)">Passed <date>May 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1816</date></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Be it ordained by the president and Common Hall of the City of
                    <placeName>Richmond</placeName><lb/> in Common Hall assembled, and it is hereby
                ordained by the au<lb/>thority of the same, that one acre of Land belonging to the
                City of<lb/>
                <placeName>Richmond</placeName>, lying on <placeName>Schookoe Hill</placeName> as
                laid off and designated in<lb/> a plot of said land commonly called the
                    <placeName>Poor House land</placeName>,<lb/> made by <persName>Richard
                    Young</persName> surveyor of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>, be
                and<lb/> the same is hereby set apart and vested in the Hebrew Society of<lb/> the
                City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>, called in Hebrew “Kaal Kadosh Beth
                Sha<lb/>lome” in English, “The Congregation of the House of Peace” to be by<lb/>
                them held and exclusively used as a burying ground subject<lb/> to their Rites and
                Laws for that purpose and for that alone</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This ordinance shall commence and be in force from<lb/> and after
                its passage.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">In this case, a right is asserted by the German congregation<lb/> on
                a more <hi rend="underline">legal technical point</hi>, and in accordance to all
                rules<lb/> of equity that should at least govern religious bodies, it cannot<lb/> be
                sustained, and must receive the indignation of all enlightened<lb/> communities of
                Israelites especially, this case probably stands<lb/>
                <sic>unparralled</sic> in the annals of Jewish History in the <placeName>United<lb/>
                    States</placeName> and doubtless throughout the Israelitish world. In giving</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>a statement of the facts in this case the writer intends to give<lb/> them fairly and
                    <sic>inpartially</sic> without the least exaggeration, in order<lb/> that the
                discriminating and unprejudiced mind will be able to judge<lb/> upon its true
                merits.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The congregation “Beth Shalome” according to its record was<lb/>
                established in the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> about the
                    <date>1791</date> by the following<lb/> named gentlemen, <persName>Jacob
                    Mordecai</persName>, <persName>Joseph Darmstadt</persName>, <persName>Samuel
                    Alex<lb/>ander</persName>, <persName>Isaac H. Judah</persName>, <persName>Joseph
                    Marx</persName>, <persName>Isaac Mordecai</persName>, <persName>Gershom<lb/>
                    Judah</persName>, <persName>Lyon Hart</persName>, <persName>Myer M.
                    Cohen</persName>, <persName>Aaron Henry Baruch</persName>
                <persName>H. Judah</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Benjamin Wolf</persName>, <persName>John Tobias</persName>,
                    <persName>Manuel Judah</persName>, <persName>Jacob I. Cohen</persName><lb/>
                <persName>Zalma Rehine</persName>, <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName>,
                    <persName>Aaron N. Cardoza</persName>, <persName>Israel Cohen</persName><lb/>
                <persName>David Isaacs</persName>
                <persName>Benjamin Solomons</persName>
                <persName>Mordecai M. Mordecai</persName>,<lb/>
                <persName>Asher Marx</persName>, <persName>Samuel Mordecai</persName>,
                    <persName>Benjamin Myers</persName>, <persName>Mordecai<lb/> Myers</persName>,
                    <persName>Marcus Elcan</persName>, <persName>Abraham Myers</persName> and
                others, during that<lb/> year <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName> one of the founders
                of the congregation vested in<lb/> the hands of certain trustees a portion of his
                garden for a Burial<lb/> Ground for the interment of “All Jews male and female
                that<lb/> may die in the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> or whose bodies
                might be<lb/> brought there to be interred,” that ground was placed under the<lb/>
                control of that congregation, the dimensions of the ground was<lb/> 40 by 102 feet,
                and oblong square of 8 by 40 feet was to be reser<lb/>ved for the interment of
                    <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName> the granter, and his<lb/> kindred and
                    <persName>Cohen</persName> my partner in trade and his kindred,<lb/> the lot of
                ground was situated in a thickly inhabited part of the City<lb/> on
                    <placeName>Franklin near 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Street</placeName>, the
                congregation made interments in<lb/> that ground for a number of years, the walls
                became delapi<lb/>dated, and the nature of the grant was such that the
                congrega<lb/>tion could not exercise any legal control over it. It being<lb/> held
                by trustees for the Interment of Israelites generally without<lb/> any
                discrimination, their interment in the regular range<lb/> was certain
                notwithstanding the <sic>offences</sic> they may have per<lb/>petrated contrary to
                the Jewish Laws. In such cases no one<lb/> had a legal right to interfere, that
                ground was used till<lb/> about the year <date>1816</date> or probably a little
                later period. The population<lb/> of Israelites was not very dense at that time,
                consequently but<lb/> a small portion of the ground was filled, in that year the
                cong<lb/>regation deeming it necessary, as do all congregations, to hold<lb/> a
                Burying Ground under their own immediate control, and<lb/> subject to their Rites
                and Laws, and to abandon interments<lb/> in the Ground granted by <persName>Mr
                    Isaiah Isaacs</persName> for general inter-</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>ments without any restrictions, therefore at a meeting of the cong-<lb/>regation held
                on the <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Feb. 1816</date> it was</p>
            <p>“Resolved that <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName>, <persName>Manuel
                    Judah</persName> and <persName>Samuel<lb/> Myers</persName> be appointed a
                committee to investigate the records of<lb/> the Common Hall concerning the
                appropriation of some ground<lb/> that was laid off for Burying Grounds for the
                different Religious<lb/> Societies some time back, and that they use their
                endeavours to<lb/> obtain said ground for this congregation”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">At a subsequent meeting <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName>, who
                was then<lb/> a member of the Common Hall said before the meeting the ordina<lb/>nce
                with a plot of the same, and it was</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Resolved, that the congregation do accept the lot, and a<lb/> vote
                of thanks be given to <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName> for his unremit<lb/>ted
                exertions in procuring for this congregation the lot of Ground<lb/> from the Common
                Hall, and that four corner<lb/> stones with the letters <add>ב' ח'</add> thereon be
                placed on the Ground granted to<lb/> this congregation,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The congregation then built a substantial brick wall and<lb/>
                <sic>and</sic> Matar House on the ground at a cost of nearly fourteen<lb/> hundred
                dollars ($1400) which was raised by the liberal volun<lb/><sic>tarily</sic>
                contributions of the members</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Many of the members had the remains of their near relatives<lb/>
                taken from the old ground and re-interred in the new one, a<lb/> singular incident
                occurred relative to the first interment that<lb/> was made, <persName>Mr. Benjamin
                    Wolfe</persName>, the individual who used his ex<lb/>ertions in the procurement
                of the ground was the first that was<lb/> interred thereon, before the wall was
                built, or the ground proper-<lb/>ly treated, hence his tomb may now be seen at the
                N. E. part<lb/> of the Beth Haim no graves near it except some of his<lb/> family,
                the congregation commencing to bury at the western<lb/> part of the ground, a
                century may pass and <hi rend="underline">his</hi> grave still will<lb/> be solitary
                and alone as not more than about one eight of<lb/> the ground is now dug upon.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">About the year <date>1841</date> the congregation numbering from 90
                to 100<lb/> contributing members, about 18 or 20 withdrew and formed a German<lb/>
                congregation under the <add>?</add> of “Kaal Kadosh Beth Ahaba” on account<lb/> as
                some attribute it to, to the mismanagement of the former congregation<lb/> It will
                certainly be conceded by all, that as soon as the Jewish pop<lb/>ulation in all
                cities in the <placeName>United States</placeName> increase sufficiently, they
                form<lb/> separate congregations, and worship in accordance to the German</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>for the Shohet, and tendered to them the use of the Ground<lb/> free of charge, and
                directed the committee on the Ground or<lb/> the Parnass to <del>dig</del> have the
                graves dug as bear to the wishes<lb/> of the family or relatives of the deceased as
                practicable,<lb/> The congregation “Beth Ahaber” availed themselves of the
                provis-<lb/>ions of the Resolution for 4 or 5 years, when another effort<lb/> was
                made to effect a compromise, a committee appointed<lb/> by both congregations met,
                    <hi rend="underline">the German congregation claimed</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">the right to the Ground on account of a mere legal error
                    in</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">the drafting of the ordinance granting the land to the K. K. B.
                    S.</hi><lb/> that congregation then agreed rather than to have any fur-<lb/>ther
                difficulty about the Beth Haim, that if the K. K.<lb/> Beth <sic>ahaba</sic> would
                give to them the <hi rend="underline">small</hi> sum of<lb/> Two Hundred and fifty
                dollars that they <del>would</del> might<lb/> hold the ground conjointly and that
                each congregation<lb/> should have equal rights in <del>and</del> and to the said
                ground,<lb/> and that, that money should be expended in repairing the<lb/> Synagogue
                    <del>that</del> which was at that time in bad order,<lb/> the committee on the
                part of the German Congregation “Beth<lb/> Ahaba” would not agree on any terms and
                refused to give<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">one cent</hi>, the committee on the part of the “K. K. Beth
                Sha<lb/>lome” desired to <del>leave</del> submit the whole affair the
                    <sic>decission</sic><lb/> of arbitrators, and abide in their result, that
                proposition<lb/> was also <sic>preemptorily</sic> refused by the other party, the
                Resolu<lb/>tion granting the free use of the ground whenever application<lb/> was to
                be made for interment was not <sic>recinded</sic>, but kept in full<lb/> force, not
                satisfied however to use the ground under the kind<lb/> provisions of that
                resolution any longer which was addressed to on the<lb/> part of the “K. K. Beth
                Shalome” with <sic>a</sic> unbroken faith.” <hi rend="underline">That</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">congregation irreligiously had a false key made</hi> to
                enter<lb/> the ground with impunity, and inter therein without the<lb/> permission
                of the “K. K. Beth Shalome” until this time,</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It may probably seem strange to those unacquainted with<lb/> the
                statues of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, that such a trespass could be<lb/> made
                upon that ground and the infringements on the rights<lb/> of a congregation without
                any redress being sought<lb/> in order to bring the offenders to justice, and
                stranger<lb/> yet may it seem when on perusing the ordinance grant<lb/>ing the same
                to a specific congregation in their proper<lb/> name style and title, and to be used
                according to the Rites</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>and Laws of the Congregation, that that congregation should<lb/> be powerless by the
                arms of the laws and rendered unable<lb/> to defend their just and equitable rights.
                According<lb/> to the Laws of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, a religious
                Congregation is not known in<lb/>
                <sic>in</sic> law, they cannot be incorporated, and have therefore been<lb/>
                incapable to hold property, sue or be sued, though in accordance<lb/> to the statute
                of <date>1842</date> congregations could hold property to a<lb/> limited amount
                through the intervention of Trustees, but that<lb/> did not apply to property that
                had been vested in a congregation<lb/> prior to the passage of the act without the
                intervention of Trustees,<lb/> It will therefore be perceived by
                    <sic>refferrence</sic> to the Ordinance granting the<lb/> same, that the ground
                was vested in the <hi rend="underline">congregation</hi> and no indi-<lb/>viduals
                could exercise any legal authority over the same, be-<lb/>cause the power was not
                vested in them, a stranger could<lb/> therefore go on the ground and commit any act
                of degra<lb/>dation with impunity, however, no such act was ever per-<lb/>petrated
                until a sister congregation thought proper to take<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">legal advice</hi> and to avail itself of that disgraceful
                outrage<lb/> knowing that the <hi rend="underline">congregation</hi> “Beth Shalome”
                were incapable in<lb/> law to seek redress. By a recent enactment of the
                Legislature<lb/> which took effect on the <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> day of
                    July</date> last, it provided that<lb/> where property had been conveyed,
                devised or dedicated for<lb/> the use of any religious congregation for a House of
                worship<lb/> Burying Ground, or residence of their minister, since the year
                    <date>1777</date><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">with</hi> or <hi rend="underline">without</hi> the intervention
                of Trustees, when application<lb/> is made to the circuit court for the county or
                corporation wherein<lb/> the property lies, by the proper authorities of such
                congregation, the<lb/> court may appoint Trustees <sic>were</sic> there were or are
                none, in whom<lb/> the legal title of such property shall be vested. The passage of
                that<lb/> act although for the benefit of all religious congregations that<lb/> may
                wish to avail itself of its <sic>provissions</sic>, was procured at<lb/> the
                instance of some of the members of the “K. K. Beth Shalome”<lb/> in order that it
                might cover the case now in <sic>controversey</sic>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">That congregation in <date>January</date> last made application to
                the court for the appointment of Trustees therein named, which<lb/> application was
                met with the opposition of the German Congre-<lb/>gation, preventing a counter
                application to the court for <del>the</del><lb/>
                <del>same ground and</del> to have an equal number of Trustees from each<lb/>
                congregation, or the whole number from their congregation appoin<lb/>ted to take
                charge of the said ground.</p>
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>setting forth various reasons that caused them to withdraw from<lb/> the congregation
                “Beth Shalome” and that the Common Hall<lb/> intended the ground for all Israelites
                although they did not<lb/> express it so in the ordinance granting the same.</p>
            <p>Thus it will be perceived that the German Congregation “Beth Ahaba”<lb/> are
                endeavouring to obtain control of a “Belle Haim” on<lb/> account of a <hi
                    rend="underline">mere legal technicality</hi> arising from the fact<lb/> that in
                law that a religious congregation is not known,<lb/> and hence this advantage is
                sought, a more outrageous<lb/> affair on the part of a religious congregation, and
                more<lb/> particulars among Israelites, (where congregations do not hold<lb/>
                ground) conjointly) has probably never been attempted.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The style of the lease is <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> and others
                exparte, against<lb/>
                <persName>Levy</persName> and others exparte defendants, although the
                congre-<lb/>gations “Beth Shalome” made the application, the court has<lb/> it
                appears from the record made them defendants, and has<lb/> ordered that the
                commissioner <sic>accertain</sic> the number of members<lb/> of the congregation
                “Beth Shalome” at the time of Secession, and<lb/> also the number that seceded, also
                the present number of each<lb/> congregation, the cost of improvements on the ground
                and by<lb/> whom made, and whether the K. K. Beth Ahaba has paid any<lb/> thing for
                the improvement or protection of the Ground with<lb/> the knowledge or consent of
                the K. K. Beth Shalome,<lb/> and in order to <sic>accertain</sic> these facts the
                commissioner has<lb/> commenced the taking of <del>the depositions on</del> evidence
                tou<lb/>ching the matter. The testimony <del>thus far</del> elicited from<lb/> the
                Plaintiffs is thus far <del>is</del> rather novel, and as a jou-<lb/>rnalist it is
                deemed a duty incumbent on you to ex-<lb/>pose to public indignation and scorn such
                testimony as shall<lb/> seem to you to be given in order that the truth and facts of
                the<lb/> case shall not be made <sic>apparant</sic>, <del>and let</del> allowing the
                stigma of<lb/> reproach to fall on whomever may be deserving of it. There is<lb/>
                many facts connected in this particular case with which you<lb/> are conversant
                with, as well as the General customs<lb/> or usages of Jewish congregations in this
                country and else-<lb/>where, <del>or</del> therefore you will be able to judge of
                the<lb/> weight of the evidence in the matter, and show very<lb/> conclusively to
                your mind as well as to your numerous<lb/> readers the manner in which the truth is
                rather evaded<lb/> than avowed, causing the examination to be lengthy and
                tedious*</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
