<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckman, J.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item67</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Eckman, J.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Charleston, SC</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-02">25 February 1851</dateLet>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1851-02">5611</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item67_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item67_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item67_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item67_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
                <date>Febr 25. 5611</date>
            </p>
            <p>To the <addressee>Revd I Leeser</addressee></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">My dear Sir!</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Accept my thanks for the note you favored me by the medium of
                    <persName>Mrs Moise</persName>,<lb/> again for the insertion of my
                communications (which, by the by, were two, one<lb/> the opinion of <persName>Moses
                    Mendelsohn</persName> extends to “Could the noble v: <persName>Dohn</persName>
                etc<lb/> which is quite a different subject, belonging to the advancement of<lb/>
                Toleration, I ought to have given a superscription, which I omitted<lb/> thinking
                that it perhaps might have been sent before the<lb/> public with some of your
                remarks, as I may well ima<lb/>gine what your views must be on the subject</p>
            <p>The object of my communication of <persName>M's</persName> Opinions was to show<lb/>
                the public <del>that- what man of more learning genius et philos a<add>?</add><lb/>
                    than our mader<add>?</add>
                    <add>שועלים קטנים</add>
                </del> have thought on the subject.<lb/> You apologized or at least mentioned twice
                in your valuable periodical<lb/> the reason postponement, it surely the
                communication could not answer the<lb/> expectation raised by such double notice
                before hand.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the whole was only admitted into your paper as an <add>?</add> too<lb/> bad
                to be inserted &amp; too good to be rejected. Believe me dear sir!<lb/> my object is
                not to render myself conspicuous or even noticed. If<lb/> therefore I in future
                should send any thing unworthy of your notice<lb/> do not think it a humiliation for
                me—if disregarded I shall<lb/> be proud to find that we have men that supersede
                my<lb/> humble efforts. You are a plain honest man, (<persName>von <add>?</add>
                    Schrrot</persName> und <persName>Korin</persName>)<lb/> you understand my
                feelings. My aim is &amp; was, to do good, if other men<lb/> do better, I am happy
                to see it, but feel not hurt, by no means.<lb/> You know the field I have to labor
                in here—my task is an arduous<lb/> and difficult one so that it takes up almost all
                my time, &amp; would<lb/> to Him who dwells on high, it would bear to Eternity.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>My heart <del>aches</del> aches what I see, could I say with the Prophet<lb/>
                <add>פורה דרכתי לבדי... ואין איש אתי</add>. I would have been satisfied, but I
                have<lb/> worse than an <add>כנגדי איש</add>. But I hope the cause of justice <hi
                    rend="underline">truth</hi><lb/> &amp; Holiness will come off victorious at
                last<lb/> I labor hard, lecture every <date>Sabbath</date> in the Synag. &amp; again
                    <date>Sunday</date> evening in<lb/> the tabernacle which latter are not
                    <del>just do</del> just against Christianity as to<lb/> the Confirmation of our
                holy Truth—besides this I have Hebrew<lb/> school (numbering about 20 pupils fr the
                age of 10 upwards to<lb/> adults, the latter chiefly ladies; apart of those I teach
                at the Sunday<lb/> School. My congregation is (perhaps more than) satisfied, except<lb/>
                <persName>Mr P</persName>: &amp; some of his ultra attachés—whom he continually
                sets<lb/> against me, but the fury is abating.</p>
            <p>From the above you may suppose that I have enough to do,<lb/> however I was so
                disgusted at the communications of the irreverent<lb/>
                <persName>Reverend Millers</persName> insertion that I intend to write some articles
                to<lb/> the following purport</p>
            <p>Christianity founded on Prophecies which are not fulfilled in<lb/>
                <persName>Jesus</persName>—the accommodation theory is of no avail with men of<lb/>
                Reason, cannot sub<add>?</add> „Plain scripture.</p>
            <p>The gospels flow fr: an <hi rend="underline">obscure source</hi>, are not
                written<lb/> by eye witness, <del>wer</del> consequently we see the
                    <sic>forshaddowing</sic> (as<lb/> they may call it) to be but a shadow without
                substance<lb/> The system of Redemption &amp; Justification by the blood of
                    <add>?</add>...<lb/> is against reason, against scripture, &amp; would have been
                an act<lb/> of injustice &amp; cruelty of G.d, of which
                    <persName>Dionysius</persName> the tyrant<lb/> did not render one self guilty
                    (<persName>Damon</persName> &amp; <persName>Pythias</persName>) now my dear<lb/>
                sir if you think this subject not yet fully discussed in your</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Periodical I am willing to send in communications, but if this is<lb/> not done I
                will, though with reluctance try to do my duty.<lb/> But before hand I beg for no
                indulgence if you should<lb/> find my communications not relevant enough I shall
                esteem<lb/> you as I have done till now &amp; respect you more<lb/> for you already
                approved honesty &amp; candour.<lb/> My arguments will be taken fr
                    <sic>christian</sic> authorities<lb/> or better <hi rend="underline">Christian
                    divines</hi> of <placeName>Germany</placeName>
                <placeName>Engl</placeName> &amp; <placeName>America</placeName><lb/> I say divines
                for the whole system is <sic>acknowledg</sic> to be hollow<lb/> even by man of piety
                of the other party, it is but infatuation<lb/> that starts man like
                        <persName><sic>miller</sic></persName> to appear in our age with<lb/>
                absurdities long repudiated by a Herder, <persName>Reinhard Coffler<add>?</add><lb/>
                    Rosenmuller</persName> &amp; the host of even conservative divines<lb/> If you
                think it worth the while you may just notice<lb/> that in the last page 564 the
                superscription is omitted<lb/> by <sic>inadvertancy</sic> &amp; coming fr same hand
                you then<lb/> took them as one.</p>
            <p>Now I must <sic>apoligize</sic> for engrossing so much with<lb/> my affairs. It would
                be an object of deep regret if you<lb/> should discontinue your periodical, it is
                the only one bearing<lb/> distinct mark of Judaism, of <sic>of</sic> character grave
                enough to discuss<lb/> &amp; to convey more serious information, the other has more
                an<lb/> ephemeral character, nor seems the author to have the object of
                Religion<lb/> so much at heart.</p>
            <p>In reference to <persName>Millers</persName> insertions in the last he has become so
                turbu<lb/>lent that I think that they ought not to be admitted into the Jewish
                advocate</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>devoted to the diffusion of knowledge on Jewish Literature &amp; <sic>Rely</sic><lb/>
                excuse my candor, he (<persName>Miller</persName>) can but claim an act of
                toleration<lb/> in our exclusive periodicals, but never to speak, thus—what
                absurdity<lb/> &amp; pernicious poison is advanced on one page by blind
                infatuation<lb/> may require more than 20 pages to be answered by sober<lb/> reason
                &amp; erudite <sic>knowed</sic> of the spirit of the Heb: Language<lb/> &amp; Post
                Idyle. We might as well allow then to <del>come</del> sled<lb/> to our lecture rooms
                (as was done here in my tabernacle<lb/> by a mad cap <persName>Bloch</persName>)
                &amp; attack us there, and then refute them<lb/> in answer ten times as lengthy. We
                ought not to submit<lb/> to this. I wrote <persName>Mr Bloch</persName> he may come
                &amp; hear &amp; if he wishes<lb/> to refute he may do it by the medium of the
                missionary press<lb/> When again asked if I would not allow him to do so on the
                spot<lb/> I wrote him As we have before us all the trash<add>?</add> that has<lb/>
                been expectorated<add>?</add> by the <hi rend="underline">hireling</hi>, of <hi
                    rend="underline">honest</hi> but duped men<lb/> this 30 years, &amp; all amounts
                to null, I could not<lb/> expect that <hi rend="underline">he</hi> could advance any
                thing new.</p>
            <p>If you deign to answer this, I will tell you before hand as your<lb/> time is
                precious do it very short, even in abrupt <add>?</add><lb/> phrases—without
                ceremony.</p>
            <p>Accept the assurance of the sincere regards to your<lb/> character &amp; labors fr
                the improvement of our people</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">from</p>
            <p rend="indent(11)">
                <persName role="author">J Eckman</persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
