<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item34</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Anytown, St. Thomas</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1864-07" source="" attested="yes">3 July 1864</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1864-07" source="" attested="yes">5624</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item34_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>4 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> <date>3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> July 1864 &#40;5624&#41;</date></p>
				<p><addressee>Revd. Isaac Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">I am in receipt of your various favors<lb/> and also <date>June</date> Occident with my sermon on the &#8220;Citizen <persName>King</persName>.&#8221;  Your heading it<lb/> thus is no misnomer&#44; and is satisfactory.  It is very exactly reprinted&#44; and afforded&#44;<lb/> let me hope&#44; pleasure to your numerous readers.  I am glad you have spoken out plainly<lb/> on the subject of a &#8220;personal messiah.&#8221;  The events of the past&#44; and those looming out of the<lb/> future do not present anything so favorable to the Jewish mind that it should adopt the<lb/> opinions of <persName>Maunheimer</persName> and <persName>Horwitz</persName> on the subject.  I&#44; for one&#44; am undesirous of abandoning<lb/> the rich hopes of <placeName>Israel&#39;s</placeName> return to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>&#44; and the universal belief in monotheism among<lb/> the families of the earth&#44; together with the reign of absolute peace throughout the world&#44;<lb/> and all the priceless blessings attendant thereon&#44; for the vague ideas and generalities of<lb/> Jewish neologists.  I am for <add>Hebrew</add> content to die hopefully <add>Hebrew</add></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">What say you to the &#8220;Powenir<add>&#63;</add> party of <placeName>Cura&#231;ao</placeName> issuing their shameless caliency<add>&#63;</add><lb/> against their brethren&#33;  It is very painful to find Jews thus venting their spite&#44; in the<lb/> heat of local dissension&#44; to the detriment and perhaps future evil of all <placeName>Israel</placeName>.  I allude<lb/> to their publishing the libel that <add>Hebrew</add> is directed against Christians.  May the<lb/> consequences of disseminating this falsehood not recoil on themselves.  The pastoral<lb/> letter of <persName>Rabbi Chumaceiro</persName> you must have seen by this time&#44; as well as the &#8220;dingy<lb/> sheet&#8221; containing the slander.  You surely will not suffer your pen to be idle in this<lb/> emergency&#44; we all expect to see a scathing answer from you on the whole question.<lb/>  I had already in the pulpit exposed&#44; in part&#44; its other falsity&#59; and intend going on till the<lb/> subject be exhausted.  The head and front of the party was here a week ago&#44;<lb/> but I declined meeting him or extending him any courtesy.  I told his friends that</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p><del>with</del> to his and party&#39;s views on the subject of synagogal and other reforms I would<lb/> not have attacked&#44; but when he and they issued a slanderous impretation<add>&#63;</add> against<lb/> their own flesh and blood&#44; it was time&#44; since it affected the reputations of every<lb/> individual Israelite&#44; that their ignorance and malevolence should be exposed.<lb/>  His name is <persName>Abraham Cohen Henriques</persName>.  His chief collaborators and his brother<lb/> <persName>Solomon Cohen Henriques</persName>&#44; his brother in law <persName>Augel Jessuron<add>&#63;</add></persName>&#44; a <persName>Doctor Henriques</persName><lb/> and a <persName>Doctor Senior</persName>.  These are the <add>Hebrew</add>.  <persName>A. C. H.</persName> writes in Dutch.  His<lb/> effusions are then translated into French by <persName>Dr. H</persName>&#44; and <persName>Augel Jessuron</persName> then<lb/> puts the precious ideas into Spanish.  But the filtration does not purify the<lb/> feculent matter which gutters<add>&#63;</add> from their pens.  It is said that <persName>A. C. H.</persName> came on<lb/> here on a speculative trip to obtain subscribers to the party&#44; and contributions to<lb/> their <del>new</del> proposed new Synagogue&#44; the worship in which is&#44; sans doute&#44; to eclipse&#44; in its bold<lb/> departure from the ancient standards of practice&#44; and that the German and<lb/> American Reformers have hitherto established.  I do not think he gained<lb/> either subscribers or subscriptions and as his attack on the Jews was<lb/> generally denounced in no unmeasured terms by even nominal Israelites&#44;<lb/> he could not have gone home rejoicing.</p>
				<p>My post here is not an easy one&#44; but I am disposed to accept the<lb/> difficulties it presents.  Fortunately the By Laws which stipulate that<lb/> the worship shall be according to that followed by the Spa. &#38; Portug. Jews&#44; and<lb/> the power the Laws invest me with of directing and conducting the whole<lb/> economy of public worship&#44; <del>is</del> are obstacles to any sudden or ill considered<lb/> changes in the ritual or worship.  I can take my stand on these protecting<lb/> defenses&#44; and refuse to sanction what the majority of <placeName>Israel</placeName> disapproves of.  Quietness however reigns at present&#44; yet the time may not be so distant for<lb/> the outbreak of disturbances.  But I do not apprehend such violence as<lb/> the Porrenir<add>&#63;</add> party have exhibited.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We have had some little display of irreligion not withstanding.  Your old</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>correspondent <persName>M B. Simmonds</persName>&#44; now poor no longer&#44; but rich in worldly goods&#44;<lb/> has been staggered by <persName>Colenso</persName>&#44; and openly declares himself a <hi rend="underline">Unitarian</hi>&#33;&#33; <add>&#63;</add> his<lb/> disbelief in the Bible&#33;  On my election&#44; people were taxed more highly to pay my salary&#44; among<lb/> others himself.  To get rid of this demand of the Synagogue&#44; he applied to be admitted a<lb/> member of the Lutheran church&#59; the<del>y</del> authorities consented to take his money&#44; taxed him<lb/> &#36;32 <add>&#63;</add> allotted him a seat in  church &#38;c&#44; but the Govermt. told him he must<lb/> pay his finta<add>&#63;</add> to the Synagogue also&#44; unless he became a Christian.  Of course if <persName>Colenso</persName><lb/> unsettled his belief as a Jew&#44; he did not predispose him to to take up xleavity<add>&#63;</add><lb/> instead&#44; so at the present moment he contributed to Shool and Church&#44; and belongs<lb/> to neither.  Another German <persName>Shofel</persName> likewise refused to pay the whole of his<lb/> tax and sent a letter to the representatives that if they did not reduce it to half<lb/> he would <hi rend="underline">apostatise</hi>.  They sent him no answer&#44; but recorded a strong resolution<lb/> on their minutes condemnatory of his conduct.  He went to the Moravians&#44; and applied<lb/> to become a member&#59; but on being told that he must learn certain test books by<lb/> heart&#44; and he examined on them in open assembly prior to being <sic>baptised</sic>&#44; he withdrew in disgust.  So<lb/> you see I do not repose on a bed of roses</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I <sic>inclose</sic> herewith the receipt of the Captn. of the Responsible<lb/> and your Invoice Amtg to &#36;78.50  The books have not come to hand&#44;<lb/> they must have been amongst that part of the cargo condemned and<lb/> sold at <placeName>Bermuda</placeName>.  I want the small Bibles and Roads to Faith<lb/> badly&#44; and Prayer Books too.  I wrote all about them in the<lb/> letter I gave my brother&#44; and which I suppose he has handed you.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Well the Great <persName>General Grant</persName> perhaps may not turn out<lb/> a <persName>Ulysses</persName> after all&#44; and the <placeName>south</placeName> <hi rend="underline">may yet conquer a peace</hi>.  I<lb/> fervently hope and pray they may&#44; and tho&#39; I would be <sic>loth</sic> to see any<lb/> part of the Federal territory ravaged and despoiled as the Union soldiery<lb/> treated the Confederate territory&#44; yet little commiseration would be felt<lb/> if northern soil were made to feel what it is to be trodden by the armed</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>heel of the invader.  Down to date the southerners appear to have<lb/> the best of it.  The deserve success&#44; for they have sacrificed their<lb/> own lives to achieve it&#44; and not hired mercenaries to fight their<lb/> battles.  My brother has frightful northern proclivities.  His opinion<lb/> of northern honor and political honesty is lofty and grand.  We<lb/> are widely different in our Estimate of the result&#44; and the<lb/> ability as well as inclination of the Federal states to pay the<lb/> public creditor.  I hope he will not be one of the sufferers&#59;<lb/> I have urged him till I am weary to sell out&#44; and have<lb/> nothing to do with Greenbacks and 5&#47;20s&#44; and on the finely<lb/> engraved promises to pay of <persName>Mr. Chase</persName>&#44; but all my entreaties<lb/> have been of no avail.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I will write you soon again.  I delivered your<lb/> message to <persName>Mr. Osorio</persName> about the &#163;14.  The <persName>Revd. Dr. Myers</persName> of<lb/> <placeName>Kingston Ja</placeName> has received notice that his services will not be<lb/> required after his term of engagement expires&#44; this time next year.<lb/>  <persName>Mrs. Nathan</persName> and her mother send their kind regards to you<lb/> and all old friends.  <persName>Mayor Wolff&#39;s</persName> golden wedding will<lb/> take place on <date>31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> August</date>&#44; Grand preparations are being made<lb/> for the event.  I will write you all about it when it comes<lb/> off.  <persName>Chamacero</persName> is coming over for the occasion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">God bless and protect you prays</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">yours sincerely</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName></p>
				<p>The heat is dreadful.  It is really a great effort to write<lb/> a long letter&#44; and I am sure you will appreciate it.<lb/>  Tell my brother&#44; if with you&#44; that I will write soon<lb/> <add>Hebrew</add></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
