<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">[Morais, S.]</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item212</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">[Morais, S.]</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when="1864"/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item212_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item212_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item212_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item212_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>“Man cannot be established by wickedness” (Proverbs XII. 3)</p>
            <p>My friends! The present is not a season for recriminations. I will not administer
                now<lb/> the scathing rebuke which they will deserve who in their political
                harangues have<lb/> dispersed<add>?</add> the fair name of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>. Were I ever inclined to analyze at the bar of
                your<lb/> impartial opinion individuals who abused their positions by conjuring up
                the demoniac<lb/> Hurt of prejudice against my people, I would be restrained by the
                magnanimous crumple<lb/> of our chief Executive. He, than whom none could be more
                vilified by his opponents,<lb/> appeals to God as a witness, that animosity does not
                rankle in his breast.<lb/> Yes, I will say it with the ancient moralist “Hatred
                stirreth up strife, but love<lb/> covereth all sins” The heart that throbs with
                undying affection for the Union, can<lb/> forgive the offense of some of its
                narrow-minded children. We my Brethren—the<lb/> representatives of a sublime Truth,
                for the preservation of which we have suffered and<lb/> bled, ought never to judge
                of the merits of a preamble from the illiberality of some<lb/> who profess to
                advocate it. We ought, under all circumstances though unjustly held in<lb/>
                contempt, to triumph over the strides taken by our fellow-men toward the
                attainment<lb/> of glorious ends. Therefore upon this day, when the harmonious voice
                of loyalty is raised<lb/> to heaven with thanksgivings and praises, the
                    <sic>worshipper</sic> of a Unity should duly be forced<lb/>
                <del>among</del> mid the national chorus <del>of</del> that <del>In</del> celebrates
                the victories of the Union. But I see, I have,<lb/> for the sake of a rhetorical
                flourish, employed an incorrect expression. Not the victories<lb/> of the Union, but
                those of Freedom, my friends, we do celebrate. What is Union with<lb/> human
                degradation. Who would again affix his seal to the bond that resigned millions<lb/>
                to <add>?</add>dom? Not I, the enfranchised slave of <persName>Myraim</persName>.
                Not you, whose motto is progress<lb/> and civilization least then your version
                yonder, and behold the happy change wrought by the<lb/> hand of Providence. When the
                    <add>?</add> which summoned all to arms, resounded throughout this<lb/> land, a
                band of patriots vowed to set high upon <placeName>Fort Sumter</placeName> the flag
                that treason had<lb/> lowered to the earth. Who arose then to impede their work? The
                men of a state which<lb/> has now buried in the waters of the
                    <placeName>Potomac</placeName> the shackles of servitude. She blushed at a
                deed<lb/> that had stained her escutcheon, and timely laid on the national altar, an
                offering of atonement.<lb/> Her momentary indiscretion misled the foe, therefore she
                was <sic>comitted</sic> by the adversaries of a universal<lb/> freedom. They
                coquetted with her, who fancied that she would be easily <add>?</add> by their acts,
                but<lb/> she withstood the seduction, and voluntarily cast her lot among the free
                &amp; the brave. My name<lb/> shall no longer be called
                    <placeName>Maryland</placeName> but merry-land for thou hast verily breathed in
                joyous spirit<lb/> into the souls of thy inhabitants. And when I remember, my
                friend, that from the windows<lb/> of our legislative hall a scene could be
                witnessed, two years ago, that belied the enactments of<lb/> a Republican Senate, I
                discover, with a naked eye, the finger of the Almighty Creator working<lb/>
                wonders.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> gave the first impulse to the wheel
                of progress, and it has ever since<lb/> rolled on with a steady motion. My beloved
                hearers! If this alone were the issue<add>?</add> of our struggle, it<lb/> would
                suffice the philanthropist. It would offer him ample occasion to pour forth sincere
                thanksgivings<lb/> for the benevolence of his unfortunate fellow-beings. But we have
                also taught the world thereby<lb/> a lesson of incalculable utility Aye “man cannot
                be established by wickedness”. A few ambitious men<lb/> because they could not yet
                as chiefs in all high places, sought to destroy the happiness of their country.<lb/>
                But the fore-brand which they threw in her midst has very nigh well devoured their
                vitals. God who<lb/> abhors inequity confounded their counsel. Innumerable were the
                means which they employed to divide<lb/> and conquer. The diplomatic skill in which
                they confidently abound, undaunted courage, a power of<lb/> resistance worthy of a
                holy cause, all the appliances of science, all the dexterity of arts, were resorted
                to<lb/> by the leaders of factions and their deluded followers to fasten upon the
                    <placeName>North</placeName> ruin and disgrace,<lb/> but they conceived vanity
                and brought forth naught. <placeName>England</placeName>, envious of <del>he</del>
                our greatness, may<lb/> have in an <sic>earl</sic> hour for herself, lent them her
                moral or rather <hi rend="underline">im</hi>moral aid. Her Majesty of<lb/>
                <placeName>France</placeName> who ascended the throne by treading upon the corpses
                of revolutionary victims, may have inspired<lb/> the hope of an early recognition,
                but the display of our <sic>collossal</sic> strength rendered our enemies
                    <add>?</add><lb/> of their promises. Thus frustrated in all their schemes, those
                whites of the <placeName>South</placeName> that have rebelled against<lb/>
                legitimate authority, let loose now their piratical agents, and an unbridled
                soldiery to devastate our<lb/> fields and prey on our commerce, but “man cannot be
                established by wickedness. <placeName>Gettysburg</placeName> and the<lb/>
                <placeName>Shenandoah Valley</placeName> tell the flight of the invading host; the
                    <add>?</add> and <sic>Wachusset</sic> prove his<lb/> impotency. The fate of a
                confederacy founded upon fraud has been sealed above. The conqueror of<lb/>
                <placeName>Atlanta</placeName> will dismantle its ramparts; the hero of
                    <placeName>Vicksburg</placeName> will make an end of its rule.<lb/> But say
                they, who from feelings of humanity are averse to blood-shed. How dearly will our
                final victory<lb/> be bought!” It may cost the lives of thousands of our promising
                youths; it may cover the face of<lb/> the land with the pall of death; we may again
                and again be startled by the <sic>shreeks</sic> of desolate<lb/> mothers; we may
                behold the crushing sorrow of fathers. My kind-hearted friends! I also share<lb/>
                with you the horror which war inspires, and could I have averted it from this
                country of our love,<lb/> no sacrifice would have been deemed too great. I would
                have even yielded a cherished desire, which<lb/> pervades my very soul—that of
                universal liberty—and trusted to God, who might in His good time<lb/> bring it to
                pass, but the gage was thrown at our feet. We must either accept it, or bear<lb/>
                upon our foreheads the mark of ignominy. What American will hesitate how to choose
                in the<lb/> alternative? To stake his existence at the battle-field in the defense
                of the Stars and Stripes, or to<lb/> be the contempt of people and the derision of
                Kings? Life is a precious gift, but the poltroon who<lb/> to preserve it sells his
                country and his rights, is a worthless carcass. Besides, it appears (may I<lb/> not
                sin of impiety) it appears as though<del>t</del> the fiat of the Omnipotent was that
                great truths<lb/> must wend their course through blood ere they are firmly
                established upon earth. It may be with<lb/> the wise design that their value be
                enhanced in our estimation, that they may <del>me</del> be rendered dearer<lb/> to
                all hearts. But what ever may be the inscrutable motive, we cannot expect that for
                our sake<lb/> the divine decree will be altered. Deploring therefore, the dire
                necessity of war, we must not sh<add>?</add></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>from it, when the life of a nation hangs thereupon. The <sic>heros</sic> of your
                revolution, those<lb/> noble names “that grace the rolls of fame” went boldly forth
                to the conflict, because they<lb/> preferred death to foreign subjugation. Not the
                thirst of blood stirred them up, but the<lb/> conviction that from its reeking mass
                the genius of Liberty would rise. Your <persName>Montgomery</persName> and<lb/> Your
                    <persName>Warrens</persName>, who breathed their last mid the roar of the
                cannon, were the instruments by which<lb/> the God of battles, wrought the happiness
                of a whole generation. True, the men they gallantly<lb/> fought were not the
                children of this soil—brothers nurtured at the same breast. They were<lb/> the sons
                of the stranger, who attempted to rule over us. Now, alas! we are marshaled in
                mortal<lb/> array against the offspring of our kind mother. But upon them, who first
                unsheathed the<lb/>
                <sic>fritricidal</sic> sword rests the terrible responsibility. Unnatural and
                perfidious they endeavoured to sunder<lb/> at a stroke that bond of union which
                constitutes our greatness. That which <add>?</add> is the glory of
                    <placeName>America</placeName>,<lb/> and the joy of the oppressed they would
                demolish, to rear upon its ruin a monument to human bondage.<lb/> It shall not be.
                The thundering voice of millions <del>of</del> among the free has so proclaimed.
                Upon the<lb/> day that the suffrage of a sovereign people was to declare in whose
                hands they shall trust their<lb/> interests during another cycle of years, my
                anxious looks were directed to the wires whereby intelli<lb/>=gence is spread
                abroad. The air had been previously filled with inauspicious rumors. The<lb/> most
                incredulous believed that the mighty contest would surely give birth to violence and
                sedition.<lb/> My friends! We have won many battles, but the last was the most
                decisive. It cut off the<lb/> remaining prop upon which the fungus confederacy
                rested for support. No more can it trust <del>on</del><lb/> for success in the
                diversity of our political opinions. Every man exercised his elective franchise<lb/>
                agreeably to his best judgment, but even they who bestow an undue degree of pity on
                our misguided<lb/> foes refused to lead countenance to treason. The dreaded clamour
                of angry multitudes was not heard<lb/> in our borders, the threats of disaffection
                found no utterance in our midst. I <del>called</del> challenged<lb/> the world to
                show a parallel case. Of a nation, I say, wrought up to the highest pitch of<lb/>
                political effervescence who, nevertheless regulate their actions by the square and
                compass of equity.<lb/> Let now the foreign press <sic>indite</sic> its diatribes
                about man's inability for self government. We<lb/> have proved our capacity for it.
                We have proved moreover, that we are resolved at all hazards,<lb/> to bequeath to
                posterity the country founded by our <persName>Washington</persName> in all its
                untarnished <sic>lustre</sic>.<lb/> Once more will we call upon the rebellious to
                desist “Return ye wayward children; your<lb/> trespasses shall be remembered no
                more” If they hearken, we will “beat our swords into <sic>plough</sic>-shares,<lb/>
                and our spears into pruning-hooks.” If they harden their hearts, we shall lament so
                much contumacy,<lb/> but its disastrous effects shall be required at their hands.
                Oh! Let us pray that they may heed our call.<lb/> Let us in all sincerity tender the
                olive branch. Let us endeavour by honorable means to facilitate its<lb/> acceptance.
                More than in the prowess of our army and the feats of our navy we ought to seek<lb/>
                glory in laboring peacefully for the reconstruction of our once mighty Republic. Our
                progress in<lb/> arts and sciences, which thus <del>uh</del> unhappy war has caused
                to develop will sink into utter insignific<lb/>=ance before the progress which all
                the human race shall attain, when tutored by a nation whose laws</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>are the laws of righteousness and whose sole defense is peace. Oh! Let us pray for
                the<lb/> dawning of that joyous day when thirty five reunited States shall offer a
                national<lb/> thanksgiving, while the symbol of their greatness shall proudly wave
                over every<lb/> dome and sphere. Let us pray for peace.</p>
            <p>Parent of good! We lay prostrate at the footstool of Thy mercy and crave for
                peace.<lb/> Grateful for Thy manifold favors at all times and this year especially,
                we yet cannot fully<lb/> rejoice in its fruition. Thou hast verily filled to
                overflowing the cup of our prosperity, but<lb/> that of bitter sorrow is also
                brought nigh to our lips. The aspect of the dead, the<lb/> agony of the wounded, the
                moaning of the sufferers, tear our hearts. From the<lb/>
                <sic>ensanguined</sic>battle field, from the chilly and dreary camps, from the
                bereaved and lonely<lb/> hearth, a voice rises unto Thee, O compassionate Lord! and
                “peace, peace” it cries. Oh I send<lb/> a ray of Divine wisdom to <sic>illumme</sic>
                the mind of our Chief Magistrate, that he may discover<lb/> the instrument of peace.
                Let the gentle spirit of forbearance hover around the Assembly<lb/> of our Senators
                and <del>Le</del> Representatives and guide their deliberations. Repress the
                vehemence<lb/> of zealots, and let the feelings of the obdurate be softened by
                tokens of brotherhood and love.<lb/> May we speedily throw again My holy courts, to
                thank and praise Thy name, Oh most<lb/> High God! <sic>for</sic> the longed-for
                peace of our beloved Union.</p>
            <p>And now I beseech Thee O Lord! <sic>to</sic> excite within us a sentiment of
                patriotism, that we may<lb/> enlist our names among these of our beneficent men and
                women who labor for the sake of our<lb/> defenders at sea and on land. May our
                hospitals, our sanitary commissions and our<lb/> soldiers and societies obtain a
                ready and generous cooperation from those who have been taught<lb/> to believe that
                “Charity <del>delive</del> delivereth from death”. May such be Thy gracious will,
                O<lb/> Heavenly Creator. Amen.</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">A <date>thanksgiving</date> discourse for the year
                    <date>1864</date></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
