<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item99</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Nathan, M. N.</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false">Leeser,
                            Isaac</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Kingston, Jamaica</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1863-03">6 March 1863</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item99_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 6 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">
                <placeName>96 Orange St.</placeName>
            </p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Kingston Jam</placeName>: <date>6<hi rend="sup"
                        >th</hi> March<lb/>1863</date>.</p>
            <p>My dear <addressee>Mr. Leeser</addressee>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I duly acknowledge<lb/> your last 2 letters, and the receipt of<lb/>
                Occidents and 3 copies of the printed<lb/> Edition of the Pentateuch. You must<lb/>
                like all good and loyal citizens of the<lb/> great Republic, submit to the
                difficulties<lb/> of the present situation. When so much<lb/> paper is required for
                    <hi rend="underline">Green Backs</hi> and<lb/> other numerous varieties of
                notes, issued<lb/> for the maintenance of public credit, the<lb/> Editor of the
                Occident should not grumble<lb/> at the rise in price of printing material.<lb/>
                Sacrifices are indispensable on the part<lb/> of every individual when so glorious a
                war<lb/> for the redemption and freedom of the negro<lb/> race, and the subjugation
                of white rebels<lb/> is to be brought to a triumphant close.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>When that object is accomplished, your self<lb/> denial, tho' it may involve you in
                pecuniary<lb/> losses, will be appreciated; and congress, when<lb/> personally
                appealed to, will, doubtless, especially<lb/> the <hi rend="underline"
                    >republican</hi> part of it, recompense you with<lb/> a grant from the public
                treasury. Your petition<lb/> cannot fail of being signed by all the Jewish<lb/>
                population throughout the States, and public<lb/> virtue will thus meet its own
                reward. I have<lb/> not yet had time to peruse the article to which<lb/> you direct
                my attention. My time is so occupied<lb/> with my school, owing to the Shamash of
                the<lb/> Congregation; my assistant Hebrew teacher,<lb/> having left for
                    <placeName>California</placeName>, that I have had no<lb/> leisure. Our new
                minister, <persName>Mr. Myers</persName>, has got<lb/> himself into a dilemma with
                some of the big<lb/> wigs of the Synagogue, in consequence of his<lb/> many refusal
                to sanction the calling up to<lb/> the Sepher, of people married to Christian
                women,<lb/> and <hi rend="underline">colored</hi> women to boot. You can have
                no<lb/> conception of the falling off in this particular congre-<lb/>gation from
                various causes within the last twenty<lb/> years. Its numerous members have dwindled
                down<lb/> to a mere <sic>handfull</sic>; but the pride and arrogance<lb/> remain as
                of old; and tincture all their acts, to<lb/> which had feelings, towards all who
                venture to differ<lb/> from the <hi rend="underline">rulers</hi> in opinion, largely
                add their share.<lb/> As for the <hi rend="underline">minister</hi> of the other
                Synagogue, De<add>?</add><lb/> the least I say of him the better. I am not a
                    <add>מלשין</add></p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="indent(1)">work out for the Occident, if my <hi rend="underline">liver</hi> permits.<lb/>
                <persName>Moses</persName>, it is evident could not have imposed on the<lb/> 2
                    <add>?</add> tribes the duty of going over the <placeName>Jordan</placeName>
                <add>חמשים</add><lb/> but only <add>חלוצים</add> armed for war; and therefore he
                uses the<lb/> latter; whereas <persName>Joshua</persName> could, as commanded,<lb/>
                decline to forage for them, and compel them to manage<lb/> their own commissariat.
                The sacred text is not<lb/> strained to <del>meet</del>
                <sic>acord</sic> with this explanation but rather<lb/> removes the difficulty of
                accounting in what<lb/> way the people subsisted, until the <add>?</add><lb/>
                fell.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">I have formed an acquaintance with<lb/> a <persName>Dr.
                    Daniell</persName>—of the British army, a man<lb/> of wonderful knowledge in all
                matters relating<lb/> to <placeName>Africa</placeName>, where he passed 18 years of
                his life.<lb/> He is a great scholar, not alone in the studies<lb/> appertaining to
                his profession, but in others, and<lb/> is esteemed an <hi rend="underline"
                    >authority</hi> in <placeName>England</placeName> in philology,<lb/> ethnology,
                botany, &amp;c. A bosom friend of <persName>Professor<lb/> Owen</persName> the
                Eminent naturalist. We had a<lb/> delightful evening's talk till 12 o'Clock
                last<lb/> night, and that is how I spent my <date>Purim</date>. He<lb/> possesses
                monotheism, but believes in the Bible,<lb/> not I think, in the Testament.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The war, I see, continues to linger.<lb/> The termination cannot
                however be very<lb/> distant, and I hope it will end as I wish.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It may however become more complicated<lb/> by the defiant attitude of one of
                the<lb/> belligerents towards the French Emperor.<lb/> The English Government is not
                hypocritical.<lb/> Your charge is not just. If it had intervened,<lb/> I incline to
                think with <persName>Lords Palmerston</persName><lb/> and
                    <persName>Russel</persName> that the <placeName>north</placeName> would have
                raised<lb/> such an overwhelming force as would have<lb/> crushed the
                    <placeName>south</placeName> at once <add>אל תעמוד לפני רעך בשעת כעסו</add><lb/>
                applies as well to nations as individuals.<lb/>
                <placeName>England</placeName> has enough on her hands in meeting the<lb/> hungry
                cravings of her starving operatives<lb/> without putting her fingers into her
                neighbour's<lb/> dish. I call their neutral action wise and<lb/> humane, and it will
                prove to be so in the<lb/> long run. The feelings of the English government<lb/>
                &amp; nation too are with the <placeName>south</placeName>, and the<lb/> ravings of
                    <persName>Bright</persName> &amp; <persName>Cobden</persName> and the anti-<lb/>
                slavery party are ineffectual to change them.<lb/> I am alive to the short comings
                of my native<lb/> country, but <del>they are</del> in this matter it is not<lb/>
                obnoxious to the abuse lavished upon it by the<lb/> people of
                    <placeName>America</placeName>.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">My wife and mother join with<lb/> me in affectionate wishes &amp;
                regards</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">Yours Sincerely</p>
            <p rend="indent(8)">
                <persName role="author">M N Nathan</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but I would surprise you, were I to often the<lb/> budget of doings and sayings of
                this man. Judaism<lb/> is in a bad state here, spirit of religion is utterly<lb/>
                wanting, with no one competent to rouse it from the<lb/> torpor into which it has
                fallen. We have had here a<lb/> certain <persName>Rabbi Alfendri</persName> from
                    <placeName>Smyrna</placeName>, his mission<lb/> here was a failure; we are too
                poor ourselves, and<lb/> have too many indigent ones in our midst, to<lb/>
                contribute to the claims (?) of such travelling gentry.<lb/> Why don't they stop at
                home? We hear of the<lb/> doings and writings of <persName>Mr. De Solla</persName>,
                late of <placeName>Montego<lb/> Bay</placeName>, against <persName>Mr.
                    Morais</persName>. Can't you send me some<lb/> of that precious productions? Are
                you not going<lb/> to use your pen in defense of scripture against<lb/>
                <persName>Bishop Calendo</persName>? <persName>Benisch</persName> has come out
                manfully,<lb/> but altho' he has answered some points admirably,<lb/> I do not like
                    <hi rend="underline">all</hi> he has written. The wood, water,<lb/> and pasture
                question he has handled ably. I<lb/> am, just to keep my hand in, maintaining a
                cor<lb/>respondence on the subject with a <sic>xtian</sic> clergyman;<lb/> and made
                the word <add>חמשים</add>
                <del>the</del> my study, at his request.<lb/> I cannot agree that it means equipped,
                or harnessed,<lb/> in gist, or armed, but <add>?</add> think it signifies<lb/> v<hi
                    rend="underline">ictualled</hi> or <hi rend="underline">provisioned</hi> from
                    <add>חמץ</add> the abdomen.<lb/> The Bible says <add>וגם צדה לא עשו להם</add>;
                Does that imply that<lb/> they had no <hi rend="underline">food</hi> at all except
                the <add>בצק</add>? I should say<lb/> that <add>צדה</add> means <hi rend="underline"
                    >cooked</hi> or <hi rend="underline">prepared</hi> provisions, and<lb/>
                <add>עשו</add> being joined to it, an act of preparation or<lb/> cooking is
                inferred, the same as <add>אפה</add> to <add>בצק</add> before<lb/> the latter
                becomes <add>לחם</add>. Hence the Israelites might</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>not have had <add>צדה</add>, and get the onions, leeks<lb/> garlic, and Cucumbers as
                vegetables, and the<lb/> melons and <hi rend="underline">dates</hi> as fruits might
                have afforded<lb/> them a plentiful supply of food for the <add>חמץ</add> belly<lb/>
                or stomach, and hence they were <add>חמשים</add>. In
                <persName>Joshua</persName><lb/> chap: i 11 the people are ordered <add>הכינו לכם
                    צדה</add>, whilst<lb/> in verse 14 the <persName>Reub</persName>:
                    <persName>Gad</persName>: through: are told <add>חמושים</add><lb/>
                <add>ואתם תעברו חמשים</add> ye shall pass over <hi rend="underline">victualled</hi>,
                ergo, you must<lb/> furnish your own commissarist. Again in IV.12<lb/> it is written
                they passed over <add>חמשים</add>
                <hi rend="underline">provisioned</hi>, and in<lb/> the following verse <add>חלוצי
                    צבא</add> in <hi rend="underline">fighting tr<add>?</add></hi>, or<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">armed for war</hi>. In Judges VII.II the <add>חמשים</add> could
                not<lb/> have been the <hi rend="underline">armed men</hi>, or they would have
                been<lb/> called sentinels, patriots, or piquets, whose duty is<lb/> always
                    <add>בקצה המחנה</add>; and in verse 19 they are properly<lb/> named,
                    <add>שמרים</add> which you have rendered <hi rend="underline">sentinels</hi>. These<lb/>
                <add>חמשים</add> must consequently have been the <hi rend="underline"
                        ><sic>suttlers</sic></hi><lb/> whose place or station was <hi
                    rend="underline">outside</hi> the <hi rend="underline">lives</hi>, and<lb/> not
                within them with the soldiery. If this view<lb/> can be maintained, it disposes of
                the objections of<lb/> those who assert that the people had no food but<lb/> the
                    <add>בצק</add>. God did not lead them thro' a fertile country<lb/> like the
                    <add>ארץ פלשתים</add>, but into the <add>מדבר</add>; yet that unpro-<lb/>ductive
                waste had no terrors for them, they had no<lb/> immediate fears of hunger, for they
                were <add>חמשים</add> furnished<lb/> with food, tho' not with <add>צדה</add> cooked
                food. If<lb/> rationalists must be satisfied and shown demon-<lb/>stratively that
                the multitude was not in a<lb/> starving condition, my exegesis will convince<lb/>
                them. This hasty sketch I may possibly</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
