<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item66</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
						<addressee editor="true" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item66_wk1_body0012.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 12 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">For the &#8220;Occident&#8221;</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">the Burying Ground lease</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">at <placeName>Richmond Va</placeName></p>
				<p>Mr Editor&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">As perplexing as it may seem for Jewish Congregations<lb/> for to be compelled to assert their rights by appealing to the courts<lb/> of Justice relative to matters that could and ought to be settled by<lb/> their own bodies&#44; or by the arbitrament of others that are disinter<lb/>ested&#44; It is to be regretted that the Portuguese Congregation &#8220;Beth<lb/> Shalome&#8221; and the German Congregation &#8220;Beth Ahaba&#8221; have now<lb/> pending a suit in the Chancery court of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44;<lb/> depositions are now being taken in evidence for the same&#44; before<lb/> the commissioner of that court&#44; relative to the rights of the respective cong<lb/>regations to the &#8220;Beth Haim&#8221; that was vested in the former congregation<lb/> in the year <date>1816</date> by the Common<add>&#63;</add> Hall of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44; by<lb/> virtue of the following ordinance</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">An ordinance</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">concerning the Hebrew Society of <placeName>Richmond</placeName></p>
				<p rend="align(center)">Passed <date>May 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1816</date></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Be it ordained by the president and Common Hall of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName><lb/> in Common Hall assembled&#44; and it is hereby ordained by the au<lb/>thority of the same&#44; that one acre of Land belonging to the City of<lb/> <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44; lying on <placeName>Schookoe Hill</placeName> as laid off and designated in<lb/> a plot of said land commonly called the <placeName>Poor House land</placeName>&#44;<lb/> made by <persName>Richard Young</persName> surveyor of the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44; be and<lb/> the same is hereby set apart and vested in the Hebrew Society of<lb/> the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#44; called in Hebrew &#8220;Kaal Kadosh Beth Sha<lb/>lome&#8221; in English&#44; &#8220;The Congregation of the House of Peace&#8221; to be by<lb/> them held and exclusively used as a burying ground subject<lb/> to their Rites and Laws for that purpose and for that alone</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">This ordinance shall commence and be in force from<lb/> and after its passage.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In this case&#44; a right is asserted by the German congregation<lb/> on a more <hi rend="underline">legal technical point</hi>&#44; and in accordance to all rules<lb/> of equity that should at least govern religious bodies&#44; it cannot<lb/> be sustained&#44; and must receive the indignation of all enlightened<lb/> communities of Israelites especially&#44; this case probably stands<lb/> <sic>unparralled</sic> in the annals of Jewish History in the <placeName>United<lb/> States</placeName> and doubtless throughout the Israelitish world.  In giving</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>a statement of the facts in this case the writer intends to give<lb/> them fairly and <sic>inpartially</sic> without the least exaggeration&#44; in order<lb/> that the discriminating and unprejudiced mind will be able to judge<lb/> upon its true merits.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The congregation &#8220;Beth Shalome&#8221; according to its record was<lb/> established in the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> about the <date>1791</date> by the following<lb/> named gentlemen&#44; <persName>Jacob Mordecai</persName>&#44; <persName>Joseph Darmstadt</persName>&#44; <persName>Samuel Alex<lb/>ander</persName>&#44; <persName>Isaac H. Judah</persName>&#44; <persName>Joseph Marx</persName>&#44; <persName>Isaac Mordecai</persName>&#44; <persName>Gershom<lb/> Judah</persName>&#44; <persName>Lyon Hart</persName>&#44; <persName>Myer M. Cohen</persName>&#44; <persName>Aaron Henry Baruch</persName> <persName>H. Judah</persName><lb/> <persName>Benjamin Wolf</persName>&#44; <persName>John Tobias</persName>&#44; <persName>Manuel Judah</persName>&#44; <persName>Jacob I. Cohen</persName><lb/> <persName>Zalma Rehine</persName>&#44; <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName>&#44; <persName>Aaron N. Cardoza</persName>&#44; <persName>Israel Cohen</persName><lb/> <persName>David Isaacs</persName> <persName>Benjamin Solomons</persName> <persName>Mordecai M. Mordecai</persName>&#44;<lb/> <persName>Asher Marx</persName>&#44; <persName>Samuel Mordecai</persName>&#44; <persName>Benjamin Myers</persName>&#44; <persName>Mordecai<lb/> Myers</persName>&#44; <persName>Marcus Elcan</persName>&#44; <persName>Abraham Myers</persName> and others&#44; during that<lb/> year <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName> one of the founders of the congregation vested in<lb/> the hands of certain trustees a portion of his garden for a Burial<lb/> Ground for the interment of &#8220;All Jews male and female that<lb/> may die in the City of <placeName>Richmond</placeName> or whose bodies might be<lb/> brought there to be interred&#44;&#8221; that ground was placed under the<lb/> control of that congregation&#44; the dimensions of the ground was<lb/> 40 by 102 feet&#44; and oblong square of 8 by 40 feet was to be reser<lb/>ved for the interment of <persName>Isaiah Isaacs</persName> the granter&#44; and his<lb/> kindred and <persName>Cohen</persName> my partner in trade and his kindred&#44;<lb/> the lot of ground was situated in a thickly inhabited part of the City<lb/> on <placeName>Franklin near 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Street</placeName>&#44; the congregation made interments in<lb/> that ground for a number of years&#44; the walls became delapi<lb/>dated&#44; and the nature of the grant was such that the congrega<lb/>tion could not exercise any legal control over it.  It being<lb/> held by trustees for the Interment of Israelites generally without<lb/> any discrimination&#44; their interment in the regular range<lb/> was certain notwithstanding the <sic>offences</sic> they may have per<lb/>petrated contrary to the Jewish Laws.  In such cases no one<lb/> had a legal right to interfere&#44; that ground was used till<lb/> about the year <date>1816</date> or probably a little later period.  The population<lb/> of Israelites was not very dense at that time&#44; consequently but<lb/> a small portion of the ground was filled&#44; in that year the cong<lb/>regation deeming it necessary&#44; as do all congregations&#44; to hold<lb/> a Burying Ground under their own immediate control&#44; and<lb/> subject to their Rites and Laws&#44; and to abandon interments<lb/> in the Ground granted by <persName>Mr Isaiah Isaacs</persName> for general inter&#45;</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p>ments without any restrictions&#44; therefore at a meeting of the cong&#45;<lb/>regation held on the <date>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Feb. 1816</date> it was</p>
				<p>&#8220;Resolved that <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName>&#44; <persName>Manuel Judah</persName> and <persName>Samuel<lb/> Myers</persName> be appointed a committee to investigate the records of<lb/> the Common Hall concerning the appropriation of some ground<lb/> that was laid off for Burying Grounds for the different Religious<lb/> Societies some time back&#44; and that they use their endeavours to<lb/> obtain said ground for this congregation&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">At a subsequent meeting <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName>&#44; who was then<lb/> a member of the Common Hall said before the meeting the ordina<lb/>nce with a plot of the same&#44; and it was</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Resolved&#44; that the congregation do accept the lot&#44; and a<lb/> vote of thanks be given to <persName>Mr Benjamin Wolfe</persName> for his unremit<lb/>ted exertions in procuring for this congregation the lot of Ground<lb/> from the Common Hall&#44; and that four corner<lb/> stones with the letters <add>Hebrew</add> thereon be placed on the Ground granted to<lb/> this congregation&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The congregation then built a substantial brick wall and<lb/> <sic>and</sic> Matar House on the ground at a cost of nearly fourteen<lb/> hundred dollars &#40;&#36;1400&#41; which was raised by the liberal volun<lb/><sic>tarily</sic> contributions of the members</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Many of the members had the remains of their near relatives<lb/> taken from the old ground and re&#45;interred in the new one&#44; a<lb/> singular incident occurred relative to the first interment that<lb/> was made&#44; <persName>Mr. Benjamin Wolfe</persName>&#44; the individual who used his ex<lb/>ertions in the procurement of the ground was the first that was<lb/> interred thereon&#44; before the wall was built&#44; or the ground proper&#45;<lb/>ly treated&#44; hence his tomb may now be seen at the N. E. part<lb/> of the Beth Haim no graves near it except some of his<lb/> family&#44; the congregation commencing to bury at the western<lb/> part of the ground&#44; a century may pass and <hi rend="underline">his</hi> grave still will<lb/> be solitary and alone as not more than about one eight of<lb/> the ground is now dug upon.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">About the year <date>1841</date> the congregation numbering from 90 to 100<lb/> contributing members&#44; about 18 or 20 withdrew and formed a German<lb/> congregation under the <add>&#63;</add> of &#8220;Kaal Kadosh Beth Ahaba&#8221; on account<lb/> as some attribute it to&#44; to the mismanagement of the former congregation<lb/> It will certainly be conceded by all&#44; that as soon as the Jewish pop<lb/>ulation in all cities in the <placeName>United States</placeName> increase sufficiently&#44; they form<lb/> separate congregations&#44; and worship in accordance to the German</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p>for the Shohet&#44; and tendered to them the use of the Ground<lb/> free of charge&#44; and directed the committee on the Ground or<lb/> the Parnass to <del>dig</del> have the graves dug as bear to the wishes<lb/> of the family or relatives of the deceased as practicable&#44;<lb/> The congregation &#8220;Beth Ahaber&#8221; availed themselves of the provis&#45;<lb/>ions of the Resolution for 4 or 5 years&#44; when another effort<lb/> was made to effect a compromise&#44; a committee appointed<lb/> by both congregations met&#44; <hi rend="underline">the German congregation claimed</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">the right to the Ground on account of a mere legal error in</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">the drafting of the ordinance granting the land to the K. K. B. S.</hi><lb/> that congregation then agreed rather than to have any fur&#45;<lb/>ther difficulty about the Beth Haim&#44; that if the K. K.<lb/> Beth <sic>ahaba</sic> would give to them the <hi rend="underline">small</hi> sum of<lb/> Two Hundred and fifty dollars that they <del>would</del> might<lb/> hold the ground conjointly and that each congregation<lb/> should have equal rights in <del>and</del> and to the said ground&#44;<lb/> and that&#44; that money should be expended in repairing the<lb/> Synagogue <del>that</del> which was at that time in bad order&#44;<lb/> the committee on the part of the German Congregation &#8220;Beth<lb/> Ahaba&#8221; would not agree on any terms and refused to give<lb/> <hi rend="underline">one cent</hi>&#44; the committee on the part of the &#8220;K. K. Beth Sha<lb/>lome&#8221; desired to <del>leave</del> submit the whole affair the <sic>decission</sic><lb/> of arbitrators&#44; and abide in their result&#44; that proposition<lb/> was also <sic>preemptorily</sic> refused by the other party&#44; the Resolu<lb/>tion granting the free use of the ground whenever application<lb/> was to be made for interment was not <sic>recinded</sic>&#44; but kept in full<lb/> force&#44; not satisfied however to use the ground under the kind<lb/> provisions of that resolution any longer which was addressed to on the<lb/> part of the &#8220;K. K. Beth Shalome&#8221; with <sic>a</sic> unbroken faith.&#8221;  <hi rend="underline">That</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">congregation irreligiously had a false key made</hi> to enter<lb/> the ground with impunity&#44; and inter therein without the<lb/> permission of the &#8220;K. K. Beth Shalome&#8221; until this time&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It may probably seem strange to those unacquainted with<lb/> the statues of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>&#44; that such a trespass could be<lb/> made upon that ground and the infringements on the rights<lb/> of a congregation without any redress being sought<lb/> in order to bring the offenders to justice&#44; and stranger<lb/> yet may it seem when on perusing the ordinance grant<lb/>ing the same to a specific congregation in their proper<lb/> name style and title&#44; and to be used according to the Rites</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
				<p>and Laws of the Congregation&#44; that that congregation should<lb/> be powerless by the arms of the laws and rendered unable<lb/> to defend their just and equitable rights.  According<lb/> to the Laws of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>&#44; a religious Congregation is not known in<lb/> <sic>in</sic> law&#44; they cannot be incorporated&#44; and have therefore been<lb/> incapable to hold property&#44; sue or be sued&#44; though in accordance<lb/> to the statute of <date>1842</date> congregations could hold property to a<lb/> limited amount through the intervention of Trustees&#44; but that<lb/> did not apply to property that had been vested in a congregation<lb/> prior to the passage of the act without the intervention of Trustees&#44;<lb/> It will therefore be perceived by <sic>refferrence</sic> to the Ordinance granting the<lb/> same&#44; that the ground was vested in the <hi rend="underline">congregation</hi> and no indi&#45;<lb/>viduals could exercise any legal authority over the same&#44; be&#45;<lb/>cause the power was not vested in them&#44; a stranger could<lb/> therefore go on the ground and commit any act of degra<lb/>dation with impunity&#44; however&#44; no such act was ever per&#45;<lb/>petrated until a sister congregation thought proper to take<lb/> <hi rend="underline">legal advice</hi> and to avail itself of that disgraceful outrage<lb/> knowing that the <hi rend="underline">congregation</hi> &#8220;Beth Shalome&#8221; were incapable in<lb/> law to seek redress.  By a recent enactment of the Legislature<lb/> which took effect on the <date>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> day of July</date> last&#44; it provided that<lb/> where property had been conveyed&#44; devised or dedicated for<lb/> the use of any religious congregation for a House of worship<lb/> Burying Ground&#44; or residence of their minister&#44; since the year <date>1777</date><lb/> <hi rend="underline">with</hi> or <hi rend="underline">without</hi> the intervention of Trustees&#44; when application<lb/> is made to the circuit court for the county or corporation wherein<lb/> the property lies&#44; by the proper authorities of such congregation&#44; the<lb/> court may appoint Trustees <sic>were</sic> there were or are none&#44; in whom<lb/> the legal title of such property shall be vested.  The passage of that<lb/> act although for the benefit of all religious congregations that<lb/> may wish to avail itself of its <sic>provissions</sic>&#44; was procured at<lb/> the instance of some of the members of the &#8220;K. K. Beth Shalome&#8221;<lb/> in order that it might cover the case now in <sic>controversey</sic>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">That congregation in <date>January</date> last made application to the court for the appointment of Trustees therein named&#44; which<lb/> application was met with the opposition of the German Congre&#45;<lb/>gation&#44; preventing a counter application to the court for <del>the</del><lb/> <del>same ground and</del> to have an equal number of Trustees from each<lb/> congregation&#44; or the whole number from their congregation appoin<lb/>ted to take charge of the said ground.</p>
			<pb n="12"/>
				<p>setting forth various reasons that caused them to withdraw from<lb/> the congregation &#8220;Beth Shalome&#8221; and that the Common Hall<lb/> intended the ground for all Israelites although they did not<lb/> express it so in the ordinance granting the same.</p>
				<p>Thus it will be perceived that the German Congregation &#8220;Beth Ahaba&#8221;<lb/> are endeavouring to obtain control of a &#8220;Belle Haim&#8221; on<lb/> account of a <hi rend="underline">mere legal technicality</hi> arising from the fact<lb/> that in law that a religious congregation is not known&#44;<lb/> and hence this advantage is sought&#44; a more outrageous<lb/> affair on the part of a religious congregation&#44; and more<lb/> particulars among Israelites&#44; &#40;where congregations do not hold<lb/> ground&#41; conjointly&#41; has probably never been attempted.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The style of the lease is <persName>Rosenfeld</persName> and others exparte&#44; against<lb/> <persName>Levy</persName> and others exparte defendants&#44; although the congre&#45;<lb/>gations &#8220;Beth Shalome&#8221; made the application&#44; the court has<lb/> it appears from the record made them defendants&#44; and has<lb/> ordered that the commissioner <sic>accertain</sic> the number of members<lb/> of the congregation &#8220;Beth Shalome&#8221; at the time of Secession&#44; and<lb/> also the number that seceded&#44; also the present number of each<lb/> congregation&#44; the cost of improvements on the ground and by<lb/> whom made&#44; and whether the K. K. Beth Ahaba has paid any<lb/> thing for the improvement or protection of the Ground with<lb/> the knowledge or consent of the K. K. Beth Shalome&#44;<lb/> and in order to <sic>accertain</sic> these facts the commissioner has<lb/> commenced the taking of <del>the depositions on</del> evidence tou<lb/>ching the matter.  The testimony <del>thus far</del> elicited from<lb/> the Plaintiffs is thus far <del>is</del> rather novel&#44; and as a jou&#45;<lb/>rnalist it is deemed a duty incumbent on you to ex&#45;<lb/>pose to public indignation and scorn such testimony as shall<lb/> seem to you to be given in order that the truth and facts of the<lb/> case shall not be made <sic>apparant</sic>&#44; <del>and let</del> allowing the stigma of<lb/> reproach to fall on whomever may be deserving of it.  There is<lb/> many facts connected in this particular case with which you<lb/> are conversant with&#44; as well as the General customs<lb/> or usages of Jewish congregations in this country and else&#45;<lb/>where&#44; <del>or</del> therefore you will be able to judge of the<lb/> weight of the evidence in the matter&#44; and show very<lb/> conclusively to your mind as well as to your numerous<lb/> readers the manner in which the truth is rather evaded<lb/> than avowed&#44; causing the examination to be lengthy and tedious&#42;</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
