<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item154</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Leeser, Isaac</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Zalma Rehine</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1842-10" source="" attested="yes">19 October 1842</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="1842-10" source="" attested="yes">15 Heshvan 5603</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item154_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>3 pages on 4 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p>Wax seal</p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)"><placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> <date>October 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Heshvan 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 5603</date>.</p>
				<p>Dear Uncle.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I should judge from your letter that when you wrote you had not<lb/> received the <add>&#63;</add> liner I had sent you by <persName>Mrs. Lyons</persName>&#44; who nevertheless<lb/> had promised to call on you on her journey to her new home.  But<lb/> I have little doubt that she fulfilled her promise by calling before she<lb/> left&#44; and that she likewise told <persName>aunt R</persName> all the particulars about<lb/> the wedding.  I am well aware that ladies like to hear such<lb/> matters&#59; but I am but little acquainted with them to give full<lb/> particulars.  The wedding however was a tolerably merry one&#44;<lb/> and plenty to eat and to drink was set before all the com&#45;<lb/>pany.  As usual some affronts were given&#59; since some persons<lb/> thought themselves entitled to an invitation which was not extended<lb/> to them.  Among the rest a cousin of the bride&#44; who expected to be <hi rend="underline">unter</hi>&#45;<lb/><hi rend="underline">ferer</hi>&#44; and not being asked she and <sic>and</sic> husband did not come<lb/> at all.  However this you know is not uncommon&#59; I myself staid till<lb/> near one o&#39;clock&#59; as they did not sit down to supper till a quarter before<lb/> twelve&#44; and I was expected to stay to say prayers.  It was rather<lb/> a later hour for me than I liked to remain out of bed&#59; but as there was<lb/> no help for it I had to submit.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Old <persName>Mr Wolff</persName> has been at our house for some weeks.<lb/>  He had a cataract on one eye&#44; and could not see well out of<lb/> the other.  He had accordingly an operation before<add>&#63;</add> to remove<lb/> the cataract from the one eye&#44; already <date>Sunday</date> two weeks ago&#59;<lb/> and as yet he has not been down stairs.  As my room is I think<lb/> the most convenient in the house I gave it up to him&#59; though I<lb/> do not hold him in very high estimation&#44; since he is for a European<lb/> as little of a Jew as ever I saw in my life.  However he too has<lb/> not escaped without his share of trouble.  I hope that in a week or two<lb/> he may be able to travel southwards as he lives in <placeName>Mobile&#44; Alabama</placeName>&#59; a person sick in a house makes a great difference in all arrange<lb/>ments.</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>As I am writing a message is brought that <persName>Rachel Pyke</persName> &#40;<persName>Peixotto</persName>&#41; was<lb/> last night confined&#59; but the child is dead.  I do not admire that couple<lb/> much.  I have recommended him to several persons to give him goods<lb/> on commission&#59; but he invariably has failed of paying over what he<lb/> sold&#44; and so he will get but little more from Jews.  He has cost me<lb/> besides somewhat like twenty Dollars in money&#44; and more indirectly&#44;<lb/> and from me therefore he has nothing to expect.  Upon the whole there<lb/> is little satisfaction in doing anything for the poor of this community.  They<lb/> generally eat up what they get&#59; and but small thanks do even fall to<lb/> my share at least&#59; I know not how it may be with other people.  It<lb/> would not matter much if I were rich&#59; but having to work for every cent<lb/> I get&#44; it is rather hard that so many make constant claim to the<lb/> little I have&#44; and do it in such a manner that a refusal is out of my<lb/> power.  I have determined at times not to be liberal&#59; but I see no way<lb/> whatever to avoid giving more than I should do for my means.  Still<lb/> as I am a single man and having no one whom I need work for&#44; it makes<lb/> but small odds at last&#44; as I hope with God&#39;s Helping to be always able to earn<lb/> my living&#59; and if I have this respectably I have no right to ask for more.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">My intention was to go to <placeName>New York</placeName> last <date>Sunday</date>.  But <persName>Mr. S. Pesoa</persName><lb/> was on <date>Thursday</date> &#38; <date>Friday</date> so ill&#44; that the Doctor had no hopes of his<lb/> living to the utmost more than 72 hours.  But last evening I went<lb/> to see him&#44; and he appeared to me not to be quite so sick as that he<lb/> might not recover.  <persName>Doctor Jackson</persName> happened to come in as I was<lb/> going away&#44; and I waited till he was going again&#44; when he asked<lb/> to ride down in his carriage&#44; and took me to <placeName>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#38; Chestnut Streets</placeName><lb/> &#40;believe in <placeName>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Walnut</placeName>&#41;&#59; he then told me that there is but small<lb/> probability of his recovery&#44; yet there is no symptom which would make<lb/> his disease necessarily fatal.  So I trust&#44; that the poor young man<lb/> may get up again&#44; especially as he has four to five children &#38; a helpless wife<lb/> depending for support upon his daily exertions.  I thought that the family might<lb/> think it unkind in me to leave the city under these circumstances&#44; so I reach<add>&#63;</add></p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>up my mind to defer my journey&#44; though I thereby will in all probabili<lb/>ty lose the fine weather which we now have.  Next <date>Sunday</date><lb/> I have <add>Hebrew</add> for my father and on <date>Tuesday</date> I believe they will<lb/> set a tombstone for <persName>Mr Allen</persName>&#44; when his year expires&#59; so I shall<lb/> not get off next week either.  So you see&#44; Uncle&#44; that my little<lb/> excursion depend upon so many circumstances&#44; that I can not even<lb/> leave within the week if I feel ever so much inclined to travel.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Have any Baltimorean signed the prospectus for the Occident&#63;<lb/>  I have about 60 already in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> and vicinity&#44; and expect at<lb/> least 20 more&#59; how many there are in <placeName>New York</placeName> I shall learn only<lb/> when I get there&#59; as the people there are too busy to write.<lb/>  I myself would never have thought of a paper for the present&#59;<lb/> but I have been induced to give the proposal in consequence<lb/> of solicitation from various quarters.  Whether the very persons who<lb/> urged me will do any thing appears very doubtful&#59; but there is <add>&#63;</add><lb/> consolation if I do not print the paper I shall lose nothing by <add>&#63;</add></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">All your friends desire to be remembered&#59; <persName>Amelia Allen</persName> in particu<lb/>lar told me I must mention her name.  It is hardly requisite to<lb/> write a page full of names&#59; so I leave you to judge who all<lb/> enquire about you.  Give my love to <persName>Aunt R.</persName> <persName>Rachel</persName>&#44; <persName>Mr Judah</persName><lb/> <persName>Mr. &#38; Mrs Block</persName>&#44; the <persName>Ettings</persName>&#44; and all our mutual friends.</p>
			<p rend="indent(6)">With high regard</p>
			<p rend="indent(7)">your obt. Nephew</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)"><persName role="author">Isaac Leeser</persName></p>
				<p>I had last week a letter</p>
				<p>from <persName>Mr. Nathan</persName> of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName></p>
				<p>neither he nor his wife was well at</p>
				<p>the time.  He makes an apology for</p>
				<p>not sending <add>Hebrew</add>.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p><addressee>Mr. Zalma Rehine</addressee></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Care of <persName>Hanover &#38; German</persName></p>
			<p rend="indent(3)"><placeName>Baltimore</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(4)"><placeName>Md.</placeName></p>
				<p><hi rend="underline">single</hi>. </p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
