<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Labatt, H. I.</author>
				<editor/>
				<sponsor/>
				<funder/>
				<principal/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
				item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note/>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution/>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item188</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head/>
					<letHeading>
						<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="yes">Labatt, H. I.</author>
						<addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
						<deliverer/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet/>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author/>
							<editor/>
							<respStmt>
								<resp/>
								<name/>
							</respStmt>
							<title/>
							<decoNote/>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl/>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation/>
							<textLang/>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item188_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item188_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item188_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item188_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
										>letter</material>letter </support>
								<extent>4 pages on 4 sheets <dimensions/>
								</extent>
								<foliation/>
								<collation/>
								<condition fragment="false"/>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout/>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote/>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote/>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions>Newspaper Clipping</additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote/>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p/>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat/>
						<envDesc occ="false"/>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin/>
						<provenance/>
						<acquisition/>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source/>
								<change/>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent/>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates/>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl/>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p/>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p/>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p/>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p/>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p/>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p/>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p/>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p/>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition/>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc/>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc/>
					<label/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation/>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item/>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""/>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p>I regret to add Dr's Statement is false in many<lb/> respects, as probably his
				information was<lb/> derived from <persName>Mr Goldsmith</persName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In the first place the Doctor is not<lb/> legally our Rabbi, he
				never was so elected.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In the second, <persName>Dr E</persName> never questioned<lb/>
				messenger but merely listened to calumny</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In the third, he had no recourse<lb/> to any expedient. The Trustees
				did so<lb/>
				<sic>authorise</sic> him to appear before the three<lb/> members without
					<persName>Mr Messinger</persName> being<lb/> aware of their action.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In the fourth. The congregation have<lb/> adopted to eat meat of no
				other shochet<lb/> than <persName>Messinger</persName> &amp; we boast as
				religious<lb/> men as any in the world, perhaps not<lb/> more so.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">There will be a sequel to this of<lb/> which I shall keep you
				advised.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Upon these remarks you may be<lb/> certain <persName>Dr
					E.</persName> cannot be reelected at<lb/> the end of the year &amp; if you know
				of any<lb/> competent ministers who of their own accord<lb/> or at your suggestion
				will visit <placeName>San<lb/> Francisco</placeName> &amp; when here will act
				prudently<lb/> they would do well to come out</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">yrs. Truly. <persName role="author">H I Labatt</persName></p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p>they intend to request the Doctor to<lb/> resign. He who was so unpopular<lb/> &amp;
				was elected by such a struggle &amp;<lb/> such sacrifices has in 6 short weeks<lb/>
				make himself outrageously inimical<lb/> to the whole congregation. I hear but<lb/>
				two opinions. One asking him to resign<lb/> the other dismissing him from his
				post.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In a new country it was in<lb/> the Doctors province to endear
				himself<lb/> to a warm &amp; ardent congregation but<lb/> he has chosen the
				opposite. Yesterday<lb/> in conversation the Doctor was advised<lb/> by my father
				&amp; myself to be careful<lb/> of his actions that the congregation were very<lb/>
				uneasy about the Schochet matter &amp; his<lb/> position &amp; <hi rend="underline"
					>might</hi> censure him. He said<lb/> on that subject he courted their
				censure<lb/> &amp; forthwith proclaimed to the world through<lb/> the papers that we
				were all fools &amp; knew<lb/> not what we did that our Shochet<lb/> was no shochet
				&amp; his Shechilah to be<lb/> Terephah. (see publication)</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I enclose you the publication with<lb/> the notes thereupon that
				seem proper.<lb/> I regret this matter on the Doctor's account</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<hi rend="bold">MISCELLANEOUS.</hi>
			</p>
			<p><hi rend="bold">NOTICE TO THE ISRAELITES OF</hi><lb/>
				<placeName>SAN FRANCISCO</placeName> AND VICINITY.</p>
			<p>
				<hi rend="italics">To the Officers of the Congregations Emanuel and Shereth<lb/>
					Israel, and to the Members of the Jewish Denomination<lb/> of this City:</hi>
			</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">BRETHREN IN FAITH!—In reply to certain queries<lb/> laid before me
				by the Prest. of K. K. Sh. Js., in a letter<lb/> dated <date>Nov. 29</date>, A. C.,
				I feel conscientiously bound to<lb/> state at large:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. That our laws in relation to animal food,
				have the<lb/> sanction of a number of passages of the Holy Writ: See<lb/> Gen. 9: 4;
				Levit. 11; 3: 17; 7: 23-27; 17: 10-14;<lb/> Deut. 14: 4-20, etc.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">2d. They were strictly adhered to by our Prophets:<lb/> See
					<persName>Ezek.</persName> 4: 14; <persName>Dan.</persName> 1: 8; and by our
				nation through<lb/> a series of ages and generations.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">These laws are preservative of physical and mental<lb/> health. By
				abstaining from the use of gross blood, (the<lb/>
				<hi rend="italics">cruor</hi>) from certain portions of (almost) indigestible fat,
				from animals that feed on carrion, that die of themselves,<lb/> that labor under
				consumptive, hepatic, <sic>hydrocephalous</sic><lb/> diseases, or of those of the
				kidneys, the heart, or the<lb/> other internal organs—not to mention the
				loathsome<lb/> disease of the swine—by abstaining from these, we reject<lb/> food
				that is a prolific source of disease, that blunts the<lb/> moral feelings, that
				inflames the passions, irritates the<lb/> blood, and rouses the animal
				propensities—that animal-<lb/>izes man.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">This fact is acknowledged by the testimony of ages<lb/> past, and by
				the light of advanced science of the present<lb/> age, as also by Christian
				commentators: See <persName>Clarke</persName> and<lb/> other commentators on Lev. 11
				et Deut. 14.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">We therefore need not wonder that men of science and<lb/>
				intelligence, as also proprietors of public establishments<lb/> of note even of
				other denominations, in places where we<lb/> and our principles are known, never use
				common animal<lb/> food whenever such as prepared for our use is within<lb/>
				reach.*</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">And in all <placeName>Israel</placeName>, from times immemorial,
				only men of<lb/> gravity, of unquestionable piety, and approved solidity<lb/> of
				character and principle, were entrusted with the<lb/> office of <hi rend="italics"
					>Shochat</hi>, i. e. of killing and inspecting the ani-<lb/>mals intended for
				the use of Israelites, who, on finding<lb/> the animal free from disease and sound,
				generally puts<lb/> a seal used solely for that purpose on different portions<lb/>
				of it, as marks of its <sic>properiety</sic> for our use.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Schochat acts under the inspection of the Rabbi.<lb/> The former
				after a proper study of Animal Anatomy and<lb/> Pathology, as laid down in our laws,
				has to submit to an<lb/> examination to a properly authorized Rabbi, (usually<lb/>
				that of the respective city where the Schochat wishes to<lb/> practice,) who, on
				finding the candidate religiously and<lb/> legally trustworthy, provides him with a
					<hi rend="italics">Rabbalah</hi>, (au-<lb/>thorization to be a Shochat,) and
				even then the Shochat<lb/> has to refer to the Rabbi certain difficult cases, and
				to<lb/> submit to re-examination at certain periods.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Only a diplomated Rabbi is authorized by our law to<lb/> institute a
				Schochat; no Schochat nor a number of Scho-<lb/>chalim dare presume to do so, such
				an act is by the law<lb/>
				<sic>delared</sic> null; and the person thus created Shochat is
					<sic>de-<lb/>clare</sic> by said laws an interloper, and unworthy of trust.<lb/>
				(Code Yorah Deah §1 let. 18, et. ib. Tor Zahab lit 4.)</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">There are cases in which even legally instituted<lb/> Shochlim
				forfeit their Rabbalah. Among others we may<lb/> mention the following, as pertinent
				to the subject.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">1. If a Shochat is found to have himself shown a dis-<lb/>regard
				towards the dietetic laws by partaking of for-<lb/>bidden food. (Code Y. D., § §1,
				2, 119 etc.)</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">2. If he violates the <date>Sabbath</date> or other national<lb/>
				laws. (Ib.)</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">3. By physical causes, as obtuseness of the senses<lb/> dim, or
				short sightedness.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">4. Besides, no Shochat is to be trusted if he is inter<lb/>ested in
				the result of his decision. (Ib. §2 Tor Zahat<lb/> ad. lit. 18.)</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Whereas, I learn that an individual <sic>practises</sic> here
				as<lb/> Shochat—and, whereas, a sacred duty imposes upon me<lb/> the hard task—and
				the letter of the President of K. K.<lb/> Sh. Is. requires me to declare whether
				said individual is<lb/> a legal Shochat, I feel obliged to state, that of five
				candi-<lb/>dates who since my stay here, (<date>July 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi></date>,
				A. C.,) presented<lb/> themselves to me for authorization or examination, only<lb/>
				two were found worthy of trust, viz:—<persName>Mr. Isaac Gold-<lb/>smith</persName>,
				the Shochat of this city, and <persName>Mr. Borier</persName> of
					<placeName>Sacra-<lb/>mento</placeName> city, and they were examined
				accordingly; the<lb/> other three were rejected for obvious reasons. Among<lb/> the
				latter is the young man in question.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">He was <sic>recommeaded</sic> to me for examination, and was<lb/>
				rejected on the ground of his falling under cases 1, 2, 3, 4,<lb/> state above as
				disqualifications for said office. He is<lb/> known to have forfeited his
					<add>?</add><lb/> even since his few months' stay in this State.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Thus rejected by our Law, he had recourse to the fol-<lb/>lowing
				expedient. He applied for authorization for three<lb/> persons who formerly are said
				to have acted as Shochin.<lb/> But as two of them publicly work in stores on the
					<date>Sab-<lb/>bath</date> and Holydays, and the third is known——.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I deeply and sincerely lament to be in duty bound to<lb/> declare
				said expedient illegal; and—in the name of our<lb/> ancient and venerable Laws in
				Codes Yorch Deah § §<lb/> 1, 2, 119, 254; Moshen Mishpat, §34;
					<persName>Ebenezer</persName>, §123;<lb/>
				<persName>Maimonides</persName> Hilch; Gereshen Cap. 3, §15, et alibi—said<lb/>
				young man to be no Shochat; and his <hi rend="italics">Shechilah</hi> to be<lb/>
				<hi rend="italics">Terephah</hi>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">“He that doeth keep his soul will keep far from<lb/> them.”—Prov.
				22:5.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In bringing this to the notice of the scrupulous Israel-<lb/>ites of
				this city and vicinity, I sign</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)">Faithfully and humbly,</p>
			<p rend="indent(10)"><persName>JULIUS ECKMAN</persName>, Rabbi.</p>
			<p><placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date>Dec. 19, (5615) 1854</date>.</p>
			<p>* We learn that such meat is to be had, at the usual<lb/> market prices, at
					<persName>Messrs. Miller's</persName>, <placeName>Pacific, near
					Kearny</placeName><lb/>
				<add>?</add>: <persName>J. Marks</persName>, <placeName>Kearny, near
					Pacific</placeName>.</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p
				rend="The following is the back side of the newspaper clipping, thus the right edge is cut off."/>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<add>?</add>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<placeName>SAN FRANC<add>?</add></placeName>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">MISCELLANEO<add>?</add></p>
			<p rend="align(center)">UNION HOTEL,</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>Opposite Portsmouth Square</placeName>....</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">A Card:</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">THE SUBSCRIBER HAVING ENGA<add>?</add><lb/> take the general
				management of the a<add>?</add><lb/> now leased to <persName>MICHAEL
					PHELAN</persName>, h<add>?</add><lb/> fully gives notice that under his
				direction the<lb/> been thoroughly renovated and materially impr<add>?</add><lb/>
				lodging-rooms are well furnished and in charge<lb/>
				<sic>pectable</sic> female, who has had many years exp<add>?</add><lb/> chambermaid
				in first class Hotels. A large<lb/> rooms are handsomely furnished for the
					accom<add>?</add><lb/> of private Supper Parties—also for Committee<lb/>
				<sic>ety</sic> Meetings.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The spacious BILLIARD SALOON, with its<lb/> Furniture, and the
				advantage of <persName>Michael Phelan</persName><lb/> magic art in the science of
				billiard playing, is<lb/> to any similar establishment on the <placeName>Pacific
					coast</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The BAR is stocked with the choicest quality<lb/> liquors, cigars,
				etc. The commodious basemen<add>?</add><lb/> fitted up in good style, as a
				REFRESHMENT<lb/> where the finest quality of Beef Steaks, Mutt<add>?</add><lb/>
				Oysters, etc., will be served at all hours of the<lb/> evening, and the subscriber
				trusts that he will b<add>?</add><lb/> to make the “UNION” a respectable and<lb/>
				house of entertainment, and worthy of a share<lb/> patronage. <persName>GEO.
					MONTGOMERY, M<add>?</add></persName></p>
			<p>N. B.—The undersigned returns his thanks<lb/> favors, and solicits a continuance of
				patronage<lb/> friends and the public generally.</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">
				<persName>MICHAEL PHELA<add>?</add></persName>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">Lessee of Unio<add>?</add></p>
			<p>d16 tf</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>United States</placeName> Hot</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>MONTEREY</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">THE PROPRIETOR OF THE UNITED S<add>?</add><lb/> Hotel,
					<placeName>Monterey</placeName>, respectfully notifies his<lb/> and the
					<sic>travelling</sic> public generally, that<lb/> opened this large and
				conveniently arranged ho<lb/> the accommodation of boarders, families and
					oth<add>?</add><lb/> may feel disposed to give him a call. No pains<lb/>
				<sic>pense</sic> has been spared to make this house com<lb/> and convenient to all.
				It shall be second to none<lb/> country in regard to everything appertaining to a
					<add>?</add></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The establishment is provided with good stable<lb/> horses.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Bar is supplied with the choicest wines,<lb/> and Cigars.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">His table is supplied with the best a
					<placeName>California</placeName><lb/> affords, that is all the eyes of an
				epicurean could<lb/> behold. Persons from all portions of the country<lb/>
				<placeName>Monterey</placeName> may rest assured of receiving most s<add>?</add><lb/>
				<sic>tory</sic> accommodations. The hotel is beautifully l<add>?</add><lb/> and
				commands a fine view of the bay. All we ca<add>?</add><lb/> is give us a call and
				satisfy yourselves.</p>
			<p rend="align(right)"><persName>McMILLEN</persName>, Propri<add>?</add></p>
			<p>d17tfD.</p>
			<p>FARE</p>
			<p>Reduced!</p>
			<p>ON THE <placeName>CALIFORNIA</placeName> STAGE C<add>?</add></p>
			<p>COACHES</p>
			<p>From <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> to <placeName>Red
				Woods</placeName>.........</p>
			<p>From <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> to <placeName>San
				Jose</placeName>.......</p>
			<p>From <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> to <placeName>Santa Cruz</placeName> and
					<placeName>Monterey</placeName></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The above Lines of Stages leave the Company<lb/> Plaza, (formerly
					<persName>Dillon, Hodge &amp; Co.'s</persName>,) every<lb/> at 7 ¼ and 8
				o'clock.</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">
				<persName>J. BIRC<add>?</add></persName>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">President <placeName>California</placeName> Stage
				Co<add>?</add></p>
			<p>N. B.—<persName>DILLON, HEDGE &amp; CO.</persName> will su<add>?</add><lb/> the Lines
				as heretofore. D13t</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Notice.—The interest of <sic>Jan</sic><lb/>
				<persName>TALMADGE</persName> in the Pioneer Line of Stages,<lb/>
				<sic>ning</sic> between <placeName>Oakland</placeName> and <placeName>San
					Jose</placeName>, via <placeName>Union</placeName><lb/> the <placeName>Mission
					of San Jose</placeName>, together with the st<add>?</add><lb/> the road, is now
				owned by the <placeName>California</placeName> Stage<lb/> and will hereafter be
				under superintend<add>?</add></p>
			<p><persName><add>?</add>lon, Hedge &amp; Co.</persName>
				<lb/> d14tf</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">
				<persName>J. BIRC<add>?</add></persName>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(right)">President <placeName>California</placeName> Stag<add>?</add></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
