<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item210</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Morais,
                            Sabato</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1860s">1860s</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item210_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 11 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">A <date>Thanksgiving</date> Address</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>“Oh bless our judge people, &amp; make the voice of his praise be heard” Beloved
                hearers! If<lb/> under what circumstance soever it is a moving light to behold the
                creature in humble<lb/> adoration worship his Creator, the impression upon the heart
                must be deeper still<lb/> when millions of immortal beings, prompted by community of
                sentiments, shout a<lb/> hallelujah to their Divine Benefactor; and although the
                manner in which their tokens<lb/> of gratitude are exhibited, may differ externally,
                yet when the thought which pervades<lb/> the mind is but one, it will harmonize
                every dissonance into a sweet accord. As at<lb/> the touch of the <sic>skilful</sic>
                musician, all the keys of a stringed instrument, are attuned<lb/> into a unity of
                sound, which delights the ear, &amp; softens the soul, so does<lb/> gratitude,
                striking the chords of human hearts, knit them together into a single chain<lb/> of
                godly affections. And thus is why, after he had enumerated some of the merciful
                acts<lb/> of the Deity, the Shepherd King called upon all mankind, to raise a hymn
                of thanks<lb/> to the Lord God of <placeName>Israel</placeName>. “Bless <hi
                    rend="underline">our</hi> God, ye people” he exclaimed, for ye all are the
                children<lb/> of his love &amp; the recipients of his bounty. Because they first
                acknowledged his name, he<lb/> chose the family of <placeName>Israel</placeName> as
                a kingdom of priests, but He delights in the praise of every<lb/> creatures that has
                breath. It is remarkable, however, that the sentence which precedes<lb/> this
                summons of the inspired writer, and which we have selected for our text, speaks
                of<lb/> the watchfulness of Providence in the government of nations, &amp; of his
                wisdom in thwarting<lb/> the devices of the froward. I will <del>read</del> cite it
                that you may ponder thereon: It was thus. “He<lb/> ruleth by his power for ever, his
                eyes behold the nations, let not the rebellious exalt themselves”<lb/> My Friends!
                It is to proclaim that self-same truth, that the pre-beings who populate<lb/> our
                Commonwealth, have solemnly assembled. Do acknowledge that their prosperity as
                Penn=<lb/>=sylvanians, and their greatness as an integral part of a glorious
                Confederacy, spring <del>forth</del> from the<lb/> fountain of all good, they have
                readily acquiesced in the pious request of their Governor.<lb/> They have not
                convened together, to triumph over the issue of sanguinary battles, they have
                not<lb/> brought the trophies of recent conquests, nor do they exult at this hour
                because their sword<lb/> has thinned the ranks of their adversaries; they come not
                to the dwelling of the Eternal, to rejoice<lb/> over their accession of dominion:
                no, a nobler incentive actuates the children of the American<lb/> Republic; they
                meet to thank the Rock of all ages, that He has vouchsafed to show unto them<lb/>
                also the year his mercy &amp; protection. And indeed, who can gainsay, when
                recalling to his mind<lb/> the momentous events which have rapidly succeeded each
                other, who can gainsay, but that at the<lb/> opening of this year, they
                    foreb<add>?</add> disasters! The honor of the nation was in jeopardy, our<lb/>
                heirloom so precious &amp; so cherished, had been polluted &amp; the swords of
                millions quenched in their<lb/> scabbards who curbed those vehement spirits, that
                might have hastened to a fatal termination<lb/> a transaction which demanded
                unparalleled discretion? God in his mercy. God “whose eyes<lb/> behold the nations”
                stood at the right hand of the just &amp; averted from them impending<lb/> dangers.
                He dispelled the mist which was fast gathering around our horizon, &amp; honor
                &amp;<lb/> peace continued to harbor wither our territories. Across the mighty ocean
                was the olive<lb/> branch wafted &amp; they with whose community of language &amp;
                community of interests bound with<lb/> us, disavowed their connivance at any act of
                advised contempt. But not alone from<lb/> without were the arms of the Lord extended
                to uphold our national dignity &amp; withhold<lb/> our hand from being imbued in
                human blood, but written likewise, He proved our stanchion<lb/> in the hour of
                trial. A deleterious seed had taken root amidst the salubrious plants<lb/> with
                which this garden of the <placeName>North</placeName> is replete, it rapidly spread
                its <sic>venermous</sic> influence,<lb/> &amp; threatened to sap the tree of life,
                beneath whose foliage, wearied humanity finds<lb/> a restoring shade. But the air of
                heaven blighted its growth, so that the stem it<lb/> brought forth, must need wither
                &amp; die. Ah no! God would not suffer this soil <sic>consumated</sic><lb/> to
                freedom, to become a <placeName>land of Nod</placeName>, where the exile would be
                denied a tranquil house.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for this also “is a land that the Eternal careth for, &amp; which his eyes are even
                upon, from the<lb/> beginning of the year, even unto the end of the year” He has
                cast a bulwark around it, He<lb/> has girded its walls with strength, He has
                enriched it with the treasures hid in the earth.<lb/> The sea offers tributes unto
                it, &amp; the gold of <placeName>Theba'</placeName> is poured into its lap. Like ancient<lb/>
                <placeName>Tyre</placeName>, “the merchants thereof are true princes, and the
                traffickers the honorable of the country”<lb/> They bid them “surfit messengers” go,
                &amp; they return fraught with choicest products of remote<lb/> climes. With their
                enterprising genius they have cooled, as it were, their cities &amp; towns<lb/>
                &amp; with the velocity of thoughts, from one <add>?</add> to its opposite one, they
                interchange<lb/> their wishes. But all this <hi rend="underline">Providence</hi> has
                wrought. Providence, “whose eyes behold the<lb/> nations” had blessed these regions
                with an ever growing prosperity, but solely because he<lb/> had reserved them as a
                palladium of persecuted humanity, while the oppressed of the<lb/> earth, shall reap
                unmolested the fruits of God's bounty, new viz our &amp; new freshness,<lb/> shall
                be added to this land of the free, but if theories subversive of the principles of
                justice,<lb/> should ever be engrafted in their political core then......but no, it
                shall never occur.<lb/> “God is in the midst thereof” God shall be her daily
                guardian, that “the rebellious may<lb/> not exhalt themselves” O bless <del>our
                    God</del> them ye people, &amp; make the voice of his praise be<lb/> heard
                “Already in the brief period, that elapsed since we last entered his courts with
                Thanksgiving<lb/> the Almighty gave palpable evidence of his <del>watchfulness</del>
                vigilance over our nations preservation.<lb/> He has proven to us, &amp; to the
                world at large, that He will rescue that matchless constitution<lb/> framed by the
                Sages of this Republic, both from foreign machinations &amp; domestic
                fanaticism,<lb/> &amp; even letters, when we appeared to verge towards a
                catastrophe, his pervading spirit directed<lb/> the mind of the American
                Constituents, that this beloved Union of ours, might not be<lb/> scathed. But I am
                warned, that it is not <sic>not</sic> from the pulpit that the political<lb/> events
                of the day ought to be descanted upon, &amp; truly my brethren, such was not my
                design.<lb/> I have cursorily adverted to them, solely to draw therefrom a tribute
                of thanksgiving to<lb/> our Celestial Benefactor. May He grant that whenever they
                recur to our thoughts, the<lb/> feelings they shall arouse may be, like at this
                hour, <del>a</del> noble pride &amp; heartfelt gratitude,<lb/> for, we cannot too
                highly value that inheritance which ensures to every one, the free<lb/> exercise of
                his religious tenets, &amp; the full possession of his inherent rights. Yet it
                may<lb/> be, that these inestimable immunities, bequeathed to us by the venerated
                leaders of the<lb/> revolution, have lost in the sight of their successors somewhat
                of their excellency,<lb/> for <del>what</del> that which is daily attained without
                any effort, fails to impress the mind<lb/> with its sterling worth. He has been ever
                wont to set at a luxurious table, cannot<lb/> rightly imagine the pangs occasioned
                by hunger; and <del>are</del> neither can be who has<lb/> ever basked in the sun of
                liberty, conceive the horrors concomitant with an existence<lb/> drawn in the
                darkness of tyranny. But ask it, my friends, ask it of them who<lb/> seek shelter
                beneath the extensive folds of the star spangled banner, &amp; they will tell<lb/>
                how invigorating to the mind, how vivifying to the soul is the shadow it
                overspreads.<lb/> They who felt the iron arm of despotism, they who saw the noblest
                of God's creatures<lb/> caged in dungeons, or scourged by the <add>?</add>, because,
                like your immortal progenitors,<lb/> they sought to tear their shackles asunder,
                they will say, how ineffably delight=<lb/>=ful it is to possess the consciousness of
                one's independence, to feel certain<lb/> that no man, however great or powerful can,
                at his will, crush another<lb/> man to the earth, and this consciousness, this
                assurance, every one of you<lb/> carries within himself. It will beseem you
                therefore, to <sic>forego</sic>, one day in the<lb/> year, your worldly vocations,
                &amp; convey unto the altar of your heavenly Protector,<lb/> sentiments of
                thankfulness, for “his eyes which behold the nations, have</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Deigned to look down upon you with peculiar benignity. Through his<lb/> vigilance was
                your national dignity upheld, your internal peace, maintained,<lb/> and by his grace
                the stream of your prosperity continued to flow uninterruptedly.<lb/> But despite
                the fruition of these blessing which God has supremely granted to us,<lb/> we might,
                beloved hearers? be not happy. I do not mean, individually (for amid<lb/> the
                struggles of life, nothing save an unwavering faith can render us thus) but
                nationally.<lb/> If the Almighty “shut up the heaven that there be no rain” if the
                sun instead of ripening<lb/> our products by a general heat, devoured the labor of
                the husbandman, we would<lb/> lack the principal element of happiness. It was in
                view of this incontrovertible fact that<lb/> the chief executive of our state,
                invited us to publicly avow the mercy of the omnipotent<lb/> “who has crowned the
                past year with his goodness, &amp; caused our paths to cross with fatings”<lb/> The
                unusual severity of the winter did not cut off the staff of life. The vernal
                season<lb/> was propitious, summer &amp; autumn smiled upon our soil. Not alone we
                &amp; our children,<lb/> shall, God willing, rejoice at the teeming of our crops,
                but nations we know not, will eat<lb/> of our plenteous harvest &amp; be satisfied.
                Ought we not then to be thankful? Contrast<lb/> your thriving condition with that of
                continental <placeName>Europe</placeName>. See, how a protracted war has<lb/>
                drained the sources of wealth, see the lands which might have yielded treasures,
                lying<lb/> fallow, because the stalworth arms of the
                    <sic>ploughman</sic><add>?</add>, were made <del>the</del> to <sic>weild</sic>
                the sword.<lb/> Here, poverty thicken the operatives rise against their rulers,
                there, they are compelled to<lb/> maintain by their industry, the pageants of an
                idle aristocracy. In one place the, so<lb/> called, servitors of religion, fatten
                upon the hard-earned <del>earned</del> substance of the laymen, in<lb/> another the
                riches of the country are sent afar off to replenish the coffers of foreign
                poten=<lb/>=tates. And ought we not to be thankful? Ought not the knowledge that
                our<lb/> opulence is solely ours &amp; our children's, <del>is</del> that handcraft
                obtains a commensurate re<lb/>=muneration, that the ministers of religion have no
                    <sic>ascendency</sic>, save in imparting the<lb/> dogmas of these various
                creeds; that we recognize no master, but Almighty God, ought it<lb/> not I repeat
                it, to swell our breasts with gratitude? But you will say, that these<lb/>
                privileges which we enjoy, are the natural consequences of our pre-eminence in the
                scale<lb/> of civilization. I shall not now compete your assertions, but I will
                merely inquire whether<lb/> it is by adroitness alas that the clouds become pregnant
                with exhalations, &amp; discharge upon<lb/> our land <add>?</add>ious rains, or
                whether we can by our ingenuity control light &amp; heat that they<lb/> may subserve
                our purposes. So be sure, our cooperation is <sic>needfull</sic>, nay, is
                indispen=<lb/>sable to render the gifts of the heavens useful to men, but if the
                former refuses us these<lb/> favors, all the combined efforts of the latter would
                prove futile &amp; abortive. Let us then<lb/> own our utter dependence upon the
                Creator of the universe, &amp; as we have been recom=<lb/>=mended “bless the Lord
                our God with unison of thoughts, &amp; make the voice of his praise be heard”<lb/>
                for he alone is the author of our maternal &amp; moral advancement. “He opens his
                hand widely,<lb/> to satisfy <hi rend="underline">every living being</hi>” Yes, by
                filling our granaries with his goodness, he benefits mankind<lb/> at large, as well
                as ourselves, for, strangers flock to our shores, &amp; are made participants
                of<lb/> our affluence. By sustaining our liberal constitution, he confers a boon
                alike open &amp; upon<lb/> the human race, because from it, the aliens together with
                the denizens,derive security<lb/> &amp; peace. By yearly consolidating the bonds of
                our Union, despite the machinations of spurious<lb/> children who see their
                dissolution—he significantly demonstrates, that he will be unto this<lb/> land of
                freedom “a wall of fire round a bout” &amp; he will be his glory in the midst
                thereof”<lb/> Our strength then, my beloved brethren is enormable<add>?</add>,
                because it is founded upon the execution<lb/> of what is just &amp; true; the
                republics of antiquity, &amp; throne of medial ages crumbled into<lb/> dust, because
                egotism &amp; self-aggrandizement were their props. They reputed <hi
                    rend="underline">themselves</hi><lb/> the source of light, &amp; the rest of
                mankind their satellites. <placeName>Greece</placeName> &amp;
                    <placeName>Rome</placeName> deeming<lb/> to have reached the climax of
                civilization, looked down with disdain upon millions</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of Gods creatures. Whosoever was born beyond their domains was styled with the
                name<lb/> of barbarian. <persName>Venue</persName> &amp; <persName>Genon</persName>,
                struggling for supremacy, made the <placeName>Adriatic</placeName> stream<lb/> with
                blood. <persName>Pisa</persName> &amp; <persName>Horance</persName> jealous of each
                other, exhausted their vigor in fratri<lb/>cidal wars, and now of their military
                prowess, &amp; of <del>theses</del> their vast conquests, the<lb/> memory alone has
                been left. But our strength is invisible also, my friends, because it is<lb/> not
                borrowed from foreign bayonets, but it rests upon the moral sentiment of every
                free<lb/> citizen. <placeName>Europe</placeName> is disorganized &amp; disrupted.
                Compacts formed but yesterday, are to-day<lb/> barefacedly violated. Monarchs that
                seemed to have forgotten, in struggling in the same<lb/> cause, their inveterate
                antipathies, have proven unfaithful to one another; and now the<lb/> disgraceful
                sight of a constitutional government leagued with a <sic>grovelling</sic> despotism,
                is to be<lb/> exhibited to the astounded world. Why is the history of that continent
                to be sullied by events<lb/> so opprobrious? Because its political institutions are
                rotten to the core, &amp; to prevent their<lb/> downfall, every means, even the
                foulest, must unscrupulously be resorted to.</p>
            <p>But our strength is invincible, mainly because it is built upon the Rock of all ages.
                    <hi rend="underline">That</hi><lb/> has ever been our impregnable fortress. You
                remember the motto upon the ensign of true<lb/> patriots who fought under the
                immortal <persName>Warren</persName>. On one side the words “Appeal to heaven”<lb/>
                were inscribed in blazing characters, whilst on the other, the later device “Zim
                branstaht sustinet”<lb/>
                <add>?</add> shone, as an evidence of their conviction that the <hi rend="underline"
                    >Omnipotent</hi> would have<lb/> wrought their salvation. And the same faith old
                prove, amidst all the perils of the<lb/> revolutionary war, the sustaining power of
                our gallant leaders. They never despaired of<lb/> success, but uplifted hands they
                invoked the blessing of the God of battles in their sacred cause,<lb/> hence, when a
                victory had signalized their progress, or when their enemies <del>war</del> had
                been<lb/> routed they summoned their brethren to a solemn convocation and together
                in the dwelling<lb/> of the Eternal “they made the voice of his praise be heard” I
                know not, whether it is from<lb/> this ancestral <sic>habitude</sic>, that our
                annual <date>day of thanksgiving</date> derives its origin, but spring<lb/> whence
                it may, it argues well for the descendants of our magnanimous forefathers, it<lb/>
                proves that although the pernicious connexion between religion &amp; politics has
                been for<lb/> ever dissolved, yet the former refulges<add>?</add> with undimmed
                brightness in the eyes of the sons<lb/> of <placeName>America</placeName>. It
                proves, what the enemies of liberty, would fair <hi rend="underline">dis</hi>prove,
                that<lb/> the true of religion, takes deeper root, thrives more quickly, &amp; sends
                its ramifications far<lb/> &amp; wide, whenever the dew of heaven irrigates a soil
                consecrated to freedom. I call <hi rend="underline">that a</hi><lb/> pure religion,
                which, like a spring which nature has fashioned, flows spontaneously,<lb/> &amp;
                such a religion can only be evinced, where the conscience is <sic>untramelled</sic>.
                Here therefore,<lb/> tokens of piety, ought to be the exponent of one's inward
                sentiments, and when we meet, like<lb/> upon this day, to raise a hallelujah to our
                Celestial Benefactor, we should lay upon his<lb/> altar a <hi rend="underline"
                    >sincere</hi> offering of thanksgiving. The recollection of past benefits,
                crowding our<lb/> minds, ought to make our hearts overflow with gratitude &amp; such
                    <del>was</del> has been the purport of<lb/> my address. I have striven to
                instill the belief that our prosperity, during the year<lb/> was the immediate
                effect of the goodness of the Most High. But He upheld our dignity,<lb/> when it was
                impugned, that by his unceasing watchfulness was the subtlety of<lb/> miscreants,
                detected &amp; frustrated; that through his benignity, was our Confederacy
                spared<lb/> the <sic>calamaties</sic> which afflict foreign climes, &amp; lastly
                that He has, not alone for our sake<lb/> but for that of afflicted humanity—whom we
                call brethren, &amp; whom we generously invite<lb/> to partake of our
                happiness—powerfully cemented our glorious Union, that it may endure<lb/> “as the
                days of heaven upon earth”. Now, my beloved hearers! <sic>if</sic> I have succeeded
                in<lb/> bringing these solemn truths home to your hearts, I may hope to achieve a
                still greater success<lb/> I may hope to rejoice at the supreme eminence which this
                city of love, will attain in the<lb/> scale of religious influence. As in the days
                of her youth, she was the <placeName>Areopagus</placeName><lb/> where the wrongs
                against humanity were vindicated; as <del>th</del> at that primeval time of
                    <placeName>America</placeName></p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>glory, she was the ark of the covenant, towards which the eyes of the faithful<lb/>
                looked for their deliverance, so will she now, by exhibiting a pious demeanour,<lb/>
                become a prototype, which millions will strive to copy. Clinging with<lb/>
                unyielding tenacity to the charter of her noble Constitution, she will never<lb/>
                ally herself with proscriptive castes; love is her name, &amp; from love will<lb/>
                she draw inspiration. The memory of her unparalleled achievements, during<lb/> four
                scores of years, will convince her, that whilst she adheres to the<lb/> doctrines of
                her sages, she shall grow in might &amp; grandeur; but what<lb/> will impel her with
                greater force to pursue the same course unswervingly<lb/> is the desire of doing
                what is right in the signs of the Lord God. In<lb/> the volumes which she reveres
                has been written “Love they neighbor as thy<lb/>=self” &amp;
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> will ever act in pursuance to this
                hallowed<lb/> commandment. She will not tear asunder the ties which bind her<lb/> to
                the whole human race. She will not <del>drown</del> sink into egotism, &amp;<lb/>
                disown those who suffer, because the land of their nativity lies beyond<lb/> her
                boundaries, but kindles with brotherly love, she will stand erect upon<lb/> her /
                high-places, and “come,” will she exclaim “leave ye all, who eat<lb/> the bread of
                anguish, &amp; drain the cap of sorrow, come and call the<lb/> choicest fruits
                planted in my garden, with them shall ye satisfy your<lb/> hunger, &amp; in my teats
                ye shall dwell in place, for <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> is<lb/> “the city
                of righteousness, the city of fidelity.”</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>are the laws of righteousness and whose sole defender is peace. Oh! let us pray for
                the<lb/> dawning of that joyous day when thirty five reunited States shall offer a
                national<lb/> thanksgiving, while the symbol of their greatness shall proudly wave
                over every<lb/>
                <add>?</add>ome and spire. Let us pray for peace.</p>
            <p>Parent of good! we lay prostrate at the footstool of Thy mercy and crave for
                peace,<lb/> grateful for Thy manifold favors at all times and this year especially,
                we yet cannot fully<lb/> rejoice in its fruition. Thou hast verily filled to
                overflowing the cup of our prosperity, but<lb/> that of bitter sorrow is also
                brought night to our lips. The aspect of the dead, the<lb/> agony of the wounded,
                the moaning of the sufferers, tear our hearts. From the<lb/> insanguined battle
                field, from the chilly and dreary camps, from the bereaved and lonely<lb/> hearth, a
                voice rises unto Thee, O compassionate Lord! and “peace, peace” it cries. Oh I
                send<lb/> a ray of Divine wisdom to <sic>illumme</sic> the mind of our Chief
                Magistrate, that he may discover<lb/> the instrument of peace. Let the gentle spirit
                of forbearance hover around the Assembly<lb/> of our Senators and <del>?</del>
                Representatives and guide their deliberations. Repress the vehemence<lb/> of
                zealots, and let the feelings of the obdurate be softened by tokens of brotherhood
                and love.<lb/> May we speedily throng again. My holy courts, to thank and praise Thy
                name, oh most High God! for the longed-for peace of our beloved Union.<lb/> and now
                I beseech Thee O Lord! to excite within us a sentiment of patriotism, that we
                may<lb/> enlist our names among those of our beneficent men and women who labor for
                the sake of our<lb/> defenders at sea and on land. May our hospitals, our sanitary
                commissions and our<lb/> soldiers and societies obtain a ready and generous
                cooperation from those who have been taught<lb/> to believe that “Charity
                    <del>deli?</del> delivereth from death” May such be Thy gracious will, O<lb/>
                Heavenly Creator. Amen.</p>
            <p>a <date>thanksgiving</date> discourse for the year <date>1864</date></p>
            <p
                rend="There is an arrow pointing, from the right, at the last line of the text above."/>
            <p rend="The following text is added in red ink.">This is from another sermon by
                    <persName role="author"><sic>Morris</sic></persName><lb/> NOTE the IDENTICAL
                writing of not only<lb/> all the page <hi rend="underline">but</hi> especially of
                the<lb/> word “<date>THANKSGIVING</date>” with that on the cover<lb/> sheet of this
                sermon</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p rend="The first 5 lines of the text are written in red ink."/>
            <p rend="Note:">ORIGINAL<lb/> size of letter<lb/> by<lb/>
                <persName role="author">Sabato Morais</persName><lb/> (see attached<lb/> for
                enlargement)</p>
            <p>at a special meeting of the Faculty of Maimonides College held<lb/> in consequence of
                the sad<add>?</add> bereavement <del>lately</del> recently sustained by<lb/> the
                house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, the following preamble and resolution
                were<lb/> unanimously adopted</p>
            <p>Whereas the demise of the <persName>Revd Isaac Leeser</persName> is deemed by<lb/>
                each of us a national loss, and whereas it is our conviction<lb/> that the
                establishing of this institution was principally due<lb/> to the unremitting
                exertions of our late colaborer, and to his<lb/> constant advocacy of religious
                education, therefore</p>
            <p>Resolved that we express our feelings of deep sorrow at the<lb/> loss of a man so
                zealous for the moral welfare of his people,<lb/> so energetic in promoting the
                culture of human knowledge, so<lb/> efficient as a professor, so exemplary assiduous
                in the discharge<lb/> of all his duties.</p>
            <p>Resolved that we <del>gladly</del> descry bearing our testimony to the uniform
                kindness and<lb/> courtesy that marked his official relations with us, and to<lb/>
                his timely and useful suggestions as <del>the</del> Provost of this college</p>
            <p>Resolved that we will ever cherish his memory as that of a friend,<lb/> and teach
                    <del>our</del> the students of this Institution to revere his <del>memory</del>
                name</p>
            <p>Resolved that these resolutions be published one of our dailies &amp; in all
                Jewish<lb/> periodicals; <del>and</del></p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">
                <persName role="author">S. Morais</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(5)">sect Pt.</p>
            <p>
                <date>February 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1868</date>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
