<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">[Morais, Sabato]</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item209</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">[Morais,
                            Sabato]</author>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1861">[September 1861]</dateLet>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0014.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0015.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item209_wk1_body0016.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 16 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">Reprinted in <hi rend="underline">Jewish Mess.</hi></p>
            <p rend="align(right)"><placeName>N. Y.</placeName>
                <date>Oct. 4, 1861</date> pp 52-3</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">For the <date>national fast-day</date></p>
            <p>
                <persName role="author">MORAIS, SABATO</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">Civil War Sermon</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">/1498Lcb</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">Civil War</p>
            <p rend="align(right)">PATRIOTISM etc <add>?</add> Cot 4 <persName role="author"
                    >Morais</persName></p>
            <p rend="align(right)">Sermon/</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>1</p>
            <p>Brethren! Were it my province to address an audience of non-Israelites,<lb/> I would,
                on the present occasion, select as my text a weighty sentence<lb/> which occurs in
                the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter of Exodus. It is the following <add>דבר אל זני
                    וכ"ו</add><lb/>
                <add>מים על ים</add> “The Eternal said to <persName>Moses</persName>, wherefore
                criest<lb/> thou unto me,? Bid the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> go
                forward” When dearly bought<lb/> freedom is in jeopardy; when the angry billows of a
                political sea im=<lb/>=pede the march of civilization, and the adversaries of human
                brotherhood<lb/> are skillfully <sic>marshalled</sic> for the onslaught, deeds of
                self-denial more<lb/> than psalmody<add>?</add> will sanctify the life of man. The
                Lord of hosts will<lb/> be extolled by the efforts which tried to uphold truth, more
                than by<lb/> the fervent utterance of the lips. Let him therefore who values
                his<lb/> country's honor speed on, let him trustingly follow the path which<lb/>
                leads to national deliverance, and when the happy goal shall have<lb/> been
                attained, raise the anthem which will be reverberated <add>ה' הושיעה המלך יעננו ביום
                    וגו'</add><lb/> from sea to sea, even from the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>
                to the <placeName>Pacific Ocean</placeName>.<lb/> Thus would I briefly speak this
                day, and dismiss <del>a</del> the <hi rend="underline">greater</hi> assemblage.<lb/>
                But as my lot was cast among those who are singled out in their<lb/> belief and
                their worship, I deemed it expedient to adopt a different<lb/> course. A
                non-compliance of the Hebrew Community with the<lb/> counsel of the
                    <persName>President</persName> of the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                might at this jun=<lb/>=cture, have been open to animadversion. It therefore
                became</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>2</p>
            <p>fit that we, who in our devotional outpourings at this solemn<lb/> season,
                    <del>ever</del> tearfully remembered the sorrows of
                    <placeName>America</placeName>, that we, who ceaselessly<lb/> pray for the
                welfare of the land of our adoption, and testified the love<lb/> we bear it, when at
                the first summons of the Executive we swelled the<lb/> ranks of her defenders, it
                became imperative, I say, that we should<lb/> nevertheless your own voices, this day
                also, to that of our fellow-citizens who<lb/> implore God for the restoration of
                peace. And verily, my friends!<lb/> Whatever opinion we may entertain touching the
                appositeness of the<lb/> request, our acquiescence therein <del>will</del> can be
                but the prompting of our<lb/> responsive <del>sentiments</del> feelings. This
                country, which many of you<lb/> claim at that of their birth, and some as that of
                them choice, has<lb/> not, like others that vaunt liberality, doled out her benefits
                to<lb/> you, O descendants of <persName>Jacob</persName>! but she has generously
                invited you<lb/> to participate in all the exuberance of her goods; hence, you as
                you did glory<lb/> in her happiness, <del>and</del> grieve over her distress. And
                when the custodian<lb/> of her liberties, descrying imminent danger, exhorts to
                prayer that it may be<lb/> averted, you who taught the world how to pray, will even
                at this hour<lb/> exclaim as you are wont <add>אולי</add>. “Save us O Lord,
                answer<lb/> us O King on this day that we call upon thy name”. But in<lb/> attuning
                our hearts to the national supplications, we receive an addition<lb/>=al incentive,
                in the present instance, by the remembrance that the<lb/> Chief Magistrate of our
                beloved Union, did not transcend the proper <del>his</del> limits, to</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>3</p>
            <p>pander to the irregular wishes of a majority. His proclamation is<lb/> the exponent
                of that excellent provision in the American Constitution,<lb/> which forms its
                brightest ornament, but of which zealots are now<lb/> striving to divert it. Not
                they who tender divine adoration to the man<lb/> of <placeName>Nazareth</placeName>
                are exclusively recommended to beseech the living God for<lb/> the triumph of
                rightful authority over usurpation but the people at large, so that<lb/> the
                entreats of a whole nation ascending the throne of grace may bring<lb/> down
                plentiful blessings upon our afflicted country. Such, or the like,<lb/> are his
                words; very dissimilar my Brethren! from those of some high functionaries,<lb/>
                whose narrow views debar them from discerning beyond the pale<lb/> of their
                religion, an object worthy of any consideration. In confor<lb/>mity therefore with
                so discreet a summons, we will again pour<lb/> out our souls before the Omnipotent
                    <add>עושה במלאכה ואחת מחזקת השלחבאחת ידו</add><lb/> “Peradventure will He think
                on us, that we perish not” <del>Yet</del> But, the<lb/> prayer of freedom-loving
                Americans must be accompanied by deeds of<lb/> abnegation. I will repeat it:
                    <del>That</del> Yonder sturdy man who in these<lb/> stirring times <hi
                    rend="underline">inactively</hi> contemplates the perilous state of the
                    <del>country</del> Republic,<lb/> though he bow the head as a bulrush, mistakes
                the aim of his exist<lb/>=ence. When around the noblest monument of human
                wisdom,<lb/> fall destroyers have gathered, let the vigorous, like the ancient
                Hebrews<lb/> labour with one hand in the work of reconstruction, and wield in
                the<lb/> other a repelling sword. <add>אין סומכין על הנס</add></p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>4</p>
            <p>the God of battles <del>of</del> will lead to victory. But if the patriotic
                ardour<lb/> that seemed to burn in every breast, when the national escutcheon
                was<lb/> first tarnished, has been quenched by the Liuthean<add>?</add> water of
                egotism;<lb/> if the memory of the past achievements and past glory contrasted
                with<lb/> the present humiliation does not arouse <del>not</del> in our midst the
                    <persName>Leonidas</persName>, that<lb/> will struggle for the maintenance of
                this peerless Union; if the<lb/> taunts of the ungenerous foreigner, and the
                sardonic smile of despots,<lb/> are incapable of inspiriting <hi rend="underline"
                    >all</hi> to energetic actions, the entreaties<lb/> offered this day will fail
                to <sic>propitrate</sic> the assistance of the Most High.<lb/>
                <add>בעון בצעו קצפתי ואכהו הסתר ואקצף וילך שובב בדרך לבו</add>, is a wise aphorism
                of <placeName>Israel's</placeName> ancient Teachers.<lb/> “We must not rely on
                miracles” Nothing is impossible to Him<lb/> who inspired a
                    <persName>Gideon</persName>, and by three hundred of the faithful, put to
                flight<lb/> the redoubtable <del>best</del> army of <placeName>Midian</placeName>,
                but while <del>we</del> it behooves us to beseech<lb/> Him and confide in his
                support for the ultimate success of a<lb/> righteous cause we must labour for our
                salvation. <sic>we</sic> must render ourselves deserving of it by prefer=<lb/>=ring
                to <hi rend="underline">individual</hi> promotion, national honor, national
                    <del>greatness</del> Unity,<lb/> national peace. Shall I now point out, how the
                pursuing of<lb/> the opposite course, became the bane of
                    <placeName>America</placeName>,? how personal<lb/> ambition becomes the vampire
                that fed on her life's blood? How self-<lb/>interest gave birth to parasites who
                scampered with the rich spoil of<lb/> their unsuspecting host? Shall I say, that
                even at this hour, when</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>5</p>
            <p>the tocsin resounds which tells the world that the pioneer of civil<lb/> and
                religious liberty is verging on a precipice, men—<del>shall I call them<lb/>
                    men</del>, no, heartless and soulless beings—are found, who will turn<lb/> to
                profit the mighty struggles of the brave to escape the yawning gulf?
                No<del>y</del>,<lb/> let others enumerate the sins which have exposed the country of<lb/>
                <placeName>Washington</placeName> to the contumely of the stranger and the horrors
                of war.<lb/> I will rather deplore them and acknowledge the justice of the Divine<lb/>
                <del>?</del> verdict <add>דרכיו ראיתי וארפאהו ואנחהו ואשלם נחמים לו
                ולאבליו</add><lb/> “For the inequity of his covetousness was I wrath, and smote him,
                I hid<lb/> myself and was indignant, for he went on forwardly in the way of<lb/> his
                heart”. This sentence of <persName>Isaiah</persName> so applicable to your
                unhappy<lb/> condition, O my hearers, reveals the plague which has putrified
                the<lb/> channels whence have sprung these waters of <placeName>Meribah</placeName>
                (contention). Yet, it lies<lb/> in your power to convert them again into refreshing
                streams of <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> brotherhood. God showed you the tree that will
                sweeten those<lb/> bitter waters, in the example of your immortal predecessors.<lb/>
                Let the memory of their sterling virtues cluster around your minds, and<lb/> awaken
                them to deeds of magnanimous valour, let them counsel<lb/> the renunciation of all
                preconceived <del>thoughts</del> notions for the preservation of<lb/> this palladium
                of human rights, the total subjugation of selfishness<lb/> for the
                    <del>benefit</del> prosperity of the common country, the repudiation of all</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>6</p>
            <p>doctrines subversive of the principles which they who framed the<lb/> Declaration of
                your independence unequivocally for the spread of civilization enunciated; then
                will<lb/> you regain the attitude from whence you were ruthlessly &amp; unnaturally
                    <del>cast</del> forced down,<lb/> or, to continue in the language of the prophet
                “God will see your ways and<lb/> heal you, He will guide you securely, and restore
                comforts to you and those<lb/> who mourn for your sorrows <add>Hebrew</add><lb/> And
                this day which a spirit of meekness has devoted to sacred communion,<lb/> will be
                the opening of a new era, glorious to <placeName>America</placeName>, and
                fruitful<lb/> of joy to the whole <hi rend="underline">human race</hi>.</p>
            <p>Lord God! who didst bless this land with Thy favour, restore her, we<lb/> beseech
                Thee, to Unity. Cancel her inequities, and let her be distinguished<lb/> anew for
                the virginal purity of her pristine years. Grant that<lb/> charity and truth may
                weave the garland that shall adorn her children,<lb/> for then will righteousness
                and peace be met in her midst clasped in each<lb/>
                <del>mutual, others</del> others' embrace. Guide Thou the steps which are now
                wending toward<lb/> the conquest of national supremacy over faction, that they may
                not<lb/> overreach the bounds justly prefixed. Oh! Eternal Being who didst<lb/>
                rekindle <del>the long suppressed</del> feelings of love in the bosom of the
                fierce<lb/> son of <persName>Isaac</persName>, breathe into us words of brotherly
                reconciliation, and let the hand<lb/> that wields the sword be <del>mutually,
                    grasped</del> fraternally seized with a mutual grasp <del>fraternal
                    pressure</del>. At this<lb/> hour, when the heart of a whole nation is upheaved
                to Thee, calm<lb/> O Omnipotent! its inward perturbation. Regard the prayer
                which</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>7</p>
            <p>in various strains but in consonance of thoughts is addressed to Thee;<lb/> let the
                angels of mercy present it to the throne of grace, and bring<lb/> down thy fatherly
                blessing upon thy suppliants, even, honor, Union<lb/> and peace for evermore.
                Amen.</p>
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">Specimen of <persName role="author">Morais</persName>
                writing</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">orig size of document</p>
            <p rend="Down arrow inserted, pointing to copy of document."/>
            <p>at a special meeting of the Faculty of Maimonides College held<lb/> in consequence of
                the sad<add>?</add> bereavement recently sustained by<lb/> the house of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, the following preamble and resolutions were<lb/>
                unanimously adopted</p>
            <p>Whereas the demise of the <persName>Revd Isaac Leeser</persName> is deemed by<lb/>
                each of us a national loss, and whereas it is our conviction<lb/> that the
                establishing of this institution was principally due<lb/> to the unremitting
                exertions of our late colaborer, and to his<lb/> constant advocacy of religious
                education, therefore</p>
            <p>Resolved that we express our feelings of deep sorrow at the<lb/> loss of a man so
                zealous for the moral welfare of his people,<lb/> so energetic in promoting the
                culture of human knowledge, so<lb/> efficient as a professor, so exemplary assiduous
                in the discharge<lb/> of all his duties.</p>
            <p>Resolved that we <del>gladly</del> descry bearing our testimony to the uniform
                kindness and<lb/> courtesy that marked his official relations with us, and to<lb/>
                his timely and useful suggestions as <del>the</del> Provost of this College</p>
            <p>Resolved that we will ever cherish his memory as that of a friend,<lb/> and teach
                    <del>our</del> the students of this Institution to revere his <del>memory</del>
                name</p>
            <p>Resolved that these resolutions be published in one of our dailies &amp; in all
                Jewish<lb/> periodicals; <del>and</del></p>
            <p rend="indent(3)">
                <persName role="author">S. Morais</persName>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent(4)">sect Pt.</p>
            <p>
                <date>February 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1868</date>
            </p>
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p rend="Note:">Duplicate of page 13. The following is written in the left margin, near
                the top of the page (where <placeName>Israel</placeName> is underlined): especially
                notable<lb/> comparison<lb/> line 4 page 1<lb/><date>Thanksgiving</date>
                discourse</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
