<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item89</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Sherbrooke, Canada East</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1849-02" source="" attested="yes">12 February 1849</dateLet>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes">12 February 5609</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item89_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>8 pages on 8 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>My dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Your kindness in forwarding the <date>Feby</date> No. of the Oc&#45;<lb/>cident claims my grateful thanks.  Its contents at once show the<lb/> lamentable state of disunion upon matters in connection with<lb/> religion amongst Israelites in <placeName>America</placeName>&#44; and sufficiently<lb/> exhibit the <sic>impracticability</sic> of your inserting my commu<lb/>nication&#44; up to this time.  There may be other reasons<lb/> wherefore you think it improper.  In the absence of a spe<lb/>cial explanation&#44; I can only&#44; and but imperfectly&#44; infer your<lb/> views from the course of proceedings.  Had the Occident contained<lb/> an indication of liberty to proceed in addressing your readers&#44;<lb/> this letter would&#44; agreeably to intimation&#44; have <sic>inclosed</sic> a<lb/> year&#39;s subscription&#44; as  I would not remain under obligation<lb/> for worldly favour&#44; when it is avoidable.  But since the seeking<lb/> of your assistance is&#44; or ought to be&#44; solely in obedience to<lb/> spiritual mandates which I dare not disregard&#44; I must learn<lb/> in some way&#44; if possible&#44; to what extent your good will or good<lb/> opinion towards my business may be counted upon.  To purchase<lb/> and pay for the Occident while containing nothing in this regard&#44;<lb/> would make me no wiser in that respect.  If you insert<lb/> or discuss my letters&#44; I can then learn your views on them&#59;<lb/> if you are so liberal as to continued the transmission of the Oc&#45;<lb/>cident without expectation of payment&#44; it must be from some spe<lb/>cial consideration&#59; and if you withdraw it&#44; while aware how ne<lb/>cessary it is to me to learn by its medium the prospect of the pro<lb/>posed assembly.  I shall be nonetheless enabled to appreciate your<lb/> estimation in my behalf.  I am the more anxious to learn&#44; from<lb/> practical demonstration&#44; your judgment concerning me be<lb/>cause the very extraordinary situation in which I am placed<lb/> overwhelms my weak and unsettled mind with the dread of<lb/> misconceiving my duty.  By carefully comparing ideas with<lb/> the differently affected yet interested and able to discover the<lb/> truth&#44; I may test the soundness of conceptions&#44; which&#44; without</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>some corroboration&#44; must incur distrust.  The <sic>inclosed</sic> &#36;1.00 I beg you to<lb/> accept on act. Of some No&#39;s of the O. formerly sent me at <placeName>New York</placeName>&#59; or if you<lb/> would decline it on that ground&#44; let it be to defray postage which may occur.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">One would think that&#44; while so desirous of bringing my views<lb/> before some authority in <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; I should greatly rejoice in the pros<lb/>pect of an Assembly and their doings&#44; as now before us&#59; but reflec<lb/>tion upon the issue of my formal application to the Beth Din in<lb/> <placeName>New York</placeName> as I reported it to you&#44; teaches me to expect little from<lb/> any body of men who may be actuated by a dread of compromi<lb/>sing their character for wisdom.  Yet as our excellent friend <persName>Mr.<lb/> Noot</persName>&#44; <persName>Dr. Salomon</persName> and another passed a resolution that my repre<lb/>sentations were worthy of attention and ought to be investigated &#38;<lb/> reported on by two or more persons of the first distinction for learning<lb/> devotion&#44; character and understanding&#44; I must not fail&#44; if the venerable<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName> come together&#44; to apply for the relection of a suitable<lb/> committee&#44; who after free and full communication&#44; shall formally de<lb/>clare their views of the matter submitted to their consideration.<lb/>  If you would do me the greatest kindness&#44; if you would become<lb/> nobly instrumental in relieving the deepest anxieties of a mind<lb/> that seeks to ascertain its duties in order to their discharge&#44; you<lb/> have but to forward by every means in your power my honest<lb/> aim to bring the teachings of this extraordinary state of mind<lb/> fairly and fully before the Jewish public for their consideration<lb/>  To my private desires&#44; it would seem to be of little importance how<lb/> men should entertain these disclosures provided the decision could<lb/> be final.  What makes me anxious is that whilst my thoughts<lb/> are absorbed as they are and must be for the present&#44; my<lb/> wife and children are suffering for the want of attention<lb/> which is their due&#44; and which I cannot give them&#44; as my<lb/> faculties are insufficient under such a distraction.  It appears<lb/> that I must either become an active&#44; however humble&#44; servant<lb/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; or&#44; obtaining some conscientious satisfaction that will</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p>authorize the withdrawal of my attention from the subject&#44; devote<lb/> the more energy to pursuits of a private nature.  Could I but learn<lb/> by a reasonable decision of the judgments of others upon these un<lb/>common views&#44; that they must pass for either erroneous or im<lb/>practicable&#44; gladly would I hail the liberty to apply to the cares<lb/> labours and pleasures of my family and farm&#59; gladly would<lb/> I strive to join in the common and selfish pursuits of life&#58;<lb/> but while the best and soundest with whom I am enabled to con<lb/>verse&#44; approve and even reverence my views&#44; while those who<lb/> censure are evidently inconsiderate in their examinations&#44; while<lb/> it is not only what has been manifested to an excited percep<lb/>tion&#59; but a calm examination of all current events of every sort<lb/> leads to a like conclusion&#44;&#8212;and while&#44; to my utter amazement&#44;<lb/> the whole seems indicated in the prophecies of old&#44; how can<lb/> I doubt the evidence that presents itself to one purpose in<lb/> so many different ways&#44; when that purpose is but the es<lb/>tablishment of a government recognizing&#44; what sound sense re<lb/>quires&#44; as a leading principle&#44; the accountability of man to his<lb/> maker&#63;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I do not appeal to you for the sake of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; for you<lb/> are sufficiently bound already to that consideration.  I plead<lb/> not for the good of mankind in general&#44; for you comprehend<lb/> as well as I the connection between the Restoration and the spread<lb/> of intelligence&#44; uprightness and peace.  But as the Lord so<lb/> orders that even in our highest aims we are influenced more<lb/> or less by private regards&#59; as He kindly grants the grateful<lb/> stimulus of selfish satisfaction in our most sacred aspira<lb/>tions&#59; and as we are humble men&#44; of limited capacities&#44; yet<lb/> generous and sympathetic feelings&#59; I will endeavour to elicit<lb/> your sensibilities in my favour by appealing to your knowledge<lb/> as a spiritual teacher and your heart as my brother man&#44; in<lb/> regard to my private position as a religious individual.  I have</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>two children&#44; sweet little girls&#44; the eldest but two years of age&#44; whom<lb/> I would bring up in the knowledge and fear of the Lord.  I am<lb/> an Israelite in faith&#44; if I know what it is to be an Israelite&#8212;<lb/> namely&#44; to live under a perfect sense of accountability to God&#44;<lb/> aiming in all things to do that which is right in His view&#59; there<lb/>fore necessarily adopting the high wisdom of inspiration in the<lb/> formation of rules of conduct&#44; and devoutly seeking self&#45;improvement<lb/> and the general good in associating with others disposed to wor<lb/>ship and serve God in purity and truth.  I would say with pi<lb/>ous <persName>Joshua</persName> &#8220;as for me and my house&#44; we will serve the Lord.&#8221;&#8212;<lb/> but how&#63;  Shall I take my family to a Christian Church to hear<lb/> that belief in absurdity is the vital condition of happiness hereafter.<lb/>  Shall we cultivate ignorance&#44; and avoid participating in any estab<lb/>lished form of worship&#8212;to the effect that <add>&#63;</add> be heaped upon<lb/> my innocents as being trained to error and infidelity&#63;  Or shall<lb/> I crave admission from a Jewish congregation&#44; to join in prayer<lb/> for the advent of a Messiah&#44; instead of returning thanks for<lb/> the appointment of a special and most distinguished service&#8212;<lb/> shall I enter such a congregation on condition of allegiance<lb/> to all the existing Laws and customs&#44; when I do not intend<lb/> to obey them&#44; and the very perception which makes me desire<lb/> religious association&#44; also assures me that many of those u<lb/>sages and institutions are now needless&#44; some of them wrong&#44;<lb/> and that it is my especial calling to be humbly instru<lb/>mental in their reform&#63;  Which shall I adopt&#44; of these er<lb/>roneous courses&#63;  Or rather what <hi rend="underline">can</hi> I do but prayerfully<lb/> trust in the Divine Goodness to relieve my perplexities<lb/> in due time&#44; and strive by every means to bring my views<lb/> to be compared with those of others whose superior attainments<lb/> entitle them to respect and confidence&#44; while their vital wants&#44; the<lb/> proper longing of their souls&#44; must stimulate them to discover and<lb/> approve and establish the truth if truth it be&#44; which I have to disclose</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">2</p>
				<p>I can see no other course to be right&#59; and therefore do I thus beseech assistance.<lb/>  For some half year more&#44; according to a remarkable impression&#44; must I<lb/> remain in this uncertainty and trouble&#58; if by that time there be not a<lb/> clearing up of difficulties I shall have cause to respect a radi<lb/>cal error in these sublime perceptions.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You once wrote me the story of <persName>Shaman</persName> and <persName>Hillel</persName> and one who<lb/> would become a Jew with the condition of being made High Priest.<lb/>  The case is no parallel to mine&#59; I desire no distinction&#8212;far less the<lb/> accountability of power.  I have lived forty years without at any time<lb/> being led by political ambition or religious zeal.  True heroes&#44; in my<lb/> view&#44; are those who&#44; keeping within their means&#44; devoutly apply themselves<lb/> to the common duties of life.  What devotion I have exercised may have<lb/> been far surpassed in the experience of many religious minds amongst<lb/> us.  It is prophecy a startling glimpse of the natural course of events&#44;<lb/> and their causes&#44; showing the unfailing means established for the pro<lb/>duction of good&#44; which it only devolves upon men to observe and employ&#44;<lb/> that this impels me to so strange a course.  What should I care<lb/> for worldly appearances&#63;  What is it to me if my conduct seem<lb/> unaccountable and absurd to those who know not its motives&#63;<lb/>  I must only hasten to bring matters to a crisis&#44; to attain facil<lb/>ities for efficient action&#44; or freedom to forbear from futile endeavours.<lb/>  Will you not help me&#63;  Do I ask more than naturally pertains between<lb/> man and man&#63;  You admit that the developments of the day indicate<lb/> the present as a fit time for rising in behalf of <placeName>Israel</placeName>.  Let it then<lb/> be decided whether I may lawfully and properly undertake to act<lb/> in this good cause in conjunction with the chosen servants of the<lb/> most High.  If you say that I am not a Jew&#44; let me ask&#44; was<lb/> <persName>Abraham</persName> other&#44; in that respect&#44; than I am&#63;  Or did <persName>Moses</persName><lb/> submit to a string of rabbinical exactions&#63;  Supposing he had&#44;<lb/> it would be no rule for me.  The useless part of these observances<lb/> must be done away.  The general forms of Jewish worship are as<lb/> grand in effect as venerable from antiquity.  But many spe<lb/>cial institutions which were founded in good reason from the ex<lb/>igency of circumstances&#44; have now no effect but a detrimental in</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>fluence.  Long have the people groaned under these absurd incum<lb/>brances&#59; and what is worse&#44; forsaken the faith of their fathers&#44;<lb/> to escape form such annoying accomplishments.  In assisting to re<lb/>tain these evils&#44; you become answerable for their natural conse<lb/>quences.  It needs but to prune away such exhausting&#44; useless<lb/> and unsightly branches&#8212;it needs but to exhibit the pure princi<lb/>ples of religious faith under a rational and modest form&#44;<lb/> and the tree of righteousness will flourish&#44; take root in the earth&#44;<lb/> unfold its blossoms to the world&#44; give fragrance to the airs<lb/> of heaven&#44; and yield reproductive fruit spreading abroad<lb/> for the delight and shade and comfort of regenerate man.<lb/>  The pure Jewish faith&#44; the simple belief in omnipresent Deity&#44; to whom<lb/> we are strictly accountable&#44; must become the religion of the world&#44;<lb/> not because it is written that the Lord declared so by His prophet<lb/> not because it bears a fascinating show to the imagination<lb/> for it does not&#44; but because it is <hi rend="underline">the truth</hi>&#44; and men are becom<lb/>ing sufficiently enlightened and considerate to distinguish sim<lb/>ple truth from seductive falsehood.  Let the Jew once stand<lb/> a free man in his own country&#44; and the brawling nations will<lb/> let fall their weapons in astonishment&#44; acknowledge in their heart<lb/> the truth of revelation&#44; and incline to turn from the errors of their<lb/> ways.  Then may peace and reason and kindness prevail&#59; for<lb/> men&#44; become more reflective&#44; will see it for their interests to<lb/> cultivate good dispositions.  The best minds among gentiles will<lb/> associate themselves with the already established Jews.  Dif<lb/>ferent races will thus intermingle without violence to law<lb/> or custom.  By this means a large portion of subsequent generations<lb/> will be born under the ameliorating influence of those natural<lb/> laws hereby increase of vigor is given to cross breeds.<lb/>  The ancient blood of <placeName>Israel</placeName> serving as a basis&#44; a foreign admix<lb/>ture to a certain extent&#44; will benefit the race&#44; promoting the<lb/> development of its energies&#44; and marking the Jews&#44; as a people&#44;</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p>with such physical and mental superiority&#44; as must inevitably<lb/> render them masters amongst mankind.  The use they will make<lb/> of power&#44; must depend&#44; in a great measure&#44; upon the purity of<lb/> their religious principles&#58; and it therefore devolves the more<lb/> fearfully upon us&#44; if it please God to employ our weak hands<lb/> in this His good work&#44; to aim at the highest perfection in<lb/> whatever rules and practices we may <add>&#63;</add> to establish.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It is observable from the records of history&#44; as well as re<lb/>searches into nature&#44; that the chief means whereby a race ar<lb/>rives at a high standard of perfection is the copulation of pa<lb/>rentage bringing together somewhat dissimilar constitutions&#58;<lb/> yet&#44; when one of the parties is highly cultivated&#44; extreme oppo<lb/>sition does not answer the purpose&#58; thus the refined white<lb/> and the barbarous negro or Indian cannot be intermixture<lb/> bring improvement to the superior&#59; and the effect is ques<lb/>tionable even upon the inferior race.  In a mind of much<lb/> refinement is established a deep repugnance to the coarse<lb/>ness of ignorance and vulgarity&#59; for it is decreed that<lb/> when such excellence is once attained&#44; it ought not to be<lb/> thrown away&#58; yet the two sexes are established&#44; that&#44; by<lb/> continental intermixture of different constitutions&#44; offspring<lb/> may arise inheriting the general characteristics&#44; which<lb/> it is our business to establish in ourselves&#44; of both<lb/> parents&#59; and not the particular defects which may be<lb/> beyond our control&#44; of either.  Intermarriages therefore are<lb/> predicated upon a positive&#44; though not extreme&#44; dissimilar<lb/>ity of constitution in the parties&#44; while they are as necessarily<lb/> influence by similarity of sentiments&#44; habits and pursuits.<lb/>  It is then plain that the restored Jews&#44; together with those no<lb/>ble</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>&#45;ble&#45;minded from other nations&#44; who will dare to cast off the<lb/> fetters of error and prejudice&#44; must operate under every<lb/> beneficial influence to produce the most powerful and highly<lb/> gifted race of which we can conceive&#44; precisely in accord&#45;<lb/>ance with undeviating and well known laws of nature.  There<lb/> is no record of a people becoming&#44; either on the whole or at any<lb/> particular time&#44; great and powerful in all respects&#44; whose<lb/> physical excellence is not to be traced directly to the inter&#45;<lb/>mingling of different races or dissimilar tribes.  Thus&#44; under<lb/> ordinary circumstances&#44; a conquest<add>&#63;</add> however lamentable to the<lb/> humbled people becomes the means&#44; under God&#44; of health<lb/> and blessing to posterity.  If a nation could but comprehend<lb/> their duty&#44; if a government would only provide&#44; by ade&#45;<lb/>quate and strictly natural means&#59; for the development<lb/> of every inherent energy of man&#44; and for preserving the<lb/> excellence of the race when once attained&#44; that people could<lb/> never be subdued&#59; for&#44; granting by way of argument&#44; the<lb/> existence of abler nations&#44; their ability would abundantly<lb/> supply their wants by easier and more profitable measures<lb/> than war against the unoffending&#44; who would be supported<lb/> by a sense of justice&#44; and ruled by a regard for the most<lb/> High&#44; that would require conquest and extermination to be<lb/> made <sic>synonimous</sic> terms.  Even the corrupted Jews of old were<lb/> but beaten and dispersed&#44; and not subdued like other nations&#44;<lb/> to resign their peculiar laws and coalesce with the victors.  They<lb/> were conquered as men&#8212;not as Jews.  Persecution&#44; in its ut&#45;<lb/>most violence could only cripple&#44; but never tame their true<lb/> spirit of adoration.  It has still angered upon earth and<lb/> groaned in agony unto the Lord of hosts&#44;&#8212;and lo&#33; he com&#45;<lb/>&#45;eth to relieve.   Most faithfully yours&#8212;</p>
			<p rend="indent(8)"><persName role="author">George Barnard</persName></p>
				<p><placeName>Sherbrooke C. E.</placeName> <date>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 5609</date>.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
