<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>LSTCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item92</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="unk"></author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="" source="" attested="unk"></dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0011.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0012.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>6 pages on 12 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">1</p>
				<p rend="align(center)">The Congregation Beth Elohim of <placeName>Charleston</placeName>.</p>
				<p>No 6 full price</p>
				<p>The attention of the Jewish Public being directed to the<lb/> movement of this congregation&#44; we beg leave to lay before them<lb/> a statistical and comprehensive sketch of the part and parsing<lb/> events which have agitated and are now agitating this body.</p>
				<p>At the period when the <persName>Rev Y Posnanski</persName> was elected for a probationary term of two years Hazan of the<lb/> K. K. B. E. it was one of the most Orthodox&#44; Religious&#44; &#38; <sic>Charatable</sic><lb/> in the <placeName>United States</placeName>.&#8212;after the expiration of one year.  The Congregation<lb/> in consideration of his ardent zeal in the cause of our holy Religion<lb/> his piety and conformation to all the laws both Mosaic and<lb/> Rabbinical&#44; Elected him for life.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">As soon as this event took place a course diametrically<lb/> opposite was immediately pursued by <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName>&#44; which<lb/> was the cause of the disastrous outbreak in <date>1841</date>&#44; when upwards<lb/> of Forty of the <del>oldest</del> most <sic>consciensious</sic> and <del>most</del> strictly conservative members were<lb/> scrupulously compelled to <del>resign</del> withdraw&#44; &#40;among whom were<lb/> the founders of the congregation&#41; and to leave in the power of<lb/> its rulers not only that Sacred Edifice which was identified with<lb/> many Holy associations&#44; but <sic>but</sic> were denied any participation in the management of the Kyrankyamits<lb/> Fund to which they had largely contributed until it had<lb/> accumulated to the Sum of &#36;25.000. the Interest of which<lb/> was appropriated to support the very individual who by his<lb/> arbitrary and anti Jewish Conduct cause another dispersion<lb/> in <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; and depriving the aged supporters of the Congregation<lb/> their Venerable matrons and their children&#44; not only of a place<lb/> of worship but also of the <sic>priveledges</sic> of Sepulture&#44; for imme&#45;<lb/>&#45;diately upon their withdrawal&#44; the constitution of the KKBE.<lb/> was amended as follows &#8220;Any Subscriber Yehid&#44; or member<lb/> of this Congregation&#44; male or Female who shall habitually<lb/> attend <hi rend="underline">Divine</hi> service at any other place of worship within<lb/> the city than that of the KKB.E. or subscribe there to as<lb/> members or Yeshidim shall be charged annually One Hundred<lb/> Dollars&#8221;  We do not deem any comment necessary.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Congregation remained in a lethargic state until<lb/> its second Revolution in <date>1843</date>&#44; which involved it in an</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">2</p>
				<p>expensive and tedious have Suit&#44; and ended in the withdrawal<lb/> of about 25 members&#44; who were opposed to the abrogation<lb/> of the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Day of the <sic>Hollidays</sic> and other innovations suggested<lb/> by <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName>.  This Event caused a great deal of unhappiness<lb/> and dissensions among families who had hitherto lived in<lb/> peace and Friendship&#44; <sic>untill</sic> the advent of <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName><lb/> and the promulgation of his new doctrines.  These<lb/> Twenty Five joined with those who had withdrawn in <date>1841</date>.<lb/>  The K K B.E. Is now threatened with a third&#44; and probably&#44;<lb/> <del>a</del> final dissolution&#44; when this event takes place&#8212;and<lb/> of its near approach&#44; indications never were more preferable&#8212;<lb/> it will&#44; no doubt&#44; cause the overthrow forever of the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;hallowed and vain panoply of power with which its present<lb/> Rulers are invested.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">It numbers at this time about Forty Members and<lb/> is divided into two parties whom we shall call&#44; for the<lb/> sake of distinction&#44; Radical and Conservative.  Their<lb/> present minister the <persName>Rev Julius Eckman</persName>&#44; was elected<lb/> about Eleven months ago &#40;<persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> having resigned&#41;&#44;<lb/> on a probationary term of two years.  This Gentleman<lb/> is a regularly ordained <add>Hebrew</add> &#40;and empowered&#41; by virtue of<lb/> a Diploma honorably conferred on him&#44; under the seals<lb/> of the Rabbinates of <placeName>Berlin</placeName> and <placeName>Prenzlaw</placeName> &#40;which are<lb/> two of the greatest acknowledged authorities of <placeName>Europe</placeName>&#41; and was duly prepared<lb/> by an examination at the Royal Fredrick Willhelm<lb/> College at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>&#44; and by his having been a Civis Universitatis<lb/> Berolinensis rite inscriptus&#44; for the space of five years.  He was<lb/> elected&#44; <hi rend="underline">contrary</hi> to his expectations as he had expressed<lb/> himself to all those who called on him previous to that<lb/> time as being entirely opposed to the principles <del>of</del> avowed by their<lb/> late Hazan&#44; and in his Inaugural address he express&#45;<lb/>edly told <del>them</del> the congregation that he appeared before them simply<lb/> as a teacher in <placeName>Israel</placeName> and objected to being considered<lb/> their spiritual Head.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The cause of the division unto two parties of such</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">3</p>
				<p>opposite extremes originated as follows.  The <persName>Revd Dr<lb/> Eckman</persName> from repealed conversations <del>from</del> on his first arrival<lb/> with <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> and from personal observations afterwards&#44;<lb/> found that all positive religion <del>had fallen into Decay</del> was rejected<lb/> no religious instruction was communicated in the synagogue<lb/> &#40;as <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> did not lecture&#41; prophecy was denied&#44; hence<lb/> the denial of all that is <del>Dogmatical</del> Doctrinal and National.  The<lb/> non observance of the Law not only passively connived at&#44;<lb/> but he exposed some Laws that might offend our<lb/> modern delicacy&#44; to the view of his adherents the more<lb/> effectually to prove there was no <sic>nescessity</sic> for observing them<lb/> his request to <persName>Dr. E.</persName> to preach against the <sic>Rabbies</sic> and<lb/> all observances whither Biblical or Rabbinical and his acknowledgment to him<lb/> that it was of no consequence where the bible came from<lb/> convinced <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> of <persName>Mr Posnanskis</persName> <del>rank</del> daring Infidelity&#44;<lb/> as <persName>Mr Newman</persName> calls it.  <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> kept silent<lb/> <sic>untill</sic> <date>Yom Kipur</date> when <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> was called to<lb/> take part in the sacred functions of that day.  This <persName>Dr<lb/> Eckman</persName>&#44; as an honest man&#44; could not consent to<lb/> and <sic>and</sic> privately remonstrated with <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> on the great<lb/> crime of Profanation.  <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> replied&#44; that<lb/> he not only did not believe <del>the <date>Yom Kipur</date></del> these prayers&#44;<lb/> but he detested them&#44; whereupon <persName>Dr Eckman</persName><lb/> denounced him to the Parnass.  Not only as an Infidel<lb/> but inimically disposed to the very Institution of<lb/> Judaism&#44; and positively refused to take any part<lb/> in the service of that day.  The Personal friends<lb/> of <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> immediately arrayed themselves in<lb/> open hostilities against <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> and have waged them <sic>untill</sic> the present<lb/> time.  The great Injustice of this <del>course</del> persecution being so<lb/> evident to the public&#44; and <persName>Dr. Eckmans</persName> straight<lb/> German course in the cause of Religion and Truth<lb/> has drawn to his Standard of True Faith a large<lb/> number of the most respectable and intelligent members of the congregation&#42;<lb/> The Radical or <persName>Posnanski</persName> party numbers exactly Eighteen<lb/> <del>&#42;among whom we mention <persName>Mr Joshua Lazarus</persName> the Prest of the congregation and <persName>Mr M C Mordecai<add>&#63;</add></persName>&#44;<lb/> both so honorably named in your last number.</del></p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">4</p>
				<p>the Conservative party Fifteen members and four Congregators<lb/> the remaining <del>8 or 9 members</del> Eight or nine&#44; are<lb/> indisposed to take any part in Congregational affairs.<lb/>  <del>altho we believe they  convinced of the fallacious<lb/> ideas they have recently entertained on Religious subjects.</del></p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The public denunciation of the creed By <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> at the Tabernacle<lb/> Lecture Room some weeks ago&#59; as being anti Jewish&#44; and as<lb/> having been surreptitiously introduced in the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> gave publicity to the following facts viz.</p>
				<p>The Building Committee received instructions from the<lb/> congregation to have &#8220;Our Creed <hi rend="underline">translated</hi> and placed<lb/> in the synagogue&#59; and recommended the <del>services</del> assistance of their<lb/> Hazan the <persName>Rev. G Posnanski</persName> for that purpose&#44; the committee<lb/> accordingly informed that Gentn of the wishes of the<lb/> congregation&#44; to which he assented&#44; and <del>they subsequently</del> this prepared<lb/> <del>received from him</del> creed was placed in the synagogue as Our &#8222;the Maimonidian&#8221; creed<lb/> <del>that which is now placed in the synagogue</del> It contains<lb/> like that of <persName>Maimonides</persName> thirteen articles <del>of I</del> and<lb/> purports to be &#8220;Elements of Jewish Faith.&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">This committee&#44; with the exception of <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName>&#44; with fearless <sic>magninimity</sic>&#44; have<lb/> recently expressed&#44; that they have no <sic>pretentions</sic> to<lb/> Biblical or Rabbinical Lore&#44; that they never supposed<lb/> that <del>it</del> this creed aimed a blow at the very vitals of Judaism&#44;<lb/> they received <del>this creed</del> it in full faith of its really<lb/> being&#44; that which the congregation requested them to<lb/> procure viz a translation of &#8220;<hi rend="underline">our</hi> the Maimonidian<lb/> Creed and if it <hi rend="underline">were</hi> any thing else&#44; it was <hi rend="underline">not</hi><lb/> the acknowledged creed of the congregation&#59;<lb/> a Public meeting of the Sunday School attached<lb/> to the K K B.E. under the sole control of the Ladies<lb/> of the Congregation&#44; was convened soon after this and<lb/> the creed which had hitherto been taught&#44; was rejected<lb/> and forever expelled from school <del>by a vote of 25 to 3</del>.<lb/>  It would not be out of place here to answer <del>&#8220;C&#8221; a</del><lb/> the objections <del>which</del> of &#8220;C&#8221; in the last &#8220;Occident&#8221; to<lb/> the views</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">5</p>
				<p><persName>Mr Newman</persName> takes &#40;on his <del>anima</del> criticism of this creed&#41; of the substitution of the Divine<lb/> Law handed by <persName>moses</persName> to our Fathers&#8221; for the Universal<lb/> believe &#40;and <hi rend="underline">correct translation of</hi> <persName>Maimonides</persName>&#41;. &#8220;that the<lb/> Law was <del>given</del> delivered unto <persName>Moses</persName> by God&#44;&#8221; <del>I</del><lb/> The only article of Faith necessary for any believer<lb/> is that of <add>Hebrew</add> if this is admitted <del>then</del> the<lb/> other two propose by &#8220;<persName>Albo</persName>&#44;&#8221; and the Twelve according to<lb/> <persName>Maimonides</persName>&#44; follow of themselves&#44; as the<del>re</del> whole<lb/> Bible is there acknowledged to be given by God<lb/> <del>to</del> and all the contents binding&#44; but this very<lb/> article is distorted and rendered inane by<lb/> the alteration introduced in article 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> where<lb/> instead of the Universal belief that the Law was<lb/> delivered to <persName>Moses</persName> by God&#44; it is in <persName>Mr Posnanskis</persName><lb/> creed only considered as a divine Law delivered<lb/> by <persName>Moses</persName> unto our Fathers&#8212;now a &#8220;divine<lb/> Law delivered by <persName>Moses</persName> may mean no more<lb/> <del>than</del> and stand no higher than&#44; a &#8220;Divine Poem<lb/> By <persName>Milton</persName>&#44; a Divine Hymn&#44; by <persName>Dr Watts</persName><lb/> &#8220;Divine Service by an incompetent Lay man<lb/> or a Divine Comedy by &#8220;<persName>Dante</persName>&#44;&#8221; the word<lb/> &#8220;Divine&#8221; is of less import than &#8220;Sacred&#8221;&#44; and<lb/> &#8220;divine and sacred less than &#8220;Holy&#8221;.  The draft<lb/> of the <hi rend="underline">Translator</hi> may easily be <sic>percured</sic> by<lb/> comparing Article 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> which immediately follows<lb/> when instead of the Positive and emphatic assertion<lb/> <del>that</del> of <persName>Maimonides</persName> viz we believe with a firm&#47;perfect faith&#44; that<lb/> this Law will never be changed or altered&#44; and<lb/> that there will be <hi rend="underline">no other Law Given</hi> by the<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Creator</hi> Blessed be his name&#44; he simply states<lb/> that we believe the divine Law will never be<lb/> altered or changed&#8221;&#44; he has expunged or forgot<lb/> to translate&#44; what we so <hi rend="underline">very much</hi> want to hear<lb/> viz that <hi rend="underline">the Creator blessed be his name&#44; never will</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">give any other Law.</hi><lb/>  &#8220;C&#8221; also states that <persname>Mr.
			<pb n="11"/>
				<p rend="align(right)">6</p>
			Poznanski</persname></p> &#8220;never advocated doctrines that conflicted with the<lb/> cardinal principles of our religion.&#8221;  It is not difficult<lb/> to infer what a man&#39;s moral and religious principles<lb/> are when his own words and actions sufficiently<lb/> indicate them.
				<p>Firstly&#8212;in his discussion with <persName>Dr Raphall</persName>&#44; when asked<lb/> if he believed in the Bible in the Law &#38; the Prophets<lb/> he in the presence of both Organizations replied after a long hesitation Y&#45;e&#45;s <del>with qualifications some</del><lb/> several of his <del>friends</del> own congregation inferring from<lb/> his evasion and long consideration&#44; that he did not fully believe</p>
				<p><del>Secondly&#8212;His unbelief in the coming of the personal messiah<lb/> the&#44; Ressurection<add>&#63;</add> and in the prayers which<lb/> and &#8220;that God gave the law&#44;&#8221; <add>&#63;</add> his creed&#8221;</del></p>
				<p>Secondly <del>his disbelief in</del> the non obligation of observance of the ceremonial and<lb/> Rabbinical Laws as <add>&#63;</add> to <persName>Dr Eckman</persName><lb/> and <persName>Mr Newman</persName>&#44;&#8221;</p>
				<p><del>We also understand &#8220;C&#8221; is the author of the Petition</del><lb/> and Lastly his extreme inconsistent course viz coming to <placeName>Charleston</placeName><lb/> as a pious and orthodox mosaic &#38; Rabbinical Hazan&#44;<lb/> and in a short time afterwards subverting our <hi rend="underline">faith</hi><lb/> by introducing into the synagogue&#44; one of his own<lb/> manufacture which his replete with Infidelity &#38;<lb/> Irreligion&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The <persName>Posnanski</persName> parties finding themselves reduced<lb/> in the last Ten Years from over One Hundred voting members<lb/> to only Eighteen&#44; and destruction approaching from exposure of<lb/> their leader by <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> determined as a last<lb/> resort they being in the majority on the Board of<lb/> Trustees&#44; to transmit a petition to the Board with<lb/> the request that <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> should resign as they did not think <del>men</del> suited their needs<add>&#63;</add>.  This<lb/> Petition&#44; Signed by the Eighteen members&#44; was<lb/> accordingly sent in&#44; and a resolution passed<lb/> by a note of 4 to 3 that <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> should comply<lb/> with the weeks of the petitions&#44; a contra petition<lb/> was also sent to the Board signed by Fifteen members</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
