<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>[no title given]</title>
				<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
				<editor></editor>
				<sponsor></sponsor>
				<funder></funder>
				<principal></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition></edition>
				<respStmt>
					<resp></resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet></dateLet>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution></institution>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item134</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName></msName>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head></head>
					<letHeading>
						<author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Barnard, George</author>
						<addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Leeser, Isaac</addressee>
						<deliverer></deliverer>
						<respStmt>
							<resp></resp>
							<name></name>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet></placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet when="1848-12" source="" attested="yes">4 December 1848</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author></author>
							<editor></editor>
							<respStmt>
								<resp></resp>
								<name></name>
							</respStmt>
							<title></title>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl></bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation></filiation>
							<textLang></textLang>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0001.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0002.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0003.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0004.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0005.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0006.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0007.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0008.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0009.jpg"></graphic>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item134_wk1_body0010.jpg"></graphic>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size="">letter</material>
								</support>
								<extent>10 pages on 10 sheets
									<dimensions></dimensions>
								</extent>
								<foliation></foliation>
								<collation></collation>
								<condition fragment="false"></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout></layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="manuscript">
							<handNote></handNote>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote></decoNote>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions></additions>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote></decoNote>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p></p>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat></accMat>
						<envDesc occ="false"></envDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin></origin>
						<provenance></provenance>
						<acquisition></acquisition>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source></source>
								<change></change>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent></custEvent>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates></surrogates>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl></bibl>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno></idno>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p></p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p></p>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p></p>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p></p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p></p>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p></p>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p></p>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p></p>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition></rendition>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""></tagUsage>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""></cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc></catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc></desc>
					<label></label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation></creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item></item>
						<item></item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""></classCode>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
				<p>My dear Sir&#44;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">When I wrote you last spring at <placeName>New<lb/> York</placeName>&#44; I had asked <persName>Mrs. Green</persName> the Poetess to send an<lb/> article to the Occident&#44; and I suggested to yourself&#44;<lb/> if she did so&#44; and you should wish for her farther con&#45;<lb/>tributions&#44; to return her a ten dollar bill.  I dare say<lb/> neither of you thought proper to comply with my wishes&#44;<lb/> because neither of you could see a prospect of advan<lb/>tage in so doing&#59; but had you both complied without<lb/> such a prospect&#44; I could have numbered two persons<lb/> who had once acted upon a principle of <hi rend="underline">Faith</hi>&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; seeing the right of a matter&#44; had done it at their<lb/> own cost without a mercenary view&#44; in perfect trust of<lb/> God that as the act was correct the result must be for<lb/> the best.  Probably both <persName>Mrs. G.</persName> with her poetic talent&#44; and<lb/> yourself and bank&#45;note&#44; may have been more fitly employed<lb/> though not in the exercise of greater faith&#44; yet in the use<lb/> of better discretion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">You asked me in your last letter&#44; whether I was or am<lb/> still a prophet.  I made no direct reply&#44; because then a&#45;<lb/>bout to send you the substance of my most signal im&#45;<lb/>pressions as fast as I could get them published in<lb/> a newspaper&#44; I did so.  As soon as the most important<lb/> of these views had issued&#44; the publication was discon&#45;<lb/>tinued from the difficulty of getting them completely printed&#44;<lb/> and other considerations regarding the newspaper office.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I will now endeavour to answer your question in full<lb/> by explaining for your satisfaction what it is to be a pro</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
				<p>phet&#8212;showing what constitutes the distinction between a<lb/> prophet and another man.  You are enabled from your own<lb/> knowledge to form some conception of the labours and dif&#45;<lb/>ficulties which I have encountered&#44; owing to having my<lb/> mind occupied with these considerations.  I have had no<lb/> new prophetic excitement or revelation since parting from<lb/> you in <placeName>New York</placeName>&#44; nor do I expect ever to have any<lb/> of such overwhelming force as those experienced there <del>in New</del><lb/> <del>York</del>&#44; and wherein&#44; seemingly&#44; I was admonished of all<lb/> that is material for my future guidance.  So far as<lb/> experience enables me to state&#44; the grand result of a<lb/> prophet&#39;s intentions&#44; is but to recognize the perfect<lb/> truth and correctness of the principle to do in all cases<lb/> whatever we can judge to be right before God&#44; without<lb/> regard to consequences&#44; trusting these entirely to His<lb/> disposal as immeasurably superior to our own limited<lb/> views.  Thus <persName>Mrs. G.</persName> the poetess&#44; when she had promised<lb/> me some verses&#44; would&#44; if she had acted in accordance with<lb/> the suggestions of inspiration&#44; have sent them to the Occident<lb/> at my request&#59; merely because it was <hi rend="underline">right</hi> for her<lb/> to do so&#59; and the Editor would have made her an ade<lb/>quate return in the manner pointed out&#44; as an act of sim<lb/>ple justice.  The principle of our duty to God is but Just<lb/>&#45;ice&#58; if we accept a benefit&#44; we are bound to endeavour<lb/> to return it&#58; if we would reap a good&#44; we must sow<lb/> of the kind.  This moral obligation so congenial to the<lb/> natural feelings&#44; and the conformity to which is hailed<lb/> as a divine attribute of humanity&#44; the prophet learns to be<lb/> but a just and pleasant indication of the course which is</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">2.</p>
				<p>a necessary conformity to the requirements of natural laws.<lb/>  The prophet&#44; by glimpses of the future which he afterwards<lb/> sees verified&#44; and whose connexion he can trace with volitions<lb/> of the past&#44; ascertains <hi rend="underline">of his own knowledge</hi> some outlines<lb/> of the retributive system wherein nature holds her courses<lb/> whereby God governs the universe&#44; even down to its minu<lb/>test details.  The fact of a person predicting a remark&#45;<lb/>able event which comes to pass&#44; is of little moment&#58;<lb/> the <sic>surprize</sic> and reverence of others at the prophets&#39; fore&#45;<lb/>knowledge can be but humiliating to him&#44; as it only evinces<lb/> the subject condition of his brethren upon the earth.  When<lb/> one whose mind is enlightened by prophetic or inspired<lb/> knowledge&#44; sees error reign in the mind of a person or<lb/> a people&#44; it is as natural for him to foresee suffering<lb/> and trouble as a consequence&#44; as it is for us to presume<lb/> that where weeds rankle among more delicate plants&#44;<lb/> the coop will be unsatisfactory to the husbandman.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">How it is that I&#44; so weak a man&#44; so little given<lb/> heretofore to the adoption of peculiar or precise views upon<lb/> subjects in connexion with religion and government&#44; should<lb/> be made the recipient of these revelations&#44; revelations<lb/> so powerful that they seem clearly to involve author&#45;<lb/>ization and commandment&#44; that I&#44; rather than any<lb/> other&#44; should be the person to broach this might truth&#44;<lb/> to subvert the false but fashionable creeds of the civil<lb/>ized world&#44; is more than I can comprehend&#44; and<lb/> therefore beyond my power or responsibility to account<lb/> for.  I am commissioned by revelations whose truth and<lb/> imperative command I cannot doubt&#44; to declare unto Is&#45;</p>
				<p rend="The following word continues on the next page."><placeName>Israel</placeName></p>
			<pb n="4"/>
				<p>rael that the time has come for its people to be res&#45;<lb/>tored to their ancient inheritance&#44; that little is wanting<lb/> besides their own earnest cooperation&#44; that if any of them<lb/> will give me a hearty concurrence I am bound to labour<lb/> in the cause&#59; if not&#44; I have only to discharge the duty<lb/> appointed me to render them alone answerable for the<lb/> error.  Strange as it may appear&#44; it seems to me indi&#45;<lb/>vidually&#44; a matter of indifference whether or not this<lb/> undertaking be attended with success.  If I am not<lb/> deluded&#44; it must succeed&#44; for such is my prophetic<lb/> impression&#59; but notwithstanding the deepest sense of it&#44;<lb/> importance to mankind&#44; I feel personally indifferent to<lb/> events&#59; for in these spiritual perceptions&#44; I have been<lb/> taught so clearly they wearisome vanity of all earthly<lb/> considerations&#44; that I am led to distrust more than de<lb/>sire the worldly exaltation which must be consequent<lb/> upon success.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">I am now living an idle life&#44; yet labouring in<lb/> confusion and perplexity to prepare for this great<lb/> work.  It is distinctly given me to expect that next<lb/> summer there will be a clearing away of difficulties&#44;<lb/> and consequently until then I could not look for a<lb/> worthy reception were I sooner to undertake to make<lb/> known this mission.  Still would I use every means to<lb/> prepare the way&#58; therefore was the resort to newspaper<lb/> publication for some leading particulars&#44; and there&#45;<lb/>fore&#44; being unable to visit <placeName>New York</placeName> again this sea&#45;<lb/>son&#44; I may probably go to <placeName>Montreal</placeName>&#44; which is nearer<lb/> by&#44; this winter&#44; beseeching some individual Hebrews to</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">3</p>
				<p>hear me&#44; though without the hope of producing any<lb/> important impression.  Such is the only way which lies<lb/> open to a prophet&#58; he hopes that by calling individual<lb/> attention to his views&#44; they may be spoken of again&#44; may<lb/> be reported abroad&#44; until falling under the notice of some<lb/> true mind and heart&#44; they will be made the subject of<lb/> a strict inquiry&#44; and then their merits and importance<lb/> be discovered and appreciated.  If after giving ample<lb/> opportunity to those who should be most immediately in&#45;<lb/>terested in this cause&#44; my views remain unaccepted<lb/> and my exertions unsupported&#44; I can only suppose that<lb/> a too excitable imagination may have led me in some<lb/> respects to form erroneous conclusions&#44; and willingly retire<lb/> to a private station&#44; consoling myself for the shame of<lb/> failure with the consciousness of having faithfully<lb/> endeavoured to obey the mandate which I had con&#45;<lb/>ceived to be entrusted to my execution.  If such be the<lb/> will of God&#44; &#40;which I cannot believe&#44;&#41; you Jews must<lb/> wait another while for a Messiah and your restora&#45;<lb/>tion.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But that you may at least agree in opinion with<lb/> me so far as this&#44; that the present time appears to be<lb/> a juncture most peculiarly fitted for the restoration<lb/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>&#44; I would ask you to turn your attention<lb/> to the present position of <placeName>Europe</placeName>.  The nations are all<lb/> in a ferment from the opposition of artificial classes<lb/> grown out of false institutions.  The masses of poor&#44; be<lb/>sides being crushed by the powerful&#44; have been quieted<lb/> with the cordial doctrine of tame submission for the sake</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
				<p>of reward in another world&#44; until they have so multiplied<lb/> as to crowd one another from all remunerating employment.<lb/>  Starving and desperate they seek leaders to marshal them in<lb/> the terrible <del>desperate</del> struggle for bread&#33;  The call is answered by<lb/> too many of the abandoned&#44; reckless and ambitious&#44; proud to<lb/> extort submission from the old possessors of wealth&#44; influence<lb/> and dominion.  The massive weight of old established fashion<lb/> is evenly <sic>balance</sic> by new accumulated force.  They who have<lb/> felt starvation will encounter it no more&#44; and those who<lb/> hold inherited power and position cannot yield their birth<lb/> right&#58;&#8212;&#8220;at weary bay each shatter&#39;d band<lb/> Eyeing their foeman sternly stand&#59;<lb/> And tumult wild and disarray<lb/> Mark the fell havoc of the day.&#8221;</p>
				<p>That the opposing parties are evenly balanced&#44; only foreshows<add>&#63;</add><lb/> a protracted contest.  The victory in the end is certain to<lb/> the people so fear as relates to the humiliation of their ru&#45;<lb/>lers&#44; but not as regards an effectual and permanent<lb/> amelioration of their own condition&#59; for a victory of the<lb/> government only reduces matters to their former false<lb/> position to result in a new and more violent outbreak<lb/> at the first occasion&#59; while every signal advantage<lb/> gained by the masses is a stimulus to the popes and<lb/> energies of millions.  The people then&#44; sooner or later&#44; must<lb/> triumph so far as to overturn their governments.  What then&#63;<lb/>  Are these demoralized masses qualified to hold the<lb/> reins of power&#63;  Poverty&#44; ignorance&#44; prejudice and pas<lb/>sion all combine to render them corrupt and venal&#8212;<lb/> the sport and tools of ill&#45;directed but ambitious minds.</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">4.</p>
				<p>Then what can come of all at last but a perpetual re&#45;<lb/>iteration of tyrannies&#44; conspiracies&#44; rebellions and civil<lb/> wars&#63;  And is this <hi rend="underline">Progress</hi>&#63;  Is this in accordance<lb/> with the developments of nature which science and art<lb/> are so fast unfolding in our time&#63;  No.  Then it<lb/> is not to be&#59; for the works of the Lord proceed in uni&#45;<lb/>son&#44; by general laws.  If progress betters man&#39;s outward con&#45;<lb/>dition&#44; it must also improve himself.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But whilst the governments of <placeName>Europe</placeName> are in a fer&#45;<lb/>ment&#44; where is the mighty influence of that hallowed pre<lb/>ventive and panacea of all earthly ills&#8212;the Christian Re&#45;<lb/>ligion&#63;  Where shines the force of its holy precepts of mild<lb/>ness&#44; affection&#44; long&#45;suffering and forgiveness&#63;  In the mouths<lb/> of men&#8212;not in their hearts.  The excellent instructions<lb/> derived from or attributed to the meek and lowly<lb/> <persName>Jesus</persName> have been used as salt to season&#44; to preserve<lb/> and render palatable a mass of fleshly lusts&#44; a whole<lb/> code of impositions&#44; falsehoods and absurdities&#44; destined<lb/> to exist until an hour of search and trial&#44; and no<lb/> longer.  The people have found that however the injunc&#45;<lb/>tion to submit to common sufferings in this world be&#45;<lb/>cause their happiness hereafter is supposed to be<lb/> bought and paid for&#44; may please their fancies&#44; it<lb/> will not answer the requirements of appalling famine&#59;<lb/> and they begin to suspect themselves imposed upon<lb/> when&#44; amidst their sufferings&#44; they perceive those <del>very</del><lb/> enlightened superiors who inculcate this doctrine&#44; very<lb/> carefully fortified against the contingency of having to<lb/> <sic>practise</sic> it.  Religion then&#44; as it exits among these peo</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
				<p>ple&#44; is no imperishable bond of union&#44; and no ultimate<lb/> resource for the reconstruction of their governments.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">But how is all this trouble to end&#44; how will the<lb/> nations of <placeName>Europe</placeName> settle down in quietness&#44; how can<lb/> oil be cast upon these agitated waters&#63;  With<lb/> man it is impossible&#59; but with God&#44; He <del>speaks</del><lb/> wills&#44; and it is done.  While secret causes were operating<lb/> to set these nations all against themselves&#44; the Lord<lb/> was rearing up an humble prophet who should call<lb/> upon <placeName>Israel</placeName> to come together and declare that He<lb/> is God&#44; to manifest His truth in realizing the<lb/> promises of old&#44; that all mankind might see and<lb/> know that &#8220;The Lord God Omnipotent Reigneth.&#8221;<lb/>  Can <placeName>Europe</placeName> or <placeName>Asia</placeName> behold the majesty of the most<lb/> High displayed in the restoration of His ancient people<lb/> as the prophets have foretold&#44; and not learn to love&#44; fear<lb/> and serve Him&#63;  Will they not verify the prediction &#8220;often<lb/> taking hold of the skirt of a Jew&#44; saying let us go with<lb/> you for we have heard that God is with you&#63;&#8221;</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">If this appear doubtful&#44; allow the supposition of<lb/> its untruth&#44; and observe the irresistible conclusion.  The<lb/> nations of <placeName>Europe</placeName> are impelled by absolute suffering to<lb/> overturn their existing governments&#58; the scattered Jews&#44;<lb/> properly neutral in regard to the issue&#44; must&#44; from<lb/> their wealth and ability become important allies for<lb/> either party&#58; they are therefore surrounded with temptations<lb/> to throw the weight of their influence into either scale&#58;<lb/> hence the most liberal enactments&#44; emancipation&#44; kindness.<lb/>  Jews are but <del>flesh and blood</del> human beings like other</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
				<p rend="align(center)">5</p>
				<p>men&#59; and if a remnant have preserved their faith<lb/> and fashions through the severest persecutions it does not<lb/> follow that they will equally well resist the fascinating<lb/> influence of justice and generosity.  A continuance of the<lb/> <del>the</del> action indicated by the motto &#8220;liberty&#44; fraternity&#44; equality&#44;&#8221;<lb/> must soon entice the Israelite to make common cause&#44;<lb/> and next to assimilate himself with the rational seek&#45;<lb/>ers after good&#44; in the midst of whom he lives.  At the<lb/> siege of <placeName>Cressy</placeName>&#44; <persName>Edward</persName> being conqueror&#44; ordered six<lb/> of the principal inhabitants to the scaffold&#58; his <persName>queen<lb/> Philippa</persName> begged their lives&#58; <persName>St. Pierre</persName>&#44; the leading patriot<lb/> of the city exclaimed &#8220;Ah my countrymen&#44; it is now<lb/> that I fear for you&#59; <persName>Edward</persName> only wins our cities&#44;<lb/> but <persName>Philippa</persName> conquers hearts.&#8221;  The influence of liber&#45;<lb/>ality and kindness must be the same upon the Is&#45;<lb/>raelite as another man&#59; and if he is made a debt<lb/>&#45;or for these benefits&#44; he will acquit himself of the<lb/> obligation even at the cost of <sic>cancelling</sic> his birthright.<lb/>  The Jew would be no more&#58; tempted with alliance in<lb/> marriage&#44; forced from his strict <date>sabbath</date> by custom and<lb/> the need of gain&#44; or seduced from it by the repose and<lb/> pleasures of the succeeding day&#44; flattened through the<lb/> influence of  companions&#44; from his cradle to esteem<lb/> himself and disregard his maker&#44; he would vanish<lb/> in the surrounding throng&#8212;and created time stand<lb/> conqueror of eternal truth&#33;  It cannot be&#58; the Jew<lb/> must still survive&#44; and hold his indifferent course<lb/> amidst the wreck of nations.  But to preserve his iden<lb/>tity&#44; he must owe allegiance to another state&#44; be bound</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
				<p>to a government actually existing prompt and efficient<lb/> to protect his rights&#8212;a government ordained by God<lb/> Himself even as foretold in the cherished traditions of<lb/> his fathers.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In an old No. of the Occident&#44; I saw an inquiry<lb/> for information as to the authenticity of the passage in<lb/> <persName>Josephus</persName> regarding <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.  <persName>Davis&#39;s</persName> Clairvoyant<lb/> Revelations&#44; p. 578&#44; says &#8220;the record is genuine altho&#39;<lb/> not contained in some of the early versions of <persName>Jo<lb/>sephus</persName>.&#8221;  If you have not read <persName>Mr. Davis&#39;s</persName> book&#44;<lb/> there is in the store for you a fund of astonishment&#44; if not<lb/> of entertainment and information&#44; in whatever light<lb/> you may view it.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">In the letters with which you have been so kind as to<lb/> honour me&#44; reference has once or twice been made to a passage<lb/> of scripture&#44; for my special consideration.  I find noth<lb/>ing more appropriate to the case than Deut&#58; XIII.5<lb/> first verses&#59; and by these do I desire to be judged.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">When I wrote you last it was on the <date>sabbath</date>.  Since<lb/> then I have had much reflection upon the observance of<lb/> the day&#59; but my conclusions ought to be compared with the<lb/> convictions of others before being set down as mature.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Should you issue any thing regarding me in the Occident&#44;<lb/> please forward the No. and if you think proper to honour<lb/> me with a reply to this&#44; address <placeName>Sherbrooke C. E.</placeName> <hi rend="underline">vice</hi><lb/> <placeName>Derby Vt.</placeName> Postage must be paid to the line to insure<lb/> transmission. I remain my dear Sir</p>
			<p rend="indent(6)">Most Respectfully &#38; faithfully yours</p>
			<p rend="indent(9)"><persName role="author">George Barnard</persName>.</p>
				<p><date>Decr. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1848</date>.</p>
				<p><addressee>Revd. I. Leeser</addressee></p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
