<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>TCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item225</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="true">Wise, Dr.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item225_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 8 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(center)">
                <hi rend="underline">a card</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <addressee>Rd Dr. Wise</addressee> Edt Israelite</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The following Art. appeared in your Paper on <date>Tudy<lb/> 1.
                    April</date> “<persName>Mr. Bruel</persName> on Talmud Yelodim
                    <sic>institute</sic>) <del>speaks thus</del><lb/>
                <persName>Mr. B</persName> in a lengthy <sic>Letter</sic> to the Oc<hi
                    rend="underline">cid</hi>ent notices the T Y I. thus<lb/> “The school under
                    <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> is similarly circumstanced its annual<lb/> report
                show a <sic>dificiency</sic> of 7. to 800<add>?</add> but the members of his
                congregation<lb/> are very proud of their school. They attach to it a greater degree
                of<lb/> consequence than some might think it deserves hence they endeavor<lb/> to
                preserve its <sic>existance</sic> by private contributions and other sources,”“<lb/>
                would I have <sic>preferd</sic> answering your remarks to the above in<lb/> your own
                    <sic>Paper</sic> but as you have denied me a hearing on 3 <sic>seperate</sic>
                occasions<lb/> though you profess to admit Articles of all kinds of persons in
                the<lb/> Israelite. I am reluctantly <sic>compelld</sic> to seek a hearing elsewhere,<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">reluctantly</hi>, because the public can have little interest
                in such<lb/> affairs„ The constant readers of yr. paper have satisfied
                themselves<lb/> that it invariably provokes <sic>dissention</sic> and when
                    <sic>legitimatily</sic><lb/> opposed, one is sure to be met with a torrent of
                abuse or a total deni<lb/>al is given the things it has provoked. these facts can be
                verified by the<lb/>
                <sic>Paper</sic> itself. You Sir, are not alone callous to <add>?</add> the feelings
                of others, but<lb/> are also indifferent to your own standing as a journalist, it
                should be<lb/> your duty in accordance with your profession on the forthcoming
                of<lb/> the Israelite, to place both sides of public questions before the world<lb/>
                particularly matters pertaining to <del>religion</del> theology since justice<lb/>
                toward individual members of society, will reward the press, in the form<lb/> of
                increased confidence and respect in conclusion I may remark that<lb/> no public man
                should object to have his official conduct <sic>criticised</sic><lb/> when the
                criticism manifests a desire to reveal truth and useful<lb/> information. I cannot
                conceive that the article now before<lb/> the public is in <sic>itsself</sic> of so
                flagrant a character as to cause such a<lb/> torrent of bitter recrimination, as you
                have bestowed on it, partic<lb/>ularly as you are aware I have only stated facts,,
                you commence<lb/> thus “One would scarcely think that fanaticism could thus
                mislead<lb/> an old man, as to speak slightly of an institute in which his own</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">2</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">x <sic>complaind</sic></p>
            <p>Grand children receive their education and are counted among<lb/> the best of their
                age” In reply I have reason to say, that my<lb/> Grand children are as intelligent
                for their age as most children are,<lb/> It is because they can show so little for
                their prompt attendance<lb/> of nearly 3 years in a school that boasts, having
                preeminent adean<lb/>taps<add>?</add> that cannot be had in the <placeName>U.
                    S.</placeName> or <placeName>England</placeName> nor elsewhere, it is<lb/>
                because they make no progress in things most essential at their<lb/> age, that I
                have repeatedly x to their parents, and if they are <sic>faithfull</sic><lb/> to
                their children, and to themselves I trust they will soon perceive<lb/> that I have
                not <sic>complaned</sic> in vain, but sir in what I have said<lb/> I have not
                injured the reputation of the school, unless you consider<lb/> it <sic>Treason</sic>
                to speak the truth. I am not the only <del>insidid</del> individual<lb/> who think
                    <del>so</del> its members attach <del>more</del> a greater degree of
                consequence<lb/> to their school than some might think it deserves. I can name<lb/>
                several if required, that will say the same, but sir <sic>their</sic> must be
                    <sic>othr</sic><lb/> causes which has so sorely displeased you, a
                    <sic>side</sic> from the Article<lb/> in question. May it not be that you being
                aware of the members<lb/> mistaken attachment to their school, and as the Editor of
                an Hireling Press<lb/> have again prostituted your Ephemeral sheet to please
                your<lb/> supporters, you know you did in the like manner in the fall<lb/> Edition
                which greatly facili<del>ated</del>tated to crush the cause you then<lb/> espoused.
                I spoke of the financial affairs of the school from its<lb/> annual report without
                    co<hi rend="underline">m</hi>ent. You continue that “The ortho<lb/>dox are
                    <sic>enimies</sic> to instruction. They are therefore opposed to schools”<lb/>
                you boast, “That the school sends forth American Jews no Poles, no<lb/> Germans, no
                English, and no Irish, but <sic>Genuine</sic> self reflecting
                <sic>indipendant</sic><lb/> American Jews, whom you <sic>cant</sic>
                <del>trample whom you cannot</del><lb/> trample under the feet of
                <sic>Preists</sic>. This is all true and we can <sic>imma<lb/>gine</sic> your grief,
                your burning pain, your sacred woe, you should respect<lb/> this sacred
                    plae<add>?</add> but your boundless fanaticism your unholy Zeal as<lb/> a
                partisan would not allow you to do justice to a place which is more<lb/> sacred than
                your Synagogue together with all your singing chanting<lb/> crying and jumping. Well
                    <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> you <sic>certanly</sic> x must have</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">to their school</p>
            <p><sic>labord</sic> under some spiritual illusion, when you composed the foregoing<lb/>
                sentences, but can it be believed that the man who profess to defend<lb/> the Jew,
                and Judaism against every outside attack, will himself<lb/> address his
                coreligionists so wickedly <sic>spitefull</sic>, and for no other reason than<lb/>
                their misfortune to differ with him, and because an individual hath<lb/> said, “They
                attach a greater degree of consequence “Than some might think<lb/> it deserves„
                Great man how <sic>contemptily</sic> have you fallen how differ<lb/>ently did
                    <persName>Moses</persName> our faithful preceptor act, on a similar
                occasion.</p>
            <p>“Because one man hath <sic>sind</sic>, wilt thou O Lord be indignant with an
                entire<lb/> community.” witness the language of a reformed Rabbi a teacher of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName><lb/> the head and soul of a school, when the
                    <del>sacred</del> pupils are trained to a<lb/> moral and religious course of
                education, that such a sacred place<lb/> under such a leader is more sacred than
                your <sic>Synagoge</sic>
                <sic>to gether</sic> with your<lb/> singing chanting crying and jumping„ <hi
                    rend="underline">shame</hi>
                <persName>Dr. <hi rend="underline">Wise</hi></persName> a person of your<lb/> cloth,
                to speak so insultingly to a god serving people, now can any<lb/> thing be more
                Priest trodden than this.„ let me tell you <persName>Dr. Wise</persName><lb/> there
                is not a <sic>jewish</sic> congregation on this or the old continent, that<lb/> is
                so Priestly imposed under fair <sic>pretences</sic>, as your congregation are<lb/>
                witness their reception of your new Minag (liturgy) which they<lb/> accepted by
                acclamation in its printed form, they having full<lb/> confidence in all things you
                write or preach while it is rejected<lb/> by every congregation in the union
                excepting a miserable few.<lb/> Thus you revised a prayer Book, and have stricken
                out passages<lb/> &amp; prayers, the best to fortify Israelites in a belief in god,
                as a benevolent<lb/> rewarder of the good, and the strict judge of sin, the belief
                in the life of<lb/> the spirit after death, and the eternal permanence of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> as<lb/> gods people, as also in the restoration of
                the Temple of the Lord now<lb/> in ruins and of our state, which is now no more, yes
                in order to<lb/> deprive your congregation of this belief, were all those
                prayer<lb/> which refer to it <hi rend="underline">Banished</hi> and the remainder
                so mutilated, and<lb/> discoverable only to the initiated, and to make room for such
                a <del>po</del><lb/> patch work„ you have caused them to reject a prayer book
                com<lb/>posed by <placeName>Israels</placeName> heroes, by the most famed teachers,
                whose spirit<lb/>
                <del>so</del></p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">4</p>
            <p>survives to this day among us, as the ornament and glory of
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName> whose<lb/> names will never be blotted out b y
                time, but which one age hands down to<lb/> the other by men who did not degrade
                science into an instrument for the<lb/>ir own advancement or employed as a mere
                means of getting bread. I will<lb/> spare you the pain of naming your associate
                authors, in the work of yr.<lb/> new liturgy enough to say they are all worthy of
                each other. You conclude that<lb/> “<persName>Mr Bruel</persName> boasts that his
                orthodox congregation are free of debt!!!<lb/> “This is because they do not pay
                their Hazonam (Readers) <sic>enoug</sic> to make<lb/> a living, because they have no
                synagogue of their own, because they care<lb/> not for the poor, they pay not a cent
                for education excepting a few only<lb/> they pay not a cent to our Hospital nor to
                our relief society nor to<lb/> any charitable <del>institute ton</del> purpose,
                therefore <sic>there</sic> Synagogue are<lb/> free of debt. Open your ears
                    <persName>Dr. Wise</persName> and I will tell you truths, things<lb/> indeed out
                of your line. Know then that our small congregation<lb/> pay our chazan (reader) an
                amt of salary fully equal to that which your<lb/>
                <sic>synagog</sic> or any other in this city are paying, we have a Synagogue
                &amp;<lb/> furniture of our own on a lease, a <sic>Cemetry</sic> for our dead real
                estate<lb/> paid for, our <del>congregation</del> synagogue pay as much to the
                Hospital<lb/> and relief fund as yours do. The Hospital originated with the orthodox
                while<lb/> the <sic>releif</sic> society grew out of a benevolent Institution, in a
                word, you have placed a<lb/> false constriction on the whole, because all the
                charitable institutions you have<lb/> enumerated are supported entirely by voluntary
                subscription, and all of them were in <sic>existance</sic><lb/> before you came
                here, nor do any of the synagogues here pay one cent to them from their<lb/>
                respective treasury, therefore we pay as much as you do every family obtain
                private<lb/> Hebrew teachers for their children, they need not support your schools
                if they disa<lb/>prove of its chief head. They avail themselves of our districts
                schools believing they<lb/> are better than yours. What <sic>benifit</sic> have for
                taunting a religious institution<lb/> for being cold and indifferent to the wants of
                their needy correligionists when you<lb/> know to the contrary. If I have said any
                thing <sic>offencively</sic> concerning their school<lb/> I can assure its leaders
                that none was intended, and none but a persons having the<lb/> principles of
                    <persName>Dr. Wise</persName>
                <hi rend="underline">principles</hi>, who constantly is striving to sow the seed of
                contention<lb/> would have made so much from so small an affair <hi rend="underline"
                        ><persName>S Bruel</persName></hi> ND „The Occident is<lb/> now a weekly
                paper every Israelite should read that old established sheet, whose uniform course
                have<lb/> obtained for itself a reputation for ability, truthfulness, and
                    <sic>consistancy</sic>, it is a faithful and reliable<lb/>
                <sic>Jurnal</sic> whose views and principles remain unchanged by reading the weekly
                Occidn.<lb/> persons will have the opportunity of <sic>examing</sic> both sides of
                disputed public<lb/>
                <add>?</add> the camp of <placeName>Israel</placeName></p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>
                <persName>
                    <hi rend="underline">S Bruel</hi>
                </persName>
            </p>
            <p>at. <persName>D. Wolf</persName> 50.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">
                <persName>
                    <add>?</add>
                    <hi rend="underline">S. Wert</hi>
                </persName>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
