<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Charter and By Laws of the Hebrew Education Society of Philadelphia together
					with Rules and Regulations for the Government of Maimonides College</title>
				<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Hebrew Education Society of
					Philadelphia</author>
				<editor/>
				<sponsor/>
				<funder/>
				<principal/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
				item comes later]</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Stein and Jones, printers</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<p>Not part of a series</p>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note/>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<!-- catalog entry goes here -->
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<dateLet/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country>USA</country>
						<region>PA</region>
						<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
						<institution/>
						<repository>TCAT</repository>
						<collection>Anonymous</collection>
						<idno>LSTCAT_item224</idno>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
						<msName/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<head/>
					<letHeading>
						<author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk">Hebrew Education
							Society of Philadelphia</author>
						<addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
						<deliverer/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
						<placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
						<placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
						<dateLet attested="yes" source="" when="1868">1868</dateLet>
					</letHeading>
					<msContents>
						<msItem>
							<author/>
							<editor/>
							<respStmt>
								<resp/>
								<name/>
							</respStmt>
							<title/>
							<decoNote/>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl/>
							</listBibl>
							<filiation/>
							<textLang/>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0013.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0014.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0015.jpg"/>
								<graphic url="il_tcat_item224_wk1_body0016.jpg"/>
							</figure>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support>
									<material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
										>pamphlet</material>
								</support>
								<extent>16 pages on 16 sheets <dimensions/>
								</extent>
								<foliation/>
								<collation/>
								<condition fragment="false"/>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout/>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc script="typescript">
							<handNote/>
						</handDesc>
						<decoDesc>
							<decoNote/>
						</decoDesc>
						<additions/>
						<bindingDesc>
							<binding>
								<decoNote/>
							</binding>
						</bindingDesc>
						<sealDesc>
							<seal>
								<p/>
							</seal>
						</sealDesc>
						<accMat/>
						<envDesc occ="false"/>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin/>
						<provenance/>
						<acquisition/>
					</history>
					<additional>
						<adminInfo>
							<recordHist>
								<source/>
								<change/>
							</recordHist>
							<availability status="free">
								<p>Unrestricted</p>
							</availability>
							<custodialHist>
								<custEvent/>
							</custodialHist>
						</adminInfo>
						<surrogates/>
						<listBibl>
							<bibl/>
						</listBibl>
					</additional>
					<msPart>
						<altIdentifier>
							<idno/>
						</altIdentifier>
					</msPart>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p/>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p/>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction>
					<p/>
				</correction>
				<normalization>
					<p/>
				</normalization>
				<quotation>
					<p/>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation>
					<p/>
				</hyphenation>
				<segmentation>
					<p/>
				</segmentation>
				<stdVals>
					<p/>
				</stdVals>
				<interpretation>
					<p/>
				</interpretation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition/>
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi=""/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit=""/>
			</refsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy>
					<category>
						<catDesc/>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="" version="">
					<desc/>
					<label/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation/>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="unknown">
					<list>
						<item/>
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<classCode scheme=""/>
				<catRef/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">CHARTER &amp; BY-LAWS</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF THE</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<persName role="author">Hebrew Education Society</persName>
			</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF <placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">TOGETHER WITH</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">RULES AND REGULATIONS</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">MAIMONIDES COLLEGE</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>:</p>
			<p rend="align(center)"><persName>STEIN &amp; JONES</persName>, PRINTERS, <placeName>321
					CHESTNUT STREET</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">
				<date>1868</date>
			</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">AN ACT</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">TO INCORPORATE THE <persName role="author">HEBREW EDUCATION
					SOCIETY</persName></p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF <placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 1. <hi rend="italics">Be it enacted by the Senate and House
					of Rep-<lb/>resentatives of the Commonwealth of
						<placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName> in General<lb/> Assembly met, and it is
					hereby enacted by the authority of the<lb/> same</hi>, That <persName>Solomon
					Solis</persName>, <persName>Simon Elfelt</persName>, <persName>Abraham
					Hart</persName>, <persName>Moses<lb/> A. Dropsie</persName>, <persName>Solomon
					N. Carvalho</persName>, <persName>Isidore Binswanger</persName>,
					<persName>Marcus<lb/> Cauffman</persName>, <persName>Lewis J. Cohen</persName>,
					<persName>Simon M. Klosser</persName>, <persName>Jacob
					Langs-<lb/>dorf</persName>, <persName>Isaac Leeser</persName>, <persName>Moses
					Nathans</persName>, <persName>Joseph Newhouse</persName>, <persName>Hyman<lb/>
					Polock</persName>, <persName>Julius Stern</persName>, <persName>Herman Van
					Beil</persName>, <persName>Abraham S. Wolf</persName>,<lb/>
				<persName>Lewis M. Allen</persName>, <persName>Mayer Arnold</persName>,
					<persName>Simon W. Arnold</persName>, <persName>David<lb/> Barnett</persName>,
					<persName>Leon Berg</persName>, <persName>A. I. H. Bernal</persName>,
					<persName>Bernard Blum</persName>, <persName>Myer<lb/> D. Cohen</persName>,
					<persName>Julius Davidson</persName>, <persName>Zadok A. Davis</persName>,
					<persName>Henry DeBoer</persName>,<lb/>
				<persName>Solomon Eckstein</persName>, <persName>David Eger</persName>,
					<persName>William Florance</persName>, <persName>P. Friden-<lb/>berg</persName>,
					<persName>Solomon Gans</persName>, <persName>J. Geisenberg</persName>,
					<persName>M. Gerstley</persName>, <persName>Jacob Gum-<lb/>pel</persName>,
					<persName>Selig Hohenfels</persName>, <persName>Aaron Isaacs</persName>,
					<persName>Solomon Isaacs</persName>, <persName>Julius<lb/> Jacobs</persName>,
					<persName>Israel Jacobs</persName>, <persName>B. Klein</persName>,
					<persName>Henry Lazarus</persName>, <persName>David Levine</persName>,<lb/>
				<persName>N. E. Nelson</persName>, <persName>Joseph A. Levy</persName>,
					<persName>George Phillips</persName>, <persName>Michael<lb/>
				Reinhard</persName>, <persName>Joseph Schoneman</persName>, <persName>M.
					Seidenbach</persName>, <persName>Henry Simson</persName>,<lb/>
				<persName>David H. Solis</persName>, <persName>Mayer Sternberger</persName>,
					<persName>L. Sulzberger</persName>, <persName>David Van<lb/> Beil</persName>,
					<persName>Simon Sternberger</persName>, <persName>Moses Vanderslice</persName>,
					<persName>Abraham Wolf</persName>,<lb/>
				<persName>Isaac Tassner</persName> and <persName>Doctor Samuel Wolff</persName> and
				all and every other<lb/> person or persons who shall hereafter become members of the<lb/>
				<persName role="author">Hebrew Education Society of
						<placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></persName>, be and are hereby<lb/>
				created and made a corporation or body politic and corporate,<lb/> by the name and
				style of “THE <persName role="author">HEBREW EDUCATION SOCIETY</persName></p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">4</p>
			<p>OF <placeName>PHILADELPHIA</placeName>,” and by that name shall have perpetual<lb/>
				succession, and be capable in law to take, hold and dispose of<lb/> estates, real
				and personal whatsoever, and to sue and be sued,<lb/> and to receive and make all
				deeds, transfers, contracts, con-<lb/>veyances and covenants whatsoever, and to
				make, have and<lb/> use a common seal, and the same to change and renew at<lb/>
				pleasure, and generally to do every other act or thing neces-<lb/>sary to carry into
				effect the provisions of this act, <sic>asd</sic> promote<lb/> the objects and
				designs of said corporation.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 2. The object and design of the said corporation<lb/> shall
				be the establishment of a school or schools within the<lb/> limits of the city and
				county of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, in which are to<lb/> be taught the
				elementary branches of education, together with<lb/> the sciences, and modern and
				ancient languages, always in<lb/> combination with instruction in Hebrew language,
				literature,<lb/> and religion, in the manner that may be determined from time<lb/>
				to time, by the proper officers of the Society, and as the same<lb/> may be set
				forth in their Constitution and By-laws, and<lb/> School regulations; <hi
					rend="italics">Provided</hi>, Said Constitution, By-laws, and<lb/> Regulations
				are not inconsistent with this Charter, or with<lb/> the Constitution of the
					<placeName>United States</placeName>, or the Constitution and<lb/> Laws of this
				Commonwealth.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 3. It shall also be lawful for said corporation to<lb/>
				establish, whenever their funds will permit the same to be<lb/> done, a superior
				seminary of learning, within the limits of<lb/> this Commonwealth, the faculty of
				which seminary shall have<lb/> power to furnish its graduates and others, the usual
				degrees<lb/> of Bachelor of Arts, Master of Arts, and Doctor of Law and<lb/>
				Divinity, as the same is exercised by other colleges established<lb/> in this
				Commonwealth.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 4. The Society shall have power to adopt a
				Con-<lb/>stitution and make By-laws, and the same to amend, alter or<lb/> repeal at
				pleasure.</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">5</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 5. The said Society shall not at any time have,<lb/> hold,
				enjoy or receive a clear yearly income exceeding twelve<lb/> thousand
					<sic>dollars.</sic> without first obtaining authority from the<lb/> legislature
				of this Commonwealth.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">SECTION 6. The legislature shall have power at any time<lb/> when
				the privileges hereby granted shall appear injurious to<lb/> the public, to repeal,
				alter or amend this act; but no such<lb/> repeal, alteration or amendment shall
				affect any engagement<lb/> to which the said corporation shall have become a party
				pre-<lb/>vious thereto; and in case of such repeal the said corporation<lb/> shall
				have a reasonable time to bring their accounts to a final<lb/> settlement and
				termination.</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">(Signed)<persName>WILLIAM F. PACKER</persName>,</p>
			<p rend="indent(2)">Speaker of the House of Representatives.</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">(Signed)<persName>GEORGE DARSIE</persName>,</p>
			<p rend="indent(4)">Speaker of the Senate.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">APPROVED—The <date>seventh day of April, one thousand eight<lb/>
					hundred and forty-nine</date>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(3)">(Signed)<persName>WM. F. JOHNSTON</persName>.</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">BY-LAWS.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF MEMBERS.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. Any male Israelite, aged at least
				twenty-one<lb/> years, who shall receive a majority of the votes cast at any<lb/>
				meeting of the Board or Society, shall be a member of this<lb/> Society.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 2. Each member shall pay five dollars
				yearly.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 3. A member one year or more in
				arrears, shall neither<lb/> vote nor hold office, unless exonerated from his dues by
				the<lb/> Board of Managers.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 4. A member more than two years in
				arrears may be<lb/> expelled by the Board.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF OFFICERS.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. The officers of this Society
				shall be a President,<lb/> Vice President, Treasurer, Secretary, Assistant
				Secretary, and<lb/> twelve Managers, who, together shall constitute the Board
				of<lb/> Managers. They shall hold their respective offices for one<lb/> year or
				until their successors shall have been chosen. There<lb/> shall also be Trustees of
				the College, not less than fifteen nor<lb/> more than twenty-one in number, who
				shall be elected as fol-<lb/>lows: at the first election one third of their number
				shall be<lb/> chosen for one year, one third for two years and the remain-<lb/>ing
				third for three years, and at every subsequent election<lb/> they shall be chosen
				for three years.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 2 Elections shall be held at the annual
				meetings of<lb/> the Society.</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">7</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 3. The President shall preside at all
				meetings of the<lb/> Society, Board of Managers and College Trustees, shall
				draw<lb/> orders on the Treasurer for amounts passed by the Board of<lb/> Managers
				and College Trustees; shall, whenever he may deem<lb/> it necessary, convene special
				meetings of the Society, Board of<lb/> Managers, or College Trustees, and shall
				appoint all commit-<lb/>tees, unless otherwise ordered by the Society. He shall
				have<lb/> the right to draw an order on the Treasurer for any sum not<lb/> exceeding
				twenty-five dollars, without an appropriation by<lb/> the Board.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 4. The Vice President shall in the
				absence of the Presi-<lb/>dent succeed to all his rights and duties.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 5. The Treasurer shall take charge of
				all moneys and<lb/> securities of the Society, shall pay all orders duly signed
				by<lb/> the President, or acting President, shall keep an account of<lb/> his
				receipts and disbursements, and furnish a statement of the<lb/> same at the annual
				meeting of the Society, and shall report<lb/> at every stated meeting of the board
				the amount of the balance<lb/> in his hands. He shall keep a separate account of the
				receipts<lb/> and expenditures on account of the College fund and shall<lb/> make a
				report at each meeting of the College Trustees. He<lb/> shall give such security for
				the faithful performance of his<lb/> duties, as shall be approved of by the Board,
				and within two<lb/> weeks after the election of his successor he shall deliver to
				the<lb/> latter, all moneys, papers, accounts and all other property<lb/> whatsoever
				belonging to the Society.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 6. The Secretary shall keep fair and
				correct minutes<lb/> of all transactions of the Society or Board of Managers.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 7. The Assistant Secretary shall
				prepare notices for<lb/> all meetings, shall keep the accounts with the members of
				the<lb/> Society, as well as all accounts for tuition and books, shall<lb/> prepare
				all bills, shall act as Secretary of the Boards of College<lb/> Trustees and School
				Directors, and shall perform all the duties</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">8</p>
			<p>of the Secretary in the latter's absence, for which services he<lb/> shall receive
				such compensation as may be fixed by the Board<lb/> of Managers.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 8. The Board of Managers shall fill all
				vacancies occur-<lb/>ring among their own number, shall elect the School
				Teachers,<lb/> shall employ a Messenger and Collector, and compensate<lb/> him,
				shall determine the branches of education to be taught<lb/> in the School, and shall
				do all things necessary for the gov-<lb/>ernment and maintenance of the Schools. If
				any more schools<lb/> be established, they shall elect two additional School
				Directors.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 9. The Board of College Trustees shall
				determine the<lb/> branches to be taught in the College after consulting with
				the<lb/> faculty, shall elect the Provost, Professors and other officers<lb/>
				thereof, shall determine the tuition and scholarship fees, as<lb/> also the number
				of free scholarships, shall make the appro-<lb/>priations for the payment of all the
				salaries and other expenses<lb/> of the College, shall pay the same by means of
				orders drawn<lb/> by the President on the Treasurer on account of the College<lb/>
				Fund, shall grant the degrees of Bachelor and Master of Arts<lb/> and Doctor of
				Divinity and Law to students recommended<lb/>
				<sic>therefor</sic> by the faculty and to other persons deemed properly<lb/>
				qualified, shall evidence the same by diplomas signed by the<lb/> Provost and
				Professors of the College and by the President of<lb/> the Society with the
				Society's seal attached, shall make rules<lb/> and statutes for the government of
				the College and shall do<lb/> all things necessary for the proper transaction of its
				affairs.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 10. All elections for officers or
				members of the Society<lb/> or Board shall be by ballot.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 11. In all elections for officers
				non-resident members<lb/> may vote by proxy.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF MEETINGS.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section </hi>1. The Society shall have one stated
				meeting an-<lb/>nually on the <date>Sunday before <hi rend="italics"
					>Shabu'oth</hi></date>.</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">9</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 2. The Board of Managers shall have
				four stated<lb/> meetings in each year, the first of which shall be held on the<lb/>
				<date>third Sunday</date> after the annual meeting, and the others at
				in-<lb/>tervals of three months respectively.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 3. The School Directors shall have one
				stated meeting<lb/> in each month except <date>August</date>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec</hi> 4. The Board of College Trustees shall
				have one sta-<lb/>ted meeting in every three months.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec. </hi>5. Special meetings of the Society or
				Board of Ma-<lb/>nagers or College Trustees may be called by the President<lb/>
				whenever he may deem it necessary, and it shall be his duty<lb/> to call such
				special meetings of the Society when requested by<lb/> ten members thereof, and of
				the Board of Managers when re-<lb/>quested by three of its members, and of the Board
				of College<lb/> Trustees when requested by four of its members.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 6. At the meetings of the Society,
				thirteen shall con-<lb/>stitute a quorum; of the Board, five; of the School
				Directors,<lb/> three; and of the Trustees of the College, five.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF THE SCHOOL DEPARTMENT.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. In the School or Schools there
				shall be imparted<lb/> in addition to the usual English branches, Religious
				instruc-<lb/>tion, Biblical History, and the Hebrew language according to<lb/> the
				German and Portuguese readings.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 2. The School or Schools shall be under
				the direction<lb/> of the seven School Directors, who shall be chosen yearly at<lb/>
				the first quarterly meeting of the Board of Managers. The<lb/> President shall be
					<hi rend="italics">ex-officio</hi> a member of the Board of Di-<lb/>rectors.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 3 No pupil shall be admitted into the
				School without<lb/> a written order of the Directors. They shall determine the<lb/>
				price of tuition, and in proper cases may admit pupils gratu-<lb/>itously or for
				less than the usual charges adopted by them,</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">10</p>
			<p>shall make rules and regulations for the government of the<lb/> School, shall
				determine the books to be used therein, and shall<lb/> have a general supervision of
				the School or Schools.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec. </hi>4. The Teachers' salaries shall be paid
				quarterly.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF PRIZE SCHOLARSHIPS.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. The Board of Managers shall have
				power to<lb/> establish as rewards for distinguished merit in the School,<lb/> prize
				scholarships in the College, not exceeding five in number<lb/> and shall be
				authorized to pay into the College Fund, the<lb/> necessary amounts for the tuition
				fees.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 2. No pupil shall be entitled to a
				prize scholarship<lb/> unless he be recommended for the same to the Board of
				Mana-<lb/>gers, by the Principals of the Hebrew and English departments<lb/> in the
				School, and by a majority of the Board of School<lb/> Directors.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF THE COLLEGE.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. There shall be a College in the
				city of <placeName>Philadel-<lb/>phia</placeName>, styled Maimonides College, in
				which besides the usual<lb/> collegiate branches, there shall be taught a full
				course of<lb/> Hebrew literature.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics"><sic>See</sic></hi>. 2. For the establishment and
				maintenance of this<lb/> College, there shall be a separate “College Fund.”</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec</hi>. 3. The College shall be under the
				direction of the<lb/> Trustees elected as hereinbefore provided by the Society
				from<lb/> among its members. Any vacancies in said Board of Trustees<lb/> shall be
				filled by the said Trustees. Of said Trustees at least<lb/> seven shall be residents
				of the city of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec. </hi>4. Any congregation or society
				contributing yearly<lb/> the sum of one thousand dollars to the College Fund, shall
				be<lb/> entitled to elect one additional member of the Board of<lb/> Trustees.</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">11</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec.</hi> 5. This article shall take effect on
				the <date>Sunday before<lb/>
					<hi rend="italics">Shabu'oth</hi>, 1868, (5628,)</date> and till that time the
				Board of Man-<lb/>agers shall have full power to organize and manage the
				College<lb/> as they may deem advisable, and to delegate their authority to<lb/> any
				number of members of the Society, whom they may desig-<lb/>nate as Trustees for the
				purpose.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">RULES OF ORDER.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. At all meetings the order of
				business shall be as<lb/> follows:</p>
			<list type="ordered">
				<head/>
				<item n="1"> Roll-call.</item>
				<item n="2"> Reading of the minutes of the previous meeting.</item>
				<item n="3"> Reports of Officers.</item>
				<item n="4"> Communications.</item>
				<item n="5"> Election of Officers or Members.</item>
				<item n="6"> Deferred business.</item>
				<item n="7"> New business.</item>
			</list>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Sec</hi>. 2. The yeas and nays shall be entered
				on the minutes<lb/> when required by two members.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF AMENDMENTS.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="italics">Section</hi> 1. No alteration, amendment or
				addition to these<lb/> By-laws shall be made unless proposed at one meeting of
				the<lb/> Society or Board of Managers and confirmed at the next<lb/> meeting of the
				Society by a vote of two-thirds of the members<lb/> present, the Assistant Secretary
				having sent ten days' notice<lb/> of such amendment to all the members.</p>
			<pb n="12"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">RULES AND REGULATOINS</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">MAIMONIDES COLLEGE.</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">The Faculty of Arts is composed of the following
				Professor-<lb/>ships:</p>
			<p>A Professorship of Homiletics, Belles Lettres and Comparative<lb/> Theology,</p>
			<p>“ “ The Bible and Biblical Literature.</p>
			<p>“ “ Talmud, Hebrew Philosophy, Jewish His-<lb/>tory and Literature.</p>
			<p>“ “ Mishnah with Commentaries, Shulchan<lb/> Aruch and Yad ha-Chazakah.</p>
			<p>“ “ Hebrew and Chaldaic Languages.</p>
			<p>“ “ Greek and Latin</p>
			<p>“ “ Rhetoric and English Literature.</p>
			<p>“ “ Mathematics.</p>
			<p>“ “ Natural Philosophy and Chemistry.</p>
			<p>“ “ German and French Languages.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF THE FACULTY.</p>
			<list type="ordered">
				<head/>
				<item n="1"> The Professors shall constitute “The Faculty of Arts,”<lb/> to whom, as
					a body, shall be committed the immediate regu-<lb/>lation and government of the
					Collegiate Department, subject<lb/> to the rules and statutes and the control of
					the Board of<lb/> Trustees.</item>
				<item n="2"> The College shall be under the supervision of the Pro-<lb/>vost, who
					shall make report in relation to it to the Board at<lb/> least once a
					year.</item>
			</list>
			<pb n="13"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">13</p>
			<p>3. Stated meetings of the Faculty shall be held every<lb/> month, for the purpose of
				administering the general discipline<lb/> of the College; and special meetings, as
				often as the business of<lb/> the institution may require, to be called by the
				Provost or a<lb/> majority of the members. At all meetings of the Faculty, the<lb/>
				Provost shall preside, or in his absence a chairman can be<lb/> elected.</p>
			<p>4. The Faculty shall appoint a Secretary from its own body<lb/> whose duty it shall
				be, to keep the minutes of their proceed-<lb/>ings, which shall be, at all times,
				open to the inspection of<lb/> the Trustees.</p>
			<p>5. No proceedings of the Faculty shall be considered as<lb/> valid, unless passed by
				a majority of the members at a meet-<lb/>ing formally constituted.</p>
			<p>6. It shall be the duty of the Faculty to make reports to<lb/> the Board at their
				stated meetings, upon the state of the Col-<lb/>legiate department, stating
				particularly the names and resi-<lb/>dences of such students as have been admitted
				into, or have<lb/> left the institution since the last report, with such remarks
				as<lb/> they may deem expedient.</p>
			<p>7. It shall be the special duty of the Provost, to visit and<lb/> superintend the
				various departments; to see that the rules<lb/> and statutes are duly carried into
				effect, to report to the Board<lb/> every instance of refusal and neglect to comply
				with such<lb/> rules and statutes, and to advise and suggest such alterations<lb/>
				and improvements as he may deem best calculated to promote<lb/> the welfare and
				usefulness of the institution.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF THE CLASSES.</p>
			<p>1. The students shall be distributed into five classes.</p>
			<p>2. No applicant shall be admitted into the Freshman class<lb/> under the age of 14;
				any special exception shall be decided by<lb/> the Board, upon the application of
				the Faculty. His fitness</p>
			<pb n="14"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">14</p>
			<p>must appear on examination, to be conducted by the Profes-<lb/>sors, who must concur
				in opinion that he is qualified in such<lb/> branches as shall be prescribed by the
				Board.</p>
			<p>3. The requisites for entering the Freshman class shall be<lb/> as follows:</p>
			<p>LATIN—<persName>Caesar</persName>, <persName>Virgil</persName>,
					<persName>Sallust</persName>, Odes of <persName>Horace</persName>.</p>
			<p>ENGLISH—The elements of English grammar and of modern<lb/> Geography.</p>
			<p>HEBREW—The translation of the historical portions of the<lb/> Bible with
				facility.</p>
			<p>ARITHMETIC, including fractions and extraction of roots.</p>
			<p>4. The Faculty shall keep a book called the Matriculation<lb/> book, in which every
				candidate for entrance into this College<lb/> shall, on his admission, have his
				name, age and residence<lb/> entered, and the name and residence of his parent or
				guardian.</p>
			<p>5. No student shall be admitted to advanced standing,<lb/> without being as fully
				instructed as the class to which admis-<lb/>sion is asked, in all the studies in
				which the class has been<lb/> instructed.</p>
			<p>6. Vacation shall be from the <date>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of July</date> to the
						<date>31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> of<lb/> August</date>.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">COURSE OF INSTRUCTION.</p>
			<p>1. The subjects of instruction in the institution shall be<lb/> the following:—</p>
			<p rend="indent(1)">Greek, Latin, German, French, Hebrew, Chaldaic and their<lb/>
				literatures, the Natural sciences, History, Mathematics and<lb/> Astronomy, Moral
				and Intellectual Philosophy, Constitution-<lb/>al History and Laws of the
					<placeName>United States</placeName>, Belles Lettres,<lb/> Homiletics,
				Comparative Theology, the Bible with its com-<lb/>mentaries, the Mishnah with its
				commentaries, the Shulchan<lb/> 'Aruch, Yad ha-chazakah, Jewish History and
				Literature,<lb/> Hebrew Philosophy and the Talmud with its commentaries.</p>
			<pb n="15"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">15</p>
			<p>2. At the close of each yearly term there shall be held an<lb/> examination of all
				the classes in the presence of a Committee<lb/> of the Board, and of such other
				Trustees as shall attend; after<lb/> every examination the students who are
				distinguished in each<lb/> class shall be arranged in the order of merit.</p>
			<p>3. No student shall be suffered to proceed to a higher class<lb/> who shall not, on
				examination show himself to be master of<lb/> the studies of the
					<sic>preceeding</sic> year, but he may be allowed<lb/> the privilege, (if the
				faculty shall judge it expedient to grant<lb/> it,) of a second examination for
				admission thereto, at the<lb/> opening of the next succeeding year.</p>
			<p>4. Punishment shall be exclusively directed to a sense of<lb/> duty, and the
				principles of honor and shame, and shall consist<lb/> of private admonition by a
				Professor—admonition in the pre-<lb/>sence of the Faculty—admonition in the presence
				of the Fac-<lb/>ulty and of the class of the offender—removal to a lower<lb/>
				class—suspension for a limited time from college—dismissal—<lb/>expulsion.</p>
			<p>5. No punishment except private admonition shall be in-<lb/>flicted, unless ordered
				by a resolution of a majority of the<lb/> whole of the Faculty; nor shall the
				punishment of expulsion<lb/> be inflicted unless it be first sanctioned by a vote of
				the<lb/> Trustees. In case of dismissal, the offender may be re-admit-<lb/>ted, but
				the effect of the expulsion shall be an utter disqualifica-<lb/>tion of the
				individual for re-admission into this institution,<lb/> or of receiving any of its
				honors.</p>
			<p>6. The fees for tuition of each year shall be one hundred<lb/> dollars, payable at
				the commencement thereof; and no stud-<lb/>ent shall be considered as entitled to
				his seat in the class for<lb/> the term, until such payment is made. Notice that the
				tui-<lb/>tion money is due, and that the Treasurer will at times attend<lb/> (the
				time then to be stated) shall be given by the Secretary.</p>
			<pb n="16"/>
			<p rend="align(center)">16</p>
			<p>7. The Board sanction the institution of a Literary Society,<lb/> to consist of the
				students and alumni of the college, or such of<lb/> them as shall be admitted
				members thereof, when suitable<lb/> rooms can be appropriated for their use. The
				said society to<lb/> be under the general control and supervision of the
				Faculty.</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">OF COMMENCEMENTS AND CONFERRING DEGREES</p>
			<p rend="align(center)">IN THE ARTS.</p>
			<list type="ordered">
				<head/>
				<item n="1"> There shall be an annual commencement of graduates<lb/> in the arts on
					the <date>last Thursday morning of each term</date>, at<lb/> 10 o'clock.</item>
				<item n="2"> Candidates for the degree of Bachelor in the Arts of Di-<lb/>vinity
					shall be publicly examined by the faculty in the<lb/> collegiate departments, in
					the presence of the Committee of<lb/> Examination and such other members of the
					Board of Trustees<lb/> as may attend.</item>
				<item n="3"> The Provost shall report the names of those who shall<lb/> have been
					found worthy of receiving such degree to the Board,<lb/> who shall, if the
					report be approved, confer such degree ac-<lb/>cordingly. But no degree shall be
					conferred unless by the vote<lb/> of the Trustees; and every student, before he
					can be recom-<lb/>mended for the degree of Bachelor of Arts or Divinity,
					shall<lb/> settle his account with the Treasurer.</item>
				<item n="4"> The degree of Master of Arts may be conferred on the<lb/> Alumni of the
					College, who shall have been Bachelor in the<lb/> Arts of three years standing,
					and shall apply for that honor.</item>
				<item n="5"> The order of the commencement shall be directed by<lb/> the
					Faculty.</item>
			</list>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
