<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>LSTCAT</repository>
                        <collection>Anonymous</collection>
                        <idno>LSTCAT_item92</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author accepted="yes" attested="yes" signature="unk"/>
                        <addressee accepted="yes" attested="yes" editor="false"/>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet/>
                        <placeRec>Philadelphia, PA</placeRec>
                        <dateLet attested="unk" source="" when=""/>
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0001.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0002.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0003.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0004.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0005.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0006.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0007.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0008.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0009.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0010.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0011.jpg"/>
                                <graphic url="il_tcat_item92_wk1_body0012.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="true" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >letter</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 12 sheets <dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"/>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p/>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">1</p>
            <p rend="align(center)">The Congregation Beth Elohim of
                    <placeName>Charleston</placeName>.</p>
            <p>No 6 full price</p>
            <p>The attention of the Jewish Public being directed to the<lb/> movement of this
                congregation, we beg leave to lay before them<lb/> a statistical and comprehensive
                sketch of the part and parsing<lb/> events which have agitated and are now agitating
                this body.</p>
            <p>At the period when the <persName>Rev Y Posnanski</persName> was elected for a
                probationary term of two years Hazan of the<lb/> K. K. B. E. it was one of the most
                Orthodox, Religious, &amp; <sic>Charatable</sic><lb/> in the <placeName>United
                    States</placeName>.—after the expiration of one year. The Congregation<lb/> in
                consideration of his ardent zeal in the cause of our holy Religion<lb/> his piety
                and conformation to all the laws both Mosaic and<lb/> Rabbinical, Elected him for
                life.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">As soon as this event took place a course diametrically<lb/>
                opposite was immediately pursued by <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName>, which<lb/>
                was the cause of the disastrous outbreak in <date>1841</date>, when upwards<lb/> of
                Forty of the <del>oldest</del> most <sic>consciensious</sic> and <del>most</del>
                strictly conservative members were<lb/> scrupulously compelled to <del>resign</del>
                withdraw, (among whom were<lb/> the founders of the congregation) and to leave in
                the power of<lb/> its rulers not only that Sacred Edifice which was identified
                with<lb/> many Holy associations, but <sic>but</sic> were denied any participation
                in the management of the Kyrankyamits<lb/> Fund to which they had largely
                contributed until it had<lb/> accumulated to the Sum of $25.000. the Interest of
                which<lb/> was appropriated to support the very individual who by his<lb/> arbitrary
                and anti Jewish Conduct cause another dispersion<lb/> in
                    <placeName>Israel</placeName>, and depriving the aged supporters of the
                Congregation<lb/> their Venerable matrons and their children, not only of a
                place<lb/> of worship but also of the <sic>priveledges</sic> of Sepulture, for
                imme-<lb/>-diately upon their withdrawal, the constitution of the KKBE.<lb/> was
                amended as follows “Any Subscriber Yehid, or member<lb/> of this Congregation, male
                or Female who shall habitually<lb/> attend <hi rend="underline">Divine</hi> service
                at any other place of worship within<lb/> the city than that of the KKB.E. or
                subscribe there to as<lb/> members or Yeshidim shall be charged annually One
                Hundred<lb/> Dollars” We do not deem any comment necessary.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The Congregation remained in a lethargic state until<lb/> its second
                Revolution in <date>1843</date>, which involved it in an</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">2</p>
            <p>expensive and tedious have Suit, and ended in the withdrawal<lb/> of about 25
                members, who were opposed to the abrogation<lb/> of the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Day
                of the <sic>Hollidays</sic> and other innovations suggested<lb/> by <persName>Mr
                    Posnanski</persName>. This Event caused a great deal of unhappiness<lb/> and
                dissensions among families who had hitherto lived in<lb/> peace and Friendship,
                    <sic>untill</sic> the advent of <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName><lb/> and the
                promulgation of his new doctrines. These<lb/> Twenty Five joined with those who had
                withdrawn in <date>1841</date>.<lb/> The K K B.E. Is now threatened with a third,
                and probably,<lb/>
                <del>a</del> final dissolution, when this event takes place—and<lb/> of its near
                approach, indications never were more preferable—<lb/> it will, no doubt, cause the
                overthrow forever of the un-<lb/>-hallowed and vain panoply of power with which its
                present<lb/> Rulers are invested.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">It numbers at this time about Forty Members and<lb/> is divided into
                two parties whom we shall call, for the<lb/> sake of distinction, Radical and
                Conservative. Their<lb/> present minister the <persName>Rev Julius
                Eckman</persName>, was elected<lb/> about Eleven months ago (<persName>Mr
                    Poznanski</persName> having resigned),<lb/> on a probationary term of two years.
                This Gentleman<lb/> is a regularly ordained <add>רב מורה בישראל</add> (and
                empowered) by virtue of<lb/> a Diploma honorably conferred on him, under the
                seals<lb/> of the Rabbinates of <placeName>Berlin</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Prenzlaw</placeName> (which are<lb/> two of the greatest acknowledged
                authorities of <placeName>Europe</placeName>) and was duly prepared<lb/> by an
                examination at the Royal Fredrick Willhelm<lb/> College at
                    <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, and by his having been a Civis Universitatis<lb/>
                Berolinensis rite inscriptus, for the space of five years. He was<lb/> elected, <hi
                    rend="underline">contrary</hi> to his expectations as he had expressed<lb/>
                himself to all those who called on him previous to that<lb/> time as being entirely
                opposed to the principles <del>of</del> avowed by their<lb/> late Hazan, and in his
                Inaugural address he express-<lb/>edly told <del>them</del> the congregation that he
                appeared before them simply<lb/> as a teacher in <placeName>Israel</placeName> and
                objected to being considered<lb/> their spiritual Head.</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The cause of the division unto two parties of such</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">3</p>
            <p>opposite extremes originated as follows. The <persName>Revd Dr<lb/> Eckman</persName>
                from repealed conversations <del>from</del> on his first arrival<lb/> with
                    <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> and from personal observations
                afterwards,<lb/> found that all positive religion <del>had fallen into Decay</del>
                was rejected<lb/> no religious instruction was communicated in the synagogue<lb/>
                (as <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> did not lecture) prophecy was denied,
                hence<lb/> the denial of all that is <del>Dogmatical</del> Doctrinal and National.
                The<lb/> non observance of the Law not only passively connived at,<lb/> but he
                exposed some Laws that might offend our<lb/> modern delicacy, to the view of his
                adherents the more<lb/> effectually to prove there was no <sic>nescessity</sic> for
                observing them<lb/> his request to <persName>Dr. E.</persName> to preach against the
                    <sic>Rabbies</sic> and<lb/> all observances whither Biblical or Rabbinical and
                his acknowledgment to him<lb/> that it was of no consequence where the bible came
                from<lb/> convinced <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> of <persName>Mr
                    Posnanskis</persName>
                <del>rank</del> daring Infidelity,<lb/> as <persName>Mr Newman</persName> calls it.
                    <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> kept silent<lb/>
                <sic>untill</sic>
                <date>Yom Kipur</date> when <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> was called to<lb/>
                take part in the sacred functions of that day. This <persName>Dr<lb/>
                    Eckman</persName>, as an honest man, could not consent to<lb/> and
                    <sic>and</sic> privately remonstrated with <persName>Mr Posnanski</persName> on
                the great<lb/> crime of Profanation. <persName>Mr Poznanski</persName> replied,
                that<lb/> he not only did not believe <del>the <date>Yom Kipur</date></del> these
                prayers,<lb/> but he detested them, whereupon <persName>Dr Eckman</persName><lb/>
                denounced him to the Parnass. Not only as an Infidel<lb/> but inimically disposed to
                the very Institution of<lb/> Judaism, and positively refused to take any part<lb/>
                in the service of that day. The Personal friends<lb/> of <persName>Mr
                    Posnanski</persName> immediately arrayed themselves in<lb/> open hostilities
                against <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> and have waged them <sic>untill</sic> the
                present<lb/> time. The great Injustice of this <del>course</del> persecution being
                so<lb/> evident to the public, and <persName>Dr. Eckmans</persName> straight<lb/>
                German course in the cause of Religion and Truth<lb/> has drawn to his Standard of
                True Faith a large<lb/> number of the most respectable and intelligent members of
                the congregation*<lb/> The Radical or <persName>Posnanski</persName> party numbers
                exactly Eighteen<lb/>
                <del>*among whom we mention <persName>Mr Joshua Lazarus</persName> the Prest of the
                    congregation and <persName>Mr M C Mordecai<add>?</add></persName>,<lb/> both so
                    honorably named in your last number.</del></p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">4</p>
            <p>the Conservative party Fifteen members and four Congregators<lb/> the remaining
                    <del>8 or 9 members</del> Eight or nine, are<lb/> indisposed to take any part in
                Congregational affairs.<lb/>
                <del>altho we believe they convinced of the fallacious<lb/> ideas they have recently
                    entertained on Religious subjects.</del></p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The public denunciation of the creed By <persName>Dr
                    Eckman</persName> at the Tabernacle<lb/> Lecture Room some weeks ago; as being
                anti Jewish, and as<lb/> having been surreptitiously introduced in the
                Synagogue,<lb/> gave publicity to the following facts viz.</p>
            <p>The Building Committee received instructions from the<lb/> congregation to have “Our
                Creed <hi rend="underline">translated</hi> and placed<lb/> in the synagogue; and
                recommended the <del>services</del> assistance of their<lb/> Hazan the
                    <persName>Rev. G Posnanski</persName> for that purpose, the committee<lb/>
                accordingly informed that Gentn of the wishes of the<lb/> congregation, to which he
                assented, and <del>they subsequently</del> this prepared<lb/>
                <del>received from him</del> creed was placed in the synagogue as Our „the
                Maimonidian” creed<lb/>
                <del>that which is now placed in the synagogue</del> It contains<lb/> like that of
                    <persName>Maimonides</persName> thirteen articles <del>of I</del> and<lb/>
                purports to be “Elements of Jewish Faith.”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">This committee, with the exception of <persName>Mr
                    Posnanski</persName>, with fearless <sic>magninimity</sic>, have<lb/> recently
                expressed, that they have no <sic>pretentions</sic> to<lb/> Biblical or Rabbinical
                Lore, that they never supposed<lb/> that <del>it</del> this creed aimed a blow at
                the very vitals of Judaism,<lb/> they received <del>this creed</del> it in full
                faith of its really<lb/> being, that which the congregation requested them to<lb/>
                procure viz a translation of “<hi rend="underline">our</hi> the Maimonidian<lb/>
                Creed and if it <hi rend="underline">were</hi> any thing else, it was <hi
                    rend="underline">not</hi><lb/> the acknowledged creed of the congregation;<lb/>
                a Public meeting of the Sunday School attached<lb/> to the K K B.E. under the sole
                control of the Ladies<lb/> of the Congregation, was convened soon after this
                and<lb/> the creed which had hitherto been taught, was rejected<lb/> and forever
                expelled from school <del>by a vote of 25 to 3</del>.<lb/> It would not be out of
                place here to answer <del>“C” a</del><lb/> the objections <del>which</del> of “C” in
                the last “Occident” to<lb/> the views</p>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">5</p>
            <p><persName>Mr Newman</persName> takes (on his <del>anima</del> criticism of this
                creed) of the substitution of the Divine<lb/> Law handed by
                    <persName>moses</persName> to our Fathers” for the Universal<lb/> believe (and
                    <hi rend="underline">correct translation of</hi>
                <persName>Maimonides</persName>). “that the<lb/> Law was <del>given</del> delivered
                unto <persName>Moses</persName> by God,” <del>I</del><lb/> The only article of Faith
                necessary for any believer<lb/> is that of <add>תורה מן השמים</add> if this is
                admitted <del>then</del> the<lb/> other two propose by “<persName>Albo</persName>,”
                and the Twelve according to<lb/>
                <persName>Maimonides</persName>, follow of themselves, as the<del>re</del>
                whole<lb/> Bible is there acknowledged to be given by God<lb/>
                <del>to</del> and all the contents binding, but this very<lb/> article is distorted
                and rendered inane by<lb/> the alteration introduced in article 8<hi rend="sup"
                    >th</hi> where<lb/> instead of the Universal belief that the Law was<lb/>
                delivered to <persName>Moses</persName> by God, it is in <persName>Mr
                    Posnanskis</persName><lb/> creed only considered as a divine Law delivered<lb/>
                by <persName>Moses</persName> unto our Fathers—now a “divine<lb/> Law delivered by
                    <persName>Moses</persName> may mean no more<lb/>
                <del>than</del> and stand no higher than, a “Divine Poem<lb/> By
                    <persName>Milton</persName>, a Divine Hymn, by <persName>Dr
                Watts</persName><lb/> “Divine Service by an incompetent Lay man<lb/> or a Divine
                Comedy by “<persName>Dante</persName>,” the word<lb/> “Divine” is of less import
                than “Sacred”, and<lb/> “divine and sacred less than “Holy”. The draft<lb/> of the
                    <hi rend="underline">Translator</hi> may easily be <sic>percured</sic> by<lb/>
                comparing Article 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> which immediately follows<lb/> when
                instead of the Positive and emphatic assertion<lb/>
                <del>that</del> of <persName>Maimonides</persName> viz we believe with a
                firm/perfect faith, that<lb/> this Law will never be changed or altered, and<lb/>
                that there will be <hi rend="underline">no other Law Given</hi> by the<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">Creator</hi> Blessed be his name, he simply states<lb/> that we
                believe the divine Law will never be<lb/> altered or changed”, he has expunged or
                forgot<lb/> to translate, what we so <hi rend="underline">very much</hi> want to
                hear<lb/> viz that <hi rend="underline">the Creator blessed be his name, never
                    will</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">give any other Law.</hi><lb/> “C” also states that Mr.</p>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p rend="align(right)">6</p>
            <p><persName>Poznanski</persName> “never advocated doctrines that conflicted with
                the<lb/> cardinal principles of our religion.” It is not difficult<lb/> to infer
                what a man's moral and religious principles<lb/> are when his own words and actions
                sufficiently<lb/> indicate them.</p>
            <p>Firstly—in his discussion with <persName>Dr Raphall</persName>, when asked<lb/> if he
                believed in the Bible in the Law &amp; the Prophets<lb/> he in the presence of both
                Organizations replied after a long hesitation Y-e-s <del>with qualifications
                    some</del><lb/> several of his <del>friends</del> own congregation inferring
                from<lb/> his evasion and long consideration, that he did not fully believe</p>
            <p>
                <del>Secondly—His unbelief in the coming of the personal messiah<lb/> the,
                        Ressurection<add>?</add> and in the prayers which<lb/> and “that God gave
                    the law,” <add>?</add> his creed”</del>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly <del>his disbelief in</del> the non obligation of observance of the
                ceremonial and<lb/> Rabbinical Laws as <add>?</add> to <persName>Dr
                    Eckman</persName><lb/> and <persName>Mr Newman</persName>,”</p>
            <p><del>We also understand “C” is the author of the Petition</del><lb/> and Lastly his
                extreme inconsistent course viz coming to <placeName>Charleston</placeName><lb/> as
                a pious and orthodox mosaic &amp; Rabbinical Hazan,<lb/> and in a short time
                afterwards subverting our <hi rend="underline">faith</hi><lb/> by introducing into
                the synagogue, one of his own<lb/> manufacture which his replete with Infidelity
                &amp;<lb/> Irreligion”</p>
            <p rend="indent(1)">The <persName>Posnanski</persName> parties finding themselves
                reduced<lb/> in the last Ten Years from over One Hundred voting members<lb/> to only
                Eighteen, and destruction approaching from exposure of<lb/> their leader by
                    <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> determined as a last<lb/> resort they being in
                the majority on the Board of<lb/> Trustees, to transmit a petition to the Board
                with<lb/> the request that <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> should resign as they did
                not think <del>men</del> suited their needs<add>?</add>. This<lb/> Petition, Signed
                by the Eighteen members, was<lb/> accordingly sent in, and a resolution passed<lb/>
                by a note of 4 to 3 that <persName>Dr Eckman</persName> should comply<lb/> with the
                weeks of the petitions, a contra petition<lb/> was also sent to the Board signed by
                Fifteen members</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
